<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#debates">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_fisheries_and_maritime_affairs/2025-05-15/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_fisheries_and_maritime_affairs/2025-05-15/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-05-15" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#author" href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/34/joint_committee_on_fisheries_and_maritime_affairs"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_fisheries_and_maritime_affairs/2025-05-15/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_fisheries_and_maritime_affairs/2025-05-15/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-05-15" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_fisheries_and_maritime_affairs/2025-05-15/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_fisheries_and_maritime_affairs/2025-05-15/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-05-21" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#debates">
        <TLCPerson eId="CharlesWard" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Charles-Ward.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Charles Ward"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ConorDMcGuinness" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Conor-D-McGuinness.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Conor D McGuinness"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DeeRyan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Dee-Ryan.S.2025-01-29" showAs="Dee Ryan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DiarmuidWilson" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Diarmuid-Wilson.S.2002-09-12" showAs="Diarmuid Wilson"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="GerardPCraughwell" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Gerard-P-Craughwell.S.2014-10-10" showAs="Gerard P. Craughwell"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JenniferWhitmore" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Jennifer-Whitmore.D.2020-02-08" showAs="Jennifer Whitmore"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ManusBoyle" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Manus-Boyle.S.2025-01-29" showAs="Manus Boyle"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MichaelCahill" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Michael-Cahill.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Michael Cahill"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PadraigMacLochlainn" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Pádraig-MacLochlainn.D.2011-03-09" showAs="Pádraig Mac Lochlainn"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PatTheCopeGallagher" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Pat-the-Cope-Gallagher.D.1981-06-30" showAs="Pat the Cope Gallagher"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PeterChapCleere" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Peter-'Chap'-Cleere.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Peter 'Chap' Cleere"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/chair" showAs="Chair" eId="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/vice_chairman" showAs="Vice Chairman" eId="Vice_Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/author" showAs="author" eId="author"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/editor" showAs="editor" eId="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>AN COMHCHOISTE UM IASCACH AGUS GNÓTHAÍ MUIRÍ</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>Joint Committee on Fisheries and Maritime Affairs</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2025-05-15">Déardaoin, 15 Bealtaine 2025</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2025-05-15">Thursday, 15 May 2025</docDate>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_en">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_ga">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">Tháinig an Comhchoiste le chéile ag 02:00 p.m.</summary>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">The Joint Committee met at 02:00 p.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_3">Comhaltaí a bhí i láthair / Members present:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_1">Teachtaí Dála / Deputies</p>
              </th>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_2">Seanadóirí / Senators</p>
              </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#MichaelCahill">Michael Cahill</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#VictorBoyhan">Victor Boyhan</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#PeterChapCleere">Peter 'Chap' Cleere</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#ManusBoyle">Manus Boyle</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#PatTheCopeGallagher">Pat the Cope Gallagher</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#GerardPCraughwell">Gerard P. Craughwell</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_9">
                  <person refersTo="#PadraigMacLochlainn">Pádraig Mac Lochlainn</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_10">
                  <person refersTo="#DeeRyan">Dee Ryan,*</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_11">
                  <person refersTo="#DavidMaxwell">David Maxwell</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_12">
                  <person refersTo="#DiarmuidWilson">Diarmuid Wilson.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_13">
                  <person refersTo="#CharlesWard">Charles Ward</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_14">
                  <person refersTo="#JenniferWhitmore">Jennifer Whitmore.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_4">* In éagmais / In the absence of Senator Niall Blaney.</summary>
          <summary eId="sum_5">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#ConorDMcGuinness">Teachta / Deputy Conor D. McGuinness sa Chathaoir / in the Chair.</person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Business of Joint Committee<recordedTime time="2025-05-15T14:00:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#ConorDMcGuinness" eId="spk_1">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-05-15T14:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_15">I have received apologies from Senator Niall Blaney, who has nominated Senator Dee Ryan to substitute for him.</p>
          <p eId="para_16"> Before we proceed, I have a few housekeeping matters to go through. In accordance with Standing Orders, I am required to, and I wish to, make the following declaration. Dearbhaím go sollúnta go ndéanfaidh mé, go cuí agus go dílis agus a mhéid is eol agus is cumas dom, oifig Chathaoirleach an Chomchoiste um Iascach agus Gnóthaí Muirí a fheidhmiú gan scáth gan fabhar, na rialacha mar atá siad leagtha síos ag an Teach seo a chur i bhfeidhm go cothrom neamhchlaonta, ord a choimeád agus cearta agus pribhléidí comhaltaí a chaomhnú de réir an Bhunreachta agus mBuan-Orduithe. I do solemnly declare that I will duly and faithfully and to the best of my knowledge and ability, execute the office of Cathaoirleach of the Joint Committee on Fisheries and Maritime Affairs without fear or favour, apply the rules as laid down by the House in an impartial and fair manner, maintain order and uphold the rights and privileges of members in accordance with the Constitution and Standing Orders. Gabhaim buíochas le comhaltaí as ucht a gcuid tacaíochta agus cabhrach leis sin. I would welcome members' co-operation and assistance with the onerous duty I take on. </p>
          <p eId="para_17"> I remind members of the constitutional requirement that those who participate in public meetings must be physically present within the confines of the Leinster House complex. Members of the committee attending remotely must do so from within the precincts of Leinster House. This is due to the constitutional requirement, which I think most members will be aware of already, that members must be physically present within the confines of the place where the Parliament has chosen to sit, and that is Teach Laighean, Leinster House. I ask any member participating via Teams - I do not think we have any members participating via Teams now but this applies across the board - to confirm, prior to making a contribution to the meeting, they are on the grounds of the Leinster House campus. It will be my practice while calling on a member attending a meeting via MS Teams to confirm they are on the precincts but it will be, ultimately, the responsibility of the member.</p>
          <p eId="para_18"> Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice that they should not criticise or make charges against any person or entity by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable, or otherwise engage in speech that may be regarded as damaging to the good name of a person or entity. Therefore, if their statements are potentially defamatory in relation to an identifiable person or entity, I will direct them to discontinue their remarks. It is imperative that they comply with any such direction. We have privileges here and it is important we actualise those privileges with responsibility. </p>
          <p eId="para_19"> Is mór an onóir dom fáiltiú a chur roimh comhaltaí chuig an gcéad cruinniú seo de chuid an Chomhchoiste um Iascach agus Gnóthaí Muirí. Is coiste nua é seo agus tá mé fíorbhuíoch as an muinín atá léirithe ionam le mo cheapachán mar Chathaoirleach an choiste. Tá mé ag tnúth le bheith ag obair go dlúth leis na gcomhaltaí ar fad sna míonna agus blianta amach romhainn. It is a privilege to welcome members of both Houses of the Oireachtas to the inaugural meeting of the committee. This is a new committee and we have an opportunity to shape its work in a progressive way. I want to acknowledge the weight of responsibility we carry. This is a very important committee and I look forward to working with each member.</p>
          <p eId="para_20">I will say a few words to outline my vision and where we are coming from. I had an opportunity to meet with many of the Teachtaí Dála. I have not had a chance to meet with the Seanadóirí yet, but I intend to engage with them in this committee and outside the committee room.</p>
          <p eId="para_21"> I come from a coastal community in west Waterford. From the Suir estuary in Dunmore East in the east of the county to Boatstrand in the middle and Heilbhic and Ardmore in the west, we in Waterford have a rich coastline, maritime heritage and huge potential offshore. This is true right around the coast of our island nation. Our fishing harbours and seafood sector need real and sustained investment. This committee will be the platform to ensure that Government delivers on that. This committee will fight for fairness, end neglect as I see it, advocate for improvements in dredging to our harbours, including Cé Heilbhic san áireamh, and to help shape a better future for all our coastal communities.</p>
          <p eId="para_22"> I have connections to the fishing industry on both sides of my family, on the south and east coasts in particular. As a teenager, I worked on inshore and offshore fishing boats. I know first-hand the hardship, skill and risk involved in earning a living from the sea. Fishing is not just an industry for the people who engage in it. It is a way of life. For generations the seas have provided sustenance and employment to people and communities that had little else from which to take sustenance. Too often, the concerns of our coastal and island communities have been treated as peripheral, both geographically and in policy and salience.</p>
          <p eId="para_23"> The fishing sector has faced decades of neglect, mismanagement, underinvestment and repeated policy failures that have held back, rather than supported, communities. Those of us who attended the briefing with the Minister of State, Deputy Dooley, heard some of that coming through in his presentation, and an acknowledgement of that. This committee has a chance to point the Government, the State and the agencies in the right direction. I believe this committee must be a strong and determined voice for the fishing community, islanders, workers in the maritime sector and communities in our coastal towns and villages. We are here to listen, give voice, ask hard questions and deliver changes through pointing out policy innovations that can help the people we are privileged to represent. That means challenging the Government when necessary, scrutinising its policy and the policy of the European Union, holding agencies to account and pushing for legislation that is proportionate and forward looking. Above all else, we need to push for fair quota allocations and an assertive national policy on fisheries and maritime affairs.</p>
          <p eId="para_24"> As Chair, my vision is for a committee that is active, progressive and outward looking, one that engages directly with the people affected by policy decisions, that visits our harbours and islands, that shines a light on the impact of EU quota allocations, regulatory overreach, poor enforcement and a lack of strategic investment. We must support diversification of coastal economies and promote long-term sustainable development in the marine industries. That means investing in our seafood processing sector. It means upgrading port infrastructure and dredging our harbours. It means ensuring coastal communities are not left behind in the push for offshore renewable energy but, rather, that their voices are heard, their concerns are acknowledged and they are provided with the opportunity to be partners. We must also ensure proper oversight of environmental impacts, pollution, inadequate sewage systems in our coastal towns and destructive fishing methods employed by super trawlers. We must support our rescue services, the Coast Guard, the Naval Service and the voluntary lifeboat crews who put to sea in all weathers to protect life and limb.</p>
          <p eId="para_25"> I hope this committee will become a place where solutions are found and not just where problems are described and ventilated, a space for meaningful non-partisan work that supports small boat operators as much as large vessels, that strengthens environmental protection while defending coastal livelihoods, and that recognises the full social, cultural and economic value of Ireland's relationship with the sea and our vast marine resource. Is í m'fhís mar Chathaoirleach an choiste seo ná guth láidir a thabhairt do phobail chósta agus oileánda na tíre, ó Bhaile Chaisleáin Bhéarra i gCorcaigh go dtí Ceann Chlochair, na Cealla Beaga agus an Dún Mór. Caithfimid deireadh a chur leis an neamhaird. Caithfimid cluas éisteachta a thabhairt dár bpobail cois cósta, infheistíocht cheart a dhéanamh sna céanna, sna próisis bia mara agus in earnáil na tarrthála. Mar Theachta ó Phort Láirge, táim tiomanta do bheith i mbun gnímh ar son ár bpobal cósta.</p>
          <p eId="para_26"> As I said, we have an opportunity to do real and meaningful work and to listen, investigate, advocate and deliver. I intend to make full use of this forum and I encourage members to make use of it, as I have no doubt they will, to hold the Government and agencies to account, to push for urgent investment and interventions, to help shape the policies that will support our coastal and fishing communities, not just to survive but to thrive. Go n-éirí an t-ádh leis na baill go léir. Táim fíorbhuíoch díobh as a bheith anseo i mo theannta inniu.</p>
          <p eId="para_27">I will now open the floor to comments, if anybody has any at this juncture. I remind members that we are in public session. Senator Craughwell and Deputy Gallagher have indicated that they wish to comment.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GerardPCraughwell" eId="spk_2">
          <from>Senator Gerard P. Craughwell<recordedTime time="2025-05-15T14:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_28">First and foremost, I congratulate the Chair on his appointment. His opening speech was very encouraging in that he is serious about doing a serious job.</p>
          <p eId="para_29"> One of the issues that confronts coastal areas, particularly on the Atlantic side, is the inability of the harbours to support the wind industry should we start to develop wind and hydrogen generation in the Atlantic. The problem is that none of the harbours is capable of taking craft of the size needed. I hope that fairly early in the term of this committee, we will determine how we can support those who want to develop wind energy projects. My engagement with the Germans in recent times has shown they are going as far as Australia and New Zealand rather than where they originally identified, which was the western coast of Ireland, the Atlantic coast. It would be good to carry out an investigation on that pretty quickly.</p>
          <p eId="para_30"> I was delighted to hear the Chair mention the emergency services in the coastal regions, including the Coast Guard, the RNLI and the Naval Service. In any discussion with respect to air cover for our coast, I will have to recuse myself because I am in the middle of a court action. I cannot compromise that.</p>
          <p eId="para_31"> There are a number of issues that we will consider. I mentioned to the Chair just before the meeting the case of the trawler in Arklow and the devastating impact the matter has had on a family. A family is caught up in bureaucracy on this. I formally request that we put it on the agenda.</p>
          <p eId="para_32"> Once again, I congratulate the Cathaoirleach. I look forward to working with him. There was a lovely opening to the meeting today.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ConorDMcGuinness" eId="spk_3">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-05-15T14:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_33">I thank the Deputy.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatTheCopeGallagher" eId="spk_4">
          <from>Deputy Pat the Cope Gallagher<recordedTime time="2025-05-15T14:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_34">Ar an chéad dul síos, déanaim comhghairdeas leis an Chathaoirleach as ucht a cheapacháin mar Cathaoirleach an choiste seo. Mar a dúirt sé, is coiste nua é seo. Is maith an rud é go bhfuil sé ann. Caithfear buíochas a ghabháil don Rialtas agus, ar ndóigh, do na páirtithe go léir a bhí i bhfabhar coiste mar seo a bhunú le plé le tionscadail na hiascaireachta agus na mara. Roimhe seo, ba é an coiste talmhaíochta a bhí ag plé leis an réimse seo. Ní raibh sé sin ceart ná cóir, áfach. Ní bhfuair an earnáil iascaireachta deis chun na riachtanais agus na fadhbanna a bhí aici a phlé. Ós rud é go bhfuil an coiste seo bunaithe anois, agus go bhfuil suim faoi leith ag na baill go léir sna tionscadail seo, beidh muid ábalta teacht le chéile chomh minic agus is féidir chun castáil leo siúd atá san earnáil seo, is iad sin, na dreamanna agus coistí go léir thart ar an chósta. Beidh deis acu teacht isteach anseo chun dianphlé a dhéanamh maidir lena gcuid fadhbanna.</p>
          <p eId="para_35"> I congratulate the Cathaoirleach on his appointment. He has obviously done some work in anticipation of this and future meetings considering that he has met a number of people to outline his views and the way forward. All of us have views. We will take the opportunity in the course of the coming months and years to try to assist the industry, which is based largely along the coast. Where jobs have been created in the industry, there is no other source of employment. The fishing industry is therefore important. My whole life has been in the industry and I am very familiar with places that the Cathaoirleach knows well. I refer to the buying of fish in Heilbhic and Cobh and processing in places from Dunmore East to Castletownbere and up to Galway, and even places on the other coast, including Howth and Clogherhead, and also places in my county, Donegal, including Killybegs, Greencastle and Burtonport, where the pelagic sector is so important. I hope we will have an opportunity to invite in all the national and regional organisations that wish to exchange views with us.</p>
          <p eId="para_36">Unfortunately, I can claim that, while I was in Europe, I might have been the only one who was a full-time member of the fisheries committee for the 14 years that I was there. It plays an important role and we will play an important role. With the stewardship of the Cathaoirleach, no doubt we will have an opportunity to meet that committee and the Commission.</p>
          <p eId="para_37"> In my time, I believe Brexit did more damage to the industry than most of the other issues. I looked Michel Barnier straight in the eye when he was here negotiating Brexit. He said our industry would be safe because fishing and trade would be inextricably linked, but he did not follow through on that. We can see the amount of quota we have lost as a result of Brexit. I advocated at the time that had we threatened to veto Brexit, the fishing industry would be much better off. I now read from press reports, whatever is happening in the UK, that the Prime Minister may be prepared to relinquish some of that.</p>
          <p eId="para_38"> We have a lot of work to do. I look forward to the committee working together under the stewardship of the Cathaoirleach. At least now the fishing sector and the marine sector have a committee they can call their own and we are not the poor relation of the other committee that had responsibility for fisheries.</p>
          <p eId="para_39"> Geallaim don Chathaoirleach go bhfaighidh sé tacaíocht iomlán ón taobh eile den Teach agus go mbeimid sásta obair leis na Teachtaí agus Seanadóirí go léir atá ar an gcoiste seo.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ManusBoyle" eId="spk_5">
          <from>Senator Manus Boyle<recordedTime time="2025-05-15T14:15:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_40">I congratulate the Chair on his appointment. I am delighted to see this committee up and going. To be honest, one of the fights I had for a couple of years was to try to get this committee through the programme for Government, and we have got that done. I am delighted to see it and it is great to be here today</p>
          <p eId="para_41"> As we know, the fishing industry is in bad shape. It is to be hoped, with this committee, we have an avenue to fight back for the fishing industry. As Deputy Gallagher said, quotas play a big part and our quotas have been decimated for years. All we did was give away and we never got anything back in return. We cannot sustain that. Europe is part of the problem. I was out there for one day with the fishing organisations and I could see we are not on the playing field out there. I hope that is something we can work on.</p>
          <p eId="para_42"> Deputy Gallagher said a lot of what I was going to say. We should try to get the Commissioner before the committee, if that is possible, although I do not know if it is. We need a fair playing field. Ireland did not get a fair playing field in the past 20 years. Brexit had a big say in it but, at the end of the day, we gave away a lot and all we heard coming back was that we were lucky to get the deal we had. Our people in Europe need to step up and be up for the fight. All we have done is give away and give away.</p>
          <p eId="para_43"> I support the point regarding the emergency services. At the end of the day, it is a lifeline for fishermen and fisherwomen off the coast. They have to be supported.</p>
          <p eId="para_44"> The committee should visit the six fishery harbour centres to see how they operate, and how boats are tied up for nine months of the year when everybody else is out fishing. I propose we try to visit the six fishery harbour centres so we can see first-hand how the ships are tied up when everybody else is working away. It is totally unfair.</p>
          <p eId="para_45"> I am glad the fightback is on here. As Deputy Gallagher said, we need to pull in the national organisations to try to get answers. We do not want waffle. This is my first day in a committee but I have looked at committees and I see how people run down the clock. We need to get them in here to answer the questions. That is it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelCahill" eId="spk_6">
          <from>Deputy Michael Cahill<recordedTime time="2025-05-15T14:15:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_46">I am delighted to be on this very important committee. I look forward to working with the Cathaoirleach and I congratulate him on his appointment to the role.</p>
          <p eId="para_47"> There are a few issues I want to raise and we can elaborate on them later.</p>
          <p eId="para_48">The processing of aquaculture licences has been a huge issue in my neck of the woods for many years. I live close to the fishing village of Cromane, just outside Killorglin. I know from dealing with fishermen there that they are experiencing significant delays in the processing of their applications for licences. I would like for that to be looked into.</p>
          <p eId="para_49"> Pair trawling is a big issue in Kerry as well, in Kenmare Bay and off the coast of Dingle in Dingle Bay. I have witnessed it numerous times from my own door in Rossbeigh, which is on Dingle Bay. There is considerable concern in that regard in the fishing industry in Kerry among those involved in trawlers, rod fishing, etc. I pay tribute to the students of Pobalscoil Inbhear Scéine in Kenmare, who have lobbied to bring an end to pair trawling. I would like to see that issue progress.</p>
          <p eId="para_50"> Regarding marine and leisure, I would like to see us as a committee promoting tidal swimming pools. We are an island and have plenty of appropriate locations. I can think of places in Kerry, including Rossbeigh and Fenit. It could coincide with coastal protection works. In that regard, will we liaise with the Office of Public Works and invite it to appear before the committee? I believe we should and that we should work closely together. Our two areas are closely related.</p>
          <p eId="para_51"> On infrastructure, I mentioned Cromane, which is probably one of the oldest fishing villages in the country. At one stage, it was the third largest exporter of mussels in Ireland. Today, oyster farming creates considerable employment in the locality, for young people especially. It is great to see them living and working in their area and being able to afford to build a house as well. The village of Cromane has been looking for a pier or any type of landing facility for well over 100 years. The idea of trawlers driving up onto the bank and a tractor and trailer reversing into the sea to unload mussels is not on anymore. There is a health and safety risk, if nothing else. Could we have such issues on the agenda?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterChapCleere" eId="spk_7">
          <from>Deputy Peter 'Chap' Cleere<recordedTime time="2025-05-15T14:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_52">At the outset, I congratulate the Cathaoirleach on his success in being elected. I have no doubt he will be fair and balanced. His opening remarks were very positive for this new Committee on Fisheries and Maritime Affairs.</p>
          <p eId="para_53"> I come from Kilkenny, which is an inland county, so people are probably wondering why I am on this committee. This is an area I am interested in and I am looking forward to working with all of the members for the betterment of fisheries and maritime affairs.</p>
          <p eId="para_54"> I will refer to what my colleague, Deputy Cahill, said about the Minister of State with responsibility for the OPW. Could we invite him to attend? I am examining the fishery side of things in particular in terms of the many flood relief schemes. There are great delays in them and many environmental issues. Perhaps we could examine this in the overall context at some stage over the course of this committee.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ConorDMcGuinness" eId="spk_8">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-05-15T14:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_55">I thank Deputy Cleere. Regarding this committee's scope, inland fisheries and river fisheries do not fall under our remit, unfortunately, but I take the Deputy's wider point on the coastal erosion issue that was referenced by Deputy Cahill.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PadraigMacLochlainn" eId="spk_9">
          <from>Deputy Pádraig Mac Lochlainn<recordedTime time="2025-05-15T14:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_56">When we go into private session, we will look at the work plan we will have over the next few years. This committee deals with the maritime section. There was a presentation from the Minister of State, Deputy Dooley, and his team yesterday on marine planning, marine regulation and the whole area of fisheries. We have great opportunities in terms of the waters around us. We have never got the full value from that resource. We have the richest fishing waters in Europe. They are certainly up there in the world, too.</p>
          <p eId="para_57">If we look at what Norway has taken from the waters around it and how the Norwegians have used that, we see that we lack vision. We have lacked ambition for far too long. </p>
          <p eId="para_58"> There is a space for offshore renewable energy. There has to be a much bigger space for fisheries. There needs to be co-creation. Everybody needs to be at the table as an equal partner protecting the resource for everybody. I hope this committee can steer a pathway for that. </p>
          <p eId="para_59"> There also needs to be a partnership between the inshore fishermen, the island fishermen and the offshore fishermen, all of whom are on the same team. It is about getting the maximum amount of fish for Ireland and then a fair distribution within the country.</p>
          <p eId="para_60"> I congratulate the Chairperson. Deputy McGuinness comes from a fishing family and has the passion to do the job. He will be an excellent Chairperson and I look forward to working with him.</p>
          <p eId="para_61"> There may be rows on the floor of the Dáil and Seanad but committees are where people work together on a cross-party basis to get things done. I am excited to work with everybody on this committee to pursue all of the objectives we agree together. Well done, Chair, and good luck.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ConorDMcGuinness" eId="spk_10">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-05-15T14:25:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_62">Go raibh maith agat, a Theachta Mac Lochlainn. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CharlesWard" eId="spk_11">
          <from>Deputy Charles Ward<recordedTime time="2025-05-15T14:25:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_63">Congratulations, Chairman. It is an honour for me, as an islander from Arranmore Island, County Donegal, to be here working with the other committee members, as I will do over the next few years.</p>
          <p eId="para_64"> Inshore fishing is the biggest issue the islands have. It is a lifeline. The inshore fishery, once a thriving industry, is now basically non-existent, bar a few fishers. Islanders, who have been working on lobsters and crabs for years trying to maintain stocks, need funding. We need to look at that in the long run and try to bring this industry back to the islands. If we do that over the next few years, it will be an achievement for us all. We can all push together on that to make inshore fisheries sustainable. Our children are still going away to Australia. We understand that people leave to work in industries. In the 1980s, there was an abundance of boats, particularly in Burtonport and on Arranmore. They are now non-existent. Over the next few years, however, if everybody pushes together, we will definitely be able to look into certain aspects of the issue. For instance, opening up pollock for small boats would be a great start. If it takes time to achieve these things, so be it. I look forward to working with all members over the next few years.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ConorDMcGuinness" eId="spk_12">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-05-15T14:25:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_65">Go raibh maith agat, a Theachta. Glaoim ar an Teachta Cummins, sorry, an Teachta Whitmore. My apologies. With the square room, I find it quite difficult to see some members. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JenniferWhitmore" eId="spk_13">
          <from>Deputy Jennifer Whitmore<recordedTime time="2025-05-15T14:25:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_66">We have four years to get to know each other, Chair. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ConorDMcGuinness" eId="spk_14">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-05-15T14:25:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_67">Deputy Whitmore is one of the few Teachtaí I did not get a chance to meet last week, unfortunately.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JenniferWhitmore" eId="spk_15">
          <from>Deputy Jennifer Whitmore<recordedTime time="2025-05-15T14:25:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_68">I congratulate you on your new role, Chair. Following our briefing with the Minister of State the other day, I was quite excited about the potential of this committee. It is great to see the committee operating. There seems to be an emphasis from the Government that we will be able to push recommendations and really make a change in the area of fisheries and the marine.</p>
          <p eId="para_69"> My family was also involved in the marine, both in fisheries and the merchant navy. I am a marine biologist and I worked with the Marine Institute at one stage. I also spent quite a while in the aquaculture industry, which is an area I am keen to look at. </p>
          <p eId="para_70"> Our marine and fisheries have huge potential. We have a traditional connection with the marine in Ireland that we are starting to lose. We need to emphasise it again, particularly for coastal communities. Similar to other areas of the economy, a lot of big players in the industry are doing well but all the smaller ones are struggling. We need to focus on them.</p>
          <p eId="para_71"> As a fishery scientist and ecologist, I also want to bring this back into an environmental context. That is a key component.</p>
          <p eId="para_72">In order to have a sustainable marine and sustainable fisheries, we need to work within that environmental context. We will never have a sustainable fisheries sector if we do not work within that. I think fishermen realise that. It is about working hand in hand with fishers to bring about sustainable practices.</p>
          <p eId="para_73"> As regards our environment and climate, we see a change in how we will be able to operate. We hear a lot about a just transition in the midlands. Similarly, there is a need for a just transition when it comes to fishers. We need to be cognisant of that, whether it is when we are talking about the wind sector or just the changing maritime and ecological conditions when it comes to fisheries. That needs to be a key component of this.</p>
          <p eId="para_74"> I look forward to the discussions and to working with all members.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DeeRyan" eId="spk_16">
          <from>Senator Dee Ryan<recordedTime time="2025-05-15T14:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_75">Comhghairdeas, a Chathaoirligh. I am a visitor to your committee but I wanted to wish you well in your role and the committee members well in the very important work they will do over the next four years. I am a member of the Shannon Estuary economic task force, which was constituted under the last Government and produced a report on economic potential within the Shannon Estuary region. Our biggest finding was the opportunity for floating offshore wind from the west coast, so I have a deep interest in the work the committee will do here. I have spoken to the Minister of State, Deputy Dooley, on numerous occasions already about our impatience, if I may describe it that way, for the policy development that will enable floating offshore wind to become a reality. From the perspective of climate, the environment and the economic development and revitalisation of coastal communities, the work members will do on this committee is so important and interesting. I wish them well and I hope, with your permission, a Chathaoirligh, that I will be able to join in on certain sessions over the coming years. Thank you in advance for your permission to do so.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ConorDMcGuinness" eId="spk_17">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-05-15T14:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_76">Not at all, Senator. You are very welcome. You will have a right to attend these meetings in any case but you would be very welcome and we would be delighted to have you along.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DiarmuidWilson" eId="spk_18">
          <from>Senator Diarmuid Wilson<recordedTime time="2025-05-15T14:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_77">Chair, I congratulate you on your elevation to the Chair of this very important committee. I am delighted to be a member of it. Like Deputy 'Chap' Cleere and Deputy Maxwell, I am from an inland county, the great county of Cavan, but it is world-renowned for having the best freshwater fish in the world. We have 365 lakes. I understand from your earlier comments, a Chathaoirligh, that this is not part of our remit to date but I would like to see this committee's remit extended into that area. I am very familiar with the difficulties the fishing industry has. Down through the many years I have known the Cope Gallagher, he has kept us all well informed, and he is briefed generally about not only the difficulties but also the positivities of the fishing industry. Being a frequent visitor to the Magheraroarty region of County Donegal, which is my second love apart from my own county, I am very familiar from speaking regularly to the fishermen in that area with the difficulties they are encountering. I take on board exactly what Deputy Mac Lochlainn said about the great potential this country has as regards the fishing industry. I very much look forward to playing my part as a member of this committee but I would like to see its remit extended to the inland waterways and inland fisheries of this country.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ConorDMcGuinness" eId="spk_19">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-05-15T14:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_78">Colleagues, thank you for that round-the-house discussion. It was very useful. We will, when we go into private session, have an opportunity to feed into our work plan. We have ventilated an awful lot of the issues. I was heartened to hear the approach of many members as regards offshore renewables and that there is huge scope in that regard. The discussion is about the just transition for coastal communities, as Deputy Whitmore said. It is about voices being heard, the potential for new technology in terms of offshore being raised, and, as Senator Craughwell said, the need to invest in ports and harbours.</p>
          <p eId="para_79">These are important items to consider. I am also heartened to hear the call for unity from my party colleague, an Teachta Mac Lochlainn, on inshore and offshore fisheries. If we are united in our approach, we can go further. If we are disunited, we will not achieve at the European level what we need to achieve as an island nation. There is a clear view among committee members on the need for an assertive and forward-looking approach to our national maritime resources. That is important.</p>
          <p eId="para_80"> I apologise if I sounded dismissive to Deputy Cleere when discussing inland fisheries. I did not mean to be. I agree. Flood relief schemes being held up is also an issue in my own constituency, one I am currently engaging on. It is something that we can look at and try to have that engagement to see if inland fisheries can, in some way, be added to the remit of this committee. Many of the species that are a resource in our maritime environment rely on our inland waterways for breeding and recruitment.</p>
          <p eId="para_81"> I thank committee members. We may have pre-empted some of our later discussion, so I will ask members to refrain at that point unless there is anything new to discuss. We will do ourselves all a favour if we do not repeat ourselves.</p>
          <p eId="para_82"> The next item is a note of information regarding the nominations for Leas-Chathaoirleach. As members know, a committee may choose to elect a Leas-Chathaoirleach who can perform the duties and exercise the authority of the Cathaoirleach in my absence. I propose that we request nominations for the position of Leas-Chathaoirleach. It is important that we have one for this committee. It is a new committee and I would welcome the support of having a Leas-Chathaoirleach. It would also broaden the scope of the committee and be a progressive step. Members will have an opportunity to consult one another, discuss the matter individually and consider whether they would be interested. Members can send nominations to the clerk by email, <i>fisheries@oireachtas.ie</i>, by 12 noon on Monday, 19 May. If the proposal is agreed, that is the time we will set for the receipt of nominations. Ideally, the election of the Leas-Chathaoirleach will take place at the second meeting of the committee, for which we have yet to agree the time and date. Is that agreed? Agreed.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_6"> The joint committee went into private session at 2.37 p.m. and adjourned at 3.08 p.m. until 11 a.m. on Tuesday, 20 May 2025.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
