<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#debates">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_education_and_youth/2025-07-10/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_education_and_youth/2025-07-10/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-07-10" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#author" href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/34/joint_committee_on_education_and_youth"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_education_and_youth/2025-07-10/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_education_and_youth/2025-07-10/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-07-10" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_education_and_youth/2025-07-10/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_education_and_youth/2025-07-10/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-07-19" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#debates">
        <TLCPerson eId="AislingDempsey" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Aisling-Dempsey.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Aisling Dempsey"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="CathalCrowe" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Cathal-Crowe.D.2020-02-08" showAs="Cathal Crowe"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DarrenORourke" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Darren-O'Rourke.D.2020-02-08" showAs="Darren O'Rourke"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="EmerCurrie" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Emer-Currie.S.2020-06-29" showAs="Emer Currie"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="GarethScahill" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Gareth-Scahill.S.2025-01-29" showAs="Gareth Scahill"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JenCummins" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Jen-Cummins.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Jen Cummins"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JoeConway" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Joe-Conway.S.2025-01-29" showAs="Joe Conway"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="LindaNelsonMurray" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Linda-Nelson-Murray.S.2025-01-29" showAs="Linda Nelson Murray"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaulineTully" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Pauline-Tully.D.2020-02-08" showAs="Pauline Tully"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PeterRoche" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Peter-Roche.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Peter Roche"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="RuthCoppinger" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Ruth-Coppinger.D.2014-05-23" showAs="Ruth Coppinger"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="RyanOMeara" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Ryan-O'Meara.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Ryan O'Meara"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ShaneCurley" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Shane-Curley.S.2025-01-29" showAs="Shane Curley"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ShonaghNiRaghallaigh" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Shónagh-Ní-Raghallaigh.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Shónagh Ní Raghallaigh"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/chair" showAs="Chair" eId="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/vice_chairman" showAs="Vice Chairman" eId="Vice_Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/author" showAs="author" eId="author"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/editor" showAs="editor" eId="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>AN COMHCHOISTE UM OIDEACHAS AGUS ÓIGE</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>Joint Committee on Education and Youth</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2025-07-10">Déardaoin, 10 Iúil 2025</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2025-07-10">Thursday, 10 July 2025</docDate>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_en">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_ga">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">Tháinig an Comhchoiste le chéile ag 09:30 a.m.</summary>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">The Joint Committee met at 09:30 a.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_3">Comhaltaí a bhí i láthair / Members present:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_1">Teachtaí Dála / Deputies</p>
              </th>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_2">Seanadóirí / Senators</p>
              </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#RuthCoppinger">Ruth Coppinger</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#JoeConway">Joe Conway</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#JenCummins">Jen Cummins</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#ShaneCurley">Shane Curley</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#EmerCurrie">Emer Currie</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#LindaNelsonMurray">Linda Nelson Murray</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_9">
                  <person refersTo="#AislingDempsey">Aisling Dempsey</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_10">
                  <person refersTo="#GarethScahill">Gareth Scahill</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_11">
                  <person refersTo="#ShonaghNiRaghallaigh">Shónagh Ní Raghallaigh</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_12">
                  <person refersTo="#PaulineTully">Pauline Tully.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_13">
                  <person refersTo="#RyanOMeara">Ryan O'Meara</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_14">
                  <person refersTo="#DarrenORourke">Darren O'Rourke</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_15">
                  <person refersTo="#PeterRoche">Peter Roche.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_4">I láthair / In attendance: Deputy David Cullinane.</summary>
          <summary eId="sum_5">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#CathalCrowe">Teachta / Deputy Cathal Crowe sa Chathaoir / in the Chair.</person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Pension Parity and Working Conditions for School Secretaries and Caretakers: Fórsa<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T09:30:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_1">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T09:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_16">I ask everyone attending remotely to put their microphones on mute when not contributing so the committee does not pick up any background noise or feedback. As usual, I remind all of those in attendance to ensure their mobile phones are on silent mode or switched off. Members attending remotely are reminded of the constitutional requirement that in order to participate in public meetings, they must be physically present within the confines of the Leinster House complex.</p>
          <p eId="para_17"> As they are within the precincts of Leinster House, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of the presentations they make to the committee. This means they have an absolute defence against any defamation action for anything they say at the meeting. However, they are expected not to abuse this privilege and it is my duty, as Cathaoirleach, to ensure this privilege is not abused. Therefore, if their statements are potentially defamatory in relation to an identifiable person or entity, they will be directed to discontinue their remarks. It is imperative that they comply with any such direction.</p>
          <p eId="para_18"> Members are also reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person or entity outside the House or an official of the House either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p>
          <p eId="para_19"> On the agenda for today's session is pension parity and working conditions for school secretaries and caretakers. I welcome the following witnesses from Fórsa, Mr. Andy Pike, national secretary, Ms Luisa Carty, chair of the Fórsa school secretary branch, and Mr. David Hearne, chair of the Fórsa caretakers' branch. We are delighted to have them here. I thank them for their time. I call Mr. Pike to make his opening statement.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_2">
          <from> Mr. Andy Pike<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T09:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_20">Fórsa welcomes the opportunity to address the committee on pension parity and working conditions for school secretaries and caretakers.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_3">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T09:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_21">There is no filming allowed in the room. I am sorry to interrupt Mr. Pike.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_4">
          <from> Mr. Andy Pike<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T09:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_22">No problem.</p>
          <p eId="para_23"> The basis of the current campaign for pension parity is simple. We are seeking parity and equality in the pensions and conditions of school secretaries and caretakers when compared to special needs assistants, SNAs, and teachers working in the same schools. Teachers, SNAs, secretaries and caretakers are all employed by their school board of management. Following the Fórsa pay agreement of 2022, secretaries are now paid by the Department of Education and Youth payroll system in the same way as teachers and SNAs. The Minister for Education and Youth is the paymaster and sets the terms and conditions of employment for all such staff, including granting access to the single public service pension scheme. This results in a teacher and an SNA within the same school being paid in the same way as a secretary by the Department of education. Circulars are issued by the Minister for education setting out salary levels, yet secretaries are not public servants and are denied access to the pension scheme whereas access to the scheme has been granted for teachers and SNAs.</p>
          <p eId="para_24"> It is our contention that there is no justifiable objective reason for the exclusion of secretaries and caretakers from those pension arrangements. The continued refusal to confer public service status to both secretaries and caretakers has locked out several generations of school staff from secure income in retirement. The Fórsa support our secretaries campaign, which ran from 2019 to 2022, succeeded in securing a groundbreaking pay agreement that sought to address the chronic low pay levels for secretaries who at the time were earning only €13 per hour. The final pay agreement provided for transfer to the clerical officer pay scale with some credit for prior service. This agreement increased pay levels for many secretaries by 50%. The fact that secretaries benefited from those significant pay increases should be seen in the context of the clerical officer grade being the lowest paid grade in the public service. Secretaries remain on mainly part-time contracts with most not even earning a full weekly wage during school term.</p>
          <p eId="para_25"> The agreement provided for five days paid sick leave rising to ten in line with statutory entitlements, and 22 days paid annual leave. Secretaries were given the option of claiming an allowance equal to job seekers benefit for weeks when they were laid off by their school to ensure they did not have to sign on during weeks of school closure. Over 80% of secretaries have signed up to the agreement and all new secretaries are employed on the new terms. The agreement states a similar pay framework for caretakers must be implemented. However, some three years into the lifetime of the agreement the Department has not brought forward any firm proposals for caretakers, leaving so many members on very low pay. Their hourly rate of pay has not increased since 2019 and remains €13 per hour unless an increase can be agreed locally.</p>
          <p eId="para_26"> The refusal to confer the same public service status for secretaries and caretakers as conferred on teachers and SNAs working side by side in the same schools also has other impacts. Whereas teachers and SNAs have access to the public service sick leave scheme, including access to extended critical illness benefits, secretaries and caretakers do not. Therefore, in the same school, a teacher or an SNA who becomes seriously ill with a cancer diagnosis has access to six months full pay and six months half pay, including the crucial illness benefit, whereas a secretary only has an entitlement to five days paid sick leave and a caretaker has no access to paid sick leave at all. Teachers and SNAs also have access to other public service entitlements, including bereavement leave of 20 days for an immediate close relative and five days for a member of their extended family. A secretary or a caretaker who experiences the same type of bereavement in the same school has no access to paid bereavement leave.</p>
          <p eId="para_27">This disparity of treatment shows the truth of the way the State views school secretaries and caretakers. They had to fight for many years to get on the first rung of the public service pay system, and caretakers have still no pay deal after three years. They are treated differently when they are sick, they are treated differently when they suffer a bereavement, and they are not deemed to be worthy of the same pension rights as their colleague teachers and SNAs employed by the same school board of management. They are treated differently, they are treated as second class employees, and they have been exploited for decades and decades.</p>
          <p eId="para_28"> This campaign is unusual because it is rare to find an issue raised by a trade union that has seemingly universal support among the public, parents, students, colleagues across the schools and many political parties. Any objective assessment of the employment status of school secretaries and caretakers would result in the conclusion that as a group they have been taken for granted, undervalued and ignored within the schools' sector and the political world for far too long.</p>
          <p eId="para_29"> However, this Government in common with previous Governments has refused to address this inequality citing the costs and a policy position of not extending access to the public service pension scheme and public service status for any new groups of staff. The Department of Education and Skills, as it was, in 2019 gave an estimate in evidence before this committee that the full cost of providing access to the pension scheme for our school secretary members would be €30 million. The argument that this very small measure is unaffordable simply does not stand up to scrutiny given the very healthy state of the finances of the State.</p>
          <p eId="para_30"> On 8 October 2020 the then Tánaiste, Dr. Leo Varadkar, when answering a question in the House on the issue of school secretaries and caretakers pay and pensions stated:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_31">The Government really values the essential work done by school secretaries and caretakers. Often, the school secretary is the first person one meets on the way into a school and the caretaker is the last person to leave in the evening. Schools would not operate without them and the role they play in our education system is as important as that of schoolteachers, SNAs and school principals. For that reason, it is the Government's objective to regularise their employment, terms and conditions, and pension rights. </p>
          <p eId="para_32"> We have no doubt that this statement was made in good faith and the sentiments expressed were heartfelt and genuine. However, when the issue of pension provision was raised again and again in negotiations in the Workplace Relations Commission in 2020, the union was informed that pensions could not and would not be discussed as the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform had issued instructions prohibiting any consideration of pension provision for secretaries and caretakers.</p>
          <p eId="para_33"> Our members have now concluded that they simply cannot rely on promises and commitments made by politicians, no matter how senior and distinguished they might be, and it is clear that the two-tier employment framework will be defended at all costs by senior civil servants within that single Government Department, who themselves enjoy the benefits of public service status but who continue to do everything in their considerable power to deny the same status and benefits for low-paid secretaries and caretakers.</p>
          <p eId="para_34"> It is also clear to school secretaries and caretakers that the current Minister for Education and Youth genuinely wants to help to resolve this problem. We also appreciate the support of many elected representatives from across the House from all political parties who agree that all schools' staff should have the same rights and entitlements. Yet none of that support, welcome though it is, can really make the difference needed to secure public service status and pension rights for school secretaries and caretakers.</p>
          <p eId="para_35"> When we think of our industrial relations system, it is tempting to believe that the institutions of the State should be capable of resolving this matter. A close examination demonstrates that the Department of Public Expenditure, Infrastructure, Public Service Reform and Digitalisation, as it is now titled, will only respond to pressure if that pressure is applied in the strongest way possible. To make progress it is necessary to apply sufficient pressure to ensure that a genuine negotiation can proceed without the Department yet again being able to exercise a complete veto on discussion of pension provision.</p>
          <p eId="para_36"> Our members have decided, therefore, that after decades of writing letters, of lobbying their elected representatives, and of being let down time and again, the time is right to go on strike. Our ballot of secretaries and caretakers for an indefinite strike was supported by 98% of members with a turnout of over 80%. We have a clear and strong mandate for the strike, which will commence on the morning of the 28 August next with a national rally on Merrion Street outside the offices of the Department of Public Expenditure, Infrastructure, Public Service Reform and Digitalisation. We will place pickets on those buildings for the duration of the dispute to shine a light on those responsible for denying this justice and perpetuating this injustice. From 1 September our members will picket outside their own schools where we are certain their cause will be appropriately supported by teachers, SNAs, students and parents.</p>
          <p eId="para_37"> Those responsible for determining policy on public service pensions may argue that the days where new staff could be admitted to the scheme are long gone, that to allow any new secretary or caretaker into the scheme would cause contagion. I have heard them use that very term. If this were true why did the Department of Education in June 2023 offer a deal to secretaries and caretakers in the old 1978-1979 scheme, which provided entry to the scheme and recognition for pension purposes of all their service. This offer was made to a very small cohort of staff following representations from Fórsa. It resulted in a small number of secretaries and caretakers, who previously had been unable to access the pension scheme, being offered the full public service pension in return for their lump sum being reduced to cover employee contributions. If that offer was sanctioned by the Department of Public Expenditure, Infrastructure, Public Service Reform and Digitalisation we see no reason the same or similar terms cannot be offered to all secretaries and caretakers working for school boards of management. The refusal to even consider taking such steps has caused great anger and frustration, as demonstrated by the outstanding ballot result in favour of strike action.</p>
          <p eId="para_38"> In summary, Fórsa has informed the Department of Education and Youth that we are available at any time for meaningful face-to-face talks on the terms by which our members will be granted public service status with access to the pension scheme. If our campaign succeeds, we will see an end the current situation whereby the secretary or caretaker, who after working for 40 years in the same school, and who is an integral part of the school community would retire this year with no pension provision while watching their teacher and SNA colleagues retire with full pension benefits. The secretary or caretaker who falls seriously ill and does not have the most basic safety net of sick pay would be provided with occupational sick pay in the same way as every other staff group in the schools' community, including access to critical illness benefit. On behalf of the members we represent I thank the committee for allowing us the opportunity of setting out the relevant issues. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_5">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T09:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_39">For anyone watching at home or in the Gallery, all proceedings are live streamed, or you can retrieve hourly video files retrospectively if any organisation wishes to use clips. These will be found at <i>oireachtas.ie</i>. The video files are updated hourly if anyone wants to use them.</p>
          <p eId="para_40"> I thank Mr. Pike for his opening statement. We will now go to members' questions. This is a split session and we will move into another session later. We will need to be a little bit tight on time at four minutes per member.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ShaneCurley" eId="spk_6">
          <from>Senator Shane Curley<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T09:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_41">I know Ms Carty from home but generally everything I will say today is from my own experience as a teacher in a secondary school for ten years before I became a Senator. The big issue for me is that secretaries and caretakers are not recognised as public sector workers in the same sense as teachers and SNAs. This is the huge bugbear for me. Every day when I walk into school, if it is at half past seven in the morning to train a volleyball team, a hurling team or a camogie team, the first person I meet is either the secretary or the caretaker. They are there putting out chairs for whatever meeting might be going on in the gym or they are doing some genuinely vital work in the school. The school would not function without them. I fully see the merit in the arguments being made by Mr. Pike.</p>
          <p eId="para_42"> They are separate roles. For example, if a teacher is sick and cannot get to school, the first person he or she thinks of ringing is the school secretary. It is not the school principal or the year head but it is the secretary. School secretaries play a hugely vital role. I am not here today just to pay lip service. I genuinely do not believe a school could function without a secretary and a caretaker, at second level in particular.</p>
          <p eId="para_43"> There is a huge body of work to be done here. I accept that Fórsa is fully open to negotiation with the relevant stakeholders. All I can say is that I am fully supportive. I have spoken to Ms Carty already about this and we have had good engagement. I am fully supportive of what Fórsa is looking for because it is a genuine public service that is being carried out by school secretaries and school caretakers. I would not have functioned as a teacher without the caretaker being able to look after me at times when I needed him, or the secretary in other cases. In a lot of schools the secretary actually runs the school. They run the day-to-day business of a school. I do not know how a school would function without either. To take them away from a school and say they are not providing a public service would be incredulous in my view.</p>
          <p eId="para_44"> I fully support what Fórsa is looking for and I am here to help in any way I can. I am available to engage with the witnesses in any way I can in the future. They have my full support going forward. If there is anything I can do to lobby on their behalf to try to impact any kind of change, then I am here to help. Ms Carty has my number, so she will be keeping on top of me.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_7">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_45">Thank you. Does Mr. Pike want to respond to any of those remarks?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_8">
          <from> Mr. Andy Pike<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_46">This is very typical of the interactions all of our members have with their elected representatives. Our problem is that policy on this issue does not seem to be controlled by anybody in the Oireachtas. That is our problem and that is why industrial action may be necessary.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_9">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_47">Very good. I now call Deputy O'Meara, who has four minutes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RyanOMeara" eId="spk_10">
          <from>Deputy Ryan O'Meara<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_48">I thank the witnesses for being here today. I could echo a lot of what Senator Curley has said but I am conscious of not doing that to try to make the most of our time. I have interacted with a lot of schools, particularly in recent months, that have seen growing pupil numbers. The secretaries and caretakers have been there for years but the demands of the job have grown, particularly in the case of secretaries, with pupil numbers increasing rapidly in some of the secondary schools I can think of. The additional secretarial support has not been found and it has put an enormous amount of pressure on the usually one secretary in the school. Some I can think of have been there for many years but the demands of their roles have increased dramatically due to the number of pupils within the school. The same is true of the role of caretaker and what they are expected to do with an expanding and physically growing school.</p>
          <p eId="para_49"> I get the points Mr. Pike made, so I am trying not to question him on those. That was incredibly clear, and has been made incredibly clear to us over a long period. However, in those specific circumstances, is this current situation resulting in those schools not being able to get the additional secretarial or caretaker workers they need to help them in their positions?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_11">
          <from> Ms Luisa Carty<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_50">The Department has a formula. We do not know what it is, but if anybody wants hours they have to apply through the Department. Regarding school secretaries, everyone who moved over, moved over on what they had. The schools are now applying for hours. The Department has a formula, as I said, but we do not know what it is. There are schools which cannot get the hours they need. The secretaries were being underpaid previously and the money that was going into the school previously was from the ancillary services grant. Schools were using that to put in the hours they thought they could afford at the time. Now, since the Department is paying, schools want more hours but they are not able to get them because we are told there is an allocation model in place. This is going on for over two years now. We still do not know what it is and schools are still scraping to get the hours to cover what they need, both for secretaries and caretakers. We do not know what the allocation is; only the Department knows.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RyanOMeara" eId="spk_12">
          <from>Deputy Ryan O'Meara<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_51">If I can follow up on this, specifically on the free school books scheme and the administrative burden that was put on secretaries because of that, how have the Fórsa members found that? Were there supports available to them to get that scheme out? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_13">
          <from> Ms Luisa Carty<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_52">The amount of money that has been put in place for this is minimal. This job involves manual labour. It has been imposed on a lot of school secretaries without their consent in a lot of places. They are told it is part of their job and they have to come in and do it. However, the amount of work that is involved in it and the expectations from the Department of education as regards the length of time in which this can be done means it is just not feasible. While it is very welcome for parents and families with children in the schools, it is a huge amount of work. Our job has evolved so much from what we used to do years ago when we started to what it is now. This is just an extra on top of that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RyanOMeara" eId="spk_14">
          <from>Deputy Ryan O'Meara<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_53">I thank Ms Carty. I will leave it there. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_15">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_54">The next speaker is Senator Linda Nelson Murray, who has four minutes. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LindaNelsonMurray" eId="spk_16">
          <from>Senator Linda Nelson Murray<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_55">I thank the witnesses for coming in. Similar to my colleague, Senator Curley, I do not think anyone around this table would disagree about the importance of the work secretaries and caretakers do. I have nine and ten year old girls and if I was not able to dial that secretary's number and have a chat with her, I would be lost. It is so important. Just so that I understand it properly, are we saying that we got the pay more or less sorted for secretaries a couple of years ago but we are now looking for the pension side of it? For the caretakers, am I right in saying that they are on €13 an hour? Do caretakers not get the minimum wage of €13.50? Does this not apply to them? Will the auto-enrolment that will happen take into account caretakers and secretaries?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_17">
          <from> Mr. Andy Pike<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_56">I will ask Mr. Hearne to come in on caretaker pay but the situation is that the last time the Department reviewed the hourly rate for school caretakers was 2019. The last circular on this is still at €13 an hour. Anything above that has to be negotiated with the board of management, so it is whatever someone's board of manager will give them. Auto-enrolment is far inferior to the public service pension arrangements. Even when that is implemented, we are still going to have this two-tier system, with teachers and SNAs within the public service arrangements but not caretakers. Will Mr. Hearne expand a little on caretakers pay? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_18">
          <from> Mr. David Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_57">With caretakers pay, the circular states €13 per hour but when the minimum wage increased the majority of schools increased it. They agreed that was what the caretakers deserved but that was all they got. They did not get anything else. We have a caretaker in Cork who was in the school 16 years and is on €13.50 an hour, working 37 hours a week. It is very hard in the cost-of-living crisis we are in at the moment to get by on that wage.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LindaNelsonMurray" eId="spk_19">
          <from>Senator Linda Nelson Murray<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_58">Absolutely. I wish Fórsa the very best of luck in its negotiations. I really hope we do not see any strike action at the end of August because I can just imagine what it will be like for schools. I wish the witnesses the very best of luck in their negotiations and I fully support the work of secretaries and caretakers in schools.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_20">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_59">The next speaker is Deputy Dempsey who has four minutes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AislingDempsey" eId="spk_21">
          <from>Deputy Aisling Dempsey<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_60">I apologise for only arriving now but I was next door at the children committee which was meeting with Tusla. These are all really important issues so my timing is perfect, if I do say so myself.</p>
          <p eId="para_61"> I presume everyone here is very supportive of the witnesses and their cause. Unfortunately, we are at this point. We seem to be at this point every time there is a campaign for fairness. It is a stereotype and a generalisation but the majority of school secretaries are female. They are presumably women who are trying to strike a good work-life balance, whose kids may be or were in the school. What are the views of the witnesses on that? Do they believe that is a factor as to why it has taken so long to agree this?</p>
          <p eId="para_62"> My second question - and it is not a criticism of the witnesses - relates to the strategy for these discussions and negotiations. They always seem to start with pay, in that that becomes the template and then you go for pensions. Can that be addressed from Fórsa's side? What can we do to address it from Government's side? When the union members get some of their conditions improved, surely it is short-lived joy because the next thing another knock and blow comes their way. They are undervalued and under-appreciated and presumably that is why we see strike action. Is it literally just strategy that makes Fórsa go piecemeal after these things or how can we help the witnesses address that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_22">
          <from> Mr. Andy Pike<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_63">I thank the Deputy. We have said many times that there is a lot of entrenched gender discrimination at the heart of how school secretaries have been treated for decades and decades. If they had been a well-organised group of male workers, this would have been resolved many years ago. The vast majority are low-paid, very part-time employees in schools. For them to unionise across the schools' sector, when there is only one of them in a school unlike a factory or a big local authority where there are hundreds, in the way they have demonstrates the level of anger and disenchantment that is out there. We had 700 members when we secured the pay agreement. We now have three or four times as many. It should have been resolved years ago. If they had been all male workers, maybe it would have been resolved. They may have been listened to. That is a bit of a problem sometimes.</p>
          <p eId="para_64">On the strategy for negotiation, unfortunately last time we were in the WRC for weeks and weeks and we thought we had an agreement that might well cover pensions, we were strung along and on the last day in the last session, it was very clear the Department of public expenditure had ruled out any discussion of pensions. We had people then on chronically low pay. There was a real need to get some extra money into pay packets so we agreed terms of a pay agreement, but we said very clearly we would be back looking for pensions. At that time we were in a relatively weak position. We could only influence what would happen in 700 schools. This time, letters of notice about an indefinite strike happening on 28 August have gone out to 2,600 schools, so the footprint of what we do now will be a lot bigger. We hope that will be enough to persuade the civil servants running the Department of public expenditure they need to have another look at this. Their history is they only move when that kind of pressure is put on them. We are simply not prepared to go into talks in the WRC for weeks and weeks only for the Department of public expenditure to say Fórsa may have an agreement with the Department of education but as far as it is concerned we are still not getting pensions. We know that is what is going to happen unless this action takes place.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarrenORourke" eId="spk_23">
          <from>Deputy Darren O'Rourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_65">Time is very tight and I thank the witnesses for coming in at short notice and the committee for organising it. I will come back to Ms Carty and Mr. Hearne for specific examples of the egregious parts of this, like how it feels at retirement after 40 years of work compared with their public service colleagues, the bereavement leave and the critical illness piece. I will come back to them in a minute so maybe they can have a think about it. The personal, human aspect of it is important to hear.</p>
          <p eId="para_66"> I will start with Mr. Pike. Is there a forum for engagement here or is Fórsa waiting to hear from the Department of public expenditure on this? On the argument that the floodgates will be opened, is the union making a particular case for school secretaries and caretakers? I am not arguing one way or another on that but it is said that if we provide public service status for them we will have to do it for a whole pile of other groups. Are there specific arguments Fórsa is making?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_24">
          <from> Mr. Andy Pike<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_67">I thank the Deputy. We have received no invitation to talks from the Department of education at all. We have told it we are available. We would not see the Department of public expenditure in any talks. What it does is ring up at the last minute and tell everybody if the deal can be done or not. You do not get to meet the Department face to face most of the time.</p>
          <p eId="para_68"> On floodgates and setting a precedent, I cannot think of another situation where there is a single employer - a school is a single employer with a board of management - with different terms and conditions for one category of staff over another in respect of pensions. That does not happen anywhere else. It is a unique employment situation. Any large employer has to apply the same pension terms to all employees. They do not apply different terms to one group than to another, so this situation is somewhat unique. Resolving it would not set a precedent and would not open the floodgates to thousands more people coming into the scheme.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarrenORourke" eId="spk_25">
          <from>Deputy Darren O'Rourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_69">I thank Mr. Pike. Will Mr. Hearne give an example of an egregious element of discrimination or difference?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_26">
          <from> Mr. David Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_70">Obviously in our role as caretakers we can get injured on the job. If we do, we are not entitled to any sick leave. Nothing. We have to go to the Department of social welfare and get funding off it. If a colleague of ours who is a teacher trips in school, twists his or her ankle and is out for a week, he or she is paid for that. It is two totally different levels.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarrenORourke" eId="spk_27">
          <from>Deputy Darren O'Rourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_71">Has Mr. Hearne examples of that with his colleagues?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_28">
          <from> Mr. David Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_72">Yes. A colleague up in Meath was out for 12 months with a back injury and he was literally getting no assistance but the assistance from social welfare. He was a young man with three kids and a mortgage and he was getting about €380 per week. It was disgraceful. If the same thing happened to a teacher and they were out for a number of months they would be covered.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarrenORourke" eId="spk_29">
          <from>Deputy Darren O'Rourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_73">Yes, it is different. What about Ms Carty?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_30">
          <from> Ms Luisa Carty<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_74">With the sick leave it is only five days, or even the critical illness. We had a member who had breast cancer and was out for a full year. All she got from her school was two days' sick leave. Another member who had breast cancer worked right through her chemotherapy because she could not afford to be out of work. With bereavement leave, a member's father died and there were two other staff in the same school who could go out for I think up to 20 days for-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_31">
          <from> Mr. Andy Pike<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_75">With that it would be five.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_32">
          <from> Ms Luisa Carty<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_76">Yes. She had to go an have a conversation with her school about what she could take. We have had members who have been asked by the principal to pay for the sub to come in and cover their leave. It is totally unjust.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarrenORourke" eId="spk_33">
          <from>Deputy Darren O'Rourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_77">I thank everyone. Chair, I would-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_34">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_78">You will get in again later on. We will give-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarrenORourke" eId="spk_35">
          <from>Deputy Darren O'Rourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_79">I propose the committee write to the Minister just as a formal proposal on this issue and call for urgent engagement. I mean the Ministers for education and public expenditure.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_36">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_80">Yes, we can agree that now if it is urgent engagement. If you want more detail you might put it in writing and we can agree it at the next-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarrenORourke" eId="spk_37">
          <from>Deputy Darren O'Rourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_81">That is no problem. I think people probably agree with that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_38">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_82">Is there agreement the committee should write? I agree with it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeConway" eId="spk_39">
          <from>Senator Joe Conway<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_83">A Chathaoirligh, which Minister are we referencing? It seems the Minister in-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarrenORourke" eId="spk_40">
          <from>Deputy Darren O'Rourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_84">The two Ministers is what I said.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeConway" eId="spk_41">
          <from>Senator Joe Conway<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_85">The two of them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_42">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_86">The Ministers for education and public expenditure. Is that generally agreed by all members? It is, very good. I thank Deputy O'Rourke.</p>
          <p eId="para_87"> Deputy Roche has four minutes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterRoche" eId="spk_43">
          <from>Deputy Peter Roche<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_88">I thank the Cathaoirleach and thank the witnesses for their attendance. They are pushing an open door when I am sitting in from of them, I assure them of that. That comes from my experience and my involvement through Galway and Roscommon Education and Training Board. I sat on a number of interviewing committees where the job descriptions for school secretaries and caretakers got more complex every day, especially with respect to the demands on them. They interface with parents, teaching staff and of course the general public. As somebody mentioned earlier they are the eyes and ears of the school and are required to understand everything with regard to child protection and how the whole school evolves in terms of the ever-changing climate.</p>
          <p eId="para_89"> I cannot for the life of me understand how we have arrived at a place where secretaries and caretakers feel it is necessary to protest and picket. That they have to resort to doing that to get this anomaly addressed indicates there has been a failing. My question is whether Fórsa has been invited back to the WRC, formally or otherwise, since the last ballot. Maybe it has and maybe it has not. If it has not, there is something fundamentally wrong.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_44">
          <from> Mr. Andy Pike<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_90">I thank the Deputy. We have not received any invitation to talks from the employer side, be that the Department of education or anyone else. We have said to them we are available for talks on the basis the subject for discussion is how and when our members will be admitted to the single public service pension scheme, but we have not had any invitation to talks so far.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterRoche" eId="spk_45">
          <from>Deputy Peter Roche<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_91">Okay. The witnesses are here and it is a very useful exercise and I thank them for coming. What is it they want from this committee? It is a very loaded question, but I am wondering about first steps.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_46">
          <from> Mr. Andy Pike<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_92">We see this committee hearing and subsequent engagements as an opportunity to highlight one thing that probably goes a little bit wider than school secretaries and caretakers, which is that the way our industrial relations system is working at the moment, the people we negotiate with are not the decision-makers. We are concerned that no matter what senior members of the Government might say commitments can be ignored. We quoted Dr. Leo Varadkar a few minutes ago and we were extremely appreciative of the commitment he gave in the House back in 2020, but we are concerned that that commitment was simply ignored. It did not matter to those who control policy. They went their own way and said we were not even to discuss pensions. We are, therefore, concerned that no matter what political commitments we receive - and all support is welcome - our worry is the Department of public expenditure and reform will say "No". When we look at how it responds, it only responds to things like a strike. Secretaries and caretakers are the last group Fórsa would ever think would vote for a strike, but unfortunately that is the only language the Department of public expenditure seems to respond to. The determination of our members is demonstrated by the number who voted, with 98% voting in favour of going on strike, which is not something we see very often.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_47">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_93">Senator Scahill is next and has four minutes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GarethScahill" eId="spk_48">
          <from>Senator Gareth Scahill<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_94">I thank the witnesses for attending here today. My colleague beside me mentioned the value of the secretaries and caretakers. I grew up in a time when you knew your secretary in the school and the caretaker. Sometimes there was a fear element in relation to the teachers but there were constants who you could rely on. That was the secretaries and it probably still is. Therefore, as my colleagues have said here today, Fórsa is pushing an open door. I believe it has unanimous support from the committee on this issue. </p>
          <p eId="para_95"> Has Fórsa done up a costing on this? Is there a specific request on this and can we get details on it? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_49">
          <from> Mr. Andy Pike<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_96">We gave evidence before this same committee in 2019 as did the then Department of Education and Skills. At that time, it put forward a figure to the committee that the cost of regularising school secretaries and caretakers within the public service and providing the pension would be between €30 million to €35 million and that was including retrospection. That was its figure in 2019. It has not produced any costings thus far. It has just said it is not even allowed to discuss it. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GarethScahill" eId="spk_50">
          <from>Senator Gareth Scahill<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_97">Mr. Hearne spoke on the specific case of the caretakers. Are all contracts secure and annualised now or are there still long-term contracts and situations where caretakers might have to go on social welfare during the summer? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_51">
          <from> Mr. David Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_98">At present, a contract could be ten hours or up to 40 hours. Some caretakers have to sign on in the summer, Christmas, Easter and mid-term while others work a 52-week year. The discrepancy is massive. Even our contracts are not secure. If a school drops in size and the pupil numbers go down the caretaker can be lost. There is no job security for us. As a young caretaker myself, in the job seven years, only having got married and having bought my first home, I do not know if I have a job next year. I cannot say right here and now if in September 2026 I will still be employed as a school caretaker. I do not know. There is no job security there. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GarethScahill" eId="spk_52">
          <from>Senator Gareth Scahill<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_99">It is very important that is sorted out. We will try and work with the caretakers on that because, as we have said, the caretaker is the person there at 7 a.m., and for school masses or any evening function, the caretaker is the last person there at night. Their status needs to be regularised and their jobs protected. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_53">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_100">Senator Pauline Tully is next and has four minutes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulineTully" eId="spk_54">
          <from>Senator Pauline Tully<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_101">The witnesses are very welcome. As a former teacher in a school I very much appreciate the work that both secretaries and caretakers do in the school. They know everybody on the ground, every child in the school and they know what is going on. Often they are the ones you go to to find out what is actually going on. </p>
          <p eId="para_102"> Am I right that with ETBs there is not only a discrepancy between the pay and conditions between the teachers and SNAs in the different types of schools? Someone could be doing a job in one school and another person doing the very same job in another school but because the patronage is different the pay and conditions are different? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_55">
          <from> Mr. Andy Pike<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_103">I will ask Ms Carty to expand on this but the Senator is correct. If you secure a job in an ETB school, you are a public servant and have public service conditions and access to public service pensions. That is 10% of our schools where the patron is the ETB and the ETB administers the schools. In 90% of schools, the board of management is the employer and you are not a public servant but you are doing exactly the same work. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_56">
          <from> Ms Luisa Carty<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_104">The work of a school secretary is exactly the same across the board but the way it is done with ETBs is that you are a public servant immediately. We had a member who was ancillary paid who moved overnight to an ETB school and just like that, she had all the terms and conditions including pensions, bereavement leave and sick leave; she has everything. Even in the group we are working with here, we have two secretaries working in the same school. One is Department-appointed and paid through a grant through the school. The other has now moved over to the Department payroll. They were working in the same office, doing the exact same work but one has bereavement leave, pension and everything and the girl right beside her in the same office has none of that. The disparity exists within schools but the ETBs are on a different level to us altogether, even though we are doing the exact same work. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulineTully" eId="spk_57">
          <from>Senator Pauline Tully<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_105">If pay and conditions can be granted to one sector, it makes absolutely no sense why they are not granted to all. We talk about how we are at full employment. Retention and recruitment has to be an issue when conditions are so poor. Is that the case? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_58">
          <from> Mr. David Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_106">There are caretakers around the country who go into the job and after two years say they cannot do it any more because they are not getting paid for the summer holidays or Christmas holidays, so they go off and find different jobs. At the moment, working in Aldi is better paid than being a school caretaker. Take the hours we do in schools. You might be contracted for a 39-hour week. Over the last six weeks, because of the summer holidays coming along, with teachers coming in and changing classrooms etc., my average week was averaging between 45 to 50 hours -----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulineTully" eId="spk_59">
          <from>Senator Pauline Tully<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_107">Going over and beyond.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_60">
          <from> Mr. David Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_108">----- and all we get is time in lieu because there is no overtime rate. It is up to each school what the rate is for overtime and in my school it is time in lieu.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulineTully" eId="spk_61">
          <from>Senator Pauline Tully<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_109">It is a month since the result of the ballot on strike action was made public. There was engagement in the Seanad on 18 June, during statements on education, and I raised this issue. I was told by the Minister that there would be engagement in the coming weeks. However, Fórsa is telling me there has been no engagement whatever which is very disappointing. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_62">
          <from> Mr. Andy Pike<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_110">We met the Minister. We would meet the Minister through routine engagements - we have not met specifically on this issue – but each time we have met her since she was appointed she has told us she would like to see this issue resolved and she wants to be as helpful as she can be and I believe that is a genuine commitment she is making. However, it is not within the gift of the Minister for Education and Youth to determine policy on public sector pay and pensions. That responsibility rests elsewhere. When I say there has been no engagement I am in no way being critical of the current Minister nor of the Department because it is not up to them. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulineTully" eId="spk_63">
          <from>Senator Pauline Tully<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_111">Yes. Thank you. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_64">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_112">That was very interesting. I think a lot of jaws dropped when we heard the disparity with ETBs. Per pay cycle or annually, what does that disparity look like for school secretary pay? Do the witnesses have figures to hand?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_65">
          <from> Mr. Andy Pike<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_113">The disparity is mainly now due to the fact that if someone is employed by an education and training board as a clerical officer and assigned as a secretary in a school, they have a 52-week contract. If they are employed in the independent school sector by a school board of management, most secretaries are employed during term-time only. The gap in wages is that they will be earning 12 or 14 fewer weeks in terms of salary than their ETB counterpart. The pay gap is anywhere between 30% to 40%. The hourly rate is now coming together and is nearly the same because everyone is on the same pay scale. However, the difference in pay relates to the lack of a 52-week contract. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_66">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_114">To add to Deputy O’Rourke’s proposal, I think the committee should ask the Department for the history of how it got to the point that there was an ETB clerical pay scale as opposed to those left outside. There is a big issue we are talking about but that is woeful that there are two ways. </p>
          <p eId="para_115"> We will move on. Senator Joe Conway is next and has four minutes. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeConway" eId="spk_67">
          <from>Senator Joe Conway<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_116">Ar an gcéad dul síos, ba mhaith liom mo bhuíochas a ghabháil leis na finnéithe as ucht teacht isteach ar maidin agus a gcás a phlé linn. I am delighted to be taking part in this discussion and am particularly delighted to welcome David from Waterford. I think it is the first time I have heard such a rich Waterford city accent abroad in any of the Houses or committees and it is truly uplifting.</p>
          <p eId="para_117">I am probably the only person in this room who was a school principal before the dispensation, when my school had a secretary and a caretaker, and afterwards for a number of years when I was ably served by my secretary, Eileen, and a number of caretakers for many years. However, until that time, I was what was known as a teacher principal of a four-teacher school in Dunmore East. A teacher principal is a jack-of-all-trades, handyman and secretary, and my handyman skills were of the Frank Spencer nature. It was quite a challenge. The advent of the secretary and caretaker was liberating both for me and the staff in the school. I do not want to minimise the great work that is done by secretaries and caretakers. When I met Mr. Hearne outside I used the expression "pushing at an open door", which two colleagues have already used. It is illustrative of the fact that people are very much on the witnesses' side.</p>
          <p eId="para_118"> I will ask a few questions about the dreaded spectre of a strike in the autumn. These can be answered when I am finished so that the discussion will be more orderly. Have any discussions taken place with the teacher unions, for example, the INTO, in relation to what their response will be to the official pickets on the day? As a former principal, I know in my heart of hearts what the first day of school in September means to families and children, particularly the junior infants in the reception class. They are coming in and their parents may not have had another child in school. It is a red letter day for a family. The anticipation grows over the summer for the kids and parents. To have all this blown out of the water on 1 September, if not managed well, and I do not know what side is going to manage it, this has the potential to become a nasty and messy industrial action. To what extent has Fórsa thought this through? I am conscious of the possible backlash there will be from parents. Mr. Pike mentioned that he got a lot of support from all political parties. I would be slightly critical of that phrase because, in deference to the dozens of Independent Members in the Seanad and Dáil, the phrase he should be using is "all political parties and none". The Independents in particular are fully supportive of this cause as well.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_68">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_119">I call Deputy Ruth Coppinger.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeConway" eId="spk_69">
          <from>Senator Joe Conway<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_120">I wanted to get a response.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_70">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_121">The Senator has used up his time, but he will get in again in a while.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RuthCoppinger" eId="spk_71">
          <from>Deputy Ruth Coppinger<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_122">I will give Mr. Pike a chance to answer that in a second because, contrary to what the Senator just said, I believe there will be massive support from parents and communities for caretakers and secretaries. God forbid, there would be an effective strike day on the most important day of school. The work that needs to be done on that opening day by school secretaries and caretakers is key. There are papers to be processed and all of the things that have to be done. You strike while the iron is hot, to use that metaphor. The witnesses must have the patience of saints because I am finding it hard to sit here and listen to the tea and sympathy from the Fianna Fáil and Fine Gael Deputies and Senators. They are all saying what great work school secretaries and caretakers do. A commitment is required here today from those Deputies and Senators to go and demand of higher-ups in the political parties they represent that this will be resolved.</p>
          <p eId="para_123"> In regard to caretakers, when I was teaching I worked with a caretaker to build an outside garden with some of the students. He did all the woodwork. For stand up week for LGBT, it is the caretakers who put up the flags and all of that. They get involved in the life of the school. I am shocked and horrified that they are still in this position. I would have hoped it would be resolved.</p>
          <p eId="para_124"> The secretaries do crucial work, talking to parents, management, teachers and students. It is disgraceful that the skills that are required and the work they do have been historically undervalued. That includes the remark that they are women looking for work-life balance. That can feed into a stereotype of pin money and that kind of thing that is in people's heads. Maybe Mr. Pike could comment on this idea of causing contagion. What is the problem with contagion? These people should be public sector workers.</p>
          <p eId="para_125"> Is there any legal recourse that could be taken as well as the strike action? Has Fórsa looked into that? It seems highly discriminatory that there is recognition for a clerical officer but not actually pension recognition.</p>
          <p eId="para_126"> Lastly, because I want to give Mr. Pike a chance to answer these questions, while it is great that the Minister wants to resolve this issue, I am sure Fórsa has seen all this sympathy before. Has Fórsa considered approaching the other unions? I have been on strike as a teacher. Inter-union and picket-line solidarity has broken down over a long time. We need that kind of solidarity. Would the other unions come out and support the secretaries and the caretakers for that day? Is that something that could be looked at?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_72">
          <from> Mr. Andy Pike<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_127">In response to the previous questions from Senator Conway, we are very grateful for the support of Independent Senators and TDs, including the Minister of State, Deputy Seán Canney, who is a close acquaintance of Ms Carty and from the same part of the world.</p>
          <p eId="para_128"> In relation to discussions with other trade unions, we are going to talk to the INTO, the TUI and ASTI formally about arrangements for the strike, which commences on 28 August. We have not yet had any formal discussions with them. Our position is we cannot advise them what they should do. It is up to them to advise their own members. All we can say to them is that where a secretary and-or a caretaker is standing outside their school picketing, it is an official picket. Where that happens, if you are a member of a trade union, and the school sector is heavily unionised, as members will know, it is an individual decision whether to cross a picket line or not. We are not issuing any request. We will operate within the confines of the Industrial Relations Act 1990 as well. Only workers who have been balloted for a strike under that legislation can take strike action.</p>
          <p eId="para_129"> We have thought this through. We are at the end of the road with begging, pleading, writing nice letters and petitioning. We have done all that. There is no other option. We have thought long and hard about this and we think our members deserve the opportunity to fight for fair treatment. They have been begging for too long. There is now a sufficient number of them in the union that this industrial action will be effective. Yes, there will be disruption. That is unfortunate. The disruption is the fault of those who have not allowed them into the public service pay system.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JenCummins" eId="spk_73">
          <from>Deputy Jen Cummins<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_130">I am delighted to have the witnesses here today. People may not know but I am a member of Fórsa. I was in the school completion programme branch for a very long time. I was delighted to be at the Fórsa education conference at the Easter break.</p>
          <p eId="para_131"> We in the Social Democrats fully support this strike action. We need to be very clear here. There will be huge disruption but that is the point of a strike. If it is not disruptive, then there is no point. People need to know that strike action is the end of the road. Anyone who has been in a union knows that when you take strike action it is the last resort. Nobody wants to do that. Certainly nobody working in a school wants to take strike action. They do not because it means that nothing else is working. It is not right that we have this situation. I have heard today about the pay disparity between ETB staff and non-ETB staff. That is unacceptable.</p>
          <p eId="para_132">I am quite annoyed. I will try to calm down a little bit, but it is just so infuriating that throughout my working life, the most vulnerable staff members in the education system have constantly had to fight for what is a basic right. A pension is not a gift; it is a right. People should be protected in employment contracts and should not have to sign on over the summer months. For some people, and I have experience of this, it is an absolute nightmare to sign on over the summer, particularly if a person is jointly assessed with somebody else. He or she may not get anything. That affects later pension contributions from the State. Anything we can do to support the witnesses, we will do.</p>
          <p eId="para_133"> Is there anything our witnesses would like to say? I do not have a question; I am just delighted they are here. I am thankful to Deputy O'Rourke for suggesting this, and we will write. Is there anything our witnesses would like to say here? I am happy to give that time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_74">
          <from> Mr. Andy Pike<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_134">I thank the Deputy. I will respond to a question Deputy Coppinger asked. We have looked at the legal issues here. There are some stark legal problems the employer side, the Department, would have. Our difficulty is that the last case on pensions brought by a union in the schools' sector was the Mary Boyle case, and the Department of education simply appealed it all the way to the Supreme Court. Therefore, for those members we have who are within five years of retirement, the legal route is not going to be helpful. The Department could string out a legal case for ten years. The Boyle case took that long to reach a final conclusion.</p>
          <p eId="para_135"> In response to Deputy Jen Cummins's question as to what we would ask the committee, I would say the support is really welcomed by all our members. If we consider a caretaker in a school, the school might employ 50 teachers and 20 SNAs, but there is going to be only one person in that workplace involved in this strike. It is a really brave thing for our members to say they are going to do this. Please keep up that level of support.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_75">
          <from> Ms Luisa Carty<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_136">I thank everybody for their support, which is greatly appreciated by all school secretaries and caretakers. It is invaluable to us. Hopefully, we go places with this. We want to go all the way.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_76">
          <from> Mr. David Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_137">We do not want to go on strike. The start of the school year is just as important to us as it is to parents and new students coming in. It is a chance for us to meet the students who are coming into our lives for the next eight years. They are coming into the school’s life for eight years. We get to know them from little tots to lads who are nearly as tall as me, and I am 6 ft 4 in. The school is a massive part of our lives and we go above and beyond for it but unfortunately we are forgotten by the Government. We are waiting three years for our pay to be sorted, never mind the pension. Here we are in 2025 sitting in front of this committee still looking for equality in the workplace.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_77">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_138">Deputy Currie has four minutes. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EmerCurrie" eId="spk_78">
          <from>Deputy Emer Currie<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_139">I am sorry for arriving late, but I had another meeting this morning. I do not want to be one of those people who asks the witnesses things they have already been asked. I completely agree with our witnesses that secretaries and caretakers, by the very nature of the work they do, do not want to be in this position or to put parents or schools in this position.</p>
          <p eId="para_140"> Like many parents, I am on a first name terms with our school secretary and caretaker. I have our school secretary’s number in my phone. In many ways, she is the face of our school. She provides not only all of the practical support but looks after a growing list of responsibilities, and provides emotional support to students. I am very grateful for that. This is going on far too long, and I take the point about the industrial relations structure and that it seems to be about delay.</p>
          <p eId="para_141"> Our witnesses are looking for action today and it is the very least they deserve. They have my support and that of my colleagues and this committee. If the witnesses could recap for me their engagement with the Department thus far, that would help.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_79">
          <from> Mr. Andy Pike<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_142">A recap on the engagement will be quick. There has not been any yet. There may be in future, but there has not been any yet. We have written to the Department of Education and Youth stating we are available for face to face discussions on the basis that members will be admitted to the single public service pension scheme. We are not necessarily prepared to go through endless discussions where, at the end of the day, the Department of public expenditure and reform says no. We need a commitment that the basis of the talks will be the how and when secretaries and caretakers will be admitted to the scheme because from that flows the benefits of public service status that are enjoyed, and have been for many years, by teachers and SNAs.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EmerCurrie" eId="spk_80">
          <from>Deputy Emer Currie<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_143">I thank Mr. Pike.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_81">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_144">I am the last in this round of speakers. Afterwards I am going to go back down to the list. Members might get 30 seconds each to pose additional questions. We will group them and we will give the last word to our guests from Fórsa.</p>
          <p eId="para_145"> I was a primary school teacher for 15 years. We placed huge value on our school secretary and caretaker. The school would not have functioned with them. As teachers, we operate in a silo. Once a teacher has that morning coffee at quarter to nine, he or she is in the classroom until the break and then back in again. The constant person in the school who the public interfaces with as they came through the door is the secretary as well as the caretaker who does everything from hanging pictures and notice boards to cleaning and setting out pitches. They both do invaluable work.</p>
          <p eId="para_146"> Like others, I come from a position of huge support but I wish to troubleshoot a few things that do not sit quite right in my head. It is not good to generalise but as Deputy Dempsey said earlier, rightly, most secretaries - at least in my experience locally - seem to be female while most caretakers seem to be male. That is just how it seems to pan out. The other point I wish to make about caretakers is that many of them seem to be older - again, in my experience locally - although it is great to see that Mr. Hearne is a young man. By migrating them over to becoming public servants might we have the unintended consequence of making many of them redundant? I can think of several local caretakers over the age of 70 years. They would have to retire if they were public servants. Many of these men have already retired from a previous forms of work. They are pensioned. This is a top-up income. They do a superb job, but they could lose their pension by migrating over to this.</p>
          <p eId="para_147"> The third point I wish to make is that because of the ancillary grant schools used for taking on caretakers, I know of many local schools who contracted in the local person who does lawns, hedges, etc. He is able to do his own work and work in the school for eight or ten hours a day. There are bigger schools where this is every day of the week and every hour of the day, but I am talking about rural schools.</p>
          <p eId="para_148"> This is campaign has huge support but are there unintended consequences that mean some of Fórsa’s members, by virtue this campaign, could be knocked out of the employment realm?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_82">
          <from> Mr. Andy Pike<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_149">We looked at those issues long before we started to ballot members and campaign. If a caretaker needs to stay on his or her current terms and conditions for whatever reason, he or she would be able to. What happened with the school secretary pay agreement was that secretaries were given the option of taking those terms, and 80% of them did because they worked out it was beneficial. Some 20% did not for whatever reason. When a similar agreement is finalised for caretakers, they will be able to weigh up the pros and cons and the benefits of moving across. They will be able to stay on their existing terms and conditions if they wish to. They would not automatically have to retire when they reach the age of 70. They could stay on their local contract.</p>
          <p eId="para_150"> If they move across into a new pay arrangement with access to the pension and they already have a pension from previous public sector employment, perhaps in An Garda Síochána, the Defence Forces or some other occupation, the normal rules on pension abatement would apply. They would not lose their existing pension. They would be able to continue to make contributions to the public service scheme up to the limit that applies to all public servants. They would not lose their existing pension. The normal rules on abatement, if one already has a pension, would apply.</p>
          <p eId="para_151"> We do not necessarily see any disruption in the labour market due to making this change, and that is solely because there needs to be an option for a caretaker to accept a new contract with these terms or to say that he or she is happy staying as he or she is.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_83">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_152">I hope Fórsa will not have to strike and some deal is struck between now and then. However, if it does get to a point in late August where the strike is inevitable, will Fórsa in communiques to its members explain that?</p>
          <p eId="para_153">I have had some of them onto me anxious about that unintended consequence. Of course everyone wants better pay and conditions. They should be made aware that the position Fórsa seeks to negotiate is to protect those over the age of 70 who have already retired from another form of employment, or have taken on other contractual work in the community.</p>
          <p eId="para_154"> That concludes the main body of questioning. I going to move down through members. We are going to group these and reset our clock to 30 seconds. I will start with Deputy Emer Currie.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EmerCurrie" eId="spk_84">
          <from>Deputy Emer Currie<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_155">I thank the witnesses for their contributions. They have covered everything in depth. I will raise the matter with the Minister and look for action on their behalf.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarrenORourke" eId="spk_85">
          <from>Deputy Darren O'Rourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_156">I do not have a question, but I want to highlight some of our frustrations. The Minister for public expenditure will be before the Dáil for oral questions next week. I submitted a question specifically around the engagement with Fórsa on this issue. It has been rejected and diverted to the Minister for Education and Youth. That is part of the frustration at this end.</p>
          <p eId="para_157"> Some of the witnesses will know Teresa, who is the secretary in the school that my children go to. She has been out on this issue. She has been in the job for 27 years and is incredible. It is totally unjust and unfair. When our kids are learning their letters, they say that "B is for Bernard". Who is Bernard? He is the caretaker. That just happens organically and naturally because he is at the heart of everything in the school. That is replicated across the country.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterRoche" eId="spk_86">
          <from>Deputy Peter Roche<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_158">As my colleague, Deputy Currie, has said, we will be bringing this to the attention of the relevant Ministers. We did not need to be reminded before today that we would have to do that, but I thank the witnesses for their engagement thus far. They have thrown a light on an area that needed it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GarethScahill" eId="spk_87">
          <from>Senator Gareth Scahill<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_159">I reiterate what my colleagues have said. I thank the witnesses for coming in. I found it informative. We will be following up on this and I wish them good luck.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulineTully" eId="spk_88">
          <from>Senator Pauline Tully<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_160">I thank the witnesses for coming here and I pledge my support for them. We will do anything we can to push this issue forward. I hope it is resolved before it leads to a strike. That is the last thing people want, but I understand why they would do it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeConway" eId="spk_89">
          <from>Senator Joe Conway<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_161">I have nothing further to add only to wish the people in Fórsa the very best in their mighty efforts to get these anomalies and unfairnesses dealt with by the Department of public expenditure.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RuthCoppinger" eId="spk_90">
          <from>Deputy Ruth Coppinger<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_162">I thank the representatives from Fórsa for coming and I wish them all the best with the campaign. They might consider a leaflet for the picket line that explains the issue to parents. I am sure that Fórsa has already thought of this, but I am mentioning it just in case it has not. Parents could then put pressure on their TDs and it could broaden the issue out. Fórsa might also consider a policy of no representatives from Government parties taking selfies on the picket line, which is another thing I see happening. I wish them the best of luck with the campaign.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JenCummins" eId="spk_91">
          <from>Deputy Jen Cummins<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_163">I wish the witnesses the best of luck. I hope it does not get to strike action, but in another way I hope it does because I think enough is enough. There is a point where people have tried everything they can and if this where it has to go, it is where it has to go. I do not want that for the witnesses and I know they do not want it either. However, it does need to be highlighted. I am glad that people here have heard what the witnesses have said and will go back and raise the issue with their colleagues. We will not only raise it as a committee, but also as individuals. The more pressure we can put on, the better. I wish the witnesses the best of luck and thank them for their contributions</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_92">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_164">I thank the witnesses for coming in. In their wrap-up, could they illustrate how secretaries and caretakers struggle to access basic things like mortgages and health insurance? While everyone has financial constraints, their colleague down the corridor at least has the knowledge that they have a pay cheque coming in every fortnight. Could the witnesses illustrate some of the constraints and tight situations their colleagues are facing?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_93">
          <from> Mr. Andy Pike<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_165">The biggest problem over the years has been the lay-off when schools are closed. When schools are closed, many secretaries and caretakers are laid off. They get no pay from the school. They have to go to the Department of social protection to get jobseeker's benefit if they are entitled to it. This creates a lot of uncertainty and precarious employment. The lack of respect and dignity has also been a huge problem.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_94">
          <from> Ms Luisa Carty<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_166">Until we got moved over to the Department payroll, we had just that. You could not apply for a mortgage, a car loan or any of the normal everyday necessities. You were signing on over the summer holidays and different breaks. Some people who were on a widow's pension because someone belonging to them had died could not get anything during the breaks. They were losing money in that sense.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_95">
          <from> Mr. David Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_167">From the financial side of things with caretakers, the day-to-day necessities are covered, but we cannot afford the little extras that we might enjoy on the weekend. It is as simple as that. I am paying a mortgage. I am lucky enough that my wife is teacher. She works in the same school. She does around a 30-hour week, but still comes out with over €250 extra than me. She does amazing work. All teachers do. I am not taking that from them. They work they do in school is amazing, but yet we work 40-hour weeks and at the end of it what do we have to show for it? The mental distress it is putting on caretakers and secretaries is phenomenal. We set up a Telegram group over the past six months. The caretakers who come on are seriously distressed. They do not know where they will go for the next loaf of bread. In the wintertime, how are they going to turn on the light or the heating? We want to get rid of that anxiety. We want equality in the workplace, with everyone on the same flow. We want to be looked after. Caretakers look after the school community, but the Department does not want to take care of us.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_96">
          <from> Ms Luisa Carty<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_168">Our retirement is equally as important as everyone else's retirement. We give the time to our schools and should be rewarded in the same way as our colleagues. We should not be the only ones who are left out.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_97">
          <from> Mr. Andy Pike<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_169">David came up with this quote at our conference:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_170">It is a reflection on what happens on your last day of employment in the school. On your last day of employment, you would see the teacher and the SNA retire with a bunch of flowers, a box of chocolates, good wishes and an appropriate public service pension based on their years of work. They walk out with their lump sum and access their pension.</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_171">When a caretaker or a secretary retire in that same school, the only thing they get is a bunch of flowers and a bottle of whiskey if they are lucky. They get nothing else.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_98">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_172">Just before we conclude things, we had a proposal from Deputy Darren O'Rourke, which our committee has agreed to. Arising from Senator Tully's questions about the ETBs and the responses from the witnesses, can we get agreement to find out from the Department of public expenditure the history of how this arrangement - the disparity between those on ETB central contracts and those on local school or board contracts - came about? Is there agreement that those two actions be followed up by the secretariat and that the correspondence be circulated to all members? Is that agreed? Agreed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JenCummins" eId="spk_99">
          <from>Deputy Jen Cummins<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_173">We do not need the historical reasons for it, although it would be good to put it into context; we need to know what the Department is going to do to rectify it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_100">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_174">That is Deputy O'Rourke's proposal. Absolutely. On behalf of the entire committee, I warmly thank the witnesses for attending today. I also thank their colleagues in the Public Gallery and the many more who have watched from home for their engagement with the committee. We will now briefly suspend the meeting to allow the witnesses for the next session to take their seats. Is that agreed? Agreed.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_6">
          <i>Sitting suspended at 10.49 a.m. and resumed at 10.55 a.m.</i>
        </summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>Proposed Redesignation of Schools for Children with Mild General Learning Disabilities: Principals of Special Schools<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:50:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_101">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_175">I welcome everyone this morning. I ask those attending remotely to mute themselves when they are not contributing so we do not pick up any background noise or feedback. As usual, I remind all those in attendance to ensure their mobile phones are on silent mode or switched off entirely. Those in the precincts of Leinster House are protected by absolute privilege in respect of the presentation they make to the committee. This means they have an absolute defence against any defamation action for anything they may say at the meeting. However, they are expected not to abuse this privilege and it is my duty as Cathaoirleach to ensure this privilege is not abused. Therefore, if their statements are potentially defamatory in relation to an identifiable person or entity they will be directed to discontinue their remarks. It is imperative they comply with any such direction. Members are again reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person or entity outside of the Houses or of an official of the Houses either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p>
          <p eId="para_176"> On the agenda for today's second session of the committee is the proposed redesignation of schools for children with mild general learning disabilities. I welcome Mr. Greg Browne, principal of Catherine McAuley school in Limerick; Ms Debbie O'Neill, principal of Scoil Eoin in Crumlin, Dublin 12; Mr. John Haran, principal of St. Bernadette's Special School in Letterkenny, County Donegal, who will be with us shortly; and Ms Rose-Marie Flanagan, principal of St. Anne's special school in Ennis, County Clare. They are all very welcome to today's meeting. I call on Mr. Browne to make his opening statement for which he has ten minutes. For the benefit of members, this is a combined opening statement on behalf of all four witnesses here today.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_102">
          <from> Mr. Greg Browne<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_177">On behalf of my colleagues, we thank the committee for meeting us today. The publication of Circular 39/25 has greatly alarmed not only our staff members but also our parents and the schools our pupils come from. The circular threatens our designation and, fundamentally, our ethos, which, in reality, is created by the pupils we teach.</p>
          <p eId="para_178"> It is important that committee members understand the characteristics of mild general learning disabilities which, we feel, will explain more fully our deep concerns. Between 5% and 7% of the population has a mild general learning disability, which makes it the largest cohort of students in education with a disability. The IQ range for our schools is from 50 to 79, which makes it the widest band in learning disability. Often referred to as a hidden disability, it has a number of characteristics. There are expressive and receptive language difficulties in the moderate to severe range of language disability, which on a practical level means that pupils with a mild general learning disability cannot process a huge amount of what they hear at any given time. They have major difficulties with abstract concepts, especially in maths, including time, fractions, decimals and many other maths skills required for living. They have below average reading and comprehension levels, and most pupils with a mild general learning disability lag behind their peers by several years. Many will never reach a functional reading age of nine years. They have poor self-esteem and a lack of self-management skills. They have major difficulties with fine and gross motor skills. They have major difficulties with memory, resulting in difficulties with the retention of knowledge as well as poor concentration skills. They have an inability to absorb the complexities of their environment and to make generalisations and associations from what they learn. They have an inability to see danger and imagine outcomes or consequences.</p>
          <p eId="para_179"> The famous educational psychologist Lev Vygotsky stressed the importance of language in one's overall cognitive development and the importance of structured scaffolding in the learning process, which is key to understanding a learning disability. In up to 66% of cases, a mild general learning disability is accompanied by a co-occurring disability, which impacts directly on the pupil’s ability to learn. There is co-occurrence with autism, whereby 50% of all pupils with an autism diagnosis have a mild general learning disability. </p>
          <p eId="para_180">Almost 10% of pupils with a mild general learning disability have challenging behaviour. Approximately 36% of pupils and adults with a mild general learning disability have a psychiatric disorder, which is by far the greatest cohort with psychiatric difficulties. Many of our students are being seen by the child and adolescent mental health services, CAMHS. Other disabilities include Down's syndrome, attention deficit disorder, ADD, and attention deficit hyperactivity disorder, ADHD, fragile X syndrome, Prader-Willi syndrome, global developmental delay, epilepsy, dyspraxia and selective mutism, to name but a few.</p>
          <p eId="para_181"> Why are MGLD schools so important? The development of specials schools in Ireland was initially led by religious orders and concerned parents and groups, who recognised that mainstream education did not suit the needs of a significant section of the school-going population MGLD schools have consistently shown that their pupils have greater access to an inclusive education in an environment where the pupils are at ease and work at their own pace. This allows them to access the curriculum in a more meaningful way at primary and secondary levels, with many completing junior cert levels 2 and 3, the leaving certificate applied and Quality and Qualifications Ireland, QQI, levels 1 to 4.</p>
          <p eId="para_182"> MGLD schools cater for those pupils who become marginalised in mainstream education because of learning disabilities and are in greater danger of expulsion in mainstream schools. MGLD is 14 times higher in prison inmates than in the main population, with up to 50% of all inmates having major literacy difficulties. MGLD schools have a great success rate in keeping pupils with learning difficulties in school up to the age of 18. They also have great success in providing access to either third level or further rehabilitative or vocational training, thus avoiding juvenile delinquency in their formative years.</p>
          <p eId="para_183"> MGLD schools are seen as the only hope for parents if their son or daughter is overwhelmed by the demands of mainstream education, where in many cases they have no friends as the gap between them and their peers widens with each passing year. Our schools seem to better suit the increasing number of pupils with school refusal difficulties. The right to a suitable educational placement is a cornerstone of democracy, and the right of each parent to choose our type of education is as equal as the right of any other parent to choose Educate Together schools, Gaelscoileanna or whatever they would like for their children.</p>
          <p eId="para_184"> MGLD schools have a higher proportion of students from disadvantaged areas who otherwise would have dropped out of education. They are not restrictive in their designation. In fact, what I have just stated clearly shows that our schools are the most diverse schools in Ireland.</p>
          <p eId="para_185"> Staff in MGLD schools have been some of the most innovative people in Irish education. The present-day levels 1 and 2 programmes owe their origin to the self-designed programmes that MGLD schools created over the last seven decades.</p>
          <p eId="para_186"> Our schools cater for more pupils from broken homes or in foster care and residential care than mainstream schools. We are often the one constant in their lives over many years of upheaval, and are advocates for them both while in school and when they have left after the age of 18.</p>
          <p eId="para_187"> Our schools build up networks of contacts with social workers and the HSE. In an age of online danger with social media, our school structure allows us to be most diligent about child protection for the most vulnerable and at-risk pupils.</p>
          <p eId="para_188"> Our schools cater for boys and girls whose learning disability results in severe shyness, oddities in behaviour and social interaction, low self-morale and self-esteem, autistic traits even if undiagnosed and those who might not attend school daily if we did not exist. In respect of our pupils with autism, the majority are not in autism-specific classes with a ratio of one teacher to six pupils but rather in larger MGLD classes with a ratio of one teacher to 11 pupils. The educational value of this is obvious, especially regarding socialisation and language development.</p>
          <p eId="para_189"> On Circular 39/25, our schools have major concerns. The first relates to our admissions policies. Until now, parents of prospective students applied to our schools directly, with a copy of an educational assessment showing that the pupils had a mild or borderline mild general learning disability and a recommendation for a place in our schools. These applications would then be approved at board of management level, followed by approval by our school special educational needs organiser, SENO. The circular proposes to majorly restrict the role of the board of management in its own admissions. Parents now have to seek approval from their own school SENO first to be eligible to apply for our schools. In my own case, up to ten different SENOs would determine who can or cannot apply to my school. This restrictive practice raises the question as to what will happen if a request for a letter of eligibility is refused by a SENO despite the pupil meeting the criteria of the school’s enrolment policy. Principals of MGLD schools may not even be aware of who is seeking a place in their schools.</p>
          <p eId="para_190"> No other sector in education would allow such control of admissions. To expect that parents and schools would have applied to their SENO by 1 October in the year previous to enrolment in our schools is unacceptable, to say the least, with the continuous difficulties in trying to get National Educational Psychological Service, NEPS, or private assessments. Our own system at present has its proper checks and balances for admissions. Our schools do not canvass for pupils but parents approach us, often in desperation, seeking our help. Most of our schools accept pupils only after they have experienced mainstream education and parents are then in a better position to make an informed decision.</p>
          <p eId="para_191"> Our immediate concern is that pupils with a borderline mild general learning disability will not be recognised, as recent National Council for Special Education, NCSE, pressure on our schools not to accept these pupils indicates. The circular states, "Category of special educational needs that is not in line with NCSE guidelines for the operation of special classes." That is a direct threat to our schools and the ethos, experience, superb teaching practices and dedication our schools have cultivated since the 1950s.</p>
          <p eId="para_192"> Second, our principals, staff and parents see in the circular as a clear attempt to initiate a drastic change in all special schools with the creation of a one-size-fits-all special school where the range of disability would cover all forms. We believe our schools would be used to rob Peter to pay Paul, with places going to children with much more complex needs. None of us will disagree with the need for proper provision for these children, but not at the expense of children with other needs and disabilities. This is neither just nor fair.</p>
          <p eId="para_193"> In my 40 years in special education, the increase in autism diagnoses is probably the most significant issue to affect special schools. Our schools have carried a huge proportion of this load, with up to 50% of our intake now having an autism diagnosis, coupled with the slow but steady increase in the number of students with pathological demand avoidance. There has been no proper definition of the term "complex needs" but it is taken to mean pupils with very challenging behaviour along with non-verbal difficulties, allied to learning difficulties in the moderate to severe range of learning disabilities. With the increase in pupils with such complex difficulties, a comprehensive plan needs to be formulated not just for their school years but also for after-school provision. This will take time but should not be done at the expense of pupils with a mild general learning disability. Pupils with complex needs need a suite of therapies on site along with purpose-built classrooms to cater for their needs.</p>
          <p eId="para_194"> Mild general learning disability schools have been in existence for many years and have served their students and families well. We are an integral part in the continuum of provision of suitable educational opportunities for those pupils with a mild or borderline mild general learning disability.</p>
          <p eId="para_195">Our schools are the envy of many teachers from Europe and elsewhere in the world, who visit us regularly and comment that their educational systems need our approach. Our work gives a much more educational and human meaning to the term "inclusion", which is often bandied about. The right of every student to attend a school of their choosing applies as equally to our students as to the boy or girl who seeks the primary or secondary school of their choice. Were our schools to be forced to change their designation, the immediate problem of the lack of places for pupils with complex needs would be replaced by the greater problem of increased school drop-out and expulsions. That a disability is not initially apparent does not mean it does not exist. The success of mild intellectual disability special schools in helping our students to access education should not be used as a reason to say our pupils would survive in mainstream schools with supports. For them, this has already been tried and has failed.</p>
          <p eId="para_196"> Our schools are not just places of learning; they are the homes and communities that most would not otherwise have. The term "complex" can be applied as easily to our students as it can to those with extreme behavioural needs. The demand for our schools is greater than ever, with over half having increased enrolments in recent years, while others are at full capacity given the restrictions of their sites. We simply ask that we be allowed to continue the good work we have been doing for those pupils whose disability is not as evident as that of others but nevertheless every bit as real.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_103">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_197">I thank Mr. Browne. We welcome Mr. John Haran, who has joined the witnesses. Ms Debbie O'Neill, one of our witnesses, has a letter from a parent to put on the record of the committee's proceedings. I invite her to proceed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_104">
          <from> Ms Debbie O'Neill<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_198">Given that we have given the committee a lot of factual information and statistics, I want to read a letter from a parent of a child in our school. We are going to call her "Aoife" just to keep the anonymity. You could replace "Scoil Eoin" with any of our four schools.</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_199">Dear committee members,</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_200">My daughter Aoife is 14. She has Mild General Learning Disability and her life revolves around Scoil Eoin. The plan to re-designate this school would leave children like her with nowhere to go. I'm heartbroken and deeply concerned.</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_201">Mainstream schools cannot give Aoife what she has at Scoil Eoin. Here, she plays soccer without being laughed at. If she scores into the wrong goal, she's still celebrated. She sings loudly in choir, off-key, and no one minds. She belongs.</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_202">At Scoil Eoin, Aoife is not falling behind. She is seen for who she is. She has friends. She is learning. She is confident. She is happy.</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_203">That wasn't always the case. In mainstream school, she cried every day. She called herself stupid. She couldn't keep up and was laughed at and excluded. Her self-worth disappeared. She was lost.</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_204">Now she thinks her school is like every other school. She doesn't realise the curriculum is adapted but here, she is finally learning. She is proud of herself.</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_205">Re-designating Scoil Eoin will remove the one place where children like Aoife are supported, understood and safe. Mainstream schools do not have the resources or expertise to support children like her. And the cost will be high; her mental health, her confidence, her future.</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_206">Scoil Eoin didn't just educate Aoife; it saved her. It gave her a sense of self-worth and belonging. Please don't take that away.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_105">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_207">I thank Ms O'Neill. On behalf of the committee, she might thank Aoife and her parents for laying bare how important all of this is to their family. The letter will be on the record of today's meeting.</p>
          <p eId="para_208"> We will proceed to members' questions. Each Deputy and Senator has four minutes. In that time, they should allow witnesses time to respond, so they should not fully run down the clock.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AislingDempsey" eId="spk_106">
          <from>Deputy Aisling Dempsey<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_209">I thank our guests for being here and for statements. I had a number of questions in mind that I was going to ask. It is quite difficult for me to decide where I stand on this topic because on the one hand, I want every child to go to the school that is geographically closest, where their siblings and neighbours are, and where their little friends in the local GAA club are, and on the other hand, I have had many mothers approach me since my election to say their children with dyslexia do not get the support they need because there are so many kids in their classes or schools with complex needs or autism, meaning those schools are just not able to provide what they need. The ideal is obviously a place for the child in your school, but, on the other hand, there has been an increase in diagnosis over the years. The guests have talked about their ethos since the 1950s but so much has changed since then that I really struggle with the idea of schools that deal with just one cohort. I am aware that is difficult. I could not do the delegates' job in a million years and I am sure it is really difficult. Their schools sound like fabulous places and Aoife is a lucky girl, as are her parents. I am not sure I have a question. I just wanted to say where I am really stuck on this.</p>
          <p eId="para_210"> I read the circular. I understand it is a matter of the opening discussion. I assume the delegates will engage in the process. Maybe the Minister has engaged with them directly. They might let me know.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_107">
          <from> Ms Debbie O'Neill<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_211">I will answer that. We have had no engagement. We have done a lot of media engagement on this over the past while and, despite the Minister saying there would be engagement with us, there has not been any. This is not a new thing. Redesignation has not so much been threatened – "threatened" is not the right word – but mentioned a lot over the past few years without there being an understanding of who we are and what we do. Narrow designation is referred to a lot. We have proven in our statement that our designation is the broadest that exists. If we were to expand it any more, we would be diluting the whole spectrum of provision on offer. In this day and age, we should be able to keep something that is working and build for the future for those who do not have a place yet. Make no mistake: if redesignation happens, while the children we have at the moment will not be forced back into mainstream education, those children we are yet to meet most definitely will. There are no special classes in mainstream education left for children with mild cases. There are 49 in the country. There were 50 but the CBS in Nenagh has just been refused permission to keep its one. There are 49 mild intellectual disability classes in mainstream schools across the country, so we do not know where our cohort will go.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_108">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_212">I thank Ms O'Neill.</p>
          <p eId="para_213"> Deputy Dempsey might have noticed that she still had 30 seconds left on the clock. The clock has malfunctioned. Until we get it working, I will manually keep time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LindaNelsonMurray" eId="spk_109">
          <from>Senator Linda Nelson Murray<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_214">I definitely will not need four minutes. I thank the delegates for attending. It was great to have read their submissions and to have heard from them. I am on the board of a mild learning disability school, a general learning disability school, so I will just listen to all the comments, if that is okay.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_110">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_215">Many of us here in this room have been teachers and have been involved at various levels. At the outset, we often declare an interest. Members are welcome to contribute if they wish. Is the Senator happy to listen?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LindaNelsonMurray" eId="spk_111">
          <from>Senator Linda Nelson Murray<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_216">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_112">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_217">No problem at all.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RyanOMeara" eId="spk_113">
          <from>Deputy Ryan O'Meara<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_218">Our guests are very welcome. I thank them very much for attending, particularly for what is a very detailed opening statement. There was such an incredible amount of information in it and it set out the issues so clearly that I am left wondering what questions need to be asked. The concerns have already been raised with me and I have been in contact with the relevant Ministers about the written submissions already sent. This conversation has arisen a few times already at meetings of this committee. Ms O'Neill mentioned the example of the CBS primary school in Nenagh. The concept of robbing Peter to pay Paul, which Mr. Browne referred to, is a matter I am genuinely worried about. </p>
          <p eId="para_219">There is great pressure in this country to find or create spaces for children with complex needs. A great deal of work is being done. Thankfully, we are going to see a lot of classes opening in September. A huge amount remains to be done, however. My worry is that one set of children who are disadvantaged in education and who are struggling will get something that others might then lose out on.</p>
          <p eId="para_220"> In view of the part of the country I represent, I am very familiar with Mr. Browne's school in Limerick because the children of local families have attended it and local people have taught there, are teaching there or were on placement there. There is probably a lack of understanding generally around this issue. We get it, as do the witnesses who work in the area. The families of students attending the schools also get it, but I do not know if other people know what these schools do. The witnesses have explained the broad scope of the work they do. I am concerned about those children who are on their last chance when it comes to education. The witnesses are holding onto these children and finding a way to keep them in school every day in order to give them a chance and keep them away from antisocial behaviour. That was outlined earlier. These children cannot be allowed to lose out just because there is so much pressure on us to facilitate complex needs. I refer in particular to the MGLD class in Nenagh CBS, which has highlighted the issue relating to children with Down's syndrome who often do not have an autism diagnosis but who have a special needs diagnosis, an MGLD diagnosis, and how hard it is for those children to get places because of the lack of autism diagnoses. Mr. Browne's school is highlighting the work done there, while also taking in children with autism diagnoses. What he said about a child in the school, Aoife, sums up exactly what we need to be concerned about.</p>
          <p eId="para_221"> There must be a meeting between the officials, the Minister and the representatives of these schools to ensure that there is full understanding of what is involved. Ministers have repeatedly told us that the purpose of the first circular is to start the conversation, but the Department also needs to hear about what is happening in this instance. We must feed it up the line and try to get a meeting for the school principals with the relevant individuals and the Minister, if possible.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_114">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_222">Is Deputy O'Meara formally proposing that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RyanOMeara" eId="spk_115">
          <from>Deputy Ryan O'Meara<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_223">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_116">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_224">Deputies Cummins and Dempsey have seconded the proposal. Is it agreed? Agreed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_117">
          <from> Mr. Greg Browne<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_225">Statistically, the Department is working off a figure of one in 20 children in education in Ireland who has a diagnosis of autism. When we take that figure to the broad expanse of education in Ireland, it is 50,000 pupils. Somewhere in the region of 15,000 of that huge cohort of 50,000 pupils have the most complex needs and need will a bespoke education. They will need intense therapies and all of the facilities the State can provide. We are not saying they do not need it; what we are clearly saying is that we have a cohort as well, which is equal in number, who would be lost in Irish society if our schools did not exist.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RyanOMeara" eId="spk_118">
          <from>Deputy Ryan O'Meara<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_226">I thank Mr. Browne very much.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_119">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_227">I thank Mr. Browne. The clock is back up and running. We will reset it entirely. I have the accurate time here. I thank all for their forbearance in that regard. Deputy O'Rourke has four minutes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarrenORourke" eId="spk_120">
          <from>Deputy Darren O'Rourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_228">I thank the committee, the secretariat and the Chair for facilitating this meeting. I also thank Deputy Cummins for proposing it. I thank the witnesses for being here.</p>
          <p eId="para_229"> It strikes me that there is a fundamental issue at stake in terms of the design and mix of our special education system. My concern, and what I hear from the witnesses, is that we have the potential to both lose and fail a significant number of children. I think of children with Down's syndrome who will quietly accept it, who will have no system to support them and who will be failed.</p>
          <p eId="para_230"> We have heard the Government spell out its argument to the effect that there is a move to deal with complex needs. Am I right in saying there is a risk that we will fail children? Is it the witnesses' argument that this is about additionality rather than a one-size-fits-all approach? Perhaps the witnesses could start with that question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_121">
          <from> Ms Rose-Marie Flanagan<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_231">There is a lot of research, particularly in respect of New Brunswick and the model that is in place there, but the reality is that it is very different in our settings. We do not even have sufficient support from the CDNTs, so, as it is, we are struggling to support these students.</p>
          <p eId="para_232"> From an academic point of view, all of our pupils experience a sense of success and of belonging. Going back to UNESCO and the Education Act, every child has a right to an education that is meaningful and respectful. Every child who attends our school settings has an education that is differentiated, whereby we adopt universal design for learning approaches. Every child experiences success at their level.</p>
          <p eId="para_233"> I worked in mainstream education for two decades so I get what it is like to be in that setting. These children are integrated, probably supported by special needs assistants and, unfortunately, they will not be active. Our students experience massive success, even in extracurricular activities. We have all had students experience success at national level, in higher competitions, and FAI soccer tournaments. We are going to fail those children. We are talking about the children of the future who will be failed. The current cohort will continue to excel.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarrenORourke" eId="spk_122">
          <from>Deputy Darren O'Rourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_234">What about the suggestion that we would have special classes? I know we do not have them and that we are losing them rather than increasing the number, but is there an argument that special classes might be an appropriate forum?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_123">
          <from> Ms Debbie O'Neill<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_235">I do not think that is going to happen. We can talk about it but, as of last year – my numbers are open to correction – there were 3,300 autism classes in mainstream schools, as opposed to the 49 or 50 for mild disabilities. Any school that has approached the Department to try to open a MGLD class has been refused. While that would be wonderful, I do not think it is on the cards.</p>
          <p eId="para_236"> Well-being in schools is often talked about these days. It should be first and foremost. Since 2019, SSE has all been around well-being. There is no well-being in this redesignation. It is all about the students being able to access level 1 and 2 programmes. What about their well-being?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarrenORourke" eId="spk_124">
          <from>Deputy Darren O'Rourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_237">I presume what the witnesses are urgently looking for is engagement on this issue. Do they get any succour from the Minister? It was stated at a previous meeting that there will not be a change in September.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_125">
          <from> Ms Debbie O'Neill<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_238">It will not happen in September. What we have heard is that we will be approached in September. My school has already been approached numerous times on the issue, but there has not been any consultation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarrenORourke" eId="spk_126">
          <from>Deputy Darren O'Rourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_239">Ms O'Neill wants to see that happen.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_127">
          <from> Mr. John Haran<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_240">In the context of autism classes, we were doing two weeks of the summer provision. Just this week I got a phone call from a parent in west Donegal who has a nine-year old child in an ASD class where it is not working out. The parent is looking for a place in our school. That happens all the time. Our school in Donegal has expanded massively in the past five years. That is down to a whole lot of reasons, including the brilliant staff and the great work going on. My door is being knocked down every day with parents looking to get their children in. Special education is so complex and varied. The MGLD schools are brilliant. Why would we want to mess that up for those children who are not as disabled as other children? The fundamental problem is that they are not as disabled, yet they have so many needs and they would be lost in mainstream education. It would just be a disaster.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarrenORourke" eId="spk_128">
          <from>Deputy Darren O'Rourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_241">I thank Mr. Haran.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_129">
          <from> Mr. Greg Browne<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_242">In my school, we have 280 students. It is the largest special school in Ireland. The demand for it is growing. I will give one example. I had a boy there who started in first year in a local secondary school. It was not working out. He was in the borderline range for mild disability, which means his IQ was between 70 and 79. I met him with his mam and had a chat with him. I asked him why he wants to come to our school and if he was not happy in his secondary school. What he said explains it.</p>
          <p eId="para_243">He said:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_244">Mr. Browne, I go to school every day. I am in classes. I do not understand one thing the teachers are telling me. I do not understand it. The only thing I know is I am not as bright as the other boys in the school.</p>
          <p eId="para_245"> That explains in a nutshell what we do with the borderline range of learning disabilities. I could not encapsulate it any better.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarrenORourke" eId="spk_130">
          <from>Deputy Darren O'Rourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_246">I thank Mr. Browne.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterRoche" eId="spk_131">
          <from>Deputy Peter Roche<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_247">The witnesses are most welcome. Like others, I need to inform myself more about what is being advised and the changes being made. Aoife's letter is compelling. Sometimes, when change is advised or recommended, an element of fear comes into it. Regardless of what is being proposed, fundamentally, special children need special educational teaching, coaching and mentoring. It would be a calamity if, in what is being proposed, one child were to be left behind. That is something of which we all must be cognisant. Every parent's nightmare is struggling to find a school place that suits his or her child. Parents want the best in life for their children. If children are forced into something that fundamentally goes against their wishes, it adds enormous pressure to an already complex situation for young parents who want the best for their child. As I said, I need to inform myself more about what is being proposed.</p>
          <p eId="para_248"> The presentations were quite compelling and graphic in terms of what the witnesses feel will happen as a consequence of the change. If it causes children to be left by the wayside or leaves them in mainstream schools without access to the resources needed, as in the case mentioned where a student did not have the capacity to learn because of the teaching methodologies or because he was not given enough time, that would be a calamity. This is not something that would rest easy with me. I want to know more about it. Whatever is proposed must be fit for purpose. It certainly should not and must not disadvantage any individual or family.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ShonaghNiRaghallaigh" eId="spk_132">
          <from>Deputy Shónagh Ní Raghallaigh<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_249">I apologise for being late. Gabhaim buíochas leis na finnéithe as a bheith anseo. I understand completely the very specialised service they provide and I agree that we need to protect the status of schools for children with mild general learning disabilities.</p>
          <p eId="para_250"> The Department has said there has been much positive engagement with principals regarding the redesignation. However, I have heard from principals I know, and seen in the media, that their hand was forced and that funding would be withdrawn if they did not redesignate the status of their schools. Will the witnesses offer more clarity on the type of funding that will be removed if schools do not comply?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_133">
          <from> Ms Rose-Marie Flanagan<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_251">My understanding is that, from a staffing point of view, schools will not be able to manage if they do not have appropriate teacher numbers and special needs assistants. That is at a very basic level. The changes would also impact on our capitation funding. We have to purchase a lot of extra materials and resources in comparison with a mainstream setting. The change would affect the running of our schools. Things are already really tight in terms of managing our finances to run our school effectively.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ShonaghNiRaghallaigh" eId="spk_134">
          <from>Deputy Shónagh Ní Raghallaigh<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_252">That suggests it is a case of hands being forced as opposed to the positive engagement the Department has indicated is happening.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_135">
          <from> Ms Rose-Marie Flanagan<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_253">Absolutely.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_136">
          <from> Ms Debbie O'Neill<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_254">That has not happened to our four schools. We have been extraordinarily steadfast in trying to hold the line on maintaining our designation. However, there certainly are schools among the group of 30 of which we are a part that have been forced to change designation. It is very disappointing to see the Minister sending out the very same letter every time somebody asks a question about this. It is stated that of the 30 schools, 16 have already broadened their designation. In fact, we have all broadened our designation to meet the need, but the schools that have had to change their policies are finding it extraordinarily difficult to cope because their designation has become so broad. One school in Dublin has had to stop offering the junior certificate because it can no longer provide the level of teaching required on the basis of the complexity of need of the children it has had to bring in. It is not okay just to broaden the designation and then not provide the resourcing to match it. That dilutes what can be offered across the entire cohort.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ShonaghNiRaghallaigh" eId="spk_137">
          <from>Deputy Shónagh Ní Raghallaigh<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_255">I am trying to learn. What is the difference between the schools that have broadened their designation and the change in policy?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_138">
          <from> Ms Rose-Marie Flanagan<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_256">The NCSE approached a number of schools for children with mild disabilities to cater for children with a moderate diagnosis. Schools in a local area might have taken children from the next town or from other counties that have no school places. They have been forced to open moderate classes, and that is ring-fenced separately in terms of their admissions policy.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_139">
          <from> Ms Debbie O'Neill<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_257">What is proposed in the circular, or what has been explained to us at least, is that admissions policies will need to change. Right now, our admissions policy is that a child must have a mild general learning disability. However, as Mr. Browne said, 60% of children with a mild learning disability have a co-occurring disability. It is not the narrow designation the Department is claiming it to be.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_140">
          <from> Mr. Greg Browne<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_258">We are here today because we serve a particular group of students in Irish education who have disabilities. They may not have the complex behavioural needs of other children but they are as important in the Irish education system as children with complex needs. There is a danger, as Deputy O'Meara said, of robbing Peter to pay Paul. There is going to be a crisis concerning children with complex needs. Everybody is aware of that, and the statistics bear it out. As I said, if there are 50,000 children with a diagnosis of autism, 16,000 of them will have complex needs. If we divide that 16,000 by six per class, we can work out the maths as to how many classes the Department will have to provide.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulineTully" eId="spk_141">
          <from>Senator Pauline Tully<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_259">I welcome the witnesses and thank them for attending. We all agree that every child has the right to an education in an appropriate setting. The requirement that it be appropriate to their needs is what is important. Preferably, it should be in the child's locality, alongside his or her siblings, but that is not always possible. Account must also be taken of student and parental choice. Do the witnesses find they are getting more applications from parents of children with complex needs? If so, are they having to turn them down?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_142">
          <from> Mr. John Haran<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_260">We are receiving applications from children within our designation, that is, the mild range. Perhaps that is because parents know St. Bernadette's Special School is a school for children with a mild general learning disability. Little Angels Special School is the school in Letterkenny for children with moderate and profound learning disabilities. However, we will very soon have a waiting list, which we have never had in our history. Our school will have 125 students in September, which takes us very close to capacity. We are getting loads of applications from the students who should be coming to us.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulineTully" eId="spk_143">
          <from>Senator Pauline Tully<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_261">Mr. Haran's school is seeing an increase in applications that are appropriate.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_144">
          <from> Mr. John Haran<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_262">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_145">
          <from> Ms Debbie O'Neill<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_263">The majority of our schools are seeing an increase in numbers.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulineTully" eId="spk_146">
          <from>Senator Pauline Tully<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_264">There has been an increase in the number of appropriate applications.</p>
          <p eId="para_265">Is that because there are not enough special classes in schools?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_147">
          <from> Ms Rose-Marie Flanagan<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_266">No.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulineTully" eId="spk_148">
          <from>Senator Pauline Tully<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_267">It has been said there were 50 but it is now 49 and schools have been refused.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_149">
          <from> Ms Rose-Marie Flanagan<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_268">In the context of my own school, children have moved from special classes in post-primary settings to our own setting. We find that the predominate increase in children applying are in fourth, fifth and sixth class in primary school because their primary school is not able to meet their needs. The same applies in post-primary. Mr. Browne mentioned a child who had completed first year in his school. It is very common for children to transition into our school for post-primary because basically they are being failed in the mainstream post-primary school. Unfortunately, they are having no meaningful relationships with peers and are left isolated. We know that we Maslow before we Bloom in our school context. Unfortunately, in mainstream settings there are class sizes of 30 children and more, so these children are being left behind and failed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulineTully" eId="spk_150">
          <from>Senator Pauline Tully<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_269">Concerns have been expressed about the circular. Did Ms Flanagan say the NCSE has not engaged in consultation? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_151">
          <from> Ms Rose-Marie Flanagan<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_270">There has been no consultation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulineTully" eId="spk_152">
          <from>Senator Pauline Tully<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_271">Was there none at all?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_153">
          <from> Ms Rose-Marie Flanagan<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_272">No. The Minister of State, Deputy Moynihan, visited our school and it was very positive. We were lucky to have Deputy Cathal Crowe with us on the day as well. I felt heard but I have been very disappointed since. Many parents had parliamentary questions tabled and the feedback has been very disappointing. I felt it was a box-ticking exercise but there was no mention of the circular. I highlighted the need for the NCSE to be aware of the excellent work being done in our school settings. We did feel heart but unfortunately it looks like that was not----- </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulineTully" eId="spk_154">
          <from>Senator Pauline Tully<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_273">The Department has determined that Ms Flanagan's school is not an appropriate school setting for a child with more complex needs. We need to look at that. The witnesses' schools are special schools.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_155">
          <from> Ms Rose-Marie Flanagan<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_274">Yes. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulineTully" eId="spk_156">
          <from>Senator Pauline Tully<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_275">Will they qualify for the therapeutic supports the Department is rolling out, starting with special schools? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_157">
          <from> Ms Rose-Marie Flanagan<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_276">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulineTully" eId="spk_158">
          <from>Senator Pauline Tully<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_277">I presume that will make an immense difference.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_159">
          <from> Ms Rose-Marie Flanagan<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_278">Absolutely.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulineTully" eId="spk_160">
          <from>Senator Pauline Tully<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_279">As has been said, the CDNTs are practically non-existent on the ground.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_161">
          <from> Ms Rose-Marie Flanagan<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_280">Yes. The query is how the Department is going to get the staff.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulineTully" eId="spk_162">
          <from>Senator Pauline Tully<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_281">Yes, I know.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_163">
          <from> Ms Rose-Marie Flanagan<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_282">If the CDNT unit does not have the staff, how will the Department get the staff?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_164">
          <from> Ms Debbie O'Neill<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_283">We were part of the same project, the school inclusion model, SIM, over the past number of years. The model started in 2018 and we were one of the pilot schools. After the Covid pandemic, we had a speech and language therapist but no occupational therapist. The SIM pilot project was hailed as a success but the only thing we got over the six years of SIM was a speech and language therapist and an occupational therapist for a few visits who taught us some strategies around visuals. There were no therapeutic interventions with children. If that is going to be the same again, it is not going to cut it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulineTully" eId="spk_165">
          <from>Senator Pauline Tully<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_284">We are given to understand that is not the case and SIM will be expanded. I hope that is the case because children need that support and it is not being provided on the ground.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_166">
          <from> Ms Debbie O'Neill<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_285">I agree.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_167">
          <from> Ms Rose-Marie Flanagan<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_286">In my school we have had to privately fund therapies. As we do not have sufficient therapies, we are spending in excess of €5,000 a month. I commend the staff and, in particular, the parents' association which has been fantastic at fund-raising to support that need. Without those supports, we would be at breaking point.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_168">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_287">All going well, we may get another short contribution from everyone. I am next on the speaking roster. I thanked Mr. Browne privately. A family member of mine got a wonderful ten years of education experience in his school. It was not all books; it was gardening, musicals and all of those fabulous things that allowed the person to grow and flourish. That personal development has stood to them to this day and they are long gone out of the system. I thank Mr. Browne.</p>
          <p eId="para_288"> I thank Ms O'Neill for reading her letter into the record, Mr. Haran for joining us from Donegal and Ms Flanagan for bringing us around her school on the day we visited and on the day I visited subsequently.</p>
          <p eId="para_289"> I will home in on one point. It is 20 years since the EPSEN Act was passed and we have spent 20 years getting our heads around the work of SENOs. To raise a bugbear of mine, I would not walk down the street to any of the hospitals here in Dublin, stand at the front door and decide, with my qualifications, who gets to gain access to the emergency department, who goes up upstairs to neurology or who gets admitted. I do not have the professional skill set to do that, yet we have similar expectations of SENOs. I have treble-checked and the qualification criteria have not changed in 20 years. The entry requirement is QQI level 8, which is a bachelor's degree. That is what SENOs have. They are good people who are qualified in a certain area. Are they qualified to interpret and dismiss an educational psychological report? For years, as a teacher, we just accepted this and bemoaned it in our staffroom when these reports were thrown out or thrown back at us. It was not until a few years ago that a parent, who was legally trained, made the point that no one travelling home on a motorway would pull over at roadworks, get out of the car and tell the engineers a bridge should be built differently and no one would tell other professionals that a certain person should not get into hospital. In no professional walk of like would that happen, yet we have put SENOs in that position. SENOs do a fine job collectively but the legal point should be made that we have parents, schools, NEPS and CDNTs and we have volumes of files and reports, yet this circular will put the SENO in the position of gatekeeper for these schools. What is the witnesses' take on that?</p>
          <p eId="para_290"> I said at the outset that no one can be named, including SENOs. SENOs are a collective and an entity under the EPSEN Act. Do the witnesses have faith in SENOs to interpret the circular and approve the admission of a child to a school based on the evidence in front of them?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_169">
          <from> Mr. Greg Browne<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_291">Our schools always have good working relationships with SENOs. In 99% of cases, SENOs have been very helpful. The Chairman's point is well made. As I mentioned in our presentation, the checks and balances that we had in our admission policies worked. For example, we did not accept any child who was not in our range. The child had to have an educational psychological assessment clearly stating their IQ, with a recommendation by a psychologist to come to our schools. Those are the fundamentals of our admissions policies. Now, the system is in reverse. The parents must contact their local SENO and get a letter for eligibility by 1 October of any year. By 1 October of this year, parents will have to have most of their paperwork in place to apply to have their child attend our schools next September. The power has been taken from the board of management. The checks are in our schools. We never break our admission policies. Children must have the proper IQ, there has to be a recommendation and board of management approval and, finally, the SENOs will sign off to say we are not abusing the system. That is now going the other way, however. We had a perfect system for special schools in place. It allowed no abuse. It was not that we were inflating or keeping our numbers artificially high for other reasons. We keep within the guidelines of our enrolment policies and they are approved by our patron. I hope I have answered the question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_170">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_292">Yes. We have to be careful about how we go about this. This point has been challenged by individual families representing their individual children. I think the committee should ask the NCSE a question. The NCSE set the entry criteria for people to become a SENO. Given that the new circular is out and will, we believe, be implemented, are SENOs professionally qualified and legally entitled to interpret and, on occasion, dismiss reports by educational psychologists? In particular, do they have equal or even superior qualifications? Unless I have totally misunderstood all professional life and the QQI qualifications, in the professional world the only way that someone can dismiss a report is if they are of equal or higher professional standing. That is how it works in healthcare. We have all been to the GP who will refer us on to a consultant or maybe a surgeon. There is no gatekeeper at the door saying, "Sorry, you cannot get in here." The committee should ask that question. It probably needs to be carefully worded.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_171">
          <from> Mr. Greg Browne<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_293">The question is right.</p>
          <p eId="para_294">This will result in an increase in section 29 actions against our school. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_172">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_295">Yes, absolutely.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_173">
          <from> Mr. Greg Browne<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_296">We will go to these section 29 appeals and say that we are not refusing the child. We may not even have known that the child was coming to us.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_174">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_297">Can I get agreement from the committee that we ask that question and let us see what the NCSE comes back with? We may have to go further on it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JenCummins" eId="spk_175">
          <from>Deputy Jen Cummins<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_298">I am delighted that the witnesses are here today. I thank the other members of the committee for facilitating the invitation. I think it was in May that I visited Ms O'Neill's school for the first time. When I left on my bike I was kind of floating through Crumlin to come back here, thinking what a wonderful and safe place I had just visited. I saw the students there playing in the yard and as someone described earlier, it did not matter if the ball went in or not. Everyone was delighted and cheering when the ball went in and they were all helping when the ball went out. It was a really caring school, with a lot of love. For me, education has to look at the child's needs. Love and care always need to be there. I see now there is a switch to it being more about numbers and ticking boxes and getting as many people in as possible. I know we have children with incredible needs who need to be minded, cared for and loved. However, my fear is that if we put everybody with such complex and different needs in, we will not be able to mind anybody. I do not want to use the word "diluted" but in our education system, I feel that staff in schools will be so stretched that they will not know where to go.</p>
          <p eId="para_299"> When I heard earlier that there were plans to get rid of the junior cycle, I thought that it is not the be-all and end-all. We know that. The other skills in Ms O'Neill's schools are maybe the skills that mainstream schools do not have time to teach, because they are teaching to the curriculum. The witnesses' schools also have the capacity to do the junior cycle at the level the student is at. Is that not what the parent was saying? Anyone here who is a parent needs to know that this could be any of our children or grandchildren. We need to have an education system that facilitates every single child. It is their right. We are not making this stuff up; it is written down. As I said in the Dáil the other day, Ireland has to give a right to children and they have rights to an education that is appropriate for them. It should be culturally sensitive and flexible according to their needs. If we are seeing that more young people are being diagnosed, then we need to be flexible on that. However, we do not need to then put everybody in the same category and - I will use the word - dilute the provision, the care and the love. This is not a case of robbing Peter to pay Paul; pitting one set of pupils against another is not right. It puts strain.</p>
          <p eId="para_300"> When I worked in education disadvantage I saw therapists or NEPS psychologists telling the teachers, SNAs and other care team staff how to support the child from an occupational therapy perspective or an educational psychology perspective. We do not need the role of the teacher or SNA being broadened to include therapies. They have a defined role and that needs to be kept. The therapists coming in need to do the therapeutic work. Everybody needs to be able to do what they are qualified and trained to do and what they love doing, to the best of their abilities.</p>
          <p eId="para_301"> I am not leaving Ms O'Neill any time to speak but I am so passionate about this. I am so happy to be pushing this. I do not know how many times I have mentioned it now. It is probably even more times than I have mentioned the school completion programme, which is my pet topic. I commend all the witnesses, particularly those who came down from Donegal. It is a very long way to come. I wish the school staff, parents and students all the best. We will keep fighting this. We will keep saying that we cannot have this redesignation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_176">
          <from> Ms Debbie O'Neill<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_302">I want to say how grateful we in Crumlin are for Deputy Cummins's support. It is rare to have somebody walk into a school for students with a mild general learning disability and automatically get it and she did so. We are very grateful for all her support and for us being here today.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DarrenORourke" eId="spk_177">
          <from>Deputy Darren O'Rourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_303">This is more a comment than a question. For me, something quite fundamental is at stake here. I refer to the mix of our education system and accessibility for children differentiated based on their needs. That is a fundamental piece and I will be very happy to work with the witnesses. We have identified this, in fairness to the committee. We will pursue it and work with the witnesses to try to get a successful resolution to it. There is a need for additionality, of course.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ShonaghNiRaghallaigh" eId="spk_178">
          <from>Deputy Shónagh Ní Raghallaigh<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_304">To follow on from the Cathaoirleach's comment about SENOs gatekeeping, are there cases of SENOs not granting letters of eligibility?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_179">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_305">We will get that question answered in a minute. Does the Deputy have any more questions? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ShonaghNiRaghallaigh" eId="spk_180">
          <from>Deputy Shónagh Ní Raghallaigh<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_306">No. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LindaNelsonMurray" eId="spk_181">
          <from>Senator Linda Nelson Murray<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_307">Every day is a learning day, and I was so glad to hear all of the contributions, particularly the letter from the woman that was read out. It is commendable that the witnesses have such a good insight into that. I feel that I do too, being on the board of one school, which is the best position I have ever taken. I see the work of the principal and the vice principal. I always bring up the issue of bus escorts in terms of the transport in the mornings and what teachers have to do, with all those kids getting on and off buses. I welcome further discussion on this. We need to get the right solution for it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AislingDempsey" eId="spk_182">
          <from>Deputy Aisling Dempsey<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_308">I thank the witnesses for coming in. To be honest, before the witnesses appeared here, I thought many of their concerns were to do with the fear of change and the fear of the unknown. I understand now that it is actually the fear of the known and what will result if this happens. I am really disappointed to hear that there was no engagement. Like the rest of the committee members, I will do what I can to support the witnesses.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RyanOMeara" eId="spk_183">
          <from>Deputy Ryan O'Meara<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_309">I thank the witnesses for being here. They have provided important information and background on an area that is often a vacuum of a lack of information, knowledge or understanding of. As Deputy Dempsey said, it is important to understand what the change means. Many times, once there is a change, there is a fear of change. We need to get the message across to people in here that this is not what this is. In my engagements on this with Mr. Browne and the MGLD class in Nenagh, I have noted the lack of information in the general population of what these schools are and the challenge of trying to get people to properly understand them. It has been very useful for the committee, and also more generally, to get this point raised in the Houses. I thank the witnesses for their contributions and the opening statement, which has been hugely helpful to our work. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JenCummins" eId="spk_184">
          <from>Deputy Jen Cummins<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_310">I am delighted that people have been able to engage. The whole point is that if people have knowledge, it means they have a full understanding of what is going on. Because the witnesses are working away nice and quietly and are busy doing what they are supposed to be doing, sometimes it is very difficult to promote this really good work. I am delighted they have had the opportunity to explain to the members their work. The proposals we have accepted have gone through and hopefully that work will happen. I look forward to working with the witnesses and I wish them safe home.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_185">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_311">That line in the Constitution about cherishing all the children of the nation equally gets overused. It is only every truly embodied in one of the witnesses's schools. Most of us have visited special schools and it is beautiful what goes on in them. There is no judgment and there is inclusion and a lot of happiness for children who may find day-to-day life difficult.</p>
          <p eId="para_312"> Regarding the roll numbers, the schools are designated as primary schools and yet are now expected to run out a full secondary school programme. This has implications for funding, curriculum, teachers and for designation. Is there now a need to have primary school roll numbers, secondary school roll numbers and special school roll numbers, so that you special schools receive special designation in their own right? We have about eight minutes left so I ask the witnesses to apportion the response times among themselves. We will start with Ms O'Neill.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_186">
          <from> Ms Debbie O'Neill<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_313">I will let the others talk on the roll numbers. If the committee could do what the Cathaoirleach suggested for us, it would be fantastic, but it is a long way from happening, I would say. I will finish with a little story about who we really are and what we do. It is hard to figure it out when talking about just numbers but we had a whole curriculum evaluation in English last year, where two inspectors came in to us for two days. Afterwards, we were brought together as a management team for feedback.</p>
          <p eId="para_314">so she could then write in the report exactly what she wanted to say. She wanted to say that the overwhelming feeling you get when you spend time in our school is one of love. It is love that we have for the children, love that the children have for us and the love that we have for each other. That environment does not happen organically in a school. One works on that all of the time as a principal and management to get the right people in to make sure that one has the right resources to work with the families and be the first point of contact all the time. I think that is really what we do and what we do well. Love means inclusion and belonging. Just because something is written about inclusion in a paper does not mean that if children go to a school they are included. My story gives a little more insight into all of our schools and what we are.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_187">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_315">Very Good.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_188">
          <from> Mr. Greg Browne<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_316">I thank everyone. I mentioned a boy who could not understand what was being said to him. This year he did the junior cert with up to six subjects and it will probably be the difference in him coming back to school.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_189">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_317">Very Good. Thank you very much.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_190">
          <from> Ms Rose-Marie Flanagan<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_318">I thank the committee for the invitation and for listening to us. I wish to point out that it is really important that we look at the most important individuals here, namely the students. We are here representing the students, our staff who are so committed and expert, the parents, the guardians, the wider school community, and our patrons and boards of management. We feel that redesignation is being forced on us, that we are not being liaised with, there is no communication and that there will be a complete lack of control from a school point of view. I think it will impact the parental voice and parental choice, which are really important.</p>
          <p eId="para_319"> An important point was made about a different roll number. It is vital that the teachers and SNAs in our schools have the same rights and terms and conditions as teachers in primary and post-primary school settings. As has been said, 65% of our school population are post-primary and we are a designated primary, which has an impact in terms of funding. Unfortunately, it does have an impact in terms of parents having to make contributions to help support the needs and commitments within the school.</p>
          <p eId="para_320"> Finally, inclusion is really important. We know that there is no universal definition of inclusion. We know that every single child in our school community is actively included and involved and they experience a sense of belonging, which is really important.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_191">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_321">I ask Deputy Ní Raghallaigh to repeat the question she asked in the last round and Mr. Haran might address it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ShonaghNiRaghallaigh" eId="spk_192">
          <from>Deputy Shónagh Ní Raghallaigh<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_322">Are there cases of SENOs not granting letters of eligibility?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_193">
          <from> Mr. John Haran<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_323">In our case, no. I say that because all the parents who apply to our school know that we are a school for children with a mild general learning disability. So when parents ring me and say they are thinking about sending their child to the school, I tell them that the first thing we need is an educational and psychological report from an educational psychologist and that the child needs to have an IQ of between 50 and 69. If it is below 50 then that is the moderate to severe and profound range so means attending the Little Angels School, which is the other special school in Letterkenny. In my experience a SENO has never refused an application to our school because it would never get that far, if the Deputy understands?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ShonaghNiRaghallaigh" eId="spk_194">
          <from>Deputy Shónagh Ní Raghallaigh<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_324">Yes, I understand. Go raibh maith agat.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_195">
          <from> Mr. John Haran<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_325">I thank the committee for having us here today. It has been brilliant. I apologise for being late but my flight from Donegal was delayed by an hour.</p>
          <p eId="para_326"> St. Bernadette's school in Letterkenny is brilliant and the number of pupils attending rises every year. That is a testament to the staff in the school and the work that we are doing. Traditionally, our numbers would have increased in respect of secondary education. So children would have gone to school up until sixth class in their local community but their parents would have realised that the jump to the local secondary school with 500 or 600 students and bells ringing and classes moving around was too much. Therefore, children would come to us for their secondary education. Over the last five years, we have seen a massive increase in the number of children coming to us at an earlier age so from third, fourth or fifth class in primary school. Without exception, every parent has said to me that within six weeks of their child starting in St. Bernadette's they wished their child had been in the school years ago. That is wonderful for us to hear but sad for parents that mainstream education did not work out for them. Mainstream education does not work for everyone and that is why children come to us. These children get the most wonderful education in a place, as Ms O'Neill has said, where they are loved and cherished.</p>
          <p eId="para_327"> It is important to point out that our staff over the years have built up massive expertise and experience in the field of mild general learning disability. Our brilliant teachers applied to work in our school because it is a MGLD school. That is their passion and where their expertise lies. They will get burned out and leave if our designation is changed because it will not be for them and is not what they signed up for. They are brilliant teachers and brilliant at what we provide. Special education is complex and wide-ranging. Why change a sector that is doing so well and that works so well for our students?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalCrowe" eId="spk_196">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-10T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_328">I thank each of you. It is 10 July and our witnesses are all on their holiday leave. They have taken time out of what should be family time to come here, which is greatly appreciated. I thank them for their attendance and engagement today. I thank the technical team who keep meetings going. We had no electricity outage today, unlike yesterday. The lights dimmed yesterday but not today. I thank all the secretariat and clerical team who greatly assist this committee. I thank the witnesses, the members and the people who tuned in at home.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_7"> The joint committee adjourned at 12.07 p.m. until 12.30 p.m. on Wednesday, 16 July 2025.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
