<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#debates">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_finance_public_expenditure_public_service_reform_and_digitalisation_and_taoiseach/2025-12-03/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_finance_public_expenditure_public_service_reform_and_digitalisation_and_taoiseach/2025-12-03/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-03" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#author" href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/34/joint_committee_on_finance_public_expenditure_public_service_reform_and_digitalisation_and_taoiseach"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_finance_public_expenditure_public_service_reform_and_digitalisation_and_taoiseach/2025-12-03/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_finance_public_expenditure_public_service_reform_and_digitalisation_and_taoiseach/2025-12-03/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-03" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_finance_public_expenditure_public_service_reform_and_digitalisation_and_taoiseach/2025-12-03/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_finance_public_expenditure_public_service_reform_and_digitalisation_and_taoiseach/2025-12-03/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-11" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#debates">
        <TLCPerson eId="CianOCallaghan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Cian-O'Callaghan.D.2020-02-08" showAs="Cian O'Callaghan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="EdwardTimmins" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Edward-Timmins.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Edward Timmins"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="GeraldNash" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Gerald-Nash.D.2011-03-09" showAs="Ged Nash"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MaireadFarrell" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Mairéad-Farrell.D.2020-02-08" showAs="Mairéad Farrell"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PearseDoherty" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Pearse-Doherty.S.2007-07-23" showAs="Pearse Doherty"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ShayBrennan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Shay-Brennan.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Shay Brennan"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/chair" showAs="Chair" eId="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/vice_chairman" showAs="Vice Chairman" eId="Vice_Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/author" showAs="author" eId="author"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/editor" showAs="editor" eId="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>AN COMHCHOISTE UM AIRGEADAS, CAITEACHAS POIBLÍ, ATHCHÓIRIÚCHÁN SEIRBHÍSE POIBLÍ AGUS DIGITIÚCHÁN, AGUS AN TAOISEACH</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>Joint Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure, Public Service Reform and Digitalisation, and Taoiseach</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2025-12-03">Dé Céadaoin, 03 Nollaig 2025</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2025-12-03">Wednesday, 03 December 2025</docDate>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_en">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_ga">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">Tháinig an Comhchoiste le chéile ag 03:30 p.m.</summary>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">The Joint Committee met at 03:30 p.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_3">Comhaltaí a bhí i láthair / Members present:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_1">Teachtaí Dála / Deputies</p>
              </th>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_2">Seanadóirí / Senators</p>
              </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#ShayBrennan">Shay Brennan</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#PatCasey">Pat Casey</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#ColmBurke">Colm Burke</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#AlisonComyn">Alison Comyn.+</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#PearseDoherty">Pearse Doherty</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#GeraldNash">Ged Nash</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_9">
                  <person refersTo="#CianOCallaghan">Cian O'Callaghan</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_10">
                  <person refersTo="#EdwardTimmins">Edward Timmins.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_4">+ In éagmais le haghaidh cuid den choiste / In the absence for part of the meeting of Senator Pat Casey.</summary>
          <summary eId="sum_5">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#MaireadFarrell">Teachta / Deputy Mairéad Farrell sa Chathaoir / in the Chair.</person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Regulatory Oversight of Neobanks: Discussion<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T15:30:00+00:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_1">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T15:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_11">No apologies have been received from members.</p>
          <p eId="para_12"> I advise members of the constitutional requirement that they must be physically present within the confines of the Leinster House complex in order to participate in public meetings. I will not permit members to participate where they are not adhering to this constitutional requirement. Therefore, any member who attempts to participate from outside the precincts will be asked to leave the meeting. In this regard, I ask any member participating via MS Teams to confirm that he or she is on the grounds of the Leinster House campus prior to making a contribution to the meeting. Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not criticise or make charges against any person or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable or otherwise engage in speech that might be regarded as damaging to the good name of the person or entity. Therefore, if their statements are potentially defamatory in relation to an identifiable person or entity they will be directed to discontinue their remarks and it is imperative that they comply with any such direction.</p>
          <p eId="para_13"> Today the committee is meeting to discuss the topic of regulatory oversight of neobanks in the context of their increased presence in the Irish market. This is the first meeting on this topic. It is proposed to cover the following areas in the course of the meeting: the passporting of new banks from EU member states and issues with differences in regulation between member states; the existing regulatory environment of payment service providers, technological banks in Ireland and future legislative requirements to provide for increased regulatory oversight in a changing and developing market; the impact of the increased prevalence of neobanks in Irish banking markets; changes in consumer behaviour as a result of these banks; and insights and trends in the banking technology sector and fraud prevention in these areas.</p>
          <p eId="para_14"> In this context, I welcome the following officials from the Central Bank of Ireland to the meeting today: Mr. Colm Kincaid, deputy governor, consumer and investor protection; Ms Yvonne Madden, head of domestic banks and retail credit; and Mr. Peter Gallagher, head of enforcement - market abuse and oversight. I invite Mr. Kincaid to make his opening statement.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_2">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T15:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_15">Go raibh maith agat, a Leas-Chathaoirligh. I thank the committee members for the invitation to be here today to discuss digital banking. As the Leas-Chathaoirligh said, I am joined by my colleagues, Yvonne Madden and Peter Gallagher.</p>
          <p eId="para_16"> The digitalisation of financial services has brought many benefits to consumers. The EU system of regulation provides an important platform from which to continue to innovate in an environment that secures consumers' best interests but digitalisation has also changed how, as consumers, we receive services, financial or otherwise, and our norms and expectations around digital services and our use of technology generally continues to evolve.</p>
          <p eId="para_17">Regulation is playing its role to provide guard-rails for this digital evolution by setting out standards for new types of digital products such as crypto assets; making sure there is continuity and smooth recovery if systems go down; and dealing with the implications of artificial intelligence and codifying the requirements and rights of consumers when making payments. Importantly, many of these regulations are prescribed at EU level. This is good because it enables us to access regulated financial services not just from entities incorporated in Ireland but also from firms in other EU member states. Let us also be clear that operating in an EU system of regulation does not mean there is no role for national policies for how this digital evolution occurs. It should also be noted that the substantive requirements of banking regulation are the same for an EU bank whether it provides those services through brick-and-mortar premises or digitally, and regardless of which EU member state it is incorporated in. </p>
          <p eId="para_18"> The benefits of digitalisation will only be realised if the risks are appropriately addressed. Just as digitalisation has brought in convenience, additional functionality and lower cost for many consumers, it has also brought new opportunities for criminals to exploit. It has also resulted in variations and gaps in the nature and quality of service consumers receive, in particular when things go wrong. These are topics on which the Central Bank has work under way, including working with other agencies in Ireland, the EU and internationally, and I welcome the opportunity to explain this work and share our perspective on the path ahead. To take one of the key risks, that of digital frauds and scams, the Central Bank’s work can be described under three headings. First, working with other law enforcement agencies to combat financial crime, to minimise the threat of frauds and scams to which consumers are exposed in the first place. Second, continuing to raise standards in the firms we regulate so they protect and support their customers, including when they fall victim to frauds and scams. Third, supporting public policy and legislation, so we keep pace with the policy implications of technology and the types of criminal behaviour to which consumers are exposed. Under this heading, the Central Bank supports the reforms under way at EU level to strengthen fraud prevention, broaden liability for financial service providers for certain frauds and place additional statutory responsibilities on electronic communications service providers. </p>
          <p eId="para_19"> We are also evolving our supervisory approach to target risks relating to digitalisation more generally, including operational resilience and cybersecurity. We also see that digitalisation brings increased risks to financial services from technology platforms and means of communication that sit outside financial services. These risks must be tackled if we are to avoid actions outside financial services damaging people’s trust in financial services, while also making sure of course that financial service firms are responsible in how they use technology. Since our previous appearance on fraud before this committee, the Central Bank has engaged with large technology platforms incorporated in Ireland to get them to implement additional controls to combat unauthorised financial service providers, in some cases with considerable success. In addition, we are the first authority in Ireland to secure the EU statutory status of trusted flagger for financial frauds and scams and we have led co-ordinated engagement with these technology platforms at a global level. We are also introducing new requirements in our consumer protection code from March 2026 to ensure the firms we regulate use technology with a customer focus and not in a way that seeks to unfairly exploit or take advantage of consumers to their detriment. The code will also enhance protections for consumers in vulnerable circumstances. </p>
          <p eId="para_20"> Digitalisation and access to an EU regulated market bring great benefits for us as consumers. Digitalisation also brings new risks and the threat posed by criminals is significant and system-wide work is required. The Central Bank is active in that work at national, EU and international level and we will play our part. It is also accurate to say that there remains a lot that firms can do at a practical level to improve the quality of service they provide, whatever their business model. This too will continue to be an area of focus in our supervisory work, including as we implement new requirements that come into force in 2026. I thank members for their attention. I and my colleagues are happy to take questions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_3">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_21">It is good to see the officials back, and on a very interesting topic. The deputy governor, Mr. Kincaid, said that the benefits of digitalisation will only be realised if the risks are appropriately addressed. It is some of those risks I want to talk about. There seems to be a blurring of the boundaries between new banks and cryptocurrency exchanges. I am a user of Revolut myself, as is my family. They claim to have 3 million customers in the State now and over 400,000 under-18s. It is very interesting that their terms and conditions are changing to allow for adults to send money to children, to minors, in their apps in the future, I think in February. We might get to discuss that. It is a very impressive app system. They boasted profits of $1 billion last year and an increasing share of that is coming from crypto. Revenue from crypto went up fourfold last year. Some of these coins are well known, like Bitcoin, ETH and others, but there are many others that have massive price drops of from 80% to 95%. The Governor has talked about his own views on crypto and has suggested it is not unlike gambling. It does raise serious questions about how we protect customers in relation to these so-called investments, when they go into a banking app. I am a user of Revolut and my kids have Revolut. When you go into a banking app and can just buy these coins, literally with two touches of a button, there in the main platform, is there an issue regarding protection? What type of oversight does the Central Bank have of how Revolut and others promote crypto assets within the app? Are there any figures for the amount of money lost by retail investors? How does the Central Bank protect consumers in the face of this kind of speculation as a key part of a business model of a bank?</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_6">
          <i>Deputy Mairéad Farrell took the Chair.</i>
        </summary>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_4">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_22">The Deputy raises a really important topic there. There are a few components to unwrap. On our risk outlook in respect of crypto, we have been very clear from the get-go that it is a category of instrument with very particular risks that people need to be very aware of. We also released a piece of research earlier this year where we looked at the perspectives of retail investors. We included crypto within that because people sometimes describe it as an investment, even though that is not a term we would use ourselves because of the issues and the nature of the risk the Deputy has outlined. We see there is a significant prevalence of people investing in crypto, whether through Revolut or otherwise. Over half of them are saying they do so out of curiosity. It is an area we have very significant concerns about. That is the first thing in respect of our risk outlook.</p>
          <p eId="para_23"> To be fair, the European Union is leading the way at a global level in introducing a regime for the regulation of certain crypto asset services. We are implementing that regime. The third component, which will continue to be a challenge for us with financial services, particularly those provided digitally, and this comes to the fore in digital apps, is where there is a mixture of services that may be regulated and a mixture of services or assets that are not regulated. One of the things we consulted on when bringing in the new code was the requirements we need in that environment. We are tightening up the requirements on firms to be really clear about what is regulated and what is not regulated. That must be very clear for people. To wrap all of that up, the growing use of crypto assets in our society is something we are very live to as a risk. Our message to consumers remains that it is a very risky product. The research we have done would indicate that it is becoming more prevalent but it is not an alternative to mainstream investment for consumers. On apps, their design features need to be very clear as to what service is regulated, any services on that app that are not regulated, and what the rights and entitlements of the consumers are.</p>
          <p eId="para_24">That is a very live area of focus for us.</p>
          <p eId="para_25"> The Deputy asked a question about the figures of money lost. I was not sure whether he was referring to investment money lost on crypto by value-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_5">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_26">Yes, exactly.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_6">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_27">I do not have those figures in front of me.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_7">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_28">Obviously, the nature of banking has completely and utterly changed, and for the better. We do banking on the go now and we have access to our cash or our money and are able to transfer very quickly. Revolut is obviously the leader in that. There are other companies as well and the retail banks are trying to play catch-up. Now, as I said, it is not just crypto; you can make investments and other things as well. Those investments are fine if they are informed and people have made informed decisions. However, does the Central Bank have any policy on restrictions on promoting extremely risky types of investments, given that they are now on our phones and as accessible to us as anything else, including our WhatsApp messages coming in? It is so simple now. Is there any concern about that? What enforcement measures are available to the Central Bank if any platform is not acting in the interest of consumers in relation to promotion of those?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_8">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_29">Under EU law, a range of requirements will apply - the Deputy will be familiar with them - in relation to different types of investments, be it insurance, funds, etc., running right through to crypto. As I said, that EU legislation, through MiCAR, is being implemented. More fundamentally, however, when we were doing the public consultation for the new code, we put this question out to public consultation and in our engagements with various stakeholder groups around the country about the key requirements we want for digitalised financial services. We now have in that code a very powerful formula, which we obviously have to implement, but it goes to the heart of what the Deputy is saying, which is that all digital services have to be designed with real customer needs at their heart to serve a real need that is actually there. If they are providing information, they must inform consumers effectively. That means effective to whatever it is they are informing a person about, so, if it is about investment opportunities, that it is effective in supporting you to make those decisions; that it does not seek to exploit particular biases or lack of information that consumers have; and that it is tested to see that it provides consistent and objective outcomes. The latter is particularly important with the advent of AI and other tools, which can lead to financial exclusion, for example. Those kinds of requirements are a very powerful formula that we will deploy into our engagement with digital financial services across any platform and in any way. The other relevant area is our approach to unauthorised financial services. We will move to a situation now where it will be very difficult for a firm that we regulate to include under the banner it uses for its regulated financial services advertisements or promotions of products-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_9">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_30">That are unregulated.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_10">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_31">-----which are not regulated-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_11">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_32">I have two other questions. I am conscious-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_12">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_33">That cuts across and we have had cause to challenge on a range of those.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_13">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_34">I have two other questions. I want to go back to Revolut, but before I do, the Central Bank issued a fine in relation to Coinbase recently. Coinbase did not comply with the Criminal Justice (Money Laundering and Terrorist Financing) Act, which requires it to review transactions, to look to see if they are suspicious and, if they reach a threshold, to report them to Revenue and the Garda. In this case 30 million transactions were not monitored, and it was eventually found that 2,700 had to be reported to the Garda. The Central Bank fined Coinbase, what was it, €21 million? I am looking at what happened in the US because this happened in the US. Coinbase got a $50 million fine and was required to spend another $50 million on compliance, so that is $100 million. That is five times more - well, there is the currency exchange - than what the Central Bank fined it. In the US they did not review 100,000 transactions; here 30 million transactions were not reviewed. It looks as if the penalties are completely different. That is the first question.</p>
          <p eId="para_35"> Second, surely the Central Bank is inundated with complaints from Revolut customers. Its customer service is absolutely appalling. As I said, I am a user myself. I am a great supporter of the app in the way that it has revolutionised how all this is done, but, by God, if you have money in that app and you want access to it, you are a fool to leave it in Revolut. So many people are blocked out of the app and when they try to get back into the app, it takes weeks, if not months, and you cannot talk to any person in terms of Revolut. The Central Bank has a consumer protection role. What is it doing about this? This has been going on for years.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_14">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_36">I ask members and witnesses to be succinct because we have a split session today and we are under a bit more time pressure than usual in terms of flexibility.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_15">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_37">First, on Coinbase, I will be very succinct. As regards the level of fine we set, there is a statutory formula in the legislation. We use it. We applied a fine at the upper level of what is permitted under law because of the severity of that, and that is linked to the size of the Irish firm we fined, so that is the disparity in the amounts. It was at the very upper edge of what we were able to implement as a statutory fine.</p>
          <p eId="para_38"> On the complaints issue in relation to Revolut, I have been very clear about this, including since I came into this role. I said this in the opening statement. There is significantly more that all regulated institutions, whether they are providing services digitally or otherwise, need to do on customer service. We do not actually see a particularly different scale, number or profile of the complaints coming into any one of the banking firms we are talking about. The Deputy will understand I cannot talk about individual firms. The scale and the nature do not vary that much, actually.</p>
          <p eId="para_39"> On the issue of the ability to contact a human being, we and Ms Madden on our team have had cause to intervene with firms using chatbots to require them to also put in a facility to access a human being, particularly in relation to fraud. We are very alive to that. I am happy to pick it up bilaterally.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_16">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_40">We move on to an Teachta Brennan.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ShayBrennan" eId="spk_17">
          <from>Deputy Shay Brennan<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_41">How much Irish money is on deposit with neobanks, and how has that changed in recent years? Is that growing at any pace?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_18">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_42">I will see if we have the number for the amount on deposit. What we are seeing in terms of the scale of payments with the neobanks is still, in terms of amount, relatively small but, for example, looking ahead to today's session, we looked at the fraud statistics and the number and volume of retail payments going through. Some of those, and the Deputy mentioned one of them, would be on a par with the Irish banks, but I do not have to hand a specific number in relation to the amount on deposit. The term "neobank" is not a technical term but I am interpreting it for the purpose of this meeting to mean firms that provide their services solely digitally and that have a banking licence. A number of these entities do not have banking licences. I do not know if Ms Madden wants to add a little more detail, and we can supplement after the session.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_19">
          <from> Ms Yvonne Madden<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_43">We do not have the figures with us but it is not a significant number. There are other services that the neobanks are providing, such as lending, whether it be personal lending, credit cards or payments, so it is kind of a mixed bag of financial services products, but as regards the information we have on aggregate level, it is not at this stage a very prevalent or a significant number.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ShayBrennan" eId="spk_20">
          <from>Deputy Shay Brennan<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_44">But it is likely in the billions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_21">
          <from> Ms Yvonne Madden<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_45">Yes, it would be.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ShayBrennan" eId="spk_22">
          <from>Deputy Shay Brennan<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_46">Okay, so there are billions of euro of Irish consumers' money with these financial institutions - "neobanks" is the only term I have to hand - that are essentially regulated out of countries like Lithuania and Germany but not Ireland.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_23">
          <from> Ms Yvonne Madden<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_47">It is important to think about the role and the standards, the supervision and the regulation they are subject to. It is consistent across the eurozone and across the European Union. For example, we are a part of the Single Supervisory Mechanism and a part of the joint supervisory teams that supervise a number of the banks that operate here on a digital basis. They are supervised out of the European Central Bank with the Irish Central Bank as part of those teams. We also engage with peer regulators in other European jurisdictions such as the Netherlands and Germany, for example, which are two other countries where the neobanks have a presence. We engage with them as well on a peer-to-peer basis. They are subject to the same standards as the Irish banks.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ShayBrennan" eId="spk_24">
          <from>Deputy Shay Brennan<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_48">The consumer deposits with these neobanks are not covered by the Irish deposit guarantee scheme; they are covered by the deposit guarantee schemes in the home countries of those providers.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_25">
          <from> Ms Yvonne Madden<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_49">Yes, their branches that are operating here are covered by the home state deposit guarantee scheme. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ShayBrennan" eId="spk_26">
          <from>Deputy Shay Brennan<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_50">Does the Central Bank see any difficulty if there was to be a problem with an Irish cardholder accessing the deposit guarantee scheme in, for example, the Netherlands or Lithuania?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_27">
          <from> Ms Yvonne Madden<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_51">No. They are all subject to the same European standards in terms of the deposit guarantee scheme and the European regulations required there. There are standards in place for the funding of those schemes and within the periods with which they must make payment available to depositors. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_28">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_52">I want to give a flavour of the way that banking supervision has fundamentally changed since the global financial crisis. To paint a picture of what we are talking about, we do not see things as being regulated from member state A or B. Banking is regulated in the European system of banking supervision by ourselves and the ECB, and the national competent authorities of the other member states. In practical terms, that means Ms Madden and her colleagues sitting in a room looking at the European banking system. We have the same access to the same information in relation to a bank in one member state as we would to a domestic bank here in Ireland. If we have any concerns about the financial, or other, position of any entity in another EU country, we have access to the same information, access to the same powers and we are in the room talking about the regulation of those entities. It is a big difference from where we were pre-financial crisis when we would have had to reach out to get that information. We are now in a system where we are, essentially, supervising all of these entities within a European system. I am satisfied that we have a very good line of sight into the position of these firms. We have also seen that system to be very responsive to our concerns, including our concerns about customer service by some of these firms. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ShayBrennan" eId="spk_29">
          <from>Deputy Shay Brennan<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_53">Staying with the guarantee, is that watertight, in Mr. Kincaid's view? Say there was €5 billion on deposit from Irish consumers with these four major providers. We will take probably the biggest one, which would be Revolut. If there is a problem with Revolut, or a second banking crisis even, just to take it to its extreme, it would be the Lithuanian state paying out on the deposit guarantee scheme. Is the Central Bank confident that, if the Lithuanian state is paying out billions, an Irish national would not be put to the back of the queue and that the paperwork, the legal work and whatever they would need to do to claim, would be as simple and straightforward as if they were to claim off an Irish institution? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_30">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_54">In a word, yes. The Chair asked me to be succinct. We are operating in a European system of regulation. To be very clear, because the Deputy presented a scenario that is not a scenario that I see, the capital standards and the regulatory standards for European banks are among the highest, if not the highest, in the world. I have no concerns for the soundness of European banks. We supervise them in a European system. That system does not differentiate between depositors based on where they are located, be it Ireland or anywhere else. As I said, we are part and parcel of and around the table on the regulation of all of those firms applying the same standards. Therefore, I have no concerns in that regard. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ShayBrennan" eId="spk_31">
          <from>Deputy Shay Brennan<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_55">The witnesses from the Central Bank made reference to having trusted flagger status and being the first in the country to have that status. Will they expand on what that means and what that is likely to evolve into? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_32">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_56">I will ask Mr. Gallagher, who does that work, to take that question. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_33">
          <from> Mr. Peter Gallagher<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_57">Just to speak a bit about trusted flagger status, earlier this year we were the first organisation or entity in Ireland to be designated as a trusted flagger under the EU Digital Services Act. That means that when we report illegal content - and our area of expertise in this regard is in relation to financial scams and frauds - to large online companies, technology companies or platforms, they must prioritise that above all other reports of illegal content they have received. They must act under a legal obligation to act quickly in respect of the assessment, and, if appropriate, remove that content from their platform. Obviously, there would be regulatory consequences for them under their own regulatory regime if they failed to do that. In a nutshell, that is what the trusted flagger designation does in practice. The real value of it is that it removes the content from the platforms, thereby breaking the link between the potential fraudsters and the potential victims. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ShayBrennan" eId="spk_34">
          <from>Deputy Shay Brennan<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_58">That seems useful. Does Mr. Gallagher envisage that status being granted to other bodies in Ireland? Then, further to that, when the Central Bank flags a case, is that something done as a behest of a complaint received or is that done due to Central Bank investigation? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_35">
          <from> Mr. Peter Gallagher<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_59">As regards whether others will receive the designation, I honestly could not say because we do not grant that designation. That is the honest answer on that front.</p>
          <p eId="para_60"> Would the Deputy mind repeating the second part of the question? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ShayBrennan" eId="spk_36">
          <from>Deputy Shay Brennan<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_61">I am just curious if, when the Central Bank flags a case, that is due to Central Bank investigation or is because a member of the public has made a complaint.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_37">
          <from> Mr. Peter Gallagher<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_62">It is a combination of both. Probably the largest source of our information in that regard comes from members of the public contacting us. We also do our own investigations. Something that we have done recently, recognising the technologically advanced environment in which we are operating, is we have developed our own tool to proactively search for potential scams online so that we can proactively identify them before a complaint comes in. That allows us to potentially report those under our trusted flagger designation. Therefore, it is a combination of both but the majority comes from public reports. To give the Deputy a sense of what we have done since receiving the designation in April this year, we have made in excess of 150 reports of separate URLs using that trusted flagger accreditation. In addition to that, we have made over 110 reports, what we call Article 16 reports, of harmful content relating to financial frauds and scams. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_38">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_63">Go raibh míle maith agat. Bogfaimid ar aghaidh go dtí an Teachta Timmins. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_39">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_64">I thank the witnesses for their presentation. I have about four or five questions. First, on data sharing, do we know of any data sharing that happens with digital banking? I refer to digital banks sharing customer information with third parties, basically selling the information to third parties, for whatever purposes - advertising or targeting or whatever else. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_40">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_65">As with any commercial entity in the EU, if we are talking about personnel data, they operate within the same personal data requirements as any other agency. I am not, as I sit here, aware of any issues having been brought to our attention about them transferring personal data to third parties in a way that has thrown up any concern. They outsource, like any other firm. If we had any concerns in relation to that, we would be engaging with the Data Protection Commissioner.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_41">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_66">Are they subject to the same regulations that the Irish-based banks are? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_42">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_67">Yes. I am not a data protection legal expert but it is an EU regime so they would be subject to the same data protection requirements. To be very clear, from our perspective they are, in any event, subject to the same requirements in terms of how they deal with their customers. We would see the use of those customers' data as being part of that. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_43">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_68">Mr. Kincaid alluded briefly to fraud earlier. Is the proportion of fraud, in terms of numbers and in value, in neobanks higher relative to the Irish retail banks?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_44">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_69">No, we do not see a disparity between them as a category. What we see is that different types of business models are attacked by the fraudsters in different ways. We see that the range of fraud levels by volume and by value across the system as a whole are remaining relatively steady year on year and they are broadly similar across the institutions. It is within a range but the range does not break down based on whether they are digital or non-digital banks. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_45">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_70">There is no stand-out data that shows customers are at a higher risk of fraud operating with a neobank than they are with a regular retail bank? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_46">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_71">No. It may be useful if we break the frauds into two categories. One is unauthorised payment fraud where a person just steals your data, essentially pretends to be you and makes a payment using your card or whatever.</p>
          <p eId="para_72">That is becoming less prominent of a feature as we have improved the systems and controls within financial services to fend that off. What we are seeing increasingly is a type of fraud that is authorised payment fraud, which is where the fraudsters use social media and other tools to manipulate people. That fraud is taking place 80% plus of the time on social media and online platforms. That fraud is not taking place in the financial system. It is taking place on those platforms and then being executed through the financial system. What we see is that as we use online and digital payments now, more of those payments are online and digital because that is the way the consumers are dealing-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_47">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_73">Mr. Kincaid has answered the question. I am conscious of time. In relation to phone numbers and getting a live body when people phone up, that is clearly a challenge. That is a challenge in the existing bank system. Only this week, I had a case of an elderly couple wanting to get a statement from their post office account for the purpose of applying for a non-contributory old age pension. They spent three days trying to ring An Post to get a bank statement. They cannot get it. To go into the post office - no chance. They can provide numbers. There is a number and An Post provides a number. Digital banks have to provide numbers, and they do. I ask that the witnesses monitor whether those numbers are functional. This is a simple case. It is An Post - an Irish-based bank effectively - and it does not answer the phone. People cannot get a bank statement. They get one automatically once a year but if they need a current one for a simple application they cannot succeed. I want the witnesses to be aware of that. </p>
          <p eId="para_74"> Back to the difference between Irish retail banks and neobanks from the Revenue Commissioners point of view. The Revenue Commissioners can have access to peoples' bank accounts. They have to go to court for whatever reasons to access them but they have the same powers to access the neobanks that are not Irish-based banks in terms of looking to establish information in case of investigations. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_48">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_75">I would be going way beyond my area of expertise or knowledge. I would have to let the Revenue Commissioners speak to that. Our powers are the same. I am satisfied with our ability to do our job with digital loaning, passporting or domestic bank but I would have to let the Revenue Commissioners speak on their powers. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_49">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_76">A simple thing of fraud - and I am sure we have all experienced this - is that we just get a phone call. It could be an Irish mobile number, a number from Italy or wherever. You know it is fraud and hang up. This is wandering slightly outside of the remit here today but is there follow up on that? Is there a way of tracing where these calls are coming from? Has there been any success in pursuing this fraudulent behaviour? Someone just rings up and looks for banking information. They may have some information on the person. They may know that they have a bank account or Visa card and are looking for the details. Is there any way of comeback of following that? This is equally with emails, but it is more so the phone calls. They are more prevalent. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_50">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_77">There have been steps taken under the banner of communications regulation rather than of our own in relation to phone-based fraud. They have been quite successful, but again I cannot speak authoritatively to the statistics or the figures around that. One of the things we have done since the last time we were before the committee to talk about this is that we have required the institutions that we regulate to have a single common approach to how they make reports to An Garda Síochána. In relation to the entities we regulate, regulated financial service providers are required to report any suspicions of fraudulent activity to An Garda Síochána and to have a single dedicated way of doing that. That supports An Garda Síochána to pursue that, including to pursue it in other jurisdictions. At any given point in time, for example, in the Central Bank, we would be engaged with half a dozen or so requests to assist law enforcement agencies in other jurisdictions around the world. Through the channel of financial services, any reports are followed through whether it is by phone, email and so on. On the communications side, steps have been taken in relation to trying to make it harder and blocking calls and so forth but I am not the authority on that. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_51">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_78">In relation to the back up of data systems, regular companies or any organisation has backup in case their systems collapse. The Irish banks have quite robust systems. Does the Central Bank do any work or have any regulation in terms of the neobanks regarding whether they have robust backup systems in the event of their systems going down and that for the records and account holders' details, their account balances and how much money is held on deposit that those systems are as robust as they should be as we would expect with an Irish bank?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_52">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_79">The requirements are exactly the same. We supervise those requirements. The phrase we use is "operational resilience" to make sure the firms can deal with those situations. I will let Ms Madden to speak to the practicalities of the work we are doing on that front across the whole system at European level. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_53">
          <from> Ms Yvonne Madden<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_80">Some of the work we do is that we look at firms’ operational resilience and we have the Digital Operational Resilience Act, DORA, that has come in at the European level as well. Any of work we do, a fundamental expectation we have is that banks have systems that can be trusted, are safe and can be reliable but they are resilient so that if they get into trouble, they are recoverable. It is a real focus of the work we do in terms of our engagement with firms. Across a number of firms, we will do reviews as part of our supervisory review and valuation process. I apologise for using technical terms. We look at operational resilience through that as part of our role in the joint supervisory team in the European Central Bank. We also do things like look at business continuity plans, such as looking at the ability of-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_54">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_81">Does this cover neobanks?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_55">
          <from> Ms Yvonne Madden<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_82">Exactly. It goes back to the original point, which is all firms and all banks that are supervised under the EU regulations and as part of the European systems supervision are subject to the same rules and requirements. For example, some of the neobanks are significant institutions. They are supervised out of Frankfurt by the ECB and we are a member of that joint supervisory team. We are looking at things like operational resilience. It is a key focus area of ours. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GeraldNash" eId="spk_56">
          <from>Deputy Ged Nash<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_83">I apologise, I was late arriving to the meeting. The witnesses may have addressed this already, but Mr. Gallagher referenced in an earlier contribution about the trusted flagger designation. Who designates?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_57">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_84">That designation is by Coimisiún na Meán. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GeraldNash" eId="spk_58">
          <from>Deputy Ged Nash<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_85">That is interesting. It came to my attention in recent days that the whole area of financial fraud that we might be familiar with through text messaging and telecoms companies is now under the remit of the Department of culture and potentially Coimisiún na Meán as well. That is a change in approach. I am not sure that is the best Department and agency to host this issue but that is a discussion for another day. </p>
          <p eId="para_86"> Regarding the trusted flagger designation, Mr. Gallagher talked us through the experience in recent months. The designation of the Central Bank as a trusted flagger is in its infancy. It was April when it received this designation. Mr. Gallagher talked us through the number of warnings issued to organisations who may have been in breach of their obligations and responsibilities. Are there any live cases under investigation where, for example, an organisation decides that it does not want to comply with the Central Bank's instruction? What is the next step then? What is the ultimate sanction? It may be too early and the Central Bank may not have concluded any cases in terms of investigations. Are there any live formal investigations being undertaken by the Central Bank into breaches since it was designated as a trusted flagger? What are the ultimate sanctions for organisations that are found not to be in compliance?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_59">
          <from> Mr. Peter Gallagher<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_87">While the Central Bank of Ireland has been designated as a trusted flagger, it is not the responsible competent authority to enforce failures by the technology company in complying with a report made by a trusted flagger. I could not speak to whether another agency has investigations live. It would not be appropriate for me to speak to whether they have live investigations in any event, but that----- </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GeraldNash" eId="spk_60">
          <from>Deputy Ged Nash<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_88">What is that other agency?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_61">
          <from> Mr. Peter Gallagher<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_89">It is Coimisiún na Meán. That is how it operates. The commission is responsible for enforcement with regard to any breaches within the sector it regulates. We are the designated trusted flagger.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_62">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_90">As Mr. Gallagher was speaking, something encouraged me to give the Deputy a sense of the weight the Central Bank of Ireland brings to this and has put behind it. We have intervened with the large technology providers in the country to get them to put in place checks in relation to financial services so that, if they are putting up advertisements for financial services, they have checked that the financial service provider is regulated. We do not regulate these entities. We do not have the power to require them to do that but we have had some success in getting them to do it. Google has made an announcement in relation to that. Where we have seen it brought in, it has been extremely successful. We worked at international level to rally other regulators around the world to contact over 80 platform providers around the world with the same demand. We argued for it to be included at EU level in laws that were announced last week. These will take time to implement but they are there, which I very much welcome. By the way, I see absolutely no reason for those platform providers to wait for that law to come into force before they bring those measures into play. We do not regulate these entities. To be very clear, our demeanour towards this is that we will follow unregulated financial services that harm consumers wherever we find them. We will follow them into whatever corporate entity we find them in and we will push our powers to the limit in doing so. However, as Mr. Gallagher has said, Coimisiún na Meán has a statutory role. To be very clear, we take a strong view of our role and use our powers to pursue anyone engaged in this activity.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GeraldNash" eId="spk_63">
          <from>Deputy Ged Nash<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_91">Accepting that Coimisiún na Meán has statutory responsibility in this space, the Central Bank has appropriately been designated as a trusted flagger. It makes absolute sense for the Central Bank of Ireland to have that designation. Is there a formal co-operation agreement with Coimisiún na Meán that formalises that arrangement? Is that relationship with Coimisiún na Meán structured or does it just happen by happenstance? This is a serious issue. I have no doubt that there is regular communication between the Central Bank and Coimisiún na Meán but will Mr. Gallagher confirm whether there is a formal co-operation agreement in place? If so, how is that relationship structured? If there is no such agreement, there ought to be.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_64">
          <from> Mr. Peter Gallagher<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_92">As far as I know, there is no formal agreement, any form of co-operation agreement or memorandum of understanding between the two agencies at this point in time. However, as the Deputy alluded to, there is a very strong working relationship between the two agencies. In the context of applying for the designation of trusted flagger, there was an extremely exacting process that took place over a period of months in 2024, which ultimately led up to the grant. While I do not want to go into the intimate details, throughout that process, there were a huge number of questions to and engagement with Coimisiún na Meán around all aspects of how it would operate in practice. That contact between the two agencies is all documented. We were very clear as to roles, responsibilities, processes, expertise, resources and all of the things we need to do to deliver on our status as trusted flagger.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GeraldNash" eId="spk_65">
          <from>Deputy Ged Nash<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_93">That means that everybody is clear on their mutual obligations. There may very well be a strong argument for a formal memorandum of understanding to ensure there is absolutely no ambiguity about the relationship. That would be good practice and it should be considered. </p>
          <p eId="para_94"> There was mention earlier of the work at EU level to make tech companies liable for losses incurred as a result of scams. That is an important development. We will watch that evolving space with interest. There is obvious tension between the Department of enterprise, the Department of Finance and, potentially although I do not know, the Central Bank in that regard. We have read in recent times that the Department of enterprise expressed concerns about foreign direct investment and what it might see as some form of regulatory overreach by some who are trying to get a handle on this. However, ultimately, the interests of the consumer need to come first. </p>
          <p eId="para_95"> If I may, I will raise one or two issues in relation to the overall issue of online scams and fraud. It was inevitable that a lot of this conversation would be dominated by this issue because it is something that comes across our desks quite frequently. It is a live issue for the public. There is a lot of talk about how so-called influencers are operating online and their promotion of what are, in some cases, unauthorised products from unauthorised and unregulated firms. Does the Central Bank have a view on that? Obviously, it does not regulate the online space <i>per se</i> but it may have a view. Will the witnesses talk us through some of the work being done in that space and the bank's interest in it?</p>
          <p eId="para_96"> I have a final overarching question. The evolution of new digital financial instruments is happening all of the time. With the best will in the world, it is very difficult for regulators to keep pace. Is the Central Bank satisfied that MiCAR and the various other approaches that are being taken are fit for purpose and that we are anticipating as best we can the evolution of new products that will ultimately need to be regulated to keep consumers safe and protected?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_66">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_97">Will the witnesses try to answer that within a minute?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_67">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_98">I will do my very best. On MiCAR and the regime, at a global level, we are now in an era where there is something of a pendulum swing in relation to regulation after the global financial crisis. I personally think that, in time, people will see that the sorts of regimes the Deputy has mentioned are the things that maintain people's trust in financial services as they evolve. I am satisfied we have the powers we need to do our job. That includes pursuing people in whatever forum they are in who are providing financial advice or advertising financial services without an authorisation to do so.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CianOCallaghan" eId="spk_68">
          <from>Deputy Cian O'Callaghan<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_99">I thank the witnesses for coming in. On the issue of financial fraud, where people have had their funds stolen when using a digital app like Revolut, part of the problem has been very weak authorisations and permissions being required in comparison with other banking services. What is being done to tackle that? The authorisations or permissions needed to break into a system are weak and people are losing substantial amounts as a result.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_69">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_100">The standards firms are required to meet to be authorised as a licensed bank or payment firm under the payments services directive are the same in every jurisdiction. They are assessed under a European system of supervision, which Ms Madden referred to. There is no way in which a firm that only provides services digitally can be subject to a different set of regulatory requirements than any other firm providing the same services. I just wished to be clear on that.</p>
          <p eId="para_101"> On making it harder for fraudsters to hack, to access your details and to carry out transactions you did not authorise on your behalf, regulated institutions in Ireland and around the European Union have taken many steps to put systems and controls in place to make that harder. The evidence of this is that we are now seeing fraudsters moving on from that kind of activity and into authorised payment fraud. This is where they trick people into making payments to them, particularly online, by impersonation using AI or other tools. To think of it as a perimeter fence, as we improve our systems and controls in one area, the fraudsters will look to some other area. To be fair to financial institutions, it is important to remember that the fraudsters decide where they want to target the fraud. If they decide to target the fraud at a particular firm, which we sometimes see, or a particular type of firm, we expect those firms to react. It is not necessarily a reflection on the business model of those firms but we expect them to deliver on their promises to their consumers and to have strong systems and controls to deal with the typologies of fraud we know about and to learn from the new typologies of fraud that come along all the time. This is why information sharing among the institutions is so important. We will continue with a process of improvement and learning in this space for many years to come because the fraudsters are going to continue to evolve.</p>
          <p eId="para_102">There is an estimate that around €1 billion is lost globally through financial fraud and scams. This is a lucrative area for criminals, and these are not just criminals in this area but in other areas too. As we talk about this, it is important to keep our eye on the ball. The most important thing for the system to do is to combat the fraud and stop it happening in the first place. We will, though, obviously remain vigilant with the firms we regulate to make sure they have good customer supports for customers who do fall victim to those frauds.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CianOCallaghan" eId="spk_70">
          <from>Deputy Cian O'Callaghan<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_103">Is good customer support offered by all the different platforms operating in Ireland? There are huge variances for people who fall victim in this regard in terms of how they are supported. I appreciate the legal requirements are the same, but there are huge variances the level of protections around authorisations as well. Some platforms go to quite substantial lengths to have robust measures in place while others are much looser.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_71">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_104">At the risk of repeating myself when time is so tight, to be very clear, and I said this in the opening statement, the move into the digitalisation of financial services has brought about variations and gaps in the service levels people receive. Our message and my message since I have taken this role to the firms we regulate is that all of them have things they need to do better in terms of customer service, including in relation to fraud.</p>
          <p eId="para_105"> Regarding the authorisations mentioned by the Deputy, does he mean those required to open an account or to make a payment, as opposed to-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CianOCallaghan" eId="spk_72">
          <from>Deputy Cian O'Callaghan<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_106">Yes, to make a payment.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_73">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_107">Firms will continue to innovate and use technology to innovate in this space. We have a constant tension between providing convenience and speed to people versus the fact it is that convenience and speed the fraudsters will try to exploit.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CianOCallaghan" eId="spk_74">
          <from>Deputy Cian O'Callaghan<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_108">I wish to ask about two other areas. Deputy Doherty mentioned earlier a situation where people are locked out of their digital account. They are asked to submit documentation. They submit it. They are then told that documentation does not work and it must be resubmitted. They resubmit but they cannot find out what is wrong with the documentation. They are locked out of their account, no longer have access to their funds and cannot talk to a human to get this rectified. What is being done to tackle this problem? Is anything being done to tackle it? How do people get their money back? What do they do? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_75">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_109">First, it is for firms who decide on their business model to own their business model and make sure they deliver on it. Different firms will have different models and different specific technological ways they use. To take the Deputy's example of opening an account, the firms will use that technology. We look at the outcomes for the consumers to make sure that whatever systems or technologies are used, they are effective to deliver the service the customer requires. I mentioned the example of chatbots earlier because I know that has come up. We have intervened with firms to require them to also put in place human support along with the chatbot support. So, there-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CianOCallaghan" eId="spk_76">
          <from>Deputy Cian O'Callaghan<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_110">I am sorry. My question is what recourse does someone have if they have funds in a digital platform account they are locked out of and cannot get back into access them. How can they get their money back? This is a real problem for people at the moment. How do they get their money back? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_77">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_111">Yes, I understand. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_78">
          <from> Ms Yvonne Madden<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_112">It is something that is hugely important in the context of making sure contingency arrangements are in place. If people have an app, for example, cannot access it and have been locked out, some neobanks will have the facility where people can go onto their desktop and access the website. People can then use that to contact the institution in question. People should also be able to contact a person. This is hugely important and is an intervention we have made. There is also the opportunity to have callbacks and things like that. These have been areas where we have sought to strengthen the protection for consumers because we did recognise this as an issue.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CianOCallaghan" eId="spk_79">
          <from>Deputy Cian O'Callaghan<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_113">The Central Bank is confident people can contact a person in the main digital platforms that operate in Ireland and find out how to do that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_80">
          <from> Ms Yvonne Madden<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_114">Yes, I am for ones we have looked at. One of the things we are doing is a thematic review of fraud. We really want to look not just at the information submitted to us on fraud, which we get through our conduct of business returns from firms, but to go out and look at the nature of the fraud. We want to have a better understanding of it and look to see what types of customer supports are in place. What I am saying is that we really want to get under the bonnet of this issue. It is an area of focus for us.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CianOCallaghan" eId="spk_81">
          <from>Deputy Cian O'Callaghan<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_115">I thank Ms Madden. To move to one last area, the Irish private credit market has quadrupled to being worth €70 billion. What is the level of risk to the banking sector from exposure to non-bank financial sector investment funds in terms of the interconnectedness of loans? What are the kinds of risks there and what is the Central Bank's view on the situation?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_82">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_116">In Ireland and operating from Ireland, we have a domestic financial services system that serves people here in the country, including the passporting firms we have been talking about. We have a very large globally facing financial services centre too. The whole area of private credit is one we have been very focused on, as have other regulators and central banks around the world. The Irish market is in the same position as others. There is a lot of interconnectedness in the system now. It is not really about looking in at any one particular asset category. I know that asset category has got a lot of attention and it is an area we have a lot of attention on. What we do and spend a lot of our time doing is just playing out the various scenarios that could be involved. Sometimes, it is not so much about what is happening in the private credit market, but about what the reaction is going to be if something is happening in the private credit market and what that reaction will mean for the firms we supervise, particularly in relation to our global presence as a financial services centre.</p>
          <p eId="para_117"> Our ability to anticipate and deal with wherever those issues arise has been greatly strengthened by the work we did to prepare for Brexit and the work we had to do during Covid-19. We faced a lot of these issues then where we saw an issue essentially exploding somewhere in the financial markets at global level and then having to react to it. We try not to focus too exclusively on any one asset sector but rather to constantly focus on the holistic picture, making sure we have the data and can get the data to have a really good handle on however that might play out. Even if we were to say that private credit is over there or it does not have direct links with our system, it will have indirect links depending on how it plays out. I assure the Deputy, therefore, that it is an area we are very focused on. As I said, though, this is as part of an overall picture of risks we are examining at any one point in time and making sure our firms are ready for it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_83">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_118">I have a number of questions as well. Over the nearly six years I have been in the Dáil, the issue of fraud and neobanks has been one that has come up for me quite a bit. We are talking about people losing their life savings. I dealt with a couple saving for a wedding lose thousands of euro. I had the same thing with someone saving for a deposit also losing thousands of euro. Another person in Galway who, quite publicly, lost €10,000 was able to get nothing back and there was very little assistance.</p>
          <p eId="para_119"> Clearly, these neobanks are useful. They are companies an awful lot of us use every single day. They are part of the furniture now. They do have a significant role, especially because the longer-term banks have not been up to speed in delivering products and means of use that the neobanks have done. An increasing number of people have one of these neobanks as their only bank and they put their wages in and all those kinds of things. Every time I come across someone who has been scammed out of thousands of euro, I immediately text my friend groups with a reminder to tell them to be really careful where they store their money because this keeps happening.</p>
          <p eId="para_120"> It was interesting the Central Bank mentioned it did not see a difference between scams involving neobanks versus the typical legacy banks or the commercial banks. Is it the case that the Central Bank sees the same number of scams in both contexts?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_84">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_121">Regarding what we see, I am constrained about going into individual firms.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_85">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_122">I have not mentioned any.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_86">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_123">Yes, I understand. There are not that many of them. What we see across the system are quite varying levels of fraud reported or occurring within the firms. What we are not seeing is a distinction between whether it is a digital bank or a non-digital bank.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_87">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_124">Is the Central Bank seeing the same level of fraud in non-digital banks as is being seen in digital banks?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_88">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_125">Within a band, yes. The level across the system is not even. It varies slightly across the firms, but there is no significant variance for the digital banks, <i>per se</i>, compared with the non-digital ones. In other words, we see non-digital banks with the same levels of fraud as digital banks.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_89">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_126">That is very interesting. It does not reflect what I am hearing, which-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_90">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_127">One of the things I have done since taking up this role is to try to spend some time meeting with consumers, consumer groups and others. I have sat in meetings, including with Deputies, with people who have lost their life savings as a result of dealings with unauthorised providers, fraudsters and others online. To be very clear, we see the issues the Cathaoirleach sees. We see them through what the committee brings to our attention and through the sort of interventions Mr. Gallagher and his team do. We are constantly hunting the Internet to find the fraudsters in the first place. We are trying to get the social media companies to shut things down when we see them come up and we are working with firms to get their customer service mechanisms ready. Clearly, in the context of some of the issues which I have heard the Cathaoirleach speak to publicly and which have been brought to our attention, there are particular issues with certain firms, and we will absolutely tackle those.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_91">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_128">Do the sums that are taken in digital banks tend to be larger than the sums taken in the non-digital banks?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_92">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_129">Not especially. I really think it is a question of tackling fraud and customer service in the context of fraud. The different firms have various issues on those two fronts, which we are working to tackle across all the firms we regulate. I am not trying to say-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_93">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_130">No. I do not envy Mr. Kincaid.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_94">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_131">-----that the issues the Cathaoirleach is seeing in relation to one particular firm are not there. They are there. We also see issues with the other firms.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_95">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_132">I do not envy Mr. Kincaid's task. The reality is that people losing life savings is horrific for them. What I have come across a lot is that people contact these digital banks and all they are get are chatbots or people who cannot really assist them. There are a lot of chatbots and that kind of thing. Obviously, when people are in a panic - we have all experienced panic and it is very hard to concentrate fully - to not be able to speak to a real-life person is a significant issue. This is something I have raised on many occasions. What exactly are the banks' obligations in terms of customers service?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_96">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_133">Our stance on customer service with firms is that they make the commercial decision on what business model they are going to have. They own that business model and they are responsible for it. They have to deliver a level of service that is appropriate to the business model they have chosen. If you are choosing a 24-7 convenient payment service model, you need a 24-7 convenient customer support model. Regarding chatbots, there are functionalities that this type of technology can bring that are very useful, depending on the situation you are in. However, we have looked at chatbots in digital-only firms where we have believed that there needs to be a human support as well.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_97">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_134">Can the Central Bank enforce that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_98">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_135">That is a live topic of concern for us in the context of a person who contacts a chatbot and inputs the word "fraud" being put straight through to a human being.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_99">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_136">Is that something the Central Bank can enforce?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_100">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_137">It is something we expect.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_101">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_138">I do not understand. Is the Central Bank able to enforce that or not?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_102">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_139">I always take the view that I am able to enforce the things I expect the firms we regulate to do.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_103">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_140">That is good. It was not a trick question; I was just asking.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_104">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_141">No, it was not, However, I am also conscious of the nature of the engagement we are having with these firms. I think it is fair to say that it is constructive.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_105">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_142">We are not naming any names; I was just asking. I want to ask about something else, but I only have two minutes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_106">
          <from> Ms Yvonne Madden<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_143">I will be really quick. There is a message here for consumers as well. If they are experiencing a fraud, they can go onto their apps and immediately freeze their accounts. It is really important that they do that. Then, there are the in-app facilities and the right to a callback. In other words, everything Mr. Kincaid has mentioned.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_107">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_144">The problem is that a lot of time the money is gone at that point-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_108">
          <from> Ms Yvonne Madden<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_145">True.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_109">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_146">-----and it is scary.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_110">
          <from> Ms Yvonne Madden<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_147">Some of the work we are doing in the context of where we see some firms not refunding to the same level, we are intervening on things like that to ensure firms are looking at their methodologies. That is the type of thing we are doing.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_111">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_148">From what I have been dealing with, much of the time people are being told that they clicked on something. Even though nobody can say what was clicked on and people dispute that, they are still not getting the money back.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_112">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_149">What the Cathaoirleach is describing there is the subject of a live conversation between us and the firms we are regulating.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_113">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_150">Good. I am glad to hear it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_114">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_151">We are not saying that this issue is as it should be-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_115">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_152">It is good that the witnesses are not saying that. I am happy about that. I want to ask one other question that one of our Senators who was unable to attend asked me to pose regarding the exposure relating to crypto in these digital banks. Is there a level of exposure when it comes to crypto in some digital banks?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_116">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_153">Does the Cathaoirleach mean for consumers using the platforms as opposed to the firms themselves?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_117">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_154">I understood it was actually the exposure of the banks.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_118">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_155">Exposure to----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_119">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_156">In the context of crypto. This was a question that was raised with me by somebody was not unable to attend. It is my understanding that the digital banks are exposed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_120">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_157">The banks may have investments in crypto. To go back to what I was saying earlier, they are subject to the same prudential and capital requirements as every other firm that we regulate. Any asset or investment they have, they will have to be holding the necessary capital and systems controls around it, particularly if it is an investment they have made for their own purposes and for their own balance sheet.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_121">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_158">That is fair enough. I assume that the risk involved with crypto is deemed to be far higher.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_122">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_159">It is. If we are talking about a licensed bank making a decision to invest its money in any given asset - private credit was mentioned earlier - there are very defined EU rules that it has to comply with in terms of the capital it has to hold against that and the system controls it has to have in place to cover the risk.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_123">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_160">It is stronger in Ireland, is it not? We know that there has been more regulation in terms of Irish banking. If there is a digital bank that is based somewhere else, it goes by the EU.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_124">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_161">The rules we have for the capital requirements for our banks and the system controls they have to have to look after their own financial position are the same for Irish and other banks across the EU.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_125">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_162">So it does not matter where a bank is based.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_126">
          <from> Mr. Colm Kincaid<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_163">We are operating in and supervised through an EU system.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_127">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_164">Go raibh míle maith agaibh. I thank the witnesses for that. Apologies that we are under a bit of time pressure, but we had to split the sessions. We will suspend for five minutes to allow witnesses from the Banking and Payments Federation Ireland to take their seats.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_7">
          <i>Sitting suspended at 4.48 p.m. and resumed at 4.55 p.m.</i>
        </summary>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_128">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_165">Ba mhaith liom fáilte a chur romhaibh. I welcome the following witnesses from the Banking and Payments Federation Ireland, BPFI: Mr. Brian Hayes, chief executive; Ms Gillian Byrne, head of payments; Ms Niamh Davenport, head of financial crime; and Mr. Peter McGuigan, head of EU affairs. I invite Mr. Hayes to make his opening statement.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_129">
          <from> Mr. Brian Hayes<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_166">I thank the members for the invitation. It is a great privilege to be here. I will not reintroduce my colleagues, as the Chairperson very kindly did so. We are delighted to be here to give evidence to the committee.</p>
          <p eId="para_167"> As members know, we were pleased to contribute to the process of our engagement with the committee in the past, especially on the report it published in October 2024. We regard that as a really important report. As was said on many occasions, we are very committed to seeing whether those recommendations can be fully implemented because we believe that is the beginning, middle and end of this in trying to get to a better and strengthened system.</p>
          <p eId="para_168"> The first thing I will say is that financial fraud is not a victimless crime. It causes real damage to individuals and customers and has grown in recent years. Banks of all shapes and varieties take their responsibility to protect their customers extremely seriously. This is a priority issue for us as an industry group across the sector. Just last week, we launched a cross-sector campaign on human trafficking focused on highlighting the exploitation of people who are trafficked into this country by criminal gangs. Banks are understandably at the front line in spotting unusual or suspicious transactions, protecting people against bad actors and fighting financial crime and scams.</p>
          <p eId="para_169"> Ireland’s banking landscape is undergoing significant transformation, driven largely by accelerating digitalisation and evolving consumer experiences and expectations. The Department of Finance’s consumer sentiment survey for 2025 highlights the scale of this shift: 88% of Irish consumers now engage with online banking services and more than half identify mobile apps as their primary channel for interacting with their financial provider. The adoption of neobanking services also continues to rise, with 43% of adults using these platforms. The survey also shows that most customers in Ireland are multi-banked, as is the case across the European Union. The most recent BPFI payments monitor shows that almost 60% of contactless payments are now made via mobile wallets and, overall, contactless usage accounts for nearly 88% of point-of-sale card transactions. These figures demonstrate the pace of change but also the importance of fostering a dynamic financial ecosystem.</p>
          <p eId="para_170"> Fundamental to our mandate is to support banking competition in Ireland and to improve the landscape so that new banks can enter the market and offer new products and services to customers. The BPFI strongly supports enhanced competition and the innovation it brings for consumers and the wider financial sector. Whether a bank is a fully digital bank, a more traditional bank or something in between, it must comply with all of the various regulatory frameworks within the Irish and EU markets. Equally, all payment institutions and e-money firms must fully comply with EU regulations, such as the payment services directive 2, including strong customer authentication and open banking standards, as well as Irish and EU anti-money laundering legislation and, when authorised in Ireland, the consumer protection code.</p>
          <p eId="para_171"> The shift we have seen over the past decade is reinforced by developments within Ireland’s broader fintech and digital-finance ecosystem. The country has established itself as a significant hub for financial innovation, supported by a skilled workforce, strong links between financial services and global technology firms, and a stable regulatory environment. The domestic fintech sector encompasses payments providers, digital lenders, regtech firms and embedded finance solutions, which all contribute to a diverse market landscape. At the same time, consumer expectations continue to accelerate. Demand for frictionless payments, real-time access to financial information and personalised digital tools are prompting both traditional banks and neobanks to expand their digital capacities and reconfigure their operating models.</p>
          <p eId="para_172">The interplay of these forces - strong incumbents, new entrants and an increasingly digital-first population - continues to shape banking and payments in Ireland. </p>
          <p eId="para_173"> There are, of course, new challenges from this innovation, most notably the increasing complexity and sophistication of fraud. Increasingly, fraud is no longer characterised by criminals attempting to directly compromise bank systems. Instead, perpetrators increasingly manipulate consumers and businesses into authorising payments themselves. This is commonly referred to as authorised push payment, APP, fraud. In an APP scam, a criminal uses deception and social engineering to manipulate a victim to transfer money directly from his or her account into an account controlled by the criminal. Criminals deliberately impersonate trusted entities and create false urgency. Victims genuinely believe they are making a legitimate payment and as a result, the payment is authorised by the customer. APP fraud takes many forms, including investment scams, romance scams and accommodation fraud and for businesses, invoice redirection and CEO impersonation.</p>
          <p eId="para_174"> Financial institutions have a clear role to play in preventing fraud, a responsibility the industry takes very seriously and in which it invests heavily both collectively at industry level and individually within each institution. This includes sophisticated transaction monitoring and behavioural analytics, enhanced consumer authentications and sustained investment in consumer education. Fraud prevention measures continue to evolve, leveraging artificial intelligence, which are now embedded across many detection systems, with some providers deploying increasingly dynamic interventions, and real-time warnings to protect customers at point of payment.</p>
          <p eId="para_175"> It is crucial to recognise that fraud does not originate within the banking system. The first sight a financial provider will have of an APP fraud is when a transaction has already taken place. The drivers of fraud are consistent across all institutions and always begin outside the financial system when criminals make contact with victims - typically online or via telecommunications networks. Payment service providers encounter fraud only at the final stage of a much longer criminal journey. The Central Bank of Ireland’s most recent payment fraud report reinforces this position. It highlights that the fastest growing category of fraud is credit transfer fraud, which is driven primarily by social engineering. In these cases, consumers are manipulated into authorising payments from secure devices and trusted banking applications. This highlights that the vulnerability lies not in the payment system itself but in the criminal exploitation of human behaviour. As the BPFI has consistently stated, tackling fraud requires a whole-of-system response bringing together financial services, technology platforms, telecommunications providers, law enforcement and the State. This must be a cross-border, cross-industry response that involves the public and private sectors working together.</p>
          <p eId="para_176"> The national payments strategy reinforces this need for co-ordinated actions and sets a clear direction for a more integrated national fraud response. The BPFI is leading on several of its key anti-fraud commitments, reflecting the central role the banking sector plays in its delivery. However, the reality is that financial institutions cannot address this challenge in isolation. In other jurisdictions such as the UK and the Netherlands, government-led strategies have played a pivotal role in driving alignment, accountability and resources across all sectors. Ireland would benefit from a similar co-ordinated approach at national level, one that complements the significant work already being undertaken by industry and ensures a unified, proactive response to close gaps and protect consumers. The committee’s aforementioned report on APP fraud recommended this very point - the need for a national economic crime strategy to tackle economic crime and fraud in a comprehensive and collaborative way.</p>
          <p eId="para_177"> The BPFI’s financial crime strategy is anchored on three pillars: collaboration, education and awareness, and information sharing. The BPFI is the current chair of the first national cross-sector anti-fraud forum, which was established earlier this year as part of the national payments strategy. This forum brings together representatives from the banking sector, card schemes, tech companies, law enforcement, Government Departments, industry bodies and regulators. It is driving co-ordinated action through the development of shared standards and intelligence exchange and working towards a national fraud charter. The BPFI also co-ordinates the joint intelligence group, which brings together financial institutions and An Garda Síochána to exchange intelligence on emerging fraud patterns, victim targeting and typologies. BPFI members participate in ComReg initiatives to address spoof callers and phishing, which have successfully blocked over 100 million scam calls from reaching Irish consumers.</p>
          <p eId="para_178"> Education remains one of the most effective tools in preventing fraud and reducing victimisation, particularly as fraudsters continue to target consumers directly. FraudSMART, established and led by the BPFI, is a national fraud awareness programme developed in conjunction with our members that aims to raise consumer and business awareness of the latest financial fraud activity and trends and to provide simple and impartial advice on how best they can protect themselves and their resources from fraud. The programme highlights fraud and scams through national media campaigns, social media, email alerts and direct community engagement. Our most recent campaigns have focused on investment scams, money muling, SME fraud and social engineering, working with partners such as ISME, An Garda Síochána and Google. In addition to national campaigns, FraudSMART has launched Scamchecker.ie, a free online tool that allows consumers to check the legitimacy of a website or link providing early-stage protections and helping consumers to verify suspicious links and avoid contact with fraudulent sites. FraudSMART currently has nine participating members, including domestic banks, digital banks, An Post and credit unions with support from An Garda Síochána.</p>
          <p eId="para_179"> Information sharing, which was also the subject of the committee's report last year, is key in terms of fraud prevention at scale and how we go forward. Shared fraud databases have proven highly effective in other jurisdictions, most notably in the UK and across Europe. Ireland urgently needs to follow suit. Our efforts to establish an Irish shared fraud database are stalled because enabling legislation has not yet been enacted. Without statutory authority, banks cannot exchange sensitive fraud-related data under GDPR, which leaves a critical gap in our national fraud response. Upcoming EU and Irish regulatory changes will provide the legal clarity, certainty and governance required but swift action is essential. Real-time intelligence sharing on known fraud typologies, compromised accounts and emerging risk indicators allows financial institutions to intervene earlier and with greater accuracy. The benefits extend beyond prevention. It assists law enforcement in investigations and prosecutions and protects customers whose identities may have been compromised. We strongly welcome the Department of Justice, Home Affairs and Migration's progress on this legislation and urge its swift enactment.</p>
          <p eId="para_180"> Members may be aware of the provisional agreement reached last week by the European Council and the European Parliament on the new payment services regulation and directive. We welcome the significant decision to adopt stricter provisions that require online platforms to verify the regulatory status of advertisers offering financial products to EU consumers. This is a critical intervention that tackles fraud at its true point of origin, before a victim is ever targeted. The BPFI has actively advocated for this reform for over 18 months with the support of our members and the Department of Finance. Its adoption represents a major shift towards systemic fraud prevention beyond the banking perimeter and recognises that platforms must form part of the anti-fraud architecture.</p>
          <p eId="para_181"> In the context of a very rapidly changing banking environment, fraud is a massive issue that must be addressed. We take our responsibilities as an industry group especially very seriously. We are very convinced that a number of actions identified by the committee and the Dáil could have a significant impact on protecting people as we go forward.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_130">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_182">It is nice to be interacting with Mr. Hayes here in these circumstances. In his opening statement, he referred to government-led strategies in the UK and the Netherlands.</p>
          <p eId="para_183">The implication was that we are a little bit behind here. What action should the Government here be taking? Data-sharing legislation was mentioned as something that is in the pipeline. Will Mr. Hayes expand on what the Government here is not doing or should be doing quicker?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_131">
          <from> Mr. Brian Hayes<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_184">The number one thing we are looking for is a shared fraud database. We are on the record in arguing for this for quite some time. There were concerns from the Data Protection Commission, particularly about GDPR. This has been an issue not only in Ireland but across the European Union. As we have moved forward on this, we have had very good discussions thus far with the Department of justice. This requires a statutory instrument to be laid before both Houses. Of course, the DPC will have sight of it and will be able to comment on it. We stand ready across our member banks to implement the shared fraud database as a really important example of what the collective sector can do together, by bringing together all of the information. We have been hamstrung by virtue of the fact we do not have this system. The UK has had the system for at least a decade. I will ask my colleague Ms Davenport to take this a bit further because it is our number one ask of the committee.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_132">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_185">The shared fraud database is definitely our number one ask. It is something we have been looking at for nearly ten years. The UK has had it for nearly 40 years. It is something that is well established under the same legislation. We welcome any progress from the Department of justice, and we have been engaging with it over the past year in particular on getting it over the line. We know progress has been made but we encourage swift action on it.</p>
          <p eId="para_186"> In addition to this, the Department of justice also had a consultation, which closed in November 2024, on a national economic crime strategy. This is wider than just looking at one area of information sharing. It is looking at the cross-sectoral capabilities and what law enforcement needs to be able to prosecute and get through the vast number of suspicious transaction reports received. It is about looking at technology and how Departments, industry bodies and various players in the ecosystem can use technology for the betterment of crime prevention. All of the efforts, and we will probably say this multiple times today, should be focused on prevention. This is the best way we can move forward and stop consumers being targeted by these online advertisements in particular.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_133">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_187">An education programme was mentioned. Does the Banking and Payments Federation do anything for schools? I am thinking in particular of transition year education programmes. We all remember a couple of years ago when a load of children at a school in Kerry gave their bank details and they were used for fraudulent activities.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_134">
          <from> Mr. Brian Hayes<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_188">We take this very seriously as an industry group. We have a service that we can provide to schools, community groups and a variety of various groups around the country. It is limited because we do not have huge resources in this area. We think it helps to get the message across group by group. The bigger issue is around our FraudSMART brand, which Deputy Timmins may see on occasion. We set this up and it is supported by our banks, as I said, including international banks, our domestic banks and our digital banks also. This is important because it is an opportunity to explain directly the nature of the new scams that we see. This is something we can develop further.</p>
          <p eId="para_189"> If I could make one point of criticism, if I can be frank on this, there is a tendency in other jurisdictions to do more public-private partnerships in this area. We do not have this here and we are missing out, in a sense, on the public and private sectors getting behind something together. Even though An Garda Síochána is very supportive of all that we do in FraudSMART, there is a political necessity for the Government, through one Minister, to lead out on financial crime. Sometimes we do get caught between the Department of justice and the Department of Finance, if I can be frank. Other countries have a more holistic approach to this. Certainly FraudSMART is our contribution to this and we would like to do an awful lot more.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_135">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_190">We would love to do more in schools. It is a very heavy curriculum that everybody wants to get involved in. The case Deputy Timmins referred to in Kerry involved 60 transition year students who became money mules. Every year we have a campaign on money mules and the demographic that we target is students. We run it in September generally, when students are going back to college. We see an increase in students having high costs and they get tempted into money muling. Every year we have a campaign on it to bring awareness. It is primarily on social media, given the audience. We do not expect everyone in the room here to see it but it is targeted directly at the students.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_136">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_191">I know there is a limit to what the Banking and Payments Federation can do with its resources but it is certainly something I raised with the Minister for education a few months back, with regard to educating kids in transition year and with regard to transition year programmes becoming much more relevant to real life, such as what we are talking about here today.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_137">
          <from> Mr. Brian Hayes<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_192">The whole question of financial education is a very important issue. I know in the UK it is part of the curriculum. Whether this is the approach here is another matter. This whole question of keeping people safe and making sure they are aware of financial crime could fit very neatly into a wider financial education. At one level, are we the people to do this, given the fact we represent the industry? We lobby for the industry. This is why I would make the call to the committee to consider a much wider public-private partnership piece which would involve us, the credit institutions directly and the State in doing more together. It is this holistic piece. I am aware that in other countries there are particular Ministers with responsibility for financial crime because it does fit into a number of different Departments. It is something we could learn from.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_138">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_193">It falls between stools a little bit here.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_139">
          <from> Mr. Brian Hayes<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_194">It has a tendency to do this, yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_140">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_195">To go back to an old chestnut about people wanting to hear a live voice when they ring, I gave an example earlier of an elderly couple applying for the non-contributory old age pension who could not get anybody at An Post and it is the only bank account they have. They have to send a copy of bank statements as part of means testing but they could not get anyone on the phone for three days and they only get an annual statement. There is a website with a phone number, the same as with the neobanks, but it is about trying to enforce these numbers whereby someone picks up the phone at the other end and people are not sent around the houses.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_141">
          <from> Mr. Brian Hayes<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_196">The point is well made. On occasion people need to speak directly to a human being. Each bank is different in terms of its operating model. The traditional banks in Ireland also use digital, online and apps in the same way that neobanks do. Their model is based on branch banking, online banking and call centres. It is a slightly different model on the neobanking side. Not all neobanks are the same but if they were answering the question they would probably say they have developed a system that uses chatbots to try to make sure they get to the root of the problem and then move on to a live chat for people and, in circumstances where a customer needs direct in-app conversations, this can happen also. It is a different model from the more traditional banks. The traditional banks, if they were here, would say that is their model and how they compete and, equally, the neobanks compete with their model. There are different models but the point is well made. There are occasions when people need to speak and certainly-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_142">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_197">Not everyone uses the Internet.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_143">
          <from> Mr. Brian Hayes<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_198">But, of course, if someone has neobank account they have an app.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_144">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_199">Sorry, I mean for the regular banks such as An Post.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_145">
          <from> Mr. Brian Hayes<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_200">Yes, and the point is well made.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_146">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_201">How successful are we in tracking down people who use an 087 number to phone someone and tell them their Visa account has been defrauded? I know it is a fraudulent call. I used to get a few from Italy for some reason, which began with 0039. Has there been any success in following up these numbers? Some of them are Irish mobile numbers but they are clearly not based in Ireland.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_147">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_202">I will not necessarily speak on whether they have been tracked down, as this would be a matter for An Garda Síochána, but what I can say from our perspective is that ComReg has been working on seven initiatives on prevention. One of them is DNO, which is do not originate, in which our members also participate. To use the example of a call centre, these are numbers that send online messages and never originate calls, so they cannot be used for scam calls. There was another initiative whereby there are international numbers appearing on these calls and we never see Irish numbers any more. This is down to ComReg and the initiatives it has taken. At least it is a little bit of a red flag if people are getting an international number as opposed to an Irish number. This is a huge step. ComReg also recently launched an SMS service whereby people will see if text message comes in and the business has not registered-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_148">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_203">They are untrackeable, though. The numbers that appear on one's phone are untrackeable.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_149">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_204">The numbers are being spoofed. If it is an impersonation, they are spoofing a number. It does not originate from that number.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_150">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_205">I tried dialling back the Irish mobile-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_151">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_206">You will not be able to.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_152">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_207">It is a different person producing it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_153">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_208">I am not an IT expert, but that is all working in the background. I suggest that everybody reports those to An Garda Síochána. Even if somebody has not fallen victim to a scam, it is really important to report this information because gardaí can use it to build a case. There may be another case, and they will always ask us to get that message out there. It may be a missing piece of information.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_154">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_209">Ms Davenport referred to the massive amount of data the BPFI gets. It is obviously using AI to figure things out. Does it flag stuff to the authorities, for example, the Department of Social Protection and An Garda Síochána. if it sees suspicious activity relating to accounts?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_155">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_210">All suspicious activity has to be reported. That comes under the anti-money laundering regulation. We know that the suspicious transaction reports they have to make under this regulation have tripled in the past number of years. This is why we are very supportive of the national economic crime strategy, particularly with regard to technology, to be able to enhance prosecutions on that side. All of those reports have to be made to An Garda Síochána for any suspicious transactions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_156">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_211">Does the BPFI produce data similar to crime statistics we get in respect of the number of burglaries, detection success rates and how matters are trending? Does it have such statistics? How many of cases are solved?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_157">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_212">The Central Bank produces an annual report that includes broad statistics. The report came out in October 2025 and showed a number of different areas and data points. For example, it revealed €160 million in fraudulent transactions in 2024. I would flag that this is 0.001% of the value of all payments. In its report, the Central Bank said that the level of fraud in Ireland is low and stabled in comparison with other countries. We do not have statistics on the reimbursement side or in respect of recoveries, as the Deputy referred to it, but we will have them under the new payment services regulation in respect of certain types of fraud.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_158">
          <from> Mr. Brian Hayes<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_213">There is a very important development that will make a very big difference on a number of fronts. Could Mr. McGuigan inform the committee about the change, because it is important for the committee to hear about it?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_159">
          <from> Mr. Peter McGuigan<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_214">Under the payment services regulation, European legislators have sought to tighten up the prevention of fraud and have looked at a number of mechanisms. One of these is verification. If an online company is advertising, it needs to be a regulated provider in the EU in order to ensure that it is not just anyone uploading an advertisement online. Reports need to be generated. Financial institutions would give that data to the regulator and the regulator would publish information annually on the amount in reimbursements and the number of claims that were not reimbursed for a reason, for example, gross negligence. The regulation also contains a greater requirement to share fraud information among financial institutions and, we understand, maybe within social media companies as well in order that there is more of a cross-sectoral approach. Ms Byrne can speak to the verification of payee and the mechanism that was brought in under the instant payments regulation and has been extended within the payment services regulation to all types of credit transfers.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_160">
          <from> Mr. Brian Hayes<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_215">Verification of payee only recently came in. It is an important new addition that Ms Byrne might talk about.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_161">
          <from> Ms Gill Byrne<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_216">The second phase of the instant payments roll-out was very successfully delivered on behalf of all the Irish banks and all the payment service providers across the EU on 9 October. It means that we can all make instant payments within ten seconds 24-7. That was a significant delivery and was very much welcomed by consumers wanting and choosing quick frictionless payments in line with consumer demand. Alongside this was introduced was a feature called verification of payee. A total of 88% of us have used Internet banking in the past year according to the Department of Finance customer sentiments survey. Everyone who is using an app, is online or is making a payment via a branch will have this additional feature, which provides greater assurance and control to people when they are making payments not just for instant payments but for regular payments. What it does is match the name a person inputs for the payment and confirms that the name held with the actual account of that-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_162">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_217">We have all experienced that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_163">
          <from> Ms Gill Byrne<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_218">That is a significant delivery, and a great additional layer of security.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_164">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_219">It is an extra check.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_165">
          <from> Ms Gill Byrne<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_220">Exactly.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_166">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_221">A lot of fraud is not reported. People are embarrassed. If some guy broke into your house and stole €2,000 you had under a mattress, you would report it. If he did something online, however, you are not going to report it because you are embarrassed. There is massive underreporting.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_167">
          <from> Mr. Brian Hayes<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_222">That is true. One must have a lot of sympathy for people who go through this. There is a sense of embarrassment about it. It highlights the point we are all making about the necessity of reporting this to make sure statistics accurately reflect what is happening. It is probably inevitable, given that banking has gone online that we are seeing more instances of this. It has changed dramatically.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_168">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_223">In a peculiar way, it is actually more painless. It is like buying something with a credit card. It is more painless than handing over €200 in notes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_169">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_224">We encourage people to talk about it, particularly through our FraudSMART campaign. We have seen a shift, particularly with the media reporting more on fraud, so that people are more willing to talk about it. We definitely talk about the scams but we might not be as likely to do so if we have fallen victim to one. Fraudsters are professionals. This is their full-time job so these scams are extremely sophisticated and very clever. This is not somebody chancing their arm. The scams have evolved from that. This is organised crime.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_170">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_225">Are any of them getting caught? They do not appear on the 9 o'clock news like regular guys.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_171">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_226">They are often prosecuted for different things. An Garda Síochána is taking prosecutions. There was a big prosecution earlier this year involving the Black Axe gang. This is all what this is funding so fraud and money laundering are connected. We have to look at the full picture. This is why it is really important to realise that this is what the fraud is funding. It is funding human trafficking, which is why we had the human trafficking campaign last week.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_172">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_227">It is just another arm of their business.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_173">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_228">It is.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_174">
          <from> Mr. Brian Hayes<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_229">It is also worth stating that banks are very conscious that because many people are going online, they have to put in a clunkiness sometimes that is not there. This is a clunkiness around strong customer authentication and verification of payee. Some banks impose a maximum limit for new payees on the first day.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_175">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_230">What this is for so the customer has to tick a box.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_176">
          <from> Mr. Brian Hayes<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_231">They are conscious that because people have moved online and are using their apps. They have a responsibility to make sure that people have a second look at these things. I also know that neobanks employ this as well - having a two-minute thing, "Are you sure this is the right person you're sending it to? Do you want to think about that again?". One can use digital channels in a variety of ways to make sure one protects people and they have a responsibility to get that right.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_177">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_232">We have had quite an interesting debate. The reason for it is because so many people have been defrauded. Many people have gone public. I understand that some do not go public. There is definitely an element of embarrassment involved, but the reality is that these people are professional scammers, they know what they are doing and they know how to scam all of us.</p>
          <p eId="para_233"> I am contacted more by people who have been scammed in digital banks. Digital banks play a hugely important role in our society. Loads of us have them on our phones. They are very helpful and handy, but I am generally contacted by people who have been scammed when it comes to digital banking. Do the witnesses see a difference in terms of the level of scams that happen within digital banks compared with bricks-and-mortar banks?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_178">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_234">No, we do not see any difference. What is happening - because it is consumers rather than the banks that are being targeted - is that fraudsters are targeting consumers directly. We see approximately 80% to 90% of scams originate online. That is where the scams are happening. There is no difference. The number of attempts and the targets are no different between the neobanks or digital banks and the more traditional banks.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_179">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_235">Can I assume, though, that the type of scam is different?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_180">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_236">No, they are all being targeted with the same scams. Particularly in the past six months, we have seen a lot of online ads for investment scams. There has been a huge number of investment scams in the past six to 12 months. It has been growing year on year. It is the same types of scams, because consumers are being targeted by the same ones all the time. It could be text scams, online scams or emails scams, but they are primarily online scams.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_181">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_237">Can Ms Davenport give some examples of the types of scams? Can she go into that because it would helpful?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_182">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_238">There are a range of scams. We see banking impersonation scams, where they impersonate a bank. There are investment scams, which could be for traditional investments such as bonds, shares and such things or the scam could involve cryptocurrency as well. There are a lot of ads online for cryptocurrencies. There are romance scams, which again go across all the different banks, and text message scams.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_183">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_239">That is a particularly personal scam about which people are less likely to come forward.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_184">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_240">Romance scams and investment scams are the ones we need to act quickly on. To be honest, in any authorised push-payment scams - which they fall into - people need to act as quickly as possible. However, they are quite personal and take a long time. For those two scams in particular, we find it could be six months before someone makes a payment, so it is a long time before people realise they have been scammed in many of those cases. When they realise, they might not want to believe it, so they might take even more time to report what happened. That is why it is important, in any of those authorised push-payment scams but particularly investment and romance scams, that even if people have an inkling, that they come forward as quickly as possible.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_185">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_241">Romance scams basically involve an online relationship.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_186">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_242">They involve an online relationship, yes. There have been multiple examples over the years. They might involve companionship or a romantic relationship. It can take several months. People build up the relationship and know the person. They will ignore some of the red flags they might notice. The fraudster may not even ask for money. This is how fraudsters use manipulation tactics, and this is the social engineering we talk about in all scams. It is where all scams are going now. In people's heads they are in a committed relationship. We see things like fraudsters claiming to be having trouble getting a visa or paying for flights to come and visit the person. The fraudster does not ask for any funds, but people who are in relationships want to help and will transfer the money to do so. Those are the kinds of tactics they use for romance scams.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_187">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_243">It is incredibly difficult.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_188">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_244">Yes, it is incredibly difficult. It is very personal. It is definitely one that people do not want to admit to family and friends, whereas if people have bought something online with their credit cards on a dodgy website, for example, they will tell everyone about it and tell them not to use the website. There are different characteristics of various types of scams, for sure.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_189">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_245">That is devastating.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_190">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_246">Yes, it is heartbreaking.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_191">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_247">I am sure it has huge implications for mental health and everything like that. I have not been contacted about those types of scams, probably because it is quite personal.</p>
          <p eId="para_248"> However, I have been contacted quite often when the money just comes out of the system. It happens when people are contacted by what they believe to be the bank. That is one way. There was also a scam Ms Davenport might remember, perhaps three years ago at Christmas. People gave their phone numbers when they were getting a lift and got scammed out of money that way. That was a big issue.</p>
          <p eId="para_249"> Recently, I was contacted by someone who lost all his savings for his house deposit. He believes he did not click on anything. It must have been something. I am not sure exactly how it happened, but there are things like that as well where people do not necessarily fall for something.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_192">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_250">There are multiple cases - and I will not speak about any individual case - but where people do not believe they did anything, over the years we have seen cases where there might be an app they have downloaded in the background of their phones. They do not know it is tracking their behaviour on their phones, so we always tell people, for example, to make sure they download apps from official stores. There might be something on their phones that they do not realise they have downloaded and it could take weeks. It could lie dormant on the phone before people realise and they might never know that is where it came from. There are multiple ways that fraudsters can get in. It is not always by people clicking on or going into something. They are the most common ones, but late last year there was a spate of instances. One was with a photo clean up app or something to tidy up the apps on a phone, where the apps were sitting on phones in another app, so there are lots of different ways that fraudsters can get in.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_193">
          <from> Mr. Brian Hayes<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_251">The important thing is that where these happen, neobanks and traditional banks have a responsibility to take the issues and, on a case-by-case basis, look at exactly what has happened in a given scenario. The majority of banks take a common sense approach to this. If people feel they have not been properly treated as a consequence, I can assure the committee that banks spend a lot of money on complaints processes.</p>
          <p eId="para_252"> Only last week, we had a discussion with our member banks about the upcoming revised consumer protection code, which the deputy governor spoke about earlier in the meeting and how they are preparing for it. That discussion has happened at board level, ExCo level, first line of defence and second line of defence across the whole bank. They take these issues very seriously.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_194">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_253">They may, but there is an issue. We have to be frank. I understand the witnesses are a representative group and will not realistically come and say, whatever their views are, but there is an issue. From the people who contact me, I know they are talking to bots and they never receive the money back. One woman lost €10,000 and never got anything back. She was hardly able to contact a person in customer service.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_195">
          <from> Mr. Brian Hayes<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_254">As an industry group, we think it is critically important that contact is made, particularly in that kind of scenario. We have said that publicly. There are two sides to every story about what has happened. We certainly cannot adjudicate on that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_196">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_255">I have sometimes made contact on their behalf. I will not name any names, but there have been issues. People contact me about a variety of things and ask me to help and make representations. In those instances, sometimes I get great responses, but more often than not, I do not.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_197">
          <from> Mr. Brian Hayes<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_256">The customer complaining is important because there are significant processes behind the complaints procedures. Probably some are better than others. One of the things we are conscious of as a group is to share best practice. That is why it is important that the neobanks have joined BPFI, certainly those who have authorised entities in this country, that they are part of a network and system that looks at fraud, linked to Ms Davenport's point, and that they share what they are seeing. It is really important they are part of the industry response and learn from best practice from one another. Ultimately, if a case goes before the Financial Services and Pensions Ombudsman, FSPO, it is up to him to adjudicate, but we would hope cases do not have to go to the FSPO, that they would be mediated through the bank, but each case is separate and different.</p>
          <p eId="para_257"> On the Deputy's point about the investment cases and the €10,000 case, I have spoken to international banks based in Dublin about people calling to their office saying they have just handed over €20,000 or €30,000 to Bank X, even though it is a wholesale, non-retail bank in Ireland. The prospectus the person got will have the bank and its CEO all over it, but it is all fraudulent and impersonated. It is an example of the lengths to which fraudsters will go to dupe people and take their money.</p>
          <p eId="para_258"> An important point was made about FraudSMART, that we are increasingly seeing more of our international bank colleagues join FraudSMART too, being part of it and recognising they have a role to play in this as well, particularly the larger international banks here who are well known and are being impersonated by fraudsters across the country.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_198">
          <from> Ms Gill Byrne<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_259">Also, the evolution and customers trends, which Mr. Hayes mentioned in his opening statement, show we are a multi-bank community and 46% of Irish people have a digital bank and use it on a regular basis. From the data - and previously the Central Bank of Ireland called it out as well - there does not seem to be a difference between the providers.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_199">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_260">It is very interesting.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_200">
          <from> Ms Gill Byrne<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_261">Perhaps it is more about the nature of consumer trends in general. We in Ireland are digitally savvy. We have, according to the Department of Finance customer sentiment survey, a significant portion of customers who are using multiple providers. It could be more down to consumer trends.</p>
          <p eId="para_262"> I reiterate that in terms of the evolution of the digital journey, those interventions for a lot of providers are dynamic interventions. Customers like quick and frictionless journeys when it comes to payments, as the contactless trends clearly show. Those interventions are evolving and becoming more dynamic, depending on who you are and what you are paying for, etc. Verification of the payee helps with those types of fraud cases, including romance scams and CEO impersonation. If you are making a payment and think you are paying somebody, and the name does not match the account, you are going to think twice and, we hope, will call the bank and say you have a query. If that is identified as fraud, the bank will deal with it appropriately and notify the Garda.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_201">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_263">That is if you can get through to someone. Some of the digital banks do not seem to be the same as bricks-and-mortar banks that you just walk into if you need to.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_202">
          <from> Ms Gill Byrne<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_264">Our understanding, from discussions with all our members, is that they have different customer journeys in the way they manage these queries. When it escalates and becomes a fraud case, if it is determined as a fraud, there is live customer support. That is my understanding.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_203">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_265">It is not Ms Byrne's decision so I am not casting blame. The issue is that on the one hand, we are told we need to deal with it immediately. On the other, we have a situation with some digital banks whereby you are trying to get away from the bots and find somebody live. It takes a lot of time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_204">
          <from> Ms Gill Byrne<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_266">Time is of the essence.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_205">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_267">There is a timing issue. I understand that Banking and Payments Federation Ireland cannot make the decisions on behalf of these groups, but I want to make it clear that having quicker personal customer service is essential. It is a matter that we raised with representatives of the Central Bank. It seems to be an issue that the Central Bank is looking at or negotiating. That needs to be in force. A lot of money is being held in these digital banks, and money can be made out of that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_206">
          <from> Mr. Brian Hayes<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_268">That is 100% correct. We see that in the first instance as a matter for the regulator.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_207">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_269">Yes, of course.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_208">
          <from> Mr. Brian Hayes<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_270">If the regulator is seeing poor customer service, it is its obligation to intervene and call that out. It has a bilateral relationship with the entity concerned. Irrespective of whether it is a traditional bank or a neobank, as the Chair said, banks have been using machine learning for a very long time. They have good predictive models. If they see an amount coming out of an account at a certain time of day from a certain age cohort and going to a suspicious settlement institution, those are all red flags. I was behind the scenes and looking at some of those models. Banks are determined by models for everything, including for capital, liquidity, credit risk and everything else. The model they use to look at suspicious transactions is quite sophisticated, bank by bank, in terms of the investment made. At one level, we are seeing the outcome of the cases of the Cathaoirleach's constituents and others. Equally, the banks are stopping a lot of fraud at source by using all of the prompts. Those prompts include asking if you are sure you are sending money to the right person, if someone is pressurising you and why you are making the transaction. Those kinds of prompts that the banks make behind the scenes are preventing a lot of fraud. It is about how we develop that. To the Cathaoirleach's point, which was well made, the human interaction piece is important.</p>
          <p eId="para_271"> Banks take what they call the net promoter score very seriously. The net promoter score is whether you would recommend the service of a bank to your friends and family. They take that very seriously. If the net promoter score is going in the wrong direction, it is a reputational issue for the bank.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_209">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_272">Of course.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_210">
          <from> Mr. Brian Hayes<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_273">It is an issue that is reported at board level, executive committee level and across the bank. The banks have to keep on top of the issue.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_211">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_274">Every time I am contacted by somebody about fraud and instances where they have lost thousands of euro, I immediately put it into numerous WhatsApp groups to tell my friends not to hold money in the institution because there is concern. I tell people to be very careful about where they hold their money. Mr. Hayes is saying that no matter the institution, it seems to be a massive issue.</p>
          <p eId="para_275"> What he said was interesting. I understand what he means about modelling and red flags. I have noticed that for every transaction I do at the moment, I am told it is not the correct name. That is a bit concerning because the warning becomes useless.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_212">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_276">That is the introduction of the verification of payees.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_213">
          <from> Mr. Brian Hayes<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_277">It is the law.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_214">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_278">It is happening for every single person I transact with. Does it not then really-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_215">
          <from> Ms Gill Byrne<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_279">It might depend on the name the Cathaoirleach have saved for that particular payee.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_216">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_280">I have done it wrong for everyone.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_217">
          <from> Ms Gill Byrne<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_281">It might depend. Instead of my sister's name, I might have "sister". I might have "plumber". If I am going to send a payment, "plumber" is not going to match the actual name on the account. It might depend on what name you have saved online or on your mobile banking application for a particular payee. If it matches, it will give a match. Is it always no match?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_218">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_282">Every single time. I do not know.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_219">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_283">That has happened to me recently as well. Once you change it to the actual matching name-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_220">
          <from> Mr. Brian Hayes<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_284">You will not be asked a second time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_221">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_285">-----you will not be asked a second time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_222">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_286">I am worried. I realised that I was just clicking on the "Yes" button and then thought, wait a minute-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_223">
          <from> Ms Gill Byrne<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_287">Any of the notifications are a matter of balance. We do not want people to start ignoring them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_224">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_288">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_225">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_289">That is why there has been a change, and we will continue to see a change, to more dynamic notifications. The situation is different for the verification of a payee. That is always going to be match or no match, and if it matches, a transaction will go straight through and you will not be asked. If you are making a new payment, for example, or if a payment is in a particular amount, there will be different warnings. Every institution has its own different models, but we will see more of that coming in, over time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_226">
          <from> Ms Gill Byrne<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_290">If you get a no match-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_227">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_291">Jump out.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_228">
          <from> Ms Gill Byrne<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_292">-----the motto is that you should verify the details via a validated source.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_229">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_293">Banks have their own internal mechanisms and all of that. I was contacted by one woman. I was going to say "correct me if I am wrong", but the witnesses do not know the situation. I recall that she had done a transaction and got a call from the bank to say there was an issue and she needed to transfer the money back in a particular way. In fact, it was the fraud worsening and she lost even more money.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_230">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_294">That is a common development we have seen in scams. You may get a text message. There have been fewer of them since the ComReg initiative and we should see fewer such examples. It is where you get a text message and click on a link. What you have actually done is put in information. For example, if you were to get a text message with a customs charge of €3.50, it is not the €3.50 they are looking for. When you click on that link, they are looking for your name, address and telephone number. The information you are giving out is giving them more information. They then call and ask if they are taking to, for example, Niamh Davenport. This is the social engineering piece that is luring you into the scam and making you believe that who you are talking to is who they say they are, which is not the case. They layer it. This is the sophistication we have see develop over recent years.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_231">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_295">They have people doing it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_232">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_296">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_233">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_297">It must be big business.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_234">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_298">It is big business. People are being recruited into it unwillingly in many countries. This is happening overseas-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_235">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_299">I heard that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_236">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_300">-----where people are being held against their will and made to perform these scams on a daily basis.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_237">
          <from> Mr. Brian Hayes<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_301">If they send out 1 million texts, they are looking for just one or two responses. Then they are quids in. If you speak to An Garda Síochána or any of the banks around this, it is all done outside the country ostensibly. Some of it is in the country but the majority is outside the country. They are just funnelling the numbers through.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_238">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_302">I had heard of that. There is a human trafficking element that the witnesses are saying is funding-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_239">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_303">Yes. We launched a campaign on human trafficking last week. Human trafficking, or modern day slavery, is in every town around Ireland. We launched a campaign for consumers to understand and notify where there are red flags around human trafficking in Ireland. It is happening in other countries. The people who are making these calls do not necessarily want to be a part of the scam.</p>
          <p eId="para_304">They are being held against their will. Their passports have been taken and they are being held in what are unofficially known as hotels, but they are far from being hotels.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_240">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_305">I thank Ms Davenport. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_241">
          <from> Mr. Peter McGuigan<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_306">I will just add to that in regard to some of the changes at European level being looked at prevention. A lot of the good work that ComReg does involves stopping those texts, but some of the higher value scams originate on social media and such platforms. We have been strongly advocating that social media or these companies, be it Google or whichever of them, would require that they would only accept ads from regulated financial service providers. We will have seen many of the examples where Irish politicians have been impersonated, etc. The tactic used is to get people offline. People click on the ad, give their information to invest in a government bond, for example, which might say it will give people a 5% return. People think that 5% is legitimate, but what the scammers really want are their details. Going forward, hopefully, this should be prevented with these changes at a European level, or at least the onslaught of these types of ads people are getting on certain platforms. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_242">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_307">We started this work 18 months ago on trying to lobby for that aspect to go into the new payments services regulation. It has started. We should flag that Ireland is slightly ahead in the sense that Google implemented it here a year ago. From a Google perspective, we are one of six countries, I think, to have this in. It is not across all social media, but this regulation will bring it across all technology platforms. It is a huge change. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_243">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_308">I had to pay the M50 toll today. If I google "M50 toll", my worry is always what if there is a scam that comes up first and I end up putting in all my details. Are there protections against this happening? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_244">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_309">The payments services regulation is focused solely on financial institutions and ads for financial services. It is to stop those banking impersonation scams in particular. I would not see that people would be getting one specifically on a toll road.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_245">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_310">It might be when stopping or whatever it might be. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_246">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_311">I know what the Cathaoirleach is saying. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_247">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_312">It should say it on the website. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_248">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_313">Okay.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_249">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_314">I will also use this as an opportunity to say we have <i>scamchecker.ie</i>. It was mentioned in the statement that we launched this last year. People can go onto that website, put in any URL and it will help in verifying whether it is a real one or not. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_250">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_315">That is all from me. I call an Teachta Timmins. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_251">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_316">I have a few quick questions. Ms Gill spoke about instant payments and ten seconds. To use that dreadful phrase, though, when it is gone, it is gone and the money cannot come back. Is this the case? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_252">
          <from> Ms Gill Byrne<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_317">We go back to the focus needing to be on prevention, and you have the interventions. Does the risk profile change when it is an instant payment? Naturally, it does because the money lands into the account within ten seconds and if a fraudster is on top of it, they will move the money out. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_253">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_318">Does the bank take it back before the fraudster uses it? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_254">
          <from> Ms Gill Byrne<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_319">If the fraudster is on top of it and the bank does not know about it, he or she has the potential to take it out within the ten seconds. The risk profile does change. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_255">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_320">Can the bank take it back if it gets to it first? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_256">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_321">It depends on where the funds go to. It does make it more challenging. That is totally a fair point. The risk profile does change in that it does heighten it. I suppose that is why when instant payments were rolled out, very intentionally verification of payee for instant payments and regular transfers was rolled out too to try to protect people or add an additional layer of security and greater assurance that the right person was being paid.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_257">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_322">Going back to the people issue again, I know we have probably thrashed it to death at this stage, but it is part of the customer service requirement to have a voice at the end of the phone. There is that comfort. It is like seeing gardaí on the beat. It does not have any impact but there is the comfort of having customer service confidence in the system. That is the benefit of it. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_258">
          <from> Mr. Brian Hayes<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_323">People have moved from bank branches, though not exclusively. Our pillar banks argue heavily that it is important for them as part of their competitive edge to have branches around the country in terms of-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_259">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_324">To meet a person walking in the door. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_260">
          <from> Mr. Brian Hayes<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_325">Yes. There is a different model for neobanks, though, because they do not have branches and operate through quite a slick platform. If they were here, they would make the point that they escalate to that live conversation and potentially to where that in-app call that is made. Ultimately, the question is whether this is sufficient for people who are in the middle of that very stressful situation. This is an issue they will address. Ultimately, though, it is that escalation point that is important because it can solve it. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_261">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_326">I have one final comment. I worked with a company a few years ago and we had an American bank. We had an operation in America and it was controlled from Ireland. I was controlling the bank account. If I did a transfer over $5,000 or $10,000 to pay an American supplier, for example, I got a phone call within a few minutes from the American bank asking me if I had put the transfer through before it was authorised. The voice does give confidence.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_262">
          <from> Mr. Brian Hayes<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_327">I fully accept that. Each bank has its own policy in this regard, but especially for the more traditional banks, but also for the neobanks, if a new payee is being created, there is a maximum amount a person can send in one day. They argue that having that limitation is a good thing. It might be frustrating for us because we cannot get the full amount to someone. The banks, though, argue that is a good thing because it creates a bit of friction in the system to slow things down. If they were here, bank representatives would say that for them it is an important additional protection they have introduced. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_263">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_328">In the app, it is only possible to transfer something like €1,000 a day. If I log into the online banking, though, it is possible to transfer much more through that fail-safe system. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_264">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_329">As much as consumers want frictionless fast payments, we would be looking to maybe go the opposite way sometimes from the perspective of financial crime. Those controls are there to protect consumers. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_265">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_330">I agree with Ms Davenport. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_266">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_331">From a fraud perspective, whether it is a digital bank or one of the traditional banks, we tell people to make sure they are flagging that a call is about fraud. It is important for people to say why they are ringing and to get through to the right section. From the digital perspective, for fraud, live calls available are in-app, so it is important to note that difference. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_267">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_332">That is good. It is too easy to pay. That is the bottom line.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_268">
          <from> Ms Niamh Davenport<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_333">Yes, it is.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_269">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_334">We need to make it more painful.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_270">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-03T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_335">I am not sure that should be the Deputy's election line. Go raibh maith agaibh. I thank all the witnesses for coming in front of the committee. It has been quite interesting and eye-opening. I thank members for participating in today's meeting.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_8"> The joint committee adjourned at 5.57 p.m. until 3.30 p.m. on Wednesday, 10 December 2025.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
