<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#debates">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_and_food/2025-10-08/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_and_food/2025-10-08/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-10-08" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#author" href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/34/joint_committee_on_agriculture_and_food"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_and_food/2025-10-08/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_and_food/2025-10-08/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-10-08" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_and_food/2025-10-08/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_and_food/2025-10-08/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-10-16" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#debates">
        <TLCPerson eId="AindriasMoynihan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Aindrias-Moynihan.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Aindrias Moynihan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DannyHealyRae" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Danny-Healy-Rae.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Danny Healy-Rae"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="EileenLynch" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Eileen-Lynch.S.2025-01-29" showAs="Eileen Lynch"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ErinMcGreehan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Erin-McGreehan.S.2020-06-29" showAs="Erin McGreehan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JoeCooney" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Joe-Cooney.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Joe Cooney"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MartinKenny" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Martin-Kenny.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Martin Kenny"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MichaelFitzmaurice" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Michael-Fitzmaurice.D.2014-10-10" showAs="Michael Fitzmaurice"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="NatashaNewsomeDrennan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Natasha-Newsome-Drennan.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Natasha Newsome Drennan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ParaicBrady" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paraic-Brady.S.2025-01-29" showAs="Paraic Brady"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaulDaly" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paul-Daly.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Paul Daly"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaulLawless" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paul-Lawless.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Paul Lawless"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="VictorBoyhan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Victor-Boyhan.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Victor Boyhan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="WilliamAird" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/William-Aird.D.2024-11-29" showAs="William Aird"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/chair" showAs="Chair" eId="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/vice_chairman" showAs="Vice Chairman" eId="Vice_Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/author" showAs="author" eId="author"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/editor" showAs="editor" eId="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>AN COMHCHOISTE UM THALMHAÍOCHT AGUS BIA</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>Joint Committee on Agriculture and Food</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2025-10-08">Dé Céadaoin, 08 Deireadh Fómhair 2025</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2025-10-08">Wednesday, 08 October 2025</docDate>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_en">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_ga">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">Tháinig an Comhchoiste le chéile ag 03:30 p.m.</summary>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">The Joint Committee met at 03:30 p.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_3">Comhaltaí a bhí i láthair / Members present:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_1">Teachtaí Dála / Deputies</p>
              </th>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_2">Seanadóirí / Senators</p>
              </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#WilliamAird">William Aird</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#VictorBoyhan">Victor Boyhan</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#JoeCooney">Joe Cooney</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#ParaicBrady">Paraic Brady</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#MichaelFitzmaurice">Michael Fitzmaurice</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#JoanneCollins">Joanne Collins</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_9">
                  <person refersTo="#DannyHealyRae">Danny Healy-Rae</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_10">
                  <person refersTo="#PaulDaly">Paul Daly</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_11">
                  <person refersTo="#MartinKenny">Martin Kenny</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_12">
                  <person refersTo="#EileenLynch">Eileen Lynch.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_13">
                  <person refersTo="#PaulLawless">Paul Lawless</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_14">
                  <person refersTo="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan">Natasha Newsome Drennan.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_4">I láthair / In attendance: Deputy Erin McGreehan.</summary>
          <summary eId="sum_5">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#AindriasMoynihan">Teachta / Deputy Aindrias Moynihan sa Chathaoir / in the Chair.</person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Social Farming: Discussion<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T15:30:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_1">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T15:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_15">Witnesses giving evidence from within the parliamentary precincts are protected by absolute privilege in respect of the evidence they give to the committee. This means that a witness has a full defence in any defamation action for anything said at the committee meeting. However, witnesses are expected not to abuse this privilege and may be directed to cease giving evidence on an issue at the Chair's discretion. Witnesses should follow the direction of the Chair in this regard and are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that, as is reasonable, no adverse commentary should be made against an identifiable third person or entity. Witnesses who are giving evidence from a location outside the parliamentary precincts are asked to note that they may not benefit from the same level of immunity from legal proceedings as a witness giving evidence from within the parliamentary precincts and may consider it appropriate to take legal advice on the matter. Privilege against defamation does not apply to the publication by witnesses outside of the proceedings of the meeting of any matters arising from the proceedings. </p>
          <p eId="para_16"> Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against either a person outside the Houses or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable. Parliamentary privilege is considered to apply to the utterances of members participating online in the committee meeting where their participation is from within the parliamentary precincts. Members may not participate online in a public meeting from outside the parliamentary precincts and any attempt to do so will result in the member having their online access removed. We do not have anyone online today. Everyone is in the room. </p>
          <p eId="para_17"> The agenda for our first session today relates to social farming. The committee will hear from several representative groups. I welcome from Social Farming Ireland, Mr. Brian Smyth, national project manager, Leitrim Integrated Development Company CLG; Ms. Helen Doherty, Leitrim Integrated Development Company CLG; Mr. Matthew McGreehan, social farmer, Co. Louth; and from Kerry Social Farming, Mr. Joseph McCrohan, rural development and social farming manager, South Kerry Development Partnership; Mr. Eamon Horgan, chair of Kerry Social Farming working group and host farmer; and Mr. Brendan O'Sullivan, social farming participant. The opening statements have been circulated to the members, who will have had the opportunity to read them. I will allow a short two-minute introduction of each of those opening statements before we go on to a question and answer session with the members. </p>
          <p eId="para_18"> We will start with Social Farming Ireland. I call on Mr. Brian Smyth. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_2">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T15:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_19">I thank the committee for the invitation. We are in the middle of Social Farming Awareness Week 2025, which is in its fourth year. We had an open day on a farm in Malahide this morning and we have come from there.</p>
          <p eId="para_20">It is great to get this opportunity. We have been working in social farming since 2007, initially as part of a research project with UCD and then as a community of practice nationally. The Department of agriculture has funded us since 2016.</p>
          <p eId="para_21"> In a world where there is increasing social fragmentation, ecological imbalance and the weakening of community ties, social farming helps to transform that and provide a response. It is a way of cultivating humanity and fostering dignity, solidarity and resilience. Farms transcend their role as units of production. They become a place for care and learning. They act as bridges between nature and society, and as places for building connections between people and the environment, and between people and those who work in farming.</p>
          <p eId="para_22"> Social Farming Ireland provides an outcome-focused placement based on a plan. The person is on the farm, using those natural assets of the people, the place and the activities of the farm, and is supported in a person-centred way. The person spends time on the farm and undertakes various activities. It is non-clinical and community-based. We support a wide range of people, including those recovering from mental health issues, people with disabilities, people who are new to Ireland, older people, people with dementia, people who have a difficulty at school and homeless people. A wide range of people access these farms.</p>
          <p eId="para_23"> We cover the governance and quality of it so there is a quality experience. The farms are Garda-vetted and insured, farmers are trained and inducted, and there is safeguarding and Children First guidance as required. All of that practice is supported by our five development officers around the country. It helps farmers to remain sustainable in rural areas and promotes inclusion and holistic rural development. The farmers are paid for their costs, expenses and time. It supports a wide range of activities around the farm.</p>
          <p eId="para_24"> The Department of agriculture has been very important to the funding of this since 2016, and that has increased with the new tender for the national network. Roughly 200 farms are associated with the network, and they are located in every part of the country.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_3">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_25">Thank you. We are tight on time. We move to Kerry Social Farming.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_4">
          <from> Mr. Joseph McCrohan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_26">I work with the South Kerry Development Partnership and manage the Kerry Social Farming project. With me today is Eamon Horgan, who is a host farmer and chairperson of the agriculture working group, and Brendan O'Sullivan, who is a participant.</p>
          <p eId="para_27"> Kerry Social Farming has been in operation since 2013 and seeks to innovatively target both an increasingly marginalised farming community and people with a range of disabilities by promoting social inclusion for them within their own communities. Working alongside these groups has been at the heart of the project.</p>
          <p eId="para_28"> At its heart, the process in Kerry is straightforward. Those men and women who choose to avail of social farming come to the farm one day a week for a few hours, a half day or a full day - whatever is agreed between them and the host farmer. Where necessary, their support worker accompanies them. The farm remains a working farm and normal day-to-day tasks are carried out, with time for a cup of tea or lunch. Social farming through the Kerry voluntary model of social farming continues for as long as the participant and the farmer wish. Brendan has been on the same farm for 13 years now. It is a voluntary model, so neither the host farmer nor the participant is paid, and it is not limited in time. We feel the voluntary model is a strength of social farming.</p>
          <p eId="para_29"> In Kerry today, we have 40 active host farms. Since 2013, some 81 farmers have taken participants, and there are 60 participants out on farms this week. Our vision is to promote and operate social farming in Kerry as a viable option for achieving improved quality of life, greater social inclusion and community networking for people with disabilities and those encountering mental health difficulties. Our mission is to work collectively in a shared service with the social care service providers, people with disabilities, local communities, local development companies, national and local government, the business community, the farming community and farm families. We have a wide variety of project partners but it takes a lot of work to co-ordinate the project. Our project partners include the Kerry Parents &amp; Friends Association, St. John of God services, the National Learning Network, Inspired, NOVAS disability service, Resilience Healthcare, RehabCare, Enable Ireland, Down Syndrome Kerry and Cúnamh Iveragh. These are the people who send us participants. The two local development companies involved are South Kerry Development Partnership and North East West Kerry Development. The partners also include host farmers and social farming participant representatives. The HSE, Kerry County Council and the Kerry Education and Training Board are all involved and provide funding towards the project.</p>
          <p eId="para_30"> The key funding is provided by the Department of agriculture. For our project, we receive €100,000 a year. We are very grateful to the Department of agriculture and the various Ministers back through the years. However, we cannot take the project forward and take on the extra 81 people who want to get placements on farms until we get more money. We have received funding from Kerry AgriBusiness and Kerry Dairy Ireland to facilitate our project.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_5">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_31">The committee is keen to keep a solid focus on the people who are involved in farming. Social farming is central to that focus on the person and the benefits for both the farm owner and the person coming onto the farm to take part in social farming. I will open the meeting to the floor. I call Senator Boyhan.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#VictorBoyhan" eId="spk_6">
          <from>Senator Victor Boyhan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_32">I welcome the witnesses and those in the Visitors Gallery. I am conscious that there are two groups before us today, Social Farming Ireland and Kerry Social Farming. With regard to Social Farming Ireland, which is the group I know better, I thank Ms Doherty and Mr. Smyth for the invitations to the open days. I was at an open day on Monday, with a number of other parliamentarians, at the farm of Nuala and David Reck outside Enniscorthy. I want to share with the witnesses and my colleagues on this committee my takeaways from that experience. Yet again, it stirred up in me the importance and significance of social farming and social interaction. I have been involved for many years. I established a horticultural unit in the mental health services of St. John of God, and I have tracked that for many years, so I am very familiar with this area.</p>
          <p eId="para_33"> My takeaways are captured in four key expressions that were given to me by participants, or their guardians or parents, on Monday. The first was: “My weekly attendance has increased my confidence not only in the farm environment but in my daily life.” Another was: “Support and feeling connected are of the utmost importance to me, and when struggling with anxieties about the world and other people, I find the farm a calming and supporting place.” The third statement was: “Providing social farming services has brought me a new lease of life, but it has brought a new lease of life to our farm and our neighbouring farmers.” The final comment was: “Allowing us to share our connection to the land in our community and with nature is powerful, empowering and supporting, and makes me find that I have a place within my own community.” What more can you say? They were the messages I took away from that. The one thing I asked about people’s experiences was how long they could stay there. It is all well and good having a service, but the continuity of the service is important.</p>
          <p eId="para_34"> My main question to the witnesses concerns core funding and the need for multi-annual funding. They cannot plan their programmes without multi-annual funding. It strikes me, having visited a number of the projects, and from reading the submissions from the Kerry group, that there are ongoing challenges around costs. I will deal first with Social Farming Ireland and then with Kerry Social Farming. How do they deal with funding? What are their current sources of funding? What would they like to see happen? I want this committee to have clear takeaways from their contributions today. I will begin with Social Farming Ireland.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_7">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_35">The Senator’s experience reflects what we see and hear every day on farms. Our core funding for the national network is from the Department of agriculture and comes through a tender process. That means we have development officers throughout the country with our colleague local development companies, of which we have five at the moment. The Department has tendered three times, most recently in March, and we have won that tender for the next five years. I offer thanks to the Department, the former Minister, Deputy McConalogue, and the current Minister, Deputy Heydon. That funding was increased last year and for the next five years to a level that is reasonable to allow us to develop the core.</p>
          <p eId="para_36"> The other element of what we do is to cover the costs of farmers. Farmers are providing a valuable support to a wide range of vulnerable people across the country. That is valued by the commissioning agent that commissions the placements. The placements vary for different people.</p>
          <p eId="para_37">Those engaged in mental health services are on a journey of recovery. That may mean a number of placements, but they are time limited to 12, 20, 24 or 40 weeks. They may be repeated. They are based around a plan, which is reviewed. Some people access a couple of placements or numerous placements. Other people take-short term placements. In recovery, people are on a journey. They may progress beyond the support they need.</p>
          <p eId="para_38"> People with disabilities in particular need longer term placements. That is an issue for us because there is no such thing as personalised funding in Ireland to the extent there is in other European countries. The person with a disability does not have access to a personalised support or budget plan. Rather, funding is given to one of the big disability organisations and it more or less decides what happens. The freedom to make that choice and control, which is core to the UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities, is not-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#VictorBoyhan" eId="spk_8">
          <from>Senator Victor Boyhan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_39">I am sorry to cut across Mr. Smyth but I am conscious of time. What is the core funding required for 12-month programmes?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_9">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_40">We have made a pre-budget submission to the Minister of State, Deputy Hildegarde Naughton, which looks at funding for people with disabilities for ongoing placements. We have a number of people who have their own budgets on their spending. They spend three, four or five years on the farm already. There are very few people in Ireland who have that, however.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#VictorBoyhan" eId="spk_10">
          <from>Senator Victor Boyhan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_41">What is the figure or bottom line? What is the cost for a 12-month period for Social Farming Ireland’s service?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_11">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_42">We have sought a doubling of the funding that the Department-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#VictorBoyhan" eId="spk_12">
          <from>Senator Victor Boyhan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_43">What is that? Can Mr. Smyth spell that out? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_13">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_44">At this stage, it is €400,000. It is modest.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_14">
          <from> Mr. Joseph McCrohan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_45">The Department of culture funding is core to us because we need to employ facilitators to go out to meet farmers and keep the farmers that are involved already. We have 40 farmers involved in Kerry so the heat is on us more than any other county because of the volume of what we are doing. Our project is bigger on a county-wide basis than anywhere else. We need to have those facilitators on the ground to mind, educate, bring forward and make the farmers we have better, but also find new farmers so we can take people off our waiting lists.</p>
          <p eId="para_46"> We go after everyone for money. We have a sister programme that works alongside Kerry Social Farming with funding through the Minister, Deputy Foley’s Department, namely, the school leavers programme. That is individualised funding. Some people with disabilities are receiving funding towards that. We have care workers working with South Kerry Development Partnership and they are putting people on farms. That is an operation in Kerry. It is the only place in the country where this is in operation. It is in operation because of our proven track record of long-term placements and commitment to social farming.</p>
          <p eId="para_47"> Kerry Dairy Ireland is absolutely delighted to give us funding because it sees the performance of our project. We are glad to work in partnership with such a professional organisation that has social responsibility at its core. Not only does it help us to identify new farmers, but it also gives us money.</p>
          <p eId="para_48"> We go after everyone to get money. We receive €100,000 per year, but we need to double that because we need to get double the number of participants out of farms. We want to have 100 farmers in Kerry Social Farming in five years’ time. I have no doubt about it. Social farming is built on the same principles as the GAA; namely, volunteering and people giving their time to others for the betterment of the wider community in a local capacity. It goes on as long as it goes on. We do not tell anyone what to do. We try to keep it going, as long as the participants want to and their care workers and the services they attend are happy and feel it is the right thing for that person. We continue on that basis. They are free to move onto something else if they wish. We are not holding people on farms or anything like that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DannyHealyRae" eId="spk_15">
          <from>Deputy Danny Healy-Rae<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_49">I welcome each and every one of the witnesses here, including the Leitrim social farming group and the Kerry partnership social farming group. All the people, participants, hosts, farmers and parents are welcome here today. I thank the Cathaoirleach for facilitating this meeting and inviting the participants because this is very important. We know people have little problems and there is nothing better than going out in the fresh air on a farm and seeing nature at work. People may see a sheep having a lamb, a young fella feeding a lamb with a bottle, a cow calving or a horse, pony or donkey. Nature can engage people for hours and keep them talking and interested.</p>
          <p eId="para_50"> As has been said, we have many farmers - what we call hosts - participating. Those people to me are vital for giving their time. It usually is one day or a half day per week, whatever the participant wants. I know Mr. Joe McCrohan and Mr. Eamon Horgan personally. They do tremendous work. There are people in north Kerry doing the same type of work. We have young Brendan O'Sullivan here, who is a participant. He is mad about this venture into farming and seeing what is happening. He is a great man for work and everything. The project has tremendous value. At present, we hear that there are 60 participants and that Kerry Social Farming is looking for more funding. It needs funding to increase its services. Mr. McCrohan mentioned €100,000. God almighty, compared to what is spent on different types of projects all around the country, this is a very fair-minded ask. This is a great committee, which I am proud of. Everyone engages, listens and participates. All members are listening to the witnesses. We will join together as a committee to ask as hard as we can for that €100,000 for Kerry Social Farming. I believe in the organisation. I see the work it is doing and the value it has. There is a mother and a daughter in the Gallery all the way from Valentia Island. That is a long way from Dublin, but they are here supporting the call for what is being asked for here today, that is, €100,000. In the context of the budget and the €9.4 billion given out yesterday, we are only looking for a small amount. We are only looking for the change. Honestly, the witnesses do great work.</p>
          <p eId="para_51"> One thing I hear is that the host farmer has to bring the participant to and from the farm. Would it help if there were a bus service, or some kind of a service like that, to help those farmers?</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_6">
          <i>Deputy William Aird took the Chair. </i>
        </summary>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_16">
          <from> Mr. Joseph McCrohan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_52">We use Local Link in Kerry and provide what we call a social car model. If the farmer wishes to go and pick up the participant, he or she can do so. The farmer’s petrol money is covered so he or she is not out of pocket. It is a fantastic way to transport people as opposed to putting loads of people from one social grouping into a bus because there can be a certain stigma around that. Participants are brought to and from farms either though the Local Link network or by the social car model. It is wonderful for a farmer to visit the day care centre where these people are coming from because the farmer learns so much about their background. If they go to the participant’s home, they meet and build a relationship with the family, and those relationships are the things that carry on.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DannyHealyRae" eId="spk_17">
          <from>Deputy Danny Healy-Rae<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_53">Mr. Horgan is a host famer. He is actually my next-door neighbour too. He sees the benefits first hand when the participant comes to the farm. How can we enhance things for him as a host farmer?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_18">
          <from> Mr. Eamon Horgan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_54">First, I thank the Cathaoirleach and members of the committee for having us here. I thank Deputy Healy-Rae and all the other Deputies, as well as those from Leitrim social farming. For me, it would be great if we could secure an extra €100,000 to give other participants and farmers a chance to do what we are doing. We go out in the morning to do our daily work and we just take what we are doing for granted. It is just some other job and we do it. For me, the heart-touching moment was when a participant took part in a video to give different feedback to our working group and project. That girl said that if it were not for social farming, which allows her to be out in the open in the field, look after sheep and take responsibility over her roles on the farm, she would be in a dark world looking at the four walls at home. It takes her mind away and it breaks up whatever she was thinking of during the week. She knows she has a farm to go to every week, which she can look forward to. It changed her perspective.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DannyHealyRae" eId="spk_19">
          <from>Deputy Danny Healy-Rae<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_55">Can Mr. Horgan see the confidence of the participants growing?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_20">
          <from> Mr. Eamon Horgan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_56">I suppose I was coming to that. I saw this girl collect a youngster of mine from school, bring him home and do his lessons with him. They have disabilities through no fault of their own, but what opened my eyes was their ability to do a job.</p>
          <p eId="para_57"> I had another participant another day and when he realised he could do what he had done from a one-to-one between the participant and the farmer, he turned to me as I was driving him home and he said, "God, there is nothing wrong with me." He did not realise that he had those skills or little gifts to do his own jobs, and that is so important. If I ever remember the things I have done in my life, and I have many pleasant memories, social farming and working and interacting with them will be up there.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DannyHealyRae" eId="spk_21">
          <from>Deputy Danny Healy-Rae<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_58">Could I just say-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_22">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_59">We will let the Deputy in again the next time round. I call Deputy Kenny.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_7">
          <i>Deputy Aindrias Moynihan resumed the Chair.</i>
        </summary>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_23">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_60">I welcome all the participants who are here and thank them for their statements. I am certainly conscious of how social farming has grown in County Leitrim over the past decade or more, and how it has provided leadership to many other places around the country. That is to be commended. Without that, many places would not have been able to get it started. The example was there. Often when we have a good strong example of how something can be done, other places can benefit so much from that.</p>
          <p eId="para_61"> Senator Boyhan, who was here a few minutes ago, talked about the funding as being one of the key things and, of course, it is. It is one of these things in society where we invest and we get a return. The return that comes from this small amount of investment is immense. It saves the State huge amounts of money in future care, etc., that it would have to put in to people. If these people get that correct small development at an early age and in the right environment, they flourish, do well and do not need the care that they might otherwise need. Thank God, we have moved from where things often were in the past in this country when a lot of people with different abilities rather than disabilities ended up in all kinds of institutions. This is an example of ensuring that we can have a facility in place which will give people that chance to be able to do something productive. Being with animals and being with nature enhances people's mental health and ability to move forward.</p>
          <p eId="para_62"> The asks that have been brought here today, both from the people from the kingdom and from the rest of the country, are small compared to the benefits which will come from them. They certainly will have the support of everyone on the committee. We will, of course, ask the Department of agriculture to enhance its funding. Funding also needs to come from other sources as well, particularly the Department of Health, because this is something which will save the Department and the HSE huge amounts of money in the future if we get the right funding in place at an early stage.</p>
          <p eId="para_63"> I have a few short questions, first on the numbers of participants. They mentioned that in Kerry, quite a number of farmers are interested in participating. In other parts of the country, is their experience similar?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_24">
          <from> Ms Helen Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_64">It is. We operate across every county in the country. We have had a budget for ten years of €400,000. It is pretty modest, considering we are covering quite a number of counties. We have five regional officers and we are hoping to expand on that this year.</p>
          <p eId="para_65"> We have probably in the region of 250 farmers altogether engaged in social farming. A small number of those, maybe 20 or something like that, are still in development. We are in the process of running training again, which we are hoping to accredit through Teagasc through its green cert. All of those things are in development for us at present. We are working hand-in-hand with the agricultural sector, and with the Department of agriculture as well, on that.</p>
          <p eId="para_66"> As for participants, we have supported well over 1,000 people this year to experience social farming. A number of those are repeat participants and are coming every year, or have come for a number of years. Because of the huge variety of people - we do not say that we only accept X, Y and Z - all of our farmers are open to anybody who feels they need the support that can be gained on a farm. People are supported very well on these social farms. Our farmers are trained to support people.</p>
          <p eId="para_67"> We have supported over 1,000 people and we have provided an economic benefit to all those farmers that are providing that support as well. Just like anybody else who is working in these sectors who provide value to the people they support, the farmers also provide value. You can see that evident all this week on those social farms. For the participants that are coming to those farms, farms are very often a stepping stone for people to move into a different a space as well and to move towards training, employment, and maybe volunteering-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_25">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_68">And towards farming.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_26">
          <from> Ms Helen Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_69">-----and other opportunities. Often it is not about farming at all. It is often about opening other doors in the community for people. We have had people engage in various other supports in the community. I heard a young woman on a farm this week who would not leave the house previously. When she was in the care of CAMHS, she was not able to leave the house. The first thing that she engaged with was social farming. She is now re-engaging in other things in our community and in education as well. That is transformative. As Deputy Kenny said, it is a small thing in somebody's life that transformed their life at the right time.</p>
          <p eId="para_70"> Those choices are being made by occupational therapists, social workers, community mental health teams, youth services, Foróige and the justice system right across the board all over the country. We have huge experiences being had by people and transformative ones.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_27">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_71">I take it that a lot of the participants would be referred by whatever other service they engage in-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_28">
          <from> Ms Helen Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_72">Absolutely, we work hand in glove with health and social care services.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_29">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_73">-----and the experience is that there is not enough spaces and enough social farms available for them to go to.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_30">
          <from> Ms Helen Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_74">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_31">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_75">From speaking to social workers and all kinds of people in that area, I know they all recognise the huge value of this. Unfortunately, they all feel that there is not enough availability there. That is what we need to try and change-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_32">
          <from> Ms Helen Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_76">Absolutely.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_33">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_77">-----and that will come with funding.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_34">
          <from> Ms Helen Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_78">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_35">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_79">I thank Deputy Kenny and call Deputy Newsome Drennan.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_36">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_80">I thank everybody for coming. It was great to meet Brian and Helen this morning.</p>
          <p eId="para_81"> We visited Albert and David's farm in Malahide. For us as suckler farmers, it was not our typical farm. The thing with social farming is that you do not have to change anything. It does not have to be a pet farm for all the world. It can be anything.</p>
          <p eId="para_82"> I said to my husband a couple of years ago that he should do this. Before I became a TD, I worked with adults with disabilities for 18 years. I was trying to get him to get involved because I knew how good he was with the people that I worked with. However, he said it was the education bit he would not be able for. It has been said here this morning that there is plenty of support for farmers.</p>
          <p eId="para_83"> We have heard that it is better to have a 20-mile radius so that people do not travel too far. How do we encourage more farmers to get involved and what has been done in that regard? Have they gone to the marts? Have they done that kind of stuff? A lot of the time, farmers are afraid to get engaged with it because they think it would be more work for them and they have enough work to do already. In fact, the majority of farmers I know in rural areas need this engagement. As Mr. Horgan said, it might just involve picking somebody up and dropping them off to go to a social farm. That might be their only engagement all day. It works both ways, I suppose.</p>
          <p eId="para_84"> What do farmers get in financial supports? Obviously, there is ongoing support and training throughout. I presume there is a helpline for them, as we were saying this morning. I know from working with adults with disabilities that everything could be going great and just one thing might click. Farmers may be slightly afraid of that, but to know that you have back-up and support would be important.</p>
          <p eId="para_85"> I think the witnesses are doing amazing work.</p>
          <p eId="para_86">We were talking about institutions this morning. With the Brothers of Charity, where I worked, we are trying to get away from institutions. We were moving the houses out so people were not in dormitories any more. There was a farm on the place where I worked. I was not on the farm but I would have dropped one of the men off to the farm. From learning how to do jobs on the farm and caring for the animals, they could then go and work off site. That was the serious achievement. They were beaming because they had a job. It might have only been one day a week, but I thought it was great. Anything I can do to help, I will.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_37">
          <from> Mr. Matthew McGreehan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_87">I will give a snippet of my experience. I am a social farmer in County Louth. The Deputy asked what farmers get out of it. Farmers get an awful lot out of it, the job satisfaction and everything, but we do get paid. It is about €80 per day per participant. The participants usually come out from about 10 o'clock in the morning to about 3.30 or 4 o'clock. Social farming can improve the viability of farms greatly. Obviously it is not for every farmer. A lot of farms in Ireland are very vulnerable, especially in the livestock sectors, and it can keep farms alive and important in the community. The job satisfaction the farmers get out of it is immense. They see the people coming every week and growing and see what they get out of it. It benefits the farmer's family as well. It keeps the farm alive, and keeps the farmer in the community during the day. Many social farmers might otherwise have to go to Dublin and join the rat race on a building site. It is keeping people in the community, keeping townlands alive. The training is very important as is the work that Leitrim Development Company does. Social farming is a good news story but we want to keep it that way. We do not want anything going wrong or any scandals or anything. All our courses that we do throughout the year, all our ongoing training, it is crucial that we keep it and the Leitrim Development Company can keep us on our toes and keep us reminded when we have to do a course or whatever.</p>
          <p eId="para_88"> Social farming is all about our well-being. You do not have to have a mental health problem to keep your well-being right. It is about connection and our progression as people. We have people coming out from RehabCare, people with learning disabilities who come out every week. They get great value out of it and are nearly part of the family at this stage. They come out every Wednesday.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_38">
          <from> Mr. Joseph McCrohan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_89">In Kerry we have 40 people who go out and help us to find other farmers. They are the 40 existing host farmers. The one thing that will convince your husband to be a host farmer is that some other farmer comes and tells him he is doing it and shows him how to do it. You need to get a scale of people up. They are the ones, the Eamons and the other farmers we have, Bernie O'Donoghue and other people, who will go and sell the project for us. They will convince other farmers to do it. There is a huge knack in that. You need facilitators on the ground to get it started and then it mushrooms out. You need to have 40 or 50 farmers in any county to really go with this project. This is not a new story. It is going on now for 15 or 20 years. It is time now for the Government and the Department to say it is their project, put more money into it and keep it rolling. They should keep it farmer-centred. Some other Department could run off with it and then becomes a different thing altogether. That is a very dangerous position for the Department of agriculture. If they do not move now, some other Department will take it and it will go down a different road we may not want it to go down. They need to add the funding on. To have Brendan here with us today is proof that it works.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_39">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_90">Thank you. I need to move on to Senator Lynch.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EileenLynch" eId="spk_40">
          <from>Senator Eileen Lynch<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_91">I thank the witnesses for being here today and for their presentations. I welcome the participants on the scheme who are here. I come from a farming background and am also from mid-Cork. In Cork, social farming is generally done through our local development companies. IRD Duhallow would be the one most local to me. I commend the witnesses on the fantastic work that social farming schemes do. It is very evident from listening to farmers and participants that it is making a real difference in people's lives. It is not just benefiting the participants but is also benefiting farmers. I would emphasise the impact it has on combating loneliness in rural Ireland and bringing communities together, since we are seeing a separating of communities at times. These schemes really bring communities closer together.</p>
          <p eId="para_92"> Aside from Kerry Social Farming, are all other social farming entities under Social Farming Ireland or is it largely local development companies? Are the rest of the social farming enterprises across the country run primarily by local development companies? Is Kerry an anomaly in that regard?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_41">
          <from> Mr. Joseph McCrohan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_93">I believe Duhallow would be the same as Kerry. They stand on their own two feet to get their own funding and they do their own voluntary models, as the Senator would know. That is what IRD Duhallow would want to do always, and rightly so. It is very important that the local development companies all really engage in this. As well as getting money from the Department of agriculture for this project, we need to get money from other Departments as well. That is our job. We are speaking here today about agriculture and I am pleading with the committee not to let agriculture lose this project. The Department of agriculture needs to put more money into it to get more benefit for very small money. It bridges the urban-rural divide. Some of the participants may be coming from a rural setting out to an urban area. It is a really good story for farmers. They are not getting battered about spreading slurry on the wrong day of the year, having too many cows in one place, carbon credits or whatever. This is a real project that puts farmers at the centre of the rural community. I have come across nobody who can say that what these farmers are doing is the wrong thing. It has brought farmers back to a position in society where they should be, in the centre of rural communities doing the best for the rural communities.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_42">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_94">I thank the Senator for her question. We would be delighted if every county or local development company in the country got €100,000 each, but if we add that up, it is quite a big bill. It is an awful lot more than the Department. We have suggested that and the reality is that it is probably not going to happen. We are a local development company, members of the LDCN network, as are south Kerry, north Kerry and Duhallow. We work very closely with about 18 of the local development companies that refer clients. We use the framework of those local development companies, the connections they have locally, to find farmers, commission placements and support the cohort of people they work with through the social inclusion programme, the workability programme and so on. We are very aligned and collaborate hugely with all the local development companies. We are one. We just had the lead on this project. South West Mayo Development Company, Waterford LEADER Partnership and West Limerick Resources are our contractors. They have an employee in their companies facilitating the hub in their regions. We would like nothing more than if they got €100,000 each, plus Roscommon, Sligo and Cavan, but we do not believe it is going to happen. We are delighted that Kerry does----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EileenLynch" eId="spk_43">
          <from>Senator Eileen Lynch<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_95">I am sorry, I am just conscious of my time. I appreciate Mr. Crohan's points about it being an agricultural initiative, which it is, but it is also a lot more than that. The funding is only coming from agriculture as opposed to local authorities, health, disabilities or the Department of Rural and Community Development and the Gaeltacht. Have they been approached for funding for the work that is being done? It is such a great initiative and it affects so many different Departments and areas that, while it is very much an agricultural initiative, I do not see any reason it would not have cross-departmental funding. What link does South Kerry Development Partnership have with local authorities? I note it is stated in the submission that it fed into one of the CAP referrals. In general, do the social farming groups feed into policy groups, public participation networks or strategic policy committees on local authorities? This is for the witnesses' benefit to highlight all the good work they are doing. I come from a county council background and was on Cork County Council for six years. It is important to feed into those committees.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_44">
          <from> Mr. Joseph McCrohan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_96">Kerry Social Farming gets a small amount of funding from Healthy Kerry, and it also gets funding locally in Kerry. It gets some funding from Kerry Education and Training Board for the training elements of our programme. All the money we get from the Department of agriculture is spent on paying facilitators to work with farmers. All the other support comes from where it should: the other Departments. There is a lot of work locally on the ground, but our job is to pull all the strings together. The core funding is from the Department of agriculture. We are after everybody for money.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_45">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_97">On collaborations, we work with the LCDCs. There are a number of funded programmes for placements through the LCDCs. There is the disability integration fund, which was supported by former Minister of State, Senator Rabbitte, along with a wide variety of others. There is national lottery funding, for instance. A number of our farmers are members of public participation networks, PPNs. Mr. Matthew McGreehan is on the LCDC in Louth and I am a member of the secretariat to the PPN in Leitrim, so we are connected. I was at the Rural Pact conference in Belgium in September to speak about inclusion in rural development in Ireland through social farming. We are very tied in with influencing policy change to support people, particularly people with disabilities and those in mental health services, to recover. We have a policy officer providing evidence, and there are reports on the website on the experience. The evidence base is being built in Ireland for this now.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_46">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_98">I welcome everyone here. The ask, for €100,000, is very small. If given, how would it filter down to a social farming group in a way that would enable it to say it has an extra €10,000 or €20,000 to spend in the coming year? This is very important. The whole concept is brilliant, of course. What else could we say? It is small ask and the results are so rewarding. The initiative will not be for everybody but it certainly will be for many. It does not have to be about looking at a sheep or cow. I will give a little story about a person I know who was not engaging at first with the host farmer and that farmer did not know what to do. His daughter came out and started picking blackberries and explaining to the girl in question what she was going to do with them. The two went inside with what they had picked and made a blackberry tart. The girl brought it home and the parents were so grateful. It was the first time that a present ever came from that child. This is a nice little story and it shows how engagement works. Look what came out of it. A blackberry tart was the result of the engagement on the day.</p>
          <p eId="para_99"> I would like the funding given to filter down to the likes of Mr. McCrohan. He has now grown the initiative to over 40 participants. He can engage with farmers and can see the money is having a genuine impact. If the money does not filter down, it is a problem. We, as a group, do not have a problem with the initiative. I thank Deputy Danny Healy-Rae for bringing the group up here today so we could all learn more about it. Fair play to him. It is a very small ask. You can see the effects of social farming in the brochure. It speaks volumes. The importance of the small amount of money received has been proven.</p>
          <p eId="para_100"> The witnesses are right about the Department. It is important that the Department act. I do not want to use the word “ownership” because there are other areas in need of funding. I am a member of the social protection committee also and believe there should be funding coming through on the social protection side also. However, the social farming concept is very good. People will only learn from the witnesses' achievements. Is Duhallow the name of-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_47">
          <from> Mr. Joseph McCrohan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_101">No, we are South Kerry Development Partnership.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_48">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_102">Yes. We have to congratulate those concerned. The story of its setting up and the way it operates is worth telling those interested in other counties. Farming and the social element can gel very well together. We realise there are hazards on farms and that, as has been said, not every farm will be suitable. However, all I can tell Mr. McCrohan is that he is lucky to have the like of Mr. Horgan, and to have Mr. O’Sullivan availing of the service. I am sure Mr. McCrohan will say the same to me.</p>
          <p eId="para_103"> The farming community always welcomes with open arms. If it is at all possible for it to do anything for the wider community, it will. It is very good that there is a service whereby support is available if a person needs to come to be there with another person. All I can say is that when this committee next has the Minister before it, it certainly will not be found wanting in asking him to ensure funding is allocated. Is it correct that Mr. McCrohan is asking for €100,000?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_49">
          <from> Mr. Joseph McCrohan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_104">An additional €100,000.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_50">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_105">I know that, and I know the organisation will take €120,000. Deputy Healy-Rae said it is loose change after the budget. I would call it a bit of good luck money for those in south Kerry. </p>
          <p eId="para_106"> I am delighted the witnesses are here. It is of great benefit to us today. This discussion is so different from that of last week, when we were arguing about the budget. Today we are talking about trying to provide money to people who are really making a huge difference to the lives of a small community of people. As has been said, there is nothing better for a participant than to be able to look forward every day of the week to the one day when they will get out and do something different and be part of the community. It gives them that little bit of confidence then to get involved in the community in other ways.</p>
          <p eId="para_107"> I thank the witnesses very much for attending. If they would like to comment on my remarks, it will be no problem.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_51">
          <from> Mr. Matthew McGreehan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_108">It is important that the committee know the wide variety of services that do and could use social farming. Senator Lynch mentioned the different services that should be paying in, for example, to rehabilitate offenders back into society. I have had people on my farm who, although they did not come directly from the probation service, had a life of crime but wanted to change things around and found themselves with a service that sent them out to me.</p>
          <p eId="para_109"> There are a number of ways that social farming can help society, and not just the obvious ones. There is mental health, Tusla, young people in care, Vision Ireland, which has people out with us at the minute, RehabCare, people with learning disabilities and the IPAS system. A variety of services could have people really benefit from being out on a farm. Society benefits in turn.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_52">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_110">I thank the witnesses for attending. I compliment them on the fantastic work they are doing. It can help people who unfortunately have disabilities. The kind of disability is immaterial. It can also their families, which is also important.</p>
          <p eId="para_111"> The organisation calls itself Social Farming Ireland. It has five regional offices. Is it operating nationwide or only in certain counties? Could we have an update on that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_53">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_112">We came into this with a pilot project that was INTERREG-funded. It covered 12 counties – the six counties of Northern Ireland and six in the South – between 2011 and 2014. When we met officials from the Department of agriculture, and we actually met Ms Sinéad McPhillips, who was the chief economist at the time and who has just been appointed Secretary General, and Simon Coveney, who was the then Minister, and they said at the time they wanted to see an expansion of social farming right across the country and they were going to put some funding in place to establish a national network. We bid for that funding to build the national network. We now have farms from Malin Head to Loop Head and from the Cooley Mountains to Bantry and everywhere in between. We have 200 farms and we are funded to do that. The model we operate is that those farms are established through the funding we receive from the Department of agriculture and they then progress through getting paid for the placements and support they provide, whether that is through Vision Ireland, RehabCare or whoever. The support the farmers give is as valued as it would be if it were given by some other service provider.</p>
          <p eId="para_113">It is just happening in a different place with a different set of circumstances and it interests and helps people in a very different way than, say, going to a RehabCare centre in the centre of town. That is the difference. We are reforming service provision. That is why what Mr. McGreehan has just said is vitally important - that the reform of service follows the innovation that farmers provide and provides that new response to people's needs and funds it in a different way. That is what has been difficult. Agriculture has grasped that and funded the development of social farming, the models we have here, which have been very generous at that in many ways. Obviously, everything could be more generous. If we had the €100,000 for every county it would be great but we do not. What we have to do is find a way that this will manifest. What we did was we called it Social Farming Ireland and branded it as a national network. We have the lead contract in Leitrim Development Company but we are delivering a national contract, a national network that involves all of the players, about 350 service providers including disability, mental health and also schools. We have had LCA students come out from schools who have been struggling to stay in school to finish their exams, even the junior certificate, where a period on a farm helps their interest and learning. Really, what we are saying here today is that all these other Departments need to step up like agriculture did. They must step up. That would be a great help to both the Kerry model and to what we are doing. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_54">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_114">Simply fantastic. Are the regional offices spread around the country in different locations?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_55">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_115">Yes. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_56">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_116">Where are they, roughly?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_57">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_117">We have one based in an office in Lismore in County Waterford which covers the south east. The other is in West Limerick Resources in Newcastle West. We have one in Balla in County Mayo. We have somebody based in Offaly and another person in Donegal. Then we have a small core comprising Ms Doherty, myself,and three other people in the office in Drumshambo. We deal in general with the administration and training. It is a very small, skeletal team and we are covering the whole country. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_58">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_118">Like the Kerry group, there are fantastic groups out there and fantastic people doing work. Are there volunteers involved in this? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_59">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_119">Yes there are. The farmers all come forward voluntarily. They get paid for the time they put in. We have volunteers on those farms as well who are supporting and assisting placements. It encourages and supports that as well. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_60">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_120">That is fabulous. It is great to see the volunteering side coming in too. When it comes to getting farmers involved in this scheme, is that easy or how does Social Farming Ireland get around to them? Is it involved with Macra or anything like that to make contact? It is also good for the farmers. As we know, some farmers may be living in rural parts and might not see anyone for the full week. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_61">
          <from> Ms Helen Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_121">We engage fairly extensively with all the agriculture sector and have done from the very early days. We attend IFA meetings in various counties. Mr. McGreehan is very involved in the IFA. That is probably where he heard about it initially. However, we have a small team. We cannot be everywhere all the time but, for example, we were at the ploughing championships this year and we had huge interest in social farming, which was fantastic to see. Probably the strongest way of disseminating information about social farming and encouraging farmers to get involved, as Mr. McCrohan said, is one farmer speaking to another farmer. That word of mouth is really powerful and we try to bring that to the table as often as we can. We do not do any of those events without having our farmers there with us, alongside us. It is all very fine our talking about it but farmer input is invaluable. We work extensively with Macra, Teagasc and the IFA. They are all part of our network.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_62">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_122">That is simply fantastic. Keep up the good work. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_63">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_123">I thank Deputy Cooney. Senator Brady is next.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_64">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_124">I too want to throw my support behind everything the witnesses do. Mr. Smyth and Ms Doherty are only down the road from where I come from. I come from a place called Drumlish in County Longford. We have a host family there. A good friend of mine, Donie McLoughlin, is one of the farmers who goes out there. Caoimhín McEoin in Colmcille does great work for them on the ground. Something our colleagues touched on was how we will to have to look at the model where it has to be funded across Departments – education, health, rural affairs and disability services. All those Departments have a hand to play in funding this. It can be rolled out nationwide. I think the witnesses said they have 200 host farmers there now, or 165 up to 200. Personally, after today I would like to get involved in this scheme, just going by the work outlined in the literature. It is a wonderful initiative. We have St. Christopher day service in Longford. I cannot emphasise how much work it does in the community in Longford. I am sure it is part of the whole social farming and that social aspect of it too. Any day you can have anybody out in the fresh air, no matter whether, as Deputy Aird says, it is picking berries or gathering eggs and going inside, boiling the egg and seeing how food is produced, is great. It is the whole aspect of it. There is an educational side to this too. It educates people to respect the farmer, the food, where it comes from and everything else. It is the whole package. </p>
          <p eId="para_125"> There are a couple of things I will throw at the witnesses. On my farm, I have public liability and employer's liability insurance. I am sure any of the host farmers will have to have employer's liability and public liability. Will the witnesses touch on that? Before a host farmer qualifies, I am sure there is some inspection or audit regarding health and safety and so on. What are the ins and outs of the insurance end of things?</p>
          <p eId="para_126"> The witnesses said it was one day a week but it can be longer, I am sure. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_65">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_127">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_66">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_128">Farmers use relief services but if this was made known to the wider public people might buy into this whole service and I am sure farmers would buy into it more than they have so far. I welcome and support it. Will some of the witnesses touch on the insurance aspect and the wider aspect, such as inspections? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_67">
          <from> Mr. Eamon Horgan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_129">I will leave Mr. McCrohan to answer on the insurance side. I was just listening to the presentation there. I liked the statement that this social farming that we are doing, the Kerry social farming from my side, will have huge benefits down the road. I am glad the committee has seen that. It is great to be in the Houses here today, farmers among farmers and lobbying farmers. You could not get more ideal - people who understand what we are doing and are working hard on the farm every day. There was talk of budgets earlier and I will touch on the budget. Yesterday evening, I was waiting while the budget was announced. I had a path worn to Deputy Healy-Rae’s door giving out to him. My colleague, Mr. McGreehan beside me, is on the sheep committee in Dublin. We were waiting on an announcement on a budget. My biggest fear was to face an IFA meeting and to be asked why did we lost the money but, thanks be to God, due to the hard work of the Minister of State, Deputy Healy-Rae, and all the other TDs that budget was announced yesterday evening for the sheep. That meant so much but my fear relates to when I will be sitting up on the tractor next year. We are getting budgets from three or four different bodies. I appreciate where the Senator is coming from and he is 100% right but I am just speaking from security around what we got. We have been dealing with the Department of agriculture. We could not be dealing with a nicer and sounder group of people, all farmers. We see everyone like Deputies Fitzmaurice, Healy-Rae and Collins. I was listening to them the other night, and the Senator, on the television debate fighting for farmers the whole time and there are all the other Deputies here who are fighting for farmers. My fear is that I will be sitting up on the tractor listening to the budget hearing how we get X amount from the Department of agriculture, another 10% from another body, another 10% here and another 10% there. Two of the bodies we were getting money the previous year have had their budgets cut. Now, all of a sudden, Kerry Social Farming will find they will have to pull the money from us. That is the fear I have. I appreciate that there are other bodies involved in this. In my mind there is no sounder group of people who understand this, support it and keep it going, than the Department of agriculture.</p>
          <p eId="para_130">We have an excellent relationship with the Department. That is where I am coming from. I would be confident that we will go away from here with that. I would greatly appreciate it because it is so important.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_68">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_131">Thank you. I need to bring in Deputy Fitzmaurice.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_69">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_132">I thank the witnesses for coming in. I have been on farms where, basically, a number of people have been on this together, for example, at Boyle and Ballinlough, at Murphy's in Athenry and at Barlow's in Glinsk. It is great what it has done.</p>
          <p eId="para_133"> I cannot get my head around one thing. I am trying to fathom it. Is the Leitrim body the overarching body for all of Ireland or are there different parts throughout the country? The witnesses said the Department of agriculture gave €200,000 or €400,000, and there are the other Departments, including the Minister of State, Deputy Hildegarde Naughton’s Department. How many farmers are involved? What is the administration cost against what the farmers get? I cannot fathom the whole structure.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_70">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_134">The Leitrim Development Company has a national contract to develop the national network. It amounts to €400,000 a year from the Department of agriculture. The Kerry organisation does the job for €100,000 a year in County Kerry. We do it for €400,000 in 25 counties. We subcontract three other local development companies to help us. That is how it works. We branded it overall as Social Farming Ireland so it would be a national network. Otherwise, there would be 26 social farming networks.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_71">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_135">Is €400,000 the total it gets, or are there other avenues through which it gets money?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_72">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_136">That is the total we get to run the network.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_73">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_137">That is the network.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_74">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_138">That is to set up the farmers, train them and put them in place.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_75">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_139">How many people are involved in that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_76">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_140">There are 200 farmers.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_77">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_141">How many people are directly employed for that €400,000?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_78">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_142">I only work part-time because I work on LEADER and other programmes. Ms Doherty is full-time. We have this man-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_79">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_143">What percentage do the farmers get?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_80">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_144">The farmers get paid.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_81">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_145">I heard the figure of €80.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_82">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_146">That is per person per day. We get about €250 a day.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_83">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_147">They may have to go and pick somebody up as well. I think farmers should be well looked after in this regard.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_84">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_148">They are. Last year, of the 1,000 people who went on farms, we paid about €800,000 into farmers’ pockets for the time they spent with those people. That money came from local development companies, WorkAbility programmes, Healthy Ireland, lottery funding and the HSE. It came from all over the place. That is why we went to the Minister of State, Deputy Hildegarde Naughton, and said that we need more of this because there are more people with disabilities who want to go out.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_85">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_149">What about the €100,000 that Social Farming Ireland is looking for now?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_86">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_150">That is for Kerry.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_87">
          <from> Ms Helen Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_151">The €800,000 is what our team of six people leveraged on top of the funding we get from the Department of agriculture. Some of the agriculture funding also makes its way onto farms because we use some of it for the initial placements, to set farms up and to help them with the initial couple of placements they may have. It does not all go to administration.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_88">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_152">I have seen it in action. I have been at places around the constituency when recognition is given to a group of people who are attending, such as youngsters with disabilities. It is a great system. I just wanted to establish the figures. Kerry is looking for €100,000 more. Is Social Farming Ireland funded enough?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_89">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_153">Our core from the Department is sufficient for us for now but it is not sufficient to pay the farmers for the placements. We would double the number of placements on farms and pay the farmers €1.6 million instead of the €800,000 we paid them last year if we got the money from the areas of health, social care, justice and education.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_90">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_154">Does Social Farming Ireland distribute all the money?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_91">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_155">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_92">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_156">I heard the representatives from Kerry say they got local money from X, Y and Z. Is that in addition to what Social Farming Ireland does?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_93">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_157">That is in addition to the €100,000 it gets.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_94">
          <from> Mr. Joseph McCrohan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_158">I want to be clear. In Kerry, we look after Kerry. We are very proud of that as a county. We have an opportunity, like every local development company will have next year, if the Department puts up a tender, to bid for funding again. Any company in the country can do so. We bid for it. We have to put in a proper bid, there are point scores and then we get the funding.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_95">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_159">Does the Kerry group get money from Leitrim?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_96">
          <from> Mr. Joseph McCrohan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_160">No.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_97">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_161">They are separate.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_98">
          <from> Mr. Joseph McCrohan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_162">That is correct. We are from Kerry and we look after Kerry. We are very proud of that. We have 40 farmers doing this in Kerry now. We are under savage pressure because farmers are telling more farmers about the success of this project, and they want to join. We need to manage the project with facilitators on the ground. We put our money into the facilitators on the ground. We do not pay farmers. We do not pay Kerry footballers to play for Kerry. We do not pay farmers. The principle of volunteering is the principle of our project, and we are very proud of it. If we want to pay farmers, we do it with a lot of other schemes, such as the rural social scheme, the water schemes and the whole plethora. If we want to get more money to farmers, we have lots of ways of doing that. However, if we wanted to pay farmers the rates that they should be paid for doing this, we would be looking for a minimum of €1 million-plus, and we would gladly write the cheques.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_99">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_163">The farmer gets nothing in Kerry.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_100">
          <from> Mr. Joseph McCrohan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_164">It is volunteering. Mr. Horgan gets no money.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_101">
          <from> Mr. Eamon Horgan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_165">The focus in Kerry is on the participant, the relationship, the communication and the family. I had a young fellow coming to me, and he said that Siobhan was his second mother. You cannot get any more like family than that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_102">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_166">Perhaps Brendan would like to tell us of his experience.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_103">
          <from> Mr. Brendan O'Sullivan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_167">I do social farming. I do farming down in Kerry. I go to George Kelly and I do all the farming things. George tells me what to do and I do it because I love farming. I am going to keep up farming. I do not want to lose my farm. I do not want to lose the good farming. I would like to keep up farming and do it. That is it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_104">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_168">Thank you, Brendan. I call Deputy Lawless.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_105">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_169">I thank the witnesses for coming in. It is a fantastic initiative. It is amazing. I thank Brendan for giving us his insight and first-hand experience. He is very welcome, as are all of the witnesses.</p>
          <p eId="para_170"> I want to ask about the funding as I am struggling to understand it. Kerry gets €100,000 per year but does not pay the farmers, and there is no mechanism to pay the farmers in Kerry for social farming. Social Farming Ireland gets €400,000 a year to run the other 25 counties and fund the farmers for that, but that is made up from other Departments and budgets. Is that right?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_106">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_171">That is correct.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_107">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_172">How did the differential come about?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_108">
          <from> Mr. Joseph McCrohan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_173">The Department put out a tender a number of years back for four model projects in the country. We were one of them. Field of Dreams in Cork, run by Down Syndrome Cork, was another, IRD Duhallow came in as another one, and the Leitrim Development Company came in. They were the four groups that got those pilots. The Minister at the time, Simon Coveney, wanted to see how this would work. It was thought that if we tried different things in different places, we might be able to come up with what would be the right model of social farming for the country. We worked away and did our thing as best we could. That tender is going to come up in 2026, we hope. If it does not come up, our farmers will continue volunteering, and that is it. If it comes up, we can bid again, and we can move from 40 farmers in Kerry to 60, 70 or 80.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_109">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_174">What is the barrier in terms of going from 40 to 60? Where is the additional funding required?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_110">
          <from> Mr. Joseph McCrohan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_175">It is for boots on the ground - for people to go out and knock on doors and find these farmers. There is a real skill to finding these farmers. Farmers would be unsure and wonder whether they should do it or not.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_111">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_176">It is marketing, really.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_112">
          <from> Mr. Joseph McCrohan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_177">No, it is about the facilitator-worker going out to talk to the farmers about insurance and what skills they need. We need people on the ground to do that. The funding needs to be sourced to keep the whole thing operating.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_113">
          <from> Mr. Matthew McGreehan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_178">I want to respond to the point by Senator Brady regarding insurance and training. I am with FBD. Its representatives come out to the farm and inspect it, and it is included in my package. Social farming is a business and the farmer, as a social farmer, is included in the package. FBD is very reasonable with regard to ensuring farmers for social farming.</p>
          <p eId="para_179"> Training is ongoing. I have been a social farmer for 12 years and my training is ongoing. For example, I will attend a first aid course on Friday. Leitrim Development Company keeps me and other farmers on our toes, including farmers who have been there a long time. I display my certificates for working with vulnerable adults, etc.</p>
          <p eId="para_180"> Deputy Fitzmaurice asked how much farmers get paid. It is hugely important that farmers are paid. The rate of pay is not sustainable and I said that the very first day when the pilot project commenced.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_114">
          <from> Mr. Eamon Horgan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_181">It is sustainable for us.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_115">
          <from> Mr. Matthew McGreehan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_182">Social farmers must be paid. Farmers are well used to working for low money but we have to get paid if the scheme is to be sustainable. There is nothing wrong with getting paid. Everyone else in the services is paid. It costs a huge amount of money to run these services and what social farmers get would only be minuscule. I reiterate that social farmers must get paid and the scheme is not sustainable in the long run if we do not get paid. I like social farming. I do not just do it for the money but I would not be able to afford to do it if I did not get paid.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_116">
          <from> Mr. Eamon Horgan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_183">I am doing the voluntary model. To me, they are both great models. If I were to be paid for this model at the rate that it is going, and at the rate that we should be paid, if someone landed to me with the going rate that moment then I would tell them to gather their bags and go. We have no bother with accepting the paid model but we will in the future sit in front of this committee looking for €1.5 million for Kerry Social Farming. If that money is there then we will do the paid model, no bother in the world. We would be delighted to pay the participants. Whatever about ourselves, if there was enough to pay the participants but we are working with a small budget. It is probably one of the best budgets that leaves this House here if you could see what it has done on the ground, and has done for the participants. The proof of the scheme is that farmers have continued with social farming.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_117">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_184">The social farming network has 250 farmers. What are the blockages to increasing the number of social farmers from 250 farmers to 500? Is it the payment to the farmer or are there administrative issues in the system with training, etc? Where must additional money go to increase the number?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_118">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_185">I have travelled extensively across Europe. I have been in Romania, Poland, Italy and France and models differ. Ireland has two models. In most all of those countries, farmers are paid and they bid for funding somehow. As for social farmers in the Netherlands, the average income there is a turnover of about €250,000 turnover per year. Payments depend on the funding structure of disability services and mental health services. This is about how a society supports people and how people then access those supports. Our colleague from Northern Ireland was on the farm in Malahide today. In Northern Ireland, under legislation from 2014 - when we had our first pilot project - people with disability could apply for their own personal budget and they used that to buy the services of a social farmer. In Ireland, if we had personalised budgets for people with disabilities, it would allow that to happen.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_119">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_186">I thank the witnesses for attending today. I was late arriving as I had something else on and I hope that I will not go over old ground. I thank Deputy Danny Healy-Rae for initiating this meeting and, from what I have heard, I will approach him with my own request for the budget next year.</p>
          <p eId="para_187"> I have a couple of questions on the models. It has been said there is an INTERREG European project. Did Mr. Smyth say it is a project or a pilot project? Also, is there any chance of INTERREG funding running out? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_120">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_188">An initial project. When we developed the concept with UCD we moved it into INTERREG to model the first farms that were set up in Ireland. There were ten farms in Northern Ireland and ten farms in the six Border Counties.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_121">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_189">Did that include funding from Europe? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_122">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_190">That was funded by INTERREG between 2011 and 2014. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_123">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_191">Is that funding gone?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_124">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_192">That is gone. That set up the first 20 farms in Ireland. Our friends from Kerry came up and saw that in action, from which emerged social farming in Ireland.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_125">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_193">In terms of the overall picture, irrespective of whether it is a voluntary model or a paid model, who co-ordinates this on the ground? Who accepts a farm? All the witnesses are saying they want more farmers but not every farmer, with the greatest will in the world, is ideal. Ninety-nine out of 100 farmers could be ideal for this scheme but the 100th will view the scheme as providing cheap labour.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_126">
          <from> Mr. Joseph McCrohan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_194">Yes. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_127">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_195">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_128">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_196">Who vets farmers? Who makes that call? Let us say a farmer is deemed acceptable and the scheme seems ideal, the scheme might not progress because a farm or farmyard is not safe enough.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_129">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_197">That is 100%. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_130">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_198">Who decides that a farmer or his farmyard is acceptable? Who matches the client with the farmer? I ask because clients have different needs and, therefore, people need to be matched. Who co-ordinates all of that at a micro level?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_131">
          <from> Mr. Joseph McCrohan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_199">At a micro level, the facilitators on the ground who are paid by the Department of agriculture, will allocate funding. In Kerry, it is South Kerry Development Partnership staff. Ms Emily Moran and Mr. John Lynch are out on the ground. They bring forward the farmer, the suggestion is brought to the working group and if we feel the farmer is suitable then he or she is approved to start. That process is critically important because social farming is not for every Tom, Dick and Harry. We do not want people becoming social farmers because they see big bucks in this game. This is a social inclusion project that needs to be minded and nurtured. I have walked away from farmers who were suggested but they wanted to join for the wrong reasons, which were cash and money solely. Of course, we are not foolish in Kerry and understand that money makes the world go around. It is important that the vetting is done right, that insurance and everything are in place, and continue to be in place. One of the key elements, particularly for our project in Kerry, is farmer development. Our aim is to make him or her a better host farmer year on year so that he or she stays in the project. We do that because the longer a farmer stays in the project, the more fulfilment he or she gets, the better he or she gets at it and the happier the participants. The care services refer participants who have been identified as having an interest in farming and want to participate. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_132">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_200">Is that the service provider? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_133">
          <from> Mr. Joseph McCrohan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_201">Yes, the service providers. There is a wide variety of them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_134">
          <from> Mr. Eamon Horgan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_202">I want to go back the other Paul, Deputy Paul Lawless, and his question on what extra money we seek. We have farmers and participants waiting. Let us say a farmer wanted to do a small bit of a safety upgrade on his or her farm. We would evaluate whether that work needed to be done. So it would be if the upgrade will benefit the participant, like wiring in a corner in order to put a few lambs into the space where the participant would find great peace and joy in feeding those few lambs. Little jobs like that. We do not put up sheds for farmers but just to get a picture of where our future money would go, that is what is holding us back at the moment. We have participants waiting to go on to farms and we want to get those farms ready.</p>
          <p eId="para_203"> Mr. McCrohan and I and a lot of us are farmers and so we know what a farmer is about when we go into his yard. We know what he is there for. We also know the county like the back of our hand, the same as Deputy Healy-Rae or any other of the politicians. We have a tight-knit community and have a way of knowing who is suitable for social farming. Yes, Mr. McCrohan and I have gone to the farms of three farmers and told the farmers that, sorry, what they were demanding was not about social farming but demanding improvements on their own farms. We told them that we could not approve that and could not spend money on that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_135">
          <from> Ms Helen Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_204">It is similar for Leitrim Development Company in some ways. Our five regional officers are the people on the ground who work extremely closely with farmers. They visit the farms on numerous occasions, etc. We take all of our farmers through a very extensive training programme. They learn about the framework for practice, and all the processes, procedures and policies that we have in place to safely deliver social farming. Once farmers have completed training we start to work with them on their farms. We provide mentoring on their farms and visit the farms several times. Before anybody is placed on a farm we have to be happy. Effectively, we have a training programme and an accreditation system for our farmers.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_136">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_205">Let us say I am involved and some person is due to inspect my farm in the morning but a contractor rings or the weather changes and I have a busy workload, and tomorrow is not going to be suitable for me to have anybody around my farm, who would co-ordinate a change of plan at the eleventh hour?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_137">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_206">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_138">
          <from> Ms Helen Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_207">Our regional co-ordinators. We have five co-ordinators around the country and we hope to have a few more shortly. They are at the coalface dealing with placement issues or changes. They do not happen a huge amount because a huge amount of planning goes into each placement.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_139">
          <from> Mr. Joseph McCrohan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_208">We have three of those in Kerry.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_140">
          <from> Ms Helen Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_209">There are individual support plans in place for each person and contact details, etc. Very detailed pieces of work go into every placement.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_141">
          <from> Mr. Joseph McCrohan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_210">We have three of those in Kerry.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ErinMcGreehan" eId="spk_142">
          <from>Deputy Erin McGreehan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_211">I thank the Cathaoirleach for allowing me to contribute as I am not a member of this committee. First, I wish to acknowledge the presence of my brother, Matthew McGreehan. He is my go-to person when it comes to social farming. I am a great believer in social farming and it is great that this committee is having a robust discussion on social farming.</p>
          <p eId="para_212">I want to ask, from the two points of view, what are the witnesses' experiences. This is not just about the time on the farm or the administration around it. It is about the added value that each farmer is giving into their community, the added value that the individual takes onto the farm and to their families, and the added value for the families who have social farmers on their farms. What can we do as Oireachtas Members to support that? If the voluntary model is what some farmers want to go to, I think there is a value and an economic value in supporting farmers. In the context of all the talk about low incomes and farmers, it is about keeping small farmers in rural marginal areas on the land with their families. When we are talking about diversification of the farm, and when farm incomes are at an all-time low, it is an absolute miracle that something so positive like this can keep families farming and keep families on their land. What can we do as a committee and as an Oireachtas to make sure we have more people supported in the positive activity of social farming and more families taking on social farming?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_143">
          <from> Mr. Joseph McCrohan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_213">It is a very clear answer; if the Department could double the budget every five years for all of us. That is as simple a way as I could put it. It will be a real task for us to make sure that we get the farmers to match that budget and for people as participants but we are up for the game. There is merit in it. The Deputy has alluded to it. Some farmers want to get paid and if they do then that is fine; pay them. Some farmers might want to do it voluntarily, and if they do I would not stop them. Would the Deputy stop a person because they wanted to volunteer?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ErinMcGreehan" eId="spk_144">
          <from>Deputy Erin McGreehan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_214">No. Of course not. I am not asking that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_145">
          <from> Mr. Joseph McCrohan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_215">Because if a person wants to get paid and will not do it unless they get paid, that is alright too if we can find the money to pay him or her. At the end of the day, let the show roll on and make sure the Department puts out the tender next year. They were looking for four pilot projects ten years ago. I think they would want to be looking for 24 or 25 pilot projects with one for every county at this stage of the game. In Kerry we have the biggest number. It is 40 people in a massive county. When you think about it, we need to get to 500 or 1,000 farmers doing this if we really want to keep rural Ireland going. They are there. They are training young fellas, and boys and girls, at all sports across rural Ireland and they will do this.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_146">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_216">The programme for Government mentions cross-Department actions and cross-department interaction. It is a great opportunity for the Department of agriculture to lead out on something that provides huge benefits in health and social care in children, equality, integration and in education. Bring those Departments together to say that social farming delivers. Farmers are delivering for our Department. This is something that could be taken up.</p>
          <p eId="para_217"> It is mentioned by the Minister, Deputy Norma Foley, in the recently launched National Human Rights Strategy for Disabled People 2025-2030, when she talks about the cross-Department approach to addressing barriers for disabled people. Access to farming and access to social farming for disabled people is a cross-departmental barrier. I believe the Minister's Department can help and the Department of agriculture can help.</p>
          <p eId="para_218"> As Mr. McCrohan has said, it is about the expansion and development of the funding for the concept, regardless of which model people access or provide the support under. The cross-departmental work is important in an agricultural and rural development policy that the Department is funding, because they see the benefit of diversified farm income and multifunctionality. The other Departments have not stepped up to the same level and that should happen now. Even if that fund came through the Department of agriculture, the mechanism could be defined. That would be new and it would be innovative if there were two Departments working and one of them funding it. That would be new. For disabled people, people who are recovering, people who are homeless and people who are new to this country it could be delivered through a single Department. That could be the Department of agriculture because it has taken the lead.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ErinMcGreehan" eId="spk_147">
          <from>Deputy Erin McGreehan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_219">Is there anything specific that we can support the farmers with, bar the obvious budget? What of the other supports around them to support them and encourage more people to get into it? I am aware I have only 30 seconds here.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_148">
          <from> Mr. Joseph McCrohan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_220">Very briefly, there is a renowned thing within the Department of agriculture where there are knowledge transfer, KT groups, where farmers meet one another and talk about social farming. It would be really helpful if this was rolled out across the country.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_149">
          <from> Mr. Brian Smyth<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_221">We bring our groups together and our farmers meet for peer support. We are doing a well-being project at the minute, separately funded by the Department of agriculture, for such issues as Senator Lynch mentioned.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_150">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_222">There is so much ground covered there. So many members wanted to get in on it and to ask about it. We have run well over our allocated time. I thank the witnesses for the engagement and for the huge amount of information. Most people got in for a big speak. Did Mr. Brendan O'Sullivan get to cover everything he wanted or is there anything he wants to add?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_151">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_223">More money.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_152">
          <from> Mr. Brendan O'Sullivan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_224">We are doing social farming in Kerry. We are looking for more money and people. Just get us the money to keep social farming going. We are not going to lose this. Pay for social farming. We are going to fight for this and that is all I am going to say.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_153">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_225">I thank the witnesses.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_8">
          <i>Sitting suspended at 5.06 p.m. and resumed at 5.10 p.m.</i>
        </summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>Supports for Private Advisory Providers Delivering Advice on Nitrates and Water Quality Improvements: Agricultural Consultants Association<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:10:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_154">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_226">The agenda for today's meeting is to examine the supports and resources need for private advisory providers delivering advice on nitrates and water quality improvements. The committee will hear from officials from the Agricultural Consultants Association, namely, Mr. Tom Canning, consultant; Mr. Owen O'Driscoll, consultant; and Mr. Noel Feeney, consultant. Tá fáilte romhaibh. Before that, I need to go through the note on privilege.</p>
          <p eId="para_227"> I bring to witnesses' attention that those witnesses giving evidence from within the parliamentary precincts are protected by absolute privilege in respect of the evidence they give to the committee. This means that a witness has a full defence on any defamation action for anything said at the committee meeting. However, witnesses are expected to not abuse this privilege and may be directed to cease giving evidence on an issue at the Chair's direction. Witnesses should follow the direction of the Chair in this regard and are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that, as is reasonable, no adverse commentary should be made against an identifiable third person or entity. Witnesses who are to give evidence from a location outside the parliamentary precincts are asked to note that they may not benefit from the same level of immunity from legal proceedings as a witness giving evidence from within the parliamentary precincts and may consider it appropriate to take legal advice on the matter. Privilege against defamation does not apply to the publication by witnesses outside of the proceedings held in the meeting of any matters arising from the proceedings. The witnesses' opening statement has been circulated and members have had an opportunity to read it. I will give them two minutes in which to do a brief synopsis of it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_155">
          <from> Mr. Tom Canning<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_228">I thank the Chair and members of the Oireachtas committee for their kind invitation and the opportunity to present the case for the support of the private agricultural advisory service providers in Ireland, who have made a significant contribution to the development of agriculture over a long number of years and continue to make that contribution. We believe that we have a very positive contribution to make to the future development of agriculture ,while at the same time providing accountability and value for money for the EU and Irish taxpayer.</p>
          <p eId="para_229"> We are all members of the Agricultural Consultants Association, ACA. Noel Feeney is based in County Roscommon, Owen O'Driscoll is a consultant in County Cork and I operate out of County Cavan. The ACA is the representative body for private agricultural consultants. We are the largest advisory support network for farmers in the country. In total, based on the basic income support for sustainability, BISS, scheme figures provided by the Department of Agriculture this year, our members provided BISS services to 64,500 farmers as against our counterparts in Teagasc at 41,000. We have over 200 professional members employing over 400 farm advisory system, FAS, approved advisers in the network through 169 offices stretching throughout the country. We are not funded directly by the State. We are funded from contributions made by our members and that is the sole source of our funding as of today.</p>
          <p eId="para_230"> We are here as volunteers. We act in a voluntary basis. There is so much happening in our industry that this kind of voluntary effort is not sustainable in the long term. Our organisation and members provide the same services as those provided by Teagasc. The range of services we provide can be read in the document provided to members. The key thing is that-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_156">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_231">I thank Mr. Canning but we are running behind and I am keen to give members an opportunity to speak on this issue.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_157">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_232">The witnesses are welcome. I am going to be pretty quick and there will be sharp questions. Going by the ACA's presentation, there is a problem with farmers getting information on nitrates that was promised by the Department. When was that information to be given in case farmers went over their nitrates limit each year? From the presentation, that was not given to agricultural consultants on time. Will one of the witnesses elaborate on that?</p>
          <p eId="para_233"> The Department gave out a contract to agricultural consultants which seemingly was not paid. Will the witnesses elaborate on that? My understanding is that taxpayers are paying for all of the research by another group. The guide to how to do nutrient management plans, NMPs, is available but the members of the ACA have to pay for it and it is costing them €300,000 a year. Why is that?</p>
          <p eId="para_234"> ACA members are assisting farmers with their applications for all of the schemes, including the nitrates derogation, TAMS, BISS, and the complementary redistributive income support for sustainability, CRISS, scheme. ACA members are doing at least 50% of applications and up to 68% in some schemes. Is the Department engaging with them on a constant basis? Has the ACA a central fund for training and things like that?</p>
          <p eId="para_235"> In relation to water quality, which way do the witnesses see that going? What way to we need to go forward on it? We know the amount of amount of funding that goes to other planners such as Teagasc. We know what taxpayers are giving. As for the ACA members' fees and those of other groups - we will not call them competitors because everyone is looking after farmers - are they in line, even though they are getting substantial funding?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_158">
          <from> Mr. Owen O'Driscoll<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_236">I will start with the nitrates question. The nitrates figures come out normally at the end of July. They were late coming out this year. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_159">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_237">What is late?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_160">
          <from> Mr. Owen O'Driscoll<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_238">I think it was 6 September, or thereabouts.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_161">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_239">Were they accurate?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_162">
          <from> Mr. Owen O'Driscoll<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_240">There was an inaccuracy in the calculation for nought to four months so there was about a 4% to 5% difference.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_163">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_241">Wrong.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_164">
          <from> Mr. Owen O'Driscoll<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_242">Yes, wrong. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_165">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_243">Okay. What needs to be done there?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_166">
          <from> Mr. Owen O'Driscoll<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_244">If more investment is made into the IT systems and we can get the nitrates figures earlier in the year, we can get reporting earlier and make better predictions going forward.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_167">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_245">I forgot one thing. Am I correct in saying that at the moment, a planner's licence is at risk if he or she verifies that slurry was moved but a farmer has not done what he or he said he or she would? A text comes to a farmer and not to the planner. Planners have to take the word of the farmer. Is the Department threatening that or is that just hearsay?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_168">
          <from> Mr. Owen O'Driscoll<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_246">We met Ted Massey last Thursday. We are going to get a memorandum of understanding, MOU, to protect our consultants across the board on certain items like that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_169">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_247">Are texts the solution?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_170">
          <from> Mr. Owen O'Driscoll<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_248">Texts could be a solution. We are open to all avenues to prevent this happening.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_171">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_249">Okay. Keep going on contracts and nutrient management plans.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_172">
          <from> Mr. Owen O'Driscoll<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_250">The Deputy is correct in relation to the NMP system. The NMP system is funded by the State. Teagasc is running the system and we are paying hundreds of thousands of euro each year to use that service. It is a mandatory requirement and is a tool we need to use. We ask the committee to review this and see whether we should have to pay for it-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_173">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_251">It is paid for by the taxpayer already.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_174">
          <from> Mr. Owen O'Driscoll<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_252">It is paid for the taxpayer already; correct. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_175">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_253">Keep going. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_176">
          <from> Mr. Owen O'Driscoll<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_254">We got a report done by Jim Power on recalibrating the advisory services. Everyone has been provided with a copy of it. Members can see the structure on one of the tables in it. It is about the knowledge transfer. The Government has its policies and it wants to implement them. That money funds State research whether it is to Teagasc or the colleges. That State research goes into the Teagasc head office at Oak Park for filtration and utilisation.</p>
          <p eId="para_255">That goes down through the advisory services through experts and specialists. Teagasc will have specialists within it to decant this information and give it to the Teagasc advisers, which goes down to the farmers. On the other side, we, as advisers, do not have a knowledge hub to filtrate this information down through specialists to our advisers. There is, therefore, a break in the knowledge transfer going from the research to the farmer. What we have in the middle is basically a hub for which we need to get funding. That would be a direction.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_177">
          <from> Mr. Tom Canning<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_256">In relation to the-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_178">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_257">I am sorry; Mr. Canning; we have to let the next man go.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_179">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_258">I am going to yield somewhat and tell the witnesses to carry on answering Deputy Fitzmaurice's questions, and then maybe round up at the end as to what the one big ask would be if they were in our shoes when we meet the Department on this issue. I was going to ask the same questions, so they can finish answering his questions in my time and then maybe wrap up with-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_180">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_259">The contract.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_181">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_260">-----what we can achieve.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_182">
          <from> Mr. Tom Canning<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_261">What happened in relation to the contract is that we were awarded what was called an informal environmental survey contract with the Department of agriculture, which amounted to about €5 million to complete that contract, including payment to the farmers. The Department did not fulfil that contract and as a result of that, our members and our association had invested in training and the employment of specialists to train and provide support service to our members. Indeed, some of our members employed additional graduates to take on board this additional work. However, when that contract was not fulfilled, we were left with a hole in our finances within our own association of over €300,000, which is a significant cost that each and every one of our members now has to bear. We are taking about €1,500 per adviser on top of the additional costs they have had to bear. As well as that, we were getting some small supports in terms of the promotion of organics, in terms of forestry and in terms of the agri-climate rural environment scheme, ACRES. That was withdrawn in 2024. In effect, we are left now without any State supports whatsoever throughout 2025.</p>
          <p eId="para_262"> When I look at the future in relation to the new nitrate regulations here and the protection of water quality, and this is going to answer part of Deputy Fitzmaurice's question, the real situation is that we seem to be hanging our coat on two key programmes: one is the agricultural sustainability and support advisory programme, ASSAP, and the other is the water EIP. We have been excluded from that programme to date. That is a major part of the next strategy on improvements to water quality and that is going to continue in the future. Therefore, for another five years, potentially, we, as private agriculture consultants servicing 64,500 farmers in the country, are going to be excluded. Those 64,500 farmers are going to be denied access to critical information in terms of implementing mitigation measures and, at the end of the day, achieving the objected we all want in improving water quality.</p>
          <p eId="para_263"> In comparison, in terms of looking at the structure at the moment, we operate commercial businesses here. We have to compete against Teagasc. We charge the same fees as Teagasc. We provide exactly the same services. Yet the Teagasc advisory service gets a subsidy of €27 million and an additional €14 million in fees that it brings in, which equates to €621, according to the Jim Power report. That is slightly outdated; that is from 2019. Those figures have even increased significantly since then. That is additional supports that we have to compete with in the private sector. It really is not a level playing field, and that is our argument here. We are not here to knock Teagasc, however. We are here to sell the positives that we can bring to this. What we can bring to this is a pool of dedicated, experienced, professional, qualified people but above all, trusted professionals in our own local areas who farmers within our areas can easily access and can trust - I will stress trust - in the advice we are giving them in the longer term to improve the sustainability of their farms.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_183">
          <from> Mr. Noel Feeney<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_264">Deputy Fitzmaurice also asked the question regarding Department engagement. Yes, in fairness, we do have regular Department engagement, especially with the BISS section in Portlaoise. Members of our committee and council meet its representatives quite regularly on updates regarding the introduction of the scheme each year and on how, say, entitlement transfers are progressing, etc. In fairness, they are quite good in giving us the information. We also have regular meetings with the ACRES section in Johnstown Castle. We know there have been issues with ACRES since its commencement in 2023. Again, we have contact with people on a regular basis there. Mr. O'Driscoll would be involved in that. Mr. Canning, of course, is involved with engagement on a continual basis through water quality and nitrates. There is regular engagement but as our colleague has outlined, it is all on a voluntary basis. We are not paid to be there. However, we are representing over 64,000 farmers and we have to give them the best possible service that each of us can provide to our clients. The most important thing is those farmers with whom we are all concerned.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_184">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_265">After meeting the witnesses, we will be meeting the Department. What is their big ask?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_185">
          <from> Mr. Tom Canning<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_266">There are four key asks in relation to this. As Mr. O'Driscoll already mentioned, we need funding for a knowledge hub, if you like. That is key to it in terms of feeding that information back. There is a disconnect, as Mr. O'Driscoll said, in terms of the research and the information coming back to our members.</p>
          <p eId="para_267"> Second, and critically important, is technical support. Teagasc has that structure where it has technical specialists in each of the areas. We will take the example of nitrates where it has somebody there to back it up. The goalposts are moving constantly, and we are facing into an ever-changing climate here. We are 100 days out from new nitrate regulations on 1 January. We still have not clarity on that. We need to be prepared for that, and we need the technical backup support for our members in order that we can answer the key questions very quickly because they are urgent questions.</p>
          <p eId="para_268"> Third, we need specialists who can organise and focus training that meets the specific needs of the five regions in which we operate. Without that, we are certainly disadvantaging the 64,500 farmers with whom we are dealing.</p>
          <p eId="para_269"> Fourth, we are looking for the publicly funded tools like the nutrient management planning system now. We are going to be forced into using an AgNav system under the new nitrate regulations here as well that are coming in.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_186">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_270">I thank Mr. Canning. I call Deputy Cooney.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_187">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_271">I thank the witnesses for coming in. We appreciate the great work they are doing for the farming community. I have two questions. What gaps are there in the provision of access to knowledge for farmers due to the State's exclusion of independent agricultural consultants from the water quality programme and the EIPs? How many applications have been made to the Farming for Water EIP 2024-2027 so far? Do they believe they will hit our targets if the current model continues? What do they believe would happen if private advisers are permitted to prepare plans on behalf of their clients?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_188">
          <from> Mr. Owen O'Driscoll<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_272">To put it in context, the EIP programme provides €50 million to €60 million to be invested where farmers can do measures to help water quality. It is a great concept. The issue is that we, as private advisers, are not allowed to prepare plans for our own farmers. We know the farms; we know the systems and we know how to get the optimum benefits for farmers in these areas and we are not allowed at the moment. We are excluded from the EIP programmes. We are also excluded from the ASSAP, which was the initial one. In the Timoleague catchment, I have possibly 60% or 70% of the farmers in that area to whom I provide information and advice, and I have no interaction with the ASSAP team. Therefore, we need is to be involved at an ASSAP level and an EIP level so that we have consistent messaging. One person could be saying go left and the other could be going right, so we have to avoid that confusion. Again, we met Ted Massey from the Department's nitrates division last week and we brought this issue that we need to be part of the EIP going forward as part of a sixth nitrates action programme, NAP, regulation, which is here and forth.</p>
          <p eId="para_273"><b>
						</b>I am not sure of the figures because we do not really do the plans. A client with whom I have dealt for 30 years might come into me and I have to send him or her to Teagasc to do an EIP plan, which makes no sense in my view. I cannot answer to the figures. If we had access to doing plans, we would know straight away off the tops of our heads that we could do A, B and C for a person's farm because we have known all these farms for 30 years and more. Therefore, the knowledge is what is missing here in the link.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_189">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_274">That is not good for the farming community then if that knowledge is missing or lacking and the ACA's members cannot carry out those works.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_190">
          <from> Mr. Owen O'Driscoll<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_275">It is not efficient and it is not optimum. Trust is a big thing because our clients trust us. We have dealt with them over the years, and we know the issues on farms and can solve them much easier.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_191">
          <from> Mr. Tom Canning<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_276">What is critically important is that we need to show leadership. It is vitally important that we are delivering a clearly focused, professional and consistent message to the clients we are dealing with here.</p>
          <p eId="para_277">As I said, we feel that because of the disconnect, that consistency and that clarity are not being delivered on.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_192">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_278">And the witnesses are disappointed it is not being delivered, I presume.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_193">
          <from> Mr. Tom Canning<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_279">Not only are we are disappointed for our own members, who are left out of the loop in this and are not being recognised for the contribution they are making, but, more importantly, our 64,500 farmers are also disconnected from that flow of information, as Mr. O'Driscoll has outlined.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_194">
          <from> Mr. Noel Feeney<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_280">Also, as part of the question the Deputy asks, it is important to remember that over the years private advisers have built up a close relationship with their clients. We are now advising their children who have taken over the farms. We talk about EIPs and water quality and, as we are all aware, a lot of this involves complicated paperwork and complicated science that has to be applied to each farm. After our being in the position of having the many years of relationships and trust we have built up with the farmers, all of a sudden someone else is coming in and that trust just might not be there. To gain the proper end result we all want, we believe it is not a proper delivery system. The trusted adviser should be involved in dealing with those farmers.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_195">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_281">I have one other quick question. I know my time is nearly up. What does the comparable agricultural knowledge transfer system look like in the rest of the EU? Is it delivered by the state or by the private sector? Do the witnesses believe the EU would look at the system in Ireland as being fit for purpose?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_196">
          <from> Mr. Tom Canning<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_282">It is a good question. We are very lucky in Ireland. Of the 125,000 farmers who applied for BISS this year, 105,000 engaged with the advisory services, which is the highest level of engagement of any advisory service throughout Europe. However, most of the advisory services throughout Europe are provided through private consultancy services such as ours or commercial businesses, where often there is a conflict of interest. We have spoken to Inge Van Oost in DG VI on a number of occasions and she is extremely positive about the support here for the knowledge hub we are talking about and about the involvement of the private advisory services in the development of Irish agriculture. That message, however, has appeared to fall on deaf ears until now. This is not the first time we have been lobbying in relation to this or that we have spoken to this committee. One of the recommendations that was made by the committee's predecessor, its fourth recommendation, is that the resources should be made available not only to the State but also to private advisory services here to deliver a consistent clear message in terms of nitrates and water quality improvement.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_197">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_283">I thank the witnesses for their time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_198">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_284">I thank the witnesses for coming in. To go back over this again, how many members does the ACA have and how many people do they employ, roughly?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_199">
          <from> Mr. Tom Canning<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_285">We have 219 members throughout the country employing over 400 FAS-approved agriculture consultants. They are approved by the Department of agriculture farm advisory service. There are additional admin staff in support of that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_200">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_286">So, privately, they represent 64,500 farmers.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_201">
          <from> Mr. Tom Canning<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_287">Verified by the Department of agriculture.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_202">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_288">Right. It was stated that the ACA makes a payment to Teagasc for the data.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_203">
          <from> Mr. Tom Canning<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_289">Correct.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_204">
          <from> Mr. Owen O'Driscoll<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_290">For the use of the software.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_205">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_291">For the use of Teagasc's software.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_206">
          <from> Mr. Tom Canning<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_292">The State-funded nutrient management planning system. Yes, that is correct.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_207">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_293">Well, that is the first thing I would recommend has to change because Teagasc is a semi-State body.</p>
          <p eId="para_294"> We will go back to ACA's organisation. There are codes of conduct within its organisation, so everything is transparent from top to bottom. What is the problem then? This is not ringing out right. There is something wrong here. The witnesses represent 64,500 farmers. My Teagasc adviser and I were doing training last week, only the other night. As regards the service he provides, one of the schemes now is blackleg vaccinations, which involves testing of silage. Not only did he go through the schemes and where we are at, but he gave us the bags to go home to test the silage and drop them into his office. They will be left into a lab for us. That is the service provided. If there is anything wrong in my agricultural portfolio, I can ring him. As for this thing of importing slurry, when a farmer gets a text message, it is lost. If you do not ring him there and then, all of a sudden it is forgotten about and the whole thing is upside down. There has to be a connection. There has to be interlinking. If the farmer gives permission for his data to be automatically shared with the person who is his adviser, it is a no-brainer. This, to me, is not adding up, Chair. Where are we going? How will this change? If the Department says no to this, water quality and everything else will not change for the farmers.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_208">
          <from> Mr. Tom Canning<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_295">May I answer that one? I appreciate Senator Brady's sentiments. We have been lobbying, as I said, for quite a long time here. Before I was installed as president of the ACA a number of years ago, I met a Department official and I asked him the key asks he wanted to show that we were a credible organisation that it could do business with. There were five asks in that and we delivered on every one of them. We have been involved, as Mr. Feeney has said, in regular consultations with the Department of agriculture. Mr. O'Driscoll is a part of the consultation and strategy on development of the future for CAP. We have made a serious effort in relation to this. We are fully committed to agriculture consultancy work and providing the best possible service. Being honest, we find it hard to understand why we are not engaged more fully because we believe we are an army in waiting, a huge resource that could be used to the betterment of Irish agriculture. I think we will be needed because the challenges ahead of us are so great.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_209">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_296">I can assure the witnesses that when the Department comes in here, questions have to be answered. This is the reality from this forum.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_210">
          <from> Mr. Noel Feeney<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_297">Could I add one more item to what my colleagues have said? If Senator Brady remembers, we spoke earlier about the reneged-on contract with the FAS scheme. Before we got that contract - Mr. Canning was president at the time and I came in after him - as an organisation, even to tender for that project and get it, we underwent a serious review of our administration etc. As members know, that is what you have to do when it comes to a public tender. We therefore have our house in order, so to speak, and, as my colleague has said, we are an army in waiting. The Senator asks what we are going to do about it. That is why we are here. We are looking for the committee's help.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_211">
          <from> Mr. Owen O'Driscoll<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_298">And if we do not get that help, the messaging will be mixed. We need to get a consistent message to all farmers equally. That is the key.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_212">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_299">To me, this is a no-brainer.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_213">
          <from> Mr. Owen O'Driscoll<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_300">Yes. I agree.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_214">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_301">The ACA is providing a service. There is no cost on the Exchequer-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_215">
          <from> Mr. Owen O'Driscoll<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_302">Absolutely.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_216">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_303">-----at the moment from its services. Teagasc is a cost on the Exchequer. The ACA is dealing with twice the number of farmers Teagasc is dealing with. To be honest, this is-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_217">
          <from> Mr. Tom Canning<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_304">In addition to that, we have a proven track record of delivery across all the schemes and we have the figures here to back us up and to prove that. It is universally recognised within the Department and within Teagasc that we are needed in order to meet the future challenges this country faces. However, it is a mechanism and we are asking for the committee's help on the four key asks: the knowledge hub, the resources for training and technical support for our members, the public funding to be provided free of charge and, lastly, our involvement in water quality initiatives for the future.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_218">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_305">That is fair enough and we will ask the Department.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_219">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_306">The witnesses are all very welcome and it is great to see them in. What strikes me is that there is a huge disconnect, and the Department when it comes in here needs to be reminded that whether you are working for Teagasc or as a private contractor, we are all trying to achieve the same objective in terms of supporting farmers and improving environmental standards. It is unfortunate that that seems to be missing.</p>
          <p eId="para_307"> Could Mr. Canning expand again on the fourth and final ask, the involvement in water quality? Is the ACA involved in the derogation plan, for example, and what level of information is it missing? I know that the figures relate, so how does that impact, for example, the ACA's work and its ability to advise on water quality across the country?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_220">
          <from> Mr. Tom Canning<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_308">Our key belief is in relation to nitrates and improving water quality. Proper nutrient management is a key element of that.</p>
          <p eId="para_309">It is about chemical and organic nutrients being applied to land at the right time in the right place and in as environmentally friendly a way as possible. Key to that is a nutrient management planning system. We have worked closely with Teagasc in the development of that. Unfortunately, our members are having to pay for it. When we put this argument to the Department of agriculture, it said it is only costing us €5 for every client we deal with. However, when that is added up across our membership, we are paying €300,000 or more to Teagasc. That money could be used very effectively for the training and support we could provide for our members. We need additional support and recognition from the Department of the contribution we can make.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_221">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_310">That software application is already built, having been paid for by the taxpayer.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_222">
          <from> Mr. Tom Canning<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_311">Absolutely.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_223">
          <from> Mr. Noel Feeney<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_312">To respond further on the Deputy's question, we often hear about derogation farmers, an issue that gets a lot of publicity in the agricultural papers and so on, but there are 130,000 farmers out there and approximately 7,500 are in derogation. Perhaps there are a few thousand more on the surface. The rest of the farmers, whether suckler farmers or drystock farmers in Roscommon, Mayo or Cork, still have to adhere to the nitrates regulation. That involves your NMP figures and so on. That information is very important because people are, for example, importing slurry from piggeries. That is a very common occurrence in Senator Brady's part of the country, that is, Longford, Cavan and so on. As we all know, pig slurry is fantastic. You can apply it in early spring, mix it in the tank and so on. We need to know what a farmer is looking like at the start of the year, by March and at the end of the year with regard to his nitrate figures. Without that, they are bringing in slurry, which is importing nitrogen and phosphorous onto the farm. In addition, the national fertiliser database records all chemical fertiliser purchases. This information applies to every farmer and not just derogation farmers. Every farmer in Ireland is affected by this in one way or another.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_224">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_313">Is that critically important information available to, for example, a Teagasc adviser?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_225">
          <from> Mr. Owen O'Driscoll<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_314">Yes, it is available to farmers and advisers on the MyAgFood platform.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_226">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_315">It is not only affecting consultants' ability to function but preventing the State and the Government from reaching their water quality targets.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_227">
          <from> Mr. Tom Canning<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_316">That information is already available to us but we are then having to pay for the tool to put in place the nutrient management plan for the farmer. As I have said, that is costing all of our members over €300,000.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_228">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_317">What level of training does the Department provide for consultants?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_229">
          <from> Mr. Owen O'Driscoll<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_318">To come in on the training side, we must do CPD modules to become accredited FAS advisers. Teagasc advisers get five or six days' training from in-house specialists and have access to specialists throughout the year if there are changes. In the ACA, we are all volunteers. Sometimes we do webinars ourselves. A couple of us come together to educate our members. What we really need is support. We need to have the resources through a knowledge hub or an ACA specialist, which can then filter down to the advisers and then the 63,000 farmers. We must make a submission to the CAP consultative committee. That is very difficult for me when I am working and trying to run a business. We do not have the resources as a knowledge hub. It is very difficult. The three of us here are volunteers. We meet monthly as a national council. It is more difficult if you do not have access to supports and funds. That is the big issue. We have the knowledge and the ability. We just need a small bit of cohesion to make it work. We are best described as an untapped resource.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_230">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_319">What is the association's ask of the Department with regard to slurry spreading and importing and exporting? Is it to get the direct message itself because the association represents the farmers?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_231">
          <from> Mr. Tom Canning<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_320">Our direct message to our farmers is that slurry being imported must be used consistent and responsibly used and that they should check with their advisers. We need to check what their limits are through the nutrient management planning system and the information coming from the Department of agriculture. If that information is late or inaccurate, the farmer could potentially exceed his nitrogen or phosphorous limits and end up with a serious problem.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_232">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_321">I need to move on to Deputy Aird. I remind everyone not to mention officials by name. Officials should be referred to by their office rather than their individual names.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_233">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_322">I welcome all of the witnesses here today. We recently had a good briefing from their association. Most of the questions I would have asked have been asked by Deputy Fitzmaurice, Senator Paul Daly and everybody else. To go back to the history of it, I remember that, when I started off farming, I did not need anybody. I was able to fill out the forms when they came out, although there were very few to be filled out. I remember a form coming out because the weather had been so bad. I think we got £50 in old money or something like that. You filled out the form yourself and sent it back. At one stage, I had to get a peace commissioner to sign a form to say I was who I was and was farming where I was farming. We have gone well past that. As I see it, Teagasc and the Department of Agriculture before it were funded by the taxpayers of Ireland and carried out all of the duties farmers wanted at that time. More than anything else, it was an educational system to encourage farmers to go in for better grass management and all that sort of stuff because there were no handouts, good, bad or indifferent, at that time. Any schemes that came out were made so difficult for farmers to avail of that Teagasc was then set up, funded by the taxpayers of this country. On top of that, we had people like the ACA who decided they could provide a good service. Lads started going to these consultants, having heard this, that or the other. </p>
          <p eId="para_323"> Speaking with my former councillor's hat on - all of the other members were also councillors at some stage or another - what also played into the consultants' barrow was that planning laws were changed and continuously fought because the local authorities wanted studies and reports on this, that and the other. With all due respect to the gentlemen who are here today, all that cost money and led to their private profit. There was a business there and they homed in on it. I have absolutely no problem with that. However, I have had another problem all my life. When I started off in the council, it cost £500 to do a report. It is up to €5,000 for a report now and there can be 50 of the same report typed up by the same people sitting in Laois County Council attached to different planning applications but they cannot be used by anyone else. I am using this forum to say what I have always said, which is that it is an absolute disgrace. This is coming from joint thinking between the Department of agriculture and the planning authorities and it is totally wrong. They now want reports on the curlew and the hen harrier. You have to run around the field looking for hen harriers to make sure there are none there. What is going on is absolutely disgraceful but we will leave that where it is. </p>
          <p eId="para_324"> I am delighted that the association has spoken to Ted Massey and seems to be happy enough with what it got. I can see what the problem is here. I can see State funding being put into a partly State organisation. It has results it wants to keep to itself and does not want to give to the consultants. That is basically what the problem is. Where the problem lies is that if Willie Aird is doing business with any of the three gentlemen here, he will do business with nobody else. If somebody else is with Teagasc, he or she will be able to complete 100% of the nitrates form because he or she will have the data there to do it. ACA consultants have to send their clients to Teagasc to do it. Is that not correct? The ACA wants us to bring in representatives from the Department of agriculture and tell them that its consultants want the same information that is available to Teagasc. I get a text message about the nitrates or whatever it is but unless the consultants have all of that information, they cannot meet the deadlines that are in place. I accept all of that. It is something that has to be done. Regrettably and unfortunately, this is getting worse. You can also see the whole TB debacle and what that has cost the taxpayers of this country. We are now doubling and trebling the money going into that and putting in different conditions. We wait to see what will come out of that. That is another day's work but I am looking forward to being-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_234">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_325">Go on Deputy, you should know.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_235">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_326">In all fairness to the Deputy, the Government cannot say what is going to happen with TB. She might even have more knowledge-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_236">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_327">The Deputy should know why the money is being provided.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_237">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_328">The Deputy might have more knowledge-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_238">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_329">One speaker.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_239">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_330">-----than the Government because she works with animals every day. My point is that when we have the Minister or the officials - it will be Ted Massey who comes in to us as well, and a couple more people - sitting there, we just have to ask them if we can have joined-up thinking. That is all. The farmer will have to pay again if the witnesses are able to even buy the information from the State. I am not saying that is right or wrong, but they are certainly entitled to the information that is out there. I agree with them on that. They cannot carry out the diligent work they are doing on behalf of farmers if they do not have that. It is the decision of the farmer as to where he wants to go. That is the other side of it. I have to stand up for farmers and say that. It is not an either-or situation; they all give a great service. I can give everyone the history. We cannot deny how it all started, and every grant that came out. It gets worse after that. There is no farmer now who can do it.</p>
          <p eId="para_331"> Deputy Newsome Drennan is so good at getting at me. Maybe she is able to fill up the forms-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_240">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_332">Thank you, Deputy. I need to-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_241">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_333">-----but no farmer I know is able to do the work.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_242">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_334">-----move on to Deputy-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_243">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_335">Everybody should be sharing their information on the derogation-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_244">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_336">Deputy, every other member has stayed within the time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_245">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_337">-----and that is hugely important.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_246">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_338">I remind everyone not to name individuals and officials by name. They can be referred to by their offices-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_247">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_339">And Deputy Newsome Drennan should not be heckling either.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_248">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_340">-----but not by name.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_249">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_341">I will heckle all I want when it comes to farming. The Deputy can try to stop me.</p>
          <p eId="para_342"> There is obviously a disconnect between the witnesses and the Department, and between them and Teagasc. There is €26 million a year going for the same advice the witnesses are basically providing. What are they spending that on? Those are questions that need to be answered. There is also the €80 million for research and education.</p>
          <p eId="para_343"> I go to the Department website to register my calves. I have a password to get in there and I put in whatever I want then log off, and nobody else has access to that information. It is my farm and my information, so if I decide I do not like the guy in Teagasc down beside me and I do not think he is doing the best for my farm and decide to go to a private company, I should be absolutely entitled to do that. With housing, there is room for everybody. There has to be room for a private entity here as well. It is the farmer's information, so if I decide to give that information to the witnesses and they have access to my account, who is the Department to say that I cannot pass it to somebody else? What is the disconnect? I can say, because I am in opposition, that it is all very rotten in Teagasc. If the witnesses can do it for cost and Teagasc is getting extortionate amounts of money, then there are questions to be answered as to where that money is actually being spent. I do not think the maths are going to add up on that one. They are definitely questions that need to be asked.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_250">
          <from> Mr. Noel Feeney<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_344">I will make a brief comment. It is important for us all to realise that we are not here to knock Teagasc. Those in Teagasc are our colleagues in an advisory sense. As has been stated, Teagasc is getting vast sums of money, but we are not here to knock that. As we have said to members all along - and this is why we want their help - the bottom line is that our issue is not with Teagasc; it is that we want a level playing field from the Department.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_251">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_345">Absolutely.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_252">
          <from> Mr. Noel Feeney<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_346">That is very important.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_253">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_347">There is room for everybody.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_254">
          <from> Mr. Noel Feeney<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_348">Teagasc is not our problem; it is the way the funds are dished out.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_255">
          <from> Mr. Tom Canning<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_349">On the question about the farmer's information, you must authorise the transfer of information and our access to that if you change agencies. Say you change from Teagasc to us, then you must sign all forms to grant us access to that.</p>
          <p eId="para_350"> On what Deputy Aird said, every day we go out, we have to compete. We have to provide the best possible service. We are only as good as the last job we did. We have to maintain that standard. It is vitally important. We are facing an ever-changing environment in which we operate. We need to get that information delivered to us and our members have to be trained to be able to deliver the same standard and quality of service they have provided, otherwise we will not be able to compete in the market because, as I said, we are only as good as our last job. We need the resources for training, to keep that up to date and to be fed that information in order to ensure we are giving the best possible critical advice to our farmer clients.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_256">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_351">Mr. Canning said that farmers should be paying the advisers; that I should be paying them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_257">
          <from> Mr. Tom Canning<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_352">We are in a commercial business here. We do not want our wages paid.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_258">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_353">I understand that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_259">
          <from> Mr. Tom Canning<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_354">What we need is the tools to be able to deliver the best possible service-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_260">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_355">They need the information.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_261">
          <from> Mr. Tom Canning<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_356">-----and we need to have the same conditions in which we are paid. Every time I go to a training course, I have to pay for my costs. As Mr. O'Driscoll said, our counterparts in Teagasc get six days' allowance. They are being paid to be there; they are paid regardless. Every day I spend training comes out of the cost. It is a cost to my business.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_262">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_357">If I asked a Teagasc adviser, he would say that the witnesses are earning five times more money than he is.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_263">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_358">Deputy Newsome Drennan has the floor.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_264">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_359">The other side of it is that the witnesses are servicing more people than Teagasc. This is what I am saying about how the figures just do not add up. My husband uses Teagasc and gets on great with it. As Mr. Feeney said, it is not that Teagasc is not providing a service because it absolutely is, and I will be clear about that; it is about how exactly the funds are dished out. Teagasc is not here to make a profit or at least it should not be. The books should be even. When they are not, Teagasc goes looking for more money. We have to use the witnesses because Teagasc is not going to be able to keep up with the demand. It is as simple as that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_265">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_360">Deputy Healy-Rae is next.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DannyHealyRae" eId="spk_266">
          <from>Deputy Danny Healy-Rae<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_361">This is a bit confusing for a fella like me, but anyway. Like Deputy Aird, these forms and things that have to be filled out are very confusing for farmers and they should not be that way. It is a fright to God that fellas get fouled up. I have fellas who were advised to go into partnership. Since 2023, they have not been paid their ACRES money because they did so. They were advised by certain people to do that, and there is little help coming from that quarter now to get them out of the knot they are in and get the bit of money they are waiting for. The likes of me is chiselled about it every day.</p>
          <p eId="para_362"> It is hard to get the witnesses' story and digest it in a few minutes like this, but it would only be fair and reasonable that they should get the information from the Department and not through Teagasc. I cannot see that the witnesses expect to be trained given they are private operators. They were saying Teagasc staff are trained, but Teagasc is part of the Department. I do not know how anyone private could expect to be paid by the State. I must thrash that out myself a bit further. The witnesses should be getting the same information as Teagasc at the same time. The witnesses do a good job. They said that they have 55,000 customers.</p>
          <p eId="para_363">I do not know how many clients Teagasc has but it is clear that neither of them could do the job on their own. We need more of these entities. I do not know if it is done the same way but how many do farmers require? They need any number of them, I suppose. Can the witnesses tell me how many farmers are in need of advice or anticipated as being in need of advice in the Twenty-six Counties at the present time?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_267">
          <from> Mr. Tom Canning<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_364">As I said, 125,000 farmers applied for BISS this year; 64,400 applied through the private advisory service providers, 41,000 applied through our counterparts in Teagasc. I will make it very clear to the Deputy that we are not looking for our wages to be paid. We are simply looking for access to accurate, timely information, which we are getting to a large extent from the Department of agriculture through the MyAgFood system. However, we want to make sure that is consistently delivered.</p>
          <p eId="para_365"> We need to disseminate the latest information through the knowledge hub and through the training of our members to prepare them for the future changes to regulations, such as the changes on nitrates that will come into effect on 1 January. We are facing into a whole new CAP support system post 2027. On 31 December, CAP supports end and we will be in a new programme. We have to be able to help and advise the clients we are dealing with to be able to meet the challenges they face. There may be cuts in incomes and we have to look at a sustainable system in agriculture. Our primary job is to provide the best possible advice to achieve that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DannyHealyRae" eId="spk_268">
          <from>Deputy Danny Healy-Rae<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_366">Are the witnesses saying at this exact moment that they are short of information, or is it that they are not funnelled enough information, or the proper and full information?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_269">
          <from> Mr. Tom Canning<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_367">We are getting clear information from the Department of agriculture. We need to ensure there are improvements made to that. As Mr. O'Driscoll said, we are calling for investment in IT resources to ensure that is delivered on time and is accurate as it possibly can be. We can get that information from the Department but we also need training to be able to deliver what is ahead of us with the changes in regulations. We have that information.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_270">
          <from> Mr. Owen O'Driscoll<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_368">To follow up on Deputy Healy-Rae's question, we know we are a really good resource. We are an army of advisers out there and we can deliver to the farmers. For a small investment, you could create a much better messaging system to farmers. You could spend a small amount of money on a private hub to disseminate the information from the research. If the research went into the hub and the advisers were trained on all the new information for water quality, air quality and biodiversity, that would then go down to the 63,000 farmers. They are not disadvantaged versus the 43,000 farmers. That is the big difference.</p>
          <p eId="para_369"> It is not that we are looking for more money or more information. We are all volunteers and we are doing our best to keep the organisation together. We need support or it will just wander along. If that happens, that is okay but it will be a huge opportunity lost. For example, by not being included in ASSAP or the EIPs, you are excluding 50% to 60% of the potential clients who could be in those. That is what it boils down to.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DannyHealyRae" eId="spk_271">
          <from>Deputy Danny Healy-Rae<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_370">All we can do here as Deputies is ask for a fair playing pitch for all.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_272">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_371">Does the Department of agriculture feed into the information the Agricultural Consultants Association has? There are so many people there and the consultants have a huge amount of knowledge. I presume the Department looks for that knowledge on derogation and everything like that. The consultants have a whole lot of knowledge so I presume it looks for that knowledge.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EileenLynch" eId="spk_273">
          <from>Senator Eileen Lynch<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_372">I thank all the witnesses for being with us today. I find the situation quite incredible. I have been thinking about it for the last 40 minutes or so as it has been discussed and I cannot quite believe it. I echo the comments of my colleagues. We will be raising this directly with the Minister. There are so many things wrong with this. The consultants have spoken a lot about derogation and it is obviously relevant to Mr. O'Driscoll's part of the world in Drimoleague - derogation is important for Cork in general - in terms of the water enhancement projects that have been carried out in Drimoleague.</p>
          <p eId="para_373"> When we look at the nitrates action plan 6 and the new requirement of the habitats directive when it comes to retaining our derogation, is there not information there that the ACA, which is across the country, will be able to feed back into our proposal when we are looking at our derogation proposal? It seems to be incredibly short-sighted. We are not aware of the extent of the extension of time we are looking for with derogation in order to put a proposal together that fully includes the habitats directive, as has been requested by Commissioner Roswall. We know it will take an awfully long time to put that proposal together when we look at watercourses all across the country. Is there not a role for the ACA to also feed into that? There is a lack of ecologists, which is a whole separate issue. Is there a role for the ACA to feed in? Is it not incredibly short-sighted by the Department to treat the ACA in this way?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_274">
          <from> Mr. Owen O'Driscoll<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_374">There is huge potential. We met the nitrates section last week. We would love to be part of the sixth water group. We have a lot of experience to bring to the table. The difficulty is that it will take time. We are all working in our own businesses. It is difficult unless we have a dedicated person we can feed our information to. That is probably a resource issue but we are limited by time. Certainly, there could be potential to create some sort of a conduit to get involved with it. We would be more than willing to get on board.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_275">
          <from> Mr. Tom Canning<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_375">I was part of the agriculture water group until I stepped down from that group last December. I stepped down because of the final report that went to Europe on the retention of the nitrates derogation. It did not include one mention of the ACA or the private advisory service providers in Ireland, even though I had attended all of the meetings and made what I felt were very positive contributions. They were really positive contributions. We are 100 days out from the next round of the nitrates regulations. We do not know whether we will have a derogation.</p>
          <p eId="para_376"> The implications are there. Morgan Sheehy, a classmate of mine, estimated that one of the implications of losing the derogation in Ireland was a 22% reduction in stock numbers nationwide. If farmers want to retain their stocking levels as they are currently, it would require them to rent the equivalent of County Kildare in land area. The effects are astounding and there would be trickle-down effects on every single farm in the country. Yet, we are 100 days out. If we do not get derogation, how will we prepare the clients to be ready for it and deal with the implications of that? If we get it, will there be different regulations? If there will be different regulations to deal with, how will we advise our clients properly on this?</p>
          <p eId="para_377"> This is what we are talking about. We need the training. We need the access to that information so that our members can deliver a clear, consistent, professional message to the clients we are dealing with who are going to be impacted by the new nitrates regulations coming on stream.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EileenLynch" eId="spk_276">
          <from>Senator Eileen Lynch<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_378">I know the ACA met with Department officials lately but in the last 12 months, has there been any satisfaction from either the Minister or Department officials about what is essentially the ACA's exclusion from information? Obviously, it is not only of benefit to the ACA but also of massive benefit to its clients and the 60,000 plus farmers across the country it represents. It is truly incredible. There is the whole anticompetitive element as well when it comes to EIPs, which I was not aware of before today.</p>
          <p eId="para_379"> Has there been any progress in general? Farming is under pressure and is facing an awful lot of challenges. We should be looking at anything that can be done - particularly things like sharing of knowledge and access to information - at a relatively low price. It is quite cost effective as the information is there already. I cannot comprehend the exclusion.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_277">
          <from> Mr. Tom Canning<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_380">We have grey hair for a reason. We have travelled down this road. As presidents, we have all made representations. We have gone with enthusiasm and positivity into every single meeting that we have attended here. We have a good working relationship with sections within the Department of agriculture. That is freely acknowledged. We have an excellent working relationship with our Teagasc counterparts as well. We are both critically important. We are looking for small asks. I remind members to look at that second last page and the four key asks we are looking for. By getting those supported, the multiplier effect in terms of the cost benefit to the Irish taxpayer but above all, to Irish farming, is absolutely enormous.</p>
          <p eId="para_381">We need to fulfil that potential and this is really our last chance. The committee is the last hope in terms of getting that engagement and supporting us in what we are trying to achieve.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_278">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T18:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_382">We will give a second opportunity to ask questions; three minutes each.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_279">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T18:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_383">I have one question on the training, when it is rolled out to Teagasc. When a new scheme comes on board or anything like that, training obviously has to go with it. I cannot understand why you would not get the training. What has been said with regard to the training? Is it something like, "No, you are a private company, you are not getting it"? What is the answer when it comes to that? At the end of the day, you are just passing on information to the farmer, most of whom, as the lads rightly pointed out, do not understand most of what is going on. They need somebody like an adviser, whether it is Teagasc or the witnesses, to come out and spell it out in plain English to them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_280">
          <from> Mr. Tom Canning<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T18:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_384">Very quickly, I would say we are required to do complete CPD training modules, as Mr. O'Driscoll said earlier, to get our FÁS accreditation. We have had no structured, organised, professional CPD training other than that for the past two and a half years. Our members rely on <i>ad hoc</i> training that they have to fund themselves, taking time off work to attend it. At the end of the day, there is no joined-up thinking with regard to organised training across the board.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_281">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T18:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_385">The Department should be obliged to give-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_282">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T18:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_386">Deputy Fitzmaurice is next.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_283">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T18:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_387">I want to go back to one thing, just to be clear. I am a farmer, moving slurry. My understanding, and I want clarity on this, is that if a farmer is moving slurry, the Department sends a text to the farmer and the receiver. If I put in a BISS application and I have a problem with it, it will come to me as the farmer and it will also go to the planner who filled it out. The query goes to them. Am I correct in saying that private planners do not get a text when that slurry is moving? Am I also correct in saying that, under what is being proposed at the moment by the Department, if a planner signs off on that slurry being moved, the weather becomes bad, it is not done and the planner does not have a bull's clue what is going on, because they signed off on the slurry being moved, they are liable to be struck off as one of the sanctions? Is that right or wrong? Where are we at with negotiations or when is it proposed that this will come in? That is a damning thing over your head. It is like someone else playing a game of football and you getting the blame for losing it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_284">
          <from> Mr. Noel Feeney<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T18:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_388">Deputy Fitzmaurice is correct. First, when we do a BISS application for a farmer and, two months later, maybe in the month of June, there is an issue with it, maybe after a satellite inspection, the Department will send us an email to say there is a client, herd number or whatever, and we deal with that situation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_285">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T18:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_389">The farmer gets it as well.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_286">
          <from> Mr. Noel Feeney<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T18:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_390">The farmer gets that text message as well, correct. Both farmer and adviser.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_287">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T18:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_391">Okay.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_288">
          <from> Mr. Noel Feeney<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T18:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_392">Regarding the slurry movements, if you are moving that slurry to me as a farmer, we will get text messages, but if I am your adviser on the opposite end to take in the slurry, I do not get a text message. The farmer does. Maybe the farmer presumes we are getting the text messages but we are certainly not. We are blissfully unaware in a lot of situations that there is a movement of slurry. As Mr. Canning would highlight, there was a large number of unverified movements of slurry on the Department base last year. That is one of the reasons. In fairness, proper slurry movements within nitrates rules and regulations must be adhered to, but we are in the dark.</p>
          <p eId="para_393"> We also mentioned earlier on that we do annual CPD training. In the most recent CPD training, there was an issue on fraud, etc. Again, that is the insinuation that we have got from our most recent CPD training.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_289">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T18:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_394">That the witnesses are carrying out fraud.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_290">
          <from> Mr. Noel Feeney<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T18:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_395">That is the insinuation we were looking at from the CPD training. There would be serious-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_291">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T18:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_396">The last question I have is a quick one. In regard to the fertiliser database, what date does that have to have that filled by? Is there a risk that if a merchant does not put in what they got during the year until the end of the year, a farmer could then tip over on their nitrates? Is that risk there? Is it genuine?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_292">
          <from> Mr. Tom Canning<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T18:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_397">Absolutely. That is correct. All farmers must declare their closing stock on midnight of 14 September by 15 October. That deadline is coming up very quickly. At the moment, we are finding that merchants are not, in all cases, recording the fertiliser purchases until the end of the year. We have to look at that and not take it at face value. We have to look at the receipts and the invoices that a farmer has for his fertiliser purchases to ensure that he does not go over those limits. It is not updated in real time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_293">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T18:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_398">The Senator is one-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_294">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T18:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_399">I do not need a question. I got my questions. Let Mr. Canning finish that, please.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_295">
          <from> Mr. Tom Canning<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T18:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_400">It is not updated in real time, plus, on top of that, there is an issue with imports coming in from third countries as well and across the Border. There is an issue there not being recorded.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_296">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-10-08T18:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_401">I thank Mr. Canning. I need to bring the discussion to a conclusion and thank the witnesses for the huge amount of information and the engagement on it. There is very clearly a mismatch between Teagasc and the witnesses and it is hugely important that the focus is kept very much on the farmer, the service they are getting and the information they are getting or not getting. We will be having the Department of agriculture and Teagasc in a follow-up meeting in due course and we will get a date and time agreed on that. I thank the witnesses for taking part today.</p>
          <p eId="para_402"> The next meeting of the joint committee is on Wednesday, 15 October at 3.30 p.m. and the agenda is anaerobic digestion. As there are no further matters for discussion, the meeting stands adjourned.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_9"> The joint committee adjourned at 6.17 p.m. until 3.30 p.m. on Wednesday, 15 October 2025.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
