<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#debates">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_housing_local_government_and_heritage/2025-12-09/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_housing_local_government_and_heritage/2025-12-09/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-09" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#author" href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/34/joint_committee_on_housing_local_government_and_heritage"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_housing_local_government_and_heritage/2025-12-09/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_housing_local_government_and_heritage/2025-12-09/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-09" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_housing_local_government_and_heritage/2025-12-09/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_housing_local_government_and_heritage/2025-12-09/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-16" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#debates">
        <TLCPerson eId="AubreyMcCarthy" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Aubrey-McCarthy.S.2025-01-29" showAs="Aubrey McCarthy"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ConorSheehan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Conor-Sheehan.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Conor Sheehan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="EoinOBroin" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Eoin-Ó-Broin.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Eoin Ó Broin"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JamesBrowne" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/James-Browne.D.2016-10-03" showAs="James Browne"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JoeCooney" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Joe-Cooney.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Joe Cooney"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MichealCarrigy" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Micheál-Carrigy.S.2020-03-30" showAs="Micheál Carrigy"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="RichardBoydBarrett" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Richard-Boyd-Barrett.D.2011-03-09" showAs="Richard Boyd Barrett"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="RoryHearne" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Rory-Hearne.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Rory Hearne"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="SeamusMcGrath" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Séamus-McGrath.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Séamus McGrath"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ThomasGould" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Thomas-Gould.D.2020-02-08" showAs="Thomas Gould"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="WilliamAird" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/William-Aird.D.2024-11-29" showAs="William Aird"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/chair" showAs="Chair" eId="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole eId="Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/minister/housing__local_government__heritage" showAs="Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/vice_chairman" showAs="Vice Chairman" eId="Vice_Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/author" showAs="author" eId="author"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/editor" showAs="editor" eId="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>AN COMHCHOISTE UM THITHÍOCHT, RIALTAS ÁITIÚIL AGUS OIDHREACHT</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>Joint Committee on Housing, Local Government and Heritage</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2025-12-09">Dé Máirt, 09 Nollaig 2025</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2025-12-09">Tuesday, 09 December 2025</docDate>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_en">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_ga">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">Tháinig an Comhchoiste le chéile ag 03:00 p.m.</summary>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">The Joint Committee met at 03:00 p.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_3">Comhaltaí a bhí i láthair / Members present:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_1">Teachtaí Dála / Deputies</p>
              </th>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_2">Seanadóirí / Senators</p>
              </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#WilliamAird">William Aird,*</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#AubreyMcCarthy">Aubrey McCarthy</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#RichardBoydBarrett">Richard Boyd Barrett</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#MariaMcCormack">Maria McCormack</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#JoeCooney">Joe Cooney</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#AnneRabbitte">Anne Rabbitte.*</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_9">
                  <person refersTo="#ThomasGould">Thomas Gould</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_10">
                  <person refersTo="#RoryHearne">Rory Hearne</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_11">
                  <person refersTo="#SeamusMcGrath">Séamus McGrath</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_12">
                  <person refersTo="#EoinOBroin">Eoin Ó Broin.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_4">* In éagmais / In the absence of Deputy Paula Butterly and Senator Joe Flaherty, respectively.</summary>
          <summary eId="sum_5">I láthair / In attendance: Deputy Conor Sheehan.</summary>
          <summary eId="sum_6">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#MichealCarrigy">Teachta / Deputy Micheál Carrigy sa Chathaoir / in the Chair.</person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Delivering Homes, Building Communities 2025-2030: Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:00:00+00:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_1">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_13">I would like to advise members of the constitutional requirement that members must be physically present within the confines of the Leinster House complex in order to be participate in meetings. The Government published its new national housing plan, Delivering Homes, Building Communities: An Action Plan on Housing Supply and Targeting Homelessness 2025-30 on 13 November last. It commits to delivering 300,000 homes by 2030, including 72,000 social homes. Today I am pleased to have the opportunity to consider the new housing plan with the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage, Deputy James Browne, and his officials from the Department.</p>
          <p eId="para_14"> Before we start, I wish to explain some limitations to parliamentary privilege and the practices of the Houses as regards references you may make to one another in your evidence. The evidence of witnesses physically present or who give evidence from within the parliamentary precinct is protected pursuant to the Constitution and statute by absolute privilege. Witnesses are again reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice that you should not criticise or make charges against any person or entity by name or in any such way as to make him, her or it identifiable or otherwise engage in speech that might be regarded as damaging to the good name of the person or entity. Therefore, if your statements are potentially defamatory in relation to an identifiable person or entity, you will be directed to discontinue your remarks and it is imperative that you comply with any such direction.</p>
          <p eId="para_15">The opening statement has been circulated to members. I invite the Minister to make his opening remarks. Is it agreed among members that we will publish the statement after the meeting? Agreed. I call the Minister.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage" eId="spk_2">
          <from>Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage (Deputy James Browne)<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_16">I thank the Cathaoirleach for the opportunity to address the committee today. Housing remains the defining social and economic challenge of our time. It impacts families, communities, our workforce and our national competitiveness. That is why the Government’s new plan, Delivering Homes, Building Communities, reaffirms housing as the number one priority for every arm of government, national and local, and sets out a clear, ambitious and realistic path to the delivery of the homes people need.</p>
          <p eId="para_17"> This plan builds on the progress already made under Housing for All. Over 137,000 new homes have been built, 44,000 social homes have been delivered and nearly 16,900 affordable supports have been provided, including more than 4,500 cost-rental homes, a tenure type that did not even exist five years ago. These achievements give us a strong foundation. However, now we must do more and we must do it faster.</p>
          <p eId="para_18"> Under Delivering Homes, Building Communities, we are targeting 300,000 new homes by 2030. This is not a ceiling; it is a floor. If we can deliver more, we will. Increased supply is the single most effective way to moderate price growth, improve affordability, tackle homelessness and allow more people to put down roots in communities. The plan is built on the two pillars of activating supply and supporting people. Activating supply means removing the structural barriers that have slowed housing delivery for too long. Those include barriers in planning, infrastructure, land availability, regulation, skills and finance. A major driver of this is the largest public capital investment programme in the history of the State. Over the next decade, €275 billion will be invested, ensuring delivery of the infrastructure needed for housing. To ensure this investment translates into actual homes on the ground, the Government has established the housing activation office. It is up and running and already engaging with all local authorities and industry. Its task is simple: to identify and remove blockages so land can be activated and homes can be built without delay.</p>
          <p eId="para_19"> We are also reforming the planning system through the implementation of the Planning and Development Act 2024, providing certainty, clearer timelines and better outcomes. A revised national planning framework has already allowed the zoning of significantly more land. Across government, the work of the accelerating infrastructure task force will work alongside these measures to ensure there is a pipeline of zoned, serviced land in place to support housing delivery over the lifetime of this plan.</p>
          <p eId="para_20"> To boost viability, especially for apartments, the Government has introduced a suite of complementary measures that could reduce the delivery cost of apartments by up to €160,000 per unit, unlocking developments that were stalled only months ago. Increasing skills and capacity is also essential. That is why we are doubling investment in Enterprise Ireland’s built-to-innovate programme, supporting the adoption of modern methods of construction and ensuring at least 25% of social and affordable homes will use these faster, more efficient building techniques. To support SME builders, the backbone of housing delivery in many areas, the Government has approved €400 million in ISIF equity investment for homebuilding and €200 million more for Home Building Finance Ireland. </p>
          <p eId="para_21"> The second pillar of our plan is ensuring that the homes we build meet the needs of all our people. Homelessness, particularly child homelessness, remains one of the most urgent issues facing the State. Delivering Homes, Building Communities recognises that we must both increase supply of housing and tackle the root causes of homelessness to be successful. We reaffirm our commitment to the Lisbon declaration to work towards ending homelessness by 2030. We will implement a child and family homelessness action plan and a homelessness prevention framework. We are providing an additional €100 million in capital funding in 2026 to help families to exit emergency accommodation.</p>
          <p eId="para_22"> The most powerful tool we have, however, is the delivery of social housing. Over the lifetime of the plan, we will provide 72,000 new-build social homes and provide 90,000 affordable supports. In 2026 alone, over €9 billion in capital funding will support social and affordable delivery through the Exchequer, the Land Development Agency, LDA, and the Housing Finance Agency. We are also tackling vacancy and dereliction head-on, through the expanded vacant property refurbishment grant, the extended living city initiative and a new derelict sites tax. These measures will bring thousands of homes back into use, revitalising our villages, towns and cities.</p>
          <p eId="para_23"> The plan recognises the changing needs of our population. An action plan for housing for older people will support right-sizing options and increase the delivery of suitable homes. Funding for the enhanced housing adaptation grant for older people and disabled people has been increased to €130 million and investment in Traveller-specific accommodation will rise to €34 million in 2026.</p>
          <p eId="para_24"> Delivering Homes, Building Communities is not a single programme or a single policy. It is a national effort that is long term, collaborative and ambitious. It is built on record investment, on evidence, and on the belief that every person in this country deserves the security of a place to call home. We do not underestimate the scale of the challenge ahead but in Delivering Homes, Building Communities we have a clear plan, the resources to deliver it and a shared determination to succeed. I look forward to our discussion today. I thank the Cathaoirleach.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_3">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_25">I thank the Minister. We will now go to the members for questions. I remind them that the time allotted is for questions and answers so I ask them to be specific. Time slots will last seven minutes. I call Deputy Séamus McGrath.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_4">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_26">I thank the Minister and his team for being here. The housing plan is comprehensive and I welcome it. The action plan has a significant number of different actions across a number of areas. The Minister said in his opening statement that activating supply is one of the key pillars. That is undoubtedly a critical part of trying to turn a corner on housing.</p>
          <p eId="para_27"> I wish to ask about the additional funding of €2.5 billion for the LDA. What is the Minister's vision for the LDA, going forward, in terms of its role and remit? We have seen an expanded role recently, which is important. I will take the opportunity to ask the Minister to outline his overall vision for the LDA.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_5" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_28">I thank the Deputy. Activating housing is a key priority. The LDA is a key delivery partner for the Department in delivering the homes that we need across the country. We have expanded its remit across the country, and I thank my Government colleagues for the agreement to do that. The total funding now available is €8.75 billion. An additional €2.5 billion in funding will be provided to the LDA in the form of equity investment. This is in addition to the current provision of €3.75 billion in equity investment, €1.25 billion in borrowing and €1.25 billion that can be raised by the LDA through the performance of certain functions under the LDA Act or arrangements referred to in the Affordable Housing Act 2021, as provided for in the Act of 2024.</p>
          <p eId="para_29"> The LDA is currently updating its five-year business plan to reflect an increase in ambition, its increased remit and the additional funding that has been provided. The plan will, I have been assured, be provided to me in the first quarter of 2026 and will outline delivery to 2030. In addition to the more than 2,000 homes that the LDA has already delivered, it is working on a pipeline of a further 27,000. The LDA is now active on 40 sites with a series of projects at early stage design, planning or construction. We expect in the next couple of years for it to become the largest home delivery company, if you like, or body in the country.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_6">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_30">That is very welcome. The LDA has shown itself to be active and successful in what it has done so far. To see an expanded role is welcome.</p>
          <p eId="para_31"> Another theme of the plan, and one in which the Minister strongly believes, is addressing the issue of vacant properties. There is also the under-occupation of properties and we must try to secure greater numbers of accommodation units by bringing vacant units back and increasing the occupation. Will the Minister talk about the dereliction tax that is due to come in and provide a broad timeline for it? I would also like to hear about the reform of the refurbishment grant, which I know was flagged in the plan. I also ask about the above-the-shop-type grant, which is part of the Minister's plan. On the theme of vacancy and trying to improve our overall occupation of the existing stock of buildings, perhaps the Minister will comment on how we see that unfolding in the next period.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_7" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_32">I thank the Deputy. The best homes we can deliver are those that exist and are vacant because they do not need any additional services. We must make the best use that we can of those properties and get them back into use. That is important. It is why there are so many measures to tackle vacancy and dereliction. As I have said previously, dereliction is effectively antisocial behaviour. We are looking at different ways to tackle dereliction across the country.</p>
          <p eId="para_33"> The derelict property tax was announced in budget 2026. It will replace the derelict sites levy, which is currently under the remit of the local authorities. It is subject to the necessary legislation being introduced in the finance Bill 2026. Preliminary registers will be published by local authorities in 2027 and following this, there will be time for property owners to appeal the fact that their properties, or whatever the case may be, are on the register.</p>
          <p eId="para_34">Using the Revenue Commissioners to target derelict properties is the way to go. Not too many countries have the approach to dereliction we do and the penalties we have. We do have challenges in terms of the application of our current dereliction law. Using the influence and power of the Revenue Commissioners is the appropriate way to do this.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_8">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_35">Trying to reduce homelessness and provide people with long-term secure homes is a key part of the plan. There is a particular focus on child and family homelessness and trying to address that issue in the plan. Will the Minister outline how he envisages the roll-out of that with the local authorities, approved housing bodies and the various sectoral bodies helping in the homeless situation?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_9" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_36">Tackling homelessness is a central part of the plan. That is why it is in there and forms part of the title. We are addressing homelessness in a number of different ways. The key to solving homelessness in and of itself is the sufficient supply of the homes we need in the country to tackle it. Until we get the supply up to meeting demand we have taken a number of decisions. The plan reaffirms the commitment to the Lisbon declaration in working toward the end of homelessness. We have the national homeless action plan, which in turn is helping us to develop our national homeless prevention framework. We have also secured €100 million for next year in addition to the €50 million this year, specifically to remove and exit families longest on the emergency accommodation list. We are working with every local authority as we develop our child and family homelessness action plan as well. Today I met Cork City Council. I am meeting with every local authority to ensure that not only are we making the correct decisions to tackle homelessness in this country, but that through our local authorities, which are our housing authorities, that everything is being done in each local authority to tackle homelessness. It is also to learn from them and their experience to ensure the policies we are implementing are working for the local authorities in the best way possible.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_10">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_37">Before addressing the plan I put on record my strong objection to the manner in which the Minister is railroading through significant changes to building control legislation in the Oireachtas tomorrow. These are controversial proposals. The so-called regularisation procedure in particular will have received no scrutiny whatsoever in its legislative form. It will receive no meaningful scrutiny tomorrow. It is a retrograde step. I urge the Minister, and I will do the same tomorrow, to withdraw those amendments and utilise the proper committee procedures. We have a growing number of cases where developers are commencing developments with no commencement or other forms of certification and creating a loophole by which they will effectively be able to retrospectively secure building compliance. It is fraught with difficulties. I am not saying it is impossible, but it should not be done in the manner in which the Minister is doing it. I urge to him to reconsider.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_11" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_38">Pre-legislative scrutiny was done on this in April 2024.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_12">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_39">It was, and many of these concerns were raised then. However, the Minister has now produced legislation for which there will be no Oireachtas grouping. He does not understand the seriousness of what is being proposed. Therefore, while today is about the plan-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_13">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_40">Today's meeting is about the housing plan that was announced. I received correspondence from Deputy Ó Broin and spoke to the Minister and his officials who said they are happy to do a briefing that we will arrange for the private session tomorrow morning.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_14">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_41">My objection still stands, although I will attend the briefing tomorrow. I turn to the plan. At the centre of the Minister's proposals to try to increase supply is a proposition about apartments. He has reduced apartment design standards to allow higher densities, smaller and darker developments. He will allow developers to reset rent to full market rent between tenancies and remove controls completely from the apartment developments. He will spend €640 million on a VAT tax break, with no benefit to supply, between 2026 and 2027.</p>
          <p eId="para_42"> The Society of Chartered Surveyors Ireland report today blows a huge hole into the centre of his plan. While the society has welcomed some so-called viability measures, what is striking about this report is the increasing all-in development costs for apartments. Page 17 has the full detail. Reading through that and the analysis of the implications of those costs for affordability for private rental, private purchase or cost rental it shows that the Government is not going to be able to deliver anything close to affordability, even in cost-rental schemes, with these all-in development costs, even with the huge level of subsidies it is throwing in.</p>
          <p eId="para_43"> Is the Minister concerned by the significant increases in all-in development costs in today's report? Is he concerned that in the vast majority of cases people would need a gross income of between €124,000 and €146,000 to be able to buy these homes? The rents that would be charged for the equivalent development costs would exclude 80% of working people and are going to have a significant upward pressure on cost rents. Does the Minister accept that there is now a problem that he did not fully anticipate in his plan? Is he going to reconsider his measures in light of today's report?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_15" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_44">The Deputy raised several issues. Apartment specifications are being brought back in line with what would be standard across the European Union. We have a large-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_16">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_45">The FOI from his Department disputes that but we can discuss that separately.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_17" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_46">-----number of apartments with planning permission that are not being built because of a viability issue. Part of that is the costs.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_18">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_47">We know all of that. I am asking him to respond-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_19" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_48">The Deputy raised it as an issue, and I am addressing it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_20">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_49">I did, but the question time is mine and I get to decide the questions. I am specifically asking the Minister to respond as to whether he has concerns about-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_21" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_50">The question is in the context of his entire statement.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_22">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_51">-----the price of the all-in development of these apartments.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_23">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_52">One at a time, please. The Deputy asked his question but please give the Minister time to answer.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_24" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_53">The apartment specifications are more in line with Europe because we have to get them built. The perfect apartments-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_25">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_54">Who is going to buy them at the prices that are detailed in the report?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_26" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_55">No one is going to buy any apartment that is not built.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_27">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_56">Who is going to buy an apartment costing €650,000?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_28" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_57">My entire plan-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_29">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_58">Deputies, please.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_30">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_59">The LDA will not be able to buy them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_31" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_60">-----is all about-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_32">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_61">Approved housing bodies will not be able to buy them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_33">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_62">Please, Deputy.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_34" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_63">-----the delivery of supply. The entire housing plan of this Government is about increasing supply. It is also about addressing the affordability-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_35">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_64">How can supply be increased when the prices of the units are so high there will be no buyers?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_36" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_65">-----and that is the challenge.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_37">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_66">No public or private buyers. Is the Minister not genuinely concerned by the rising prices contained in today's report, and the fact that means there will not actually be a market for apartments given their cost?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_38" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_67">I am conscious of the cost of delivering apartments and houses in this country. That is why we have taken significant viability measures. One of those was bringing specifications back in line with standards across the European Union. That is because we had standards that were too high and ensuring a situation where they were simply not being built.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_39">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_68">Has the Minister even read the report today? Even with those changes to design standards, croí cónaithe cities, STAR and the VAT reduction, we are still talking about all-in development costs of between €500,000 and €650,000. Who is going to buy them?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_40" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_69">We have taken significant measures to address the costs of delivery of housing in this country.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_41">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_70">Yet the costs continue to go up.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_42" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_71">We have also taken significant measures towards addressing the issue of affordability for people to be able to buy those homes, many of which the Deputy completely opposes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_43">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_72">I have not opposed any housing scheme anywhere.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_44" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_73">Is the Deputy not opposing the first home or help to buy schemes?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_45">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_74">What I do not understand-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_46" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_75">Is he in favour of them now?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_47">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_76">The vast majority of these apartments will not be eligible for either the first home or the help to buy scheme because of the prices. That is in today's report. My question is the same. Who is going to be able to afford to buy these? Individual buyers will not be able, individual renters will not be and State agencies will not be. Who is going to buy them at the prices detailed in today's report?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_48" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_77">We have taken significant measures to address both supply and affordability. That is what-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_49">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_78">They are all detailed in the report and the costs are still too high. Does the Minister understand the challenge here?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_50" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_79">I am very much aware of the challenging situation. That is why we have published a housing plan to address those.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_51">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_80">Is the Minister going to revise that plan in light of today's new information? It is information he clearly did not have when he produced that plan.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_52" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_81">We take into consideration any reports published by any bodies, but we also do not take any report as gospel.</p>
          <p eId="para_82">I am pretty sure the Deputy is not accepting everything in that report either, just as he waves the Housing Commission report around every day in the Dáil when he knows full well there are numerous measures in there that he does not accept. We take into consideration any report-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_53">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_83">Is the Minister saying this report is wrong, that the prices are lower than what is detailed here?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_54" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_84">We take into consideration any report, Deputy, but we also do not blindly accept any report either. We have taken significant measures in the housing plan to address both viability and affordability. We need to get apartments and houses built, and we need people to be able to afford them. That is what we are doing.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_55">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_85">I thank the Minister for his opening statement. Housing remains the defining social and economic challenge of our time, which is why I believe that the Government's new plan, Delivering Homes, Building Communities, will speed up delivery and make more homes available for our young people, who are finding it very hard to get accommodation, which we are all well aware of. Accommodation for young people is vital and important.</p>
          <p eId="para_86"> Community land trusts are an internationally accepted mechanism that can deliver permanent affordable housing and prevent local displacement, which is sometimes extremely relevant to my own county of Clare, with high levels of tourist demand for second and holiday homes. Unfortunately, that is not helping young people to get on the housing ladder.</p>
          <p eId="para_87"> Community land trusts are mentioned in section 6 of the Affordable Housing Act 2021. Housing authorities can be supported in providing affordable housing, as can community-led housing organisations and housing co-operatives. None of these options is included in the Delivering Homes, Building Communities strategy. Will the Minister commit to reviewing this oversight and consider supporting the potential of community land trusts to deliver permanent affordable houses for communities through the provision of publicly owned land?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_56" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_88">Delivering homes in rural Ireland forms a crucial part of the housing plan, whether that is in our towns or villages, on islands or in the Gaeltacht. There are numerous measures within the plan to address that, for example, our measures around vacancy derelictions and measures with Uisce Éireann to be able to get small developers to develop in rural Ireland using the general binding guidelines with the Environmental Protection Agency, EPA, and Uisce Éireann, in addition to working towards serviced sites, particularly in villages.</p>
          <p eId="para_89"> As regards community land trusts, there is a pilot project in Cork. I have no particular objections and I am happy to work with the Deputy to see how we can develop policies. At present, it is certainly at a small scale but I am very happy to work with Deputy Cooney or have my officials meet him to see how we can look at expanding the possibilities there.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_57">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_90">Does the Minister think this would deliver housing in rural parts? Does he think it would be a good idea to look at the land trusts? Would he look at the idea?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_58" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_91">It is very much something we could look at. I want to see more detail around it but it has potential. As I said, I am very happy to engage with the Deputy's idea on this.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_59">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_92">I thank the Minister.</p>
          <p eId="para_93"> Another issue is that of mixed-use single door properties. As we know, these were once the lifeblood of our towns and villages all over the country. Unfortunately, many of them are now vacant and heading into dereliction. The regeneration action under pillar 1 of the Delivering Homes, Building Communities strategy is important. The local authority purchase and renovation loan should be an obvious funding mechanism to support that. However, I have been told that single door mixed-use properties cannot be included under this scheme, which is very disappointing for rural villages and towns. We should not be closing any door that would support their reuse, which is very important, especially with the crisis we are currently in. Will the Minister commit to giving local authorities the ability to include these types of property in the local authority purchase and renovation loan scheme, even on a case-by-case pilot basis to begin with? I know from a parliamentary reply that, under the scheme, little or no use was made of the scheme between quarter 4 of 2024 and the end of quarter 2 of 2025. There were only three applications and one payout in that length of time. Something is obviously not working and it should be looked at. Does the Minister think a review of the scheme should be undertaken?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_60" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_94">I thank Deputy Cooney for his question on the local authority property and renovation loan. It has not been used to the extent we had envisaged and perhaps we need to look at the restrictions around it to see how it can be used more effectively and more efficiently across the country. There certainly have been challenges in terms of its uptake and use. Maybe part of that is around the knowledge of it, but also how it is set up. Perhaps it is simply too restrictive. It is something I want to see an awful lot more use of and the Deputy's idea relating to mixed-use single door properties is a very good one. I do not see any reason for a restriction on that but I need to investigate it a little more. I am happy to engage with the Deputy on this.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_61">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_95">If there was more use made of it, we would bring back more of those derelict houses throughout rural parts of the country in particular. We are all aware of town centres with small shops that no longer exist. Many of them closed down, unfortunately, and it is important that they are renovated back into residential properties. Whatever opportunity can be given to the owners of those premises should be given. I am disappointed that there is very little take up on this. The whole thing needs to be reviewed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_62" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_96">I agree with Deputy Cooney. The scheme needs to be looked at again to ensure it is effective. In our rural villages and towns, there are many vacant shops that are highly unlikely to come back into retail again. Using those mixed-use properties for accommodation is essential.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_63">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_97">I thank the Minister.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_64">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_98">The Minister claims the new housing plan increases protections for renters from evictions, but there are thousands of renters who have paid their rent and done nothing wrong and who are being evicted right now across the country. One contacted me on Sunday. She is a solicitor and is about to be made homeless. She has been renting for six years and has always paid her rent on time. She is being evicted but cannot find anywhere to rent that is below €2,500 per month. She does not know what she is going to do. What does the Minister think she should do?</p>
          <p eId="para_99"> Is it not true that tens of thousands who are being evicted right now, and those in existing tenancies, will receive no additional protections for tenant security from eviction after 1 March of next year? Why will the Minister not implement a temporary three-year eviction ban, like was done during Covid, to keep people in their homes?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_65" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_100">I thank the Deputy for that. The new plan around rental properties will increase security of tenure. For the first time ever, we will have fixed security of tenure in this country, as is normal across the rest of Europe. It is the correct thing to do and is why we are bringing it in. That is not the case at present. Existing tenancies will continue under the existing rules because that is the basis in which that tenancy, both from the tenant's perspective and the landlord's perspective, entered into it. For example, the resetting rules will not apply to existing tenancies. The continued protections and situation that currently exist will continue as they are.</p>
          <p eId="para_101"> As regards bringing in an eviction ban, it would supply. The Deputy's focus seems to be on being populist to protect everyone who is in a rental situation right now. I do not have that luxury. I have to deliver more property so we can support renters, not just existing renters, but also those living at home who need somewhere to live. That means driving supply. An eviction ban will not do anything to drive supply; it will kill supply. Nobody is going to deliver additional properties into this State where there is an eviction ban in place. We know that from international research. The Housing Agency has done research on this. The existing rent pressure zones are killing supply. That has been the experience across the world. The research has been done on this and that is why we are bringing balanced changes. These are changes to rent pressure zones whereby we are moving to a national rent pressure zone and security of tenure under the new system for tenants while also allowing a resetting, which gives that balance. A resetting can at most be to what the market is. We have massively increased - by 70% - the funding to the Residential Tenancies Board to ensure it has the necessary ability to protect tenants as well.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_66">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_102">That is very unfair and it is wrong to say that I am being populist in what I am saying. I am saying it because this is an ongoing humanitarian crisis. I know the Minister is aware of it and I think and hope he wants to do something more. This is an emergency and I believe that eviction ban is in place.</p>
          <p eId="para_103"> I will move on. As a result of the failure of numerous housing plans, we have over 500,000 people stuck in their parental homes, infantilised. What is in the plan to address this? Will the Minister also comment on the housing video, promoted by his Department, that advises young people dealing with the transition back to home? It has caused huge hurt and frustration to the hundreds of thousands who are locked at home in a form of hidden homelessness. Was the Minister aware that video was shared by the Department? Does he agree it should have been shared by the Department? Does he accept it has caused huge hurt for these people and is tone deaf for the hundreds of thousands who are struggling right now with the housing disaster?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_67" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_104">The people who are at home are the very people for whom I am trying to activate the market so we can get more homes delivered for purchase, including more apartments for purchase and rent. Increasing supply is the only way those people are going to get out of those bedrooms and into somewhere they can live independently, safely and securely.</p>
          <p eId="para_105"> In respect of the video, it was prepared by SpunOut, an excellent NGO. I dealt with it when I was my party’s spokesperson on mental health. It does an awful lot of great work. It was prepared and put out by young people to talk to young people. The Department of housing did not have an involvement in it, but it retweeted it. I acknowledge the good work done by those young people and why they are doing it. We are in a housing crisis. We have a serious homelessness situation that I wish to bring to an end. I am not going to knock those young people or SpunOut for doing that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_68">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_106">This is not about the young people. In the context of how it feels for those people affected, does the Minister not think this is a let-them-eat-cake moment for his Department to share and promote such a video when the Department and Government are standing over, contributing to, dealing with and responding to this situation? I have received messages from people who are living the housing crisis and what they are saying to me is that this feels completely tone deaf. Whatever about this coming from SpunOut, in respect of the Department of housing, it feels to those people that the Minister is saying this is what they should do in terms of the housing crisis. I understand some of the stuff in the video with regard to helping people through transition and change, but in the context of the housing crisis and what is going on, it has really upset people.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_69" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_107">I read the Deputy's comments. I must have missed the part where he acknowledged it was SpunOut and young people who did it. Instead, he seems to be obsessed with somehow putting the blame for it on me. My Department and I did not lead this. We did not have any involvement in it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_70">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_108">It is my understanding that the Housing Agency commissioned it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_71" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_109">I was not aware of it. An official in the Department of housing, well-intentioned but maybe misconceived, saw what young people in SpunOut were doing and reposted it. There is nothing sinister about it. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_72">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_110">It is not about being sinister; it is about-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_73" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_111">There is no conspiracy behind it. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_74">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_112">-----the frustration. As the Minister said, it was misconceived for the Department to promote that video.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_75" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_113">It was misconceived. A bit of balance is needed here. These are young people in SpunOut, who did fantastic work. They deserve credit for their work and what they were doing to try to help other young people. The Department had no role in the video but it reposted it. Reposting the video was misconceived but there is an attempt to try to paint a picture – I read comments in the national media to this effect – that somehow this was directed by me, the Department or whatever the case may be. I am conscious of the pressure young people are under living at home. I want to get them homes. While I hear what I am doing constantly being knocked, I am not hearing alternatives. My aim is to get those young people-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_76">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_114">That is not true either. We put alternatives to the Minister, like the State savings scheme, and he ignored it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_77" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_115">-----out of those homes and into homes. We did not ignore it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_78">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_116">It is not in the housing plan.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_79" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_117">There is a difference between not ignoring something and doing something. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_80">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_118">There is a difference between saying we are not putting forward any solutions when we have put forward some.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_81" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_119">All my focus is on finding homes for those young people at home. I am conscious of the stress those young people are under. As I said, everything I do every day is to try to deliver the homes for those young people to have somewhere to live safely and securely.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RichardBoydBarrett" eId="spk_82">
          <from>Deputy Richard Boyd Barrett<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_120">Susanne is in my office in Dún Laoghaire at the moment. She is facing eviction with her two children with special needs by Park Development, one of the biggest builders in the country.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_83">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_121">I ask the Deputy to be careful about naming a development company. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RichardBoydBarrett" eId="spk_84">
          <from>Deputy Richard Boyd Barrett<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_122">Why?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_85">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_123">I am just making the point. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RichardBoydBarrett" eId="spk_86">
          <from>Deputy Richard Boyd Barrett<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_124">This is not some mom-and-pop landlord, as the Minister often refers to, evicting someone. Rather, this is a business that makes money out of a housing situation in this country. Susanne wants to know what she is supposed to do. Park Development is refusing to sell to the council because it wants to get the highest price it can get. It just wants to profit out of the fact that it is going to make her and several others who are facing a similar situation in the Glencairn View estate, which is just off the N11, homeless. This is because the Minister has turned his face, and has repeated it here today, against having a no-fault eviction ban for people who have done nothing wrong and children with special needs. In the Minister’s document, it says there will be a framework to deal with the prevention of homelessness. How does it fit in with Susanne? Tell me because the plan is vague. It mentions engaging with local authorities and having a framework. How is the framework going to help Susanne and her kids and other people who are facing eviction through no fault of their own?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_87" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_125">As I said, my view is that an eviction ban will kill the supply of additional homes in this country for everyone who needs those homes, not just those who are currently renting. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RichardBoydBarrett" eId="spk_88">
          <from>Deputy Richard Boyd Barrett<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_126">Okay, the Minister has said that. What should be done for Susanne and her kids?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_89" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_127">I am not going to talk about an individual person.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RichardBoydBarrett" eId="spk_90">
          <from>Deputy Richard Boyd Barrett<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_128">For anyone in her situation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_91" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_129">For anyone in her situation, we are bringing out the homelessness prevention framework. What we do-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RichardBoydBarrett" eId="spk_92">
          <from>Deputy Richard Boyd Barrett<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_130">A framework.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_93" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_131">Where someone is coming into a homeless situation-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RichardBoydBarrett" eId="spk_94">
          <from>Deputy Richard Boyd Barrett<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_132">Will it help Susanne stay out of homelessness?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_95" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_133">-----if they cannot find an alternative place to live, what happens is the local authority, and the HAP people working within the local authority, try to help to find an alternative place to live. We are also-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RichardBoydBarrett" eId="spk_96">
          <from>Deputy Richard Boyd Barrett<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_134">She has been offered a HAP payment of €1,700. She is looking for a three-bedroom home. Try and find a rental property anywhere in south Dublin, or anywhere in Dublin, on a HAP limit of €1,700. You can forget about it. Does the Minister have any comment on the hopelessness of that situation?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_97" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_135">Every effort is then made to help find that person somewhere to live. We are also driving social housing supply so that-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RichardBoydBarrett" eId="spk_98">
          <from>Deputy Richard Boyd Barrett<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_136">What efforts are being made?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_99" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_137">-----fewer people need it. We are bringing in changes in the rent pressure zones for renters. For example, if very large landlords are selling property, they cannot sell with the tenant in it. That is why we are bringing in that security of tenure. It is to ensure that someone is protected within that. We are bringing in a number of measures, both to strengthen tenants' rights and also help prevent people going into homelessness. Where it does happen-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RichardBoydBarrett" eId="spk_100">
          <from>Deputy Richard Boyd Barrett<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_138">Can the Minister just be specific?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_101" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_139">We are also increasing the social housing supply.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RichardBoydBarrett" eId="spk_102">
          <from>Deputy Richard Boyd Barrett<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_140">Can the Minister just be specific? He has used the word "prevention" and it is in the plan. He has mentioned “prevention” and “frameworks”. How is his prevention framework going to help Susanne and her kids? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_103" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_141">I have explained it. Where someone is becoming homeless-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RichardBoydBarrett" eId="spk_104">
          <from>Deputy Richard Boyd Barrett<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_142">It is not clear to me what I should tell her.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_105">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_143">Will the Deputy please let the Minister answer? He asked a question and should let the Minister answer.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_106" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_144">Obviously, I cannot address an individual situation, but what happens is-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RichardBoydBarrett" eId="spk_107">
          <from>Deputy Richard Boyd Barrett<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_145">This is typical. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_108" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_146">-----the local authority engages with that individual person. We are increasing significantly the number of social houses. One would hope that there may be a situation where that person could be offered a social house. If not, an alternative HAP can be provided. There are also homeless HAP supports as well. We are also bringing in reforms of our landlord and tenant law to ensure that it is far more difficult for someone in that situation to be evicted in the future.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RichardBoydBarrett" eId="spk_109">
          <from>Deputy Richard Boyd Barrett<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_147">Tell that to Park Development. I understood that the LDA was supposed to be offered all public land that was available for housing. Last night, councillors on Dún Laoghaire-Rathdown County Council were informed that DLR Properties Limited, a wholly owned subsidiary of Dún Laoghaire-Rathdown County Council, is selling land to private developers after a deal with Tuath Housing, an AHB, for 67 houses collapsed.</p>
          <p eId="para_148">I do not know why it collapsed but, unbelievably, DLR Properties Limited, a wholly owned subsidiary of a local authority, is selling and the councillors are told that none of it is their business, there is nothing they can do and they have no input whatsoever. Apparently, DLR Properties Limited is going to get rid of loads more land - a lot of it is up in Cherrywood - that almost certainly could be used for public and affordable housing. I am asking for the Minister to intervene. That is a disgrace in the face of the crisis. With land prices as such, and with land banking and so on, the idea of a public body getting rid of land that could be used for public housing or affordable housing is a disgrace. Will the Minister intervene?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_110" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_149">No, I would not intervene in an individual situation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RichardBoydBarrett" eId="spk_111">
          <from>Deputy Richard Boyd Barrett<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_150">That is another one.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_112" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_151">Land is to be offered to the LDA on a first-option basis but it is not the case that the LDA will take every single piece of public land that is available. It will engage with, for example, local authorities. The local authorities do have to decide what is the best way to deliver the most amount of homes in their area.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RichardBoydBarrett" eId="spk_113">
          <from>Deputy Richard Boyd Barrett<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_152">So it is going to be allowed to sell the land. That is absolutely disgraceful and the Minister is not going to intervene.</p>
          <p eId="para_153"> I think €13 million was given in local infrastructure housing activation fund, LIHAF, funding to the developers in Cherrywood - by the way, a lot of DLR Properties Limited land is up there as well - the biggest residential development in the entire country, where properties are now being sold by private developers for €600,000 and €700,000, which is clearly unaffordable. For the €13 million in LIHAF funding, we were supposed to get affordable housing. It is more than a decade on and there is no sign of any affordable housing. There is none - zero - for the money we paid for the infrastructure. How could that be the case? Could the Minister explain that, when there is supposed to be a commitment to affordable housing from this Government?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_114" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_154">I am not familiar with the specific LIHAF situation-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RichardBoydBarrett" eId="spk_115">
          <from>Deputy Richard Boyd Barrett<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_155">Could the Minister even look into it?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_116" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_156">-----but I will engage with the local authority and my own officials.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RichardBoydBarrett" eId="spk_117">
          <from>Deputy Richard Boyd Barrett<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_157">In regard to people over the threshold, I raised this last week. If you are over the threshold and facing eviction, you are kind of goosed. What can the Minister say to people who are over the threshold and where there are no supports for them if they are facing homelessness because they are over the social housing threshold?</p>
          <p eId="para_158"> For older people who might be trying to access affordable housing, particularly those who face an eviction, any affordable schemes the Department has are pretty much closed off to them because they are too old. They will not pass muster for getting loans, even the local authority home loan, because they are too close to the end of their working lives. Is there anything the Minister can say to help them?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_118" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_159">My understanding is that the first question is in relation to somebody who is maybe above the social housing threshold but below the cost rental. Is that what the Deputy is saying? They are falling between the gap there.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RichardBoydBarrett" eId="spk_119">
          <from>Deputy Richard Boyd Barrett<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_160">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_120" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_161">I will always keep these under review and I am happy to hear any examples from the Deputy but my aim is always to ensure that on that spectrum, somebody falls in somewhere in order that if people are on the affordable housing spectrum, if it is not cost rental, there is another affordable measure there for them if they are above the social housing. It is something I keep constantly under review and I am very anxious to hear of any examples where people are falling between the different schemes - because I want to be sure there are no gaps between them - or if somebody has a solution, whatever that solution may be.</p>
          <p eId="para_162"> In relation to older people, older people who have been renting their entire lives and now find themselves in a situation where they are struggling to get a housing solution is becoming an increasing problem. I acknowledge that with the Deputy. It is a situation that the Minister of State, Deputy Kieran O'Donnell, is working on to try and come up with what measures we need to address that. I think we probably need new measures to address that particular situation, which concerns a growing cohort. It is a very frightening position for those people to be in and I certainly acknowledge that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_121">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_163">I wish to turn to the plan in relation to starter homes and the intention to deliver 15,000 starter homes per annum. I know the Minister has listened to me on occasions in regard to affordable purchase. It is critically important that this is a core part of the starter home package, in my view. Specifically, what are the key actions to try to ramp up the delivery of affordable purchase across the State, the local authorities and other suppliers and through the Part V provision as well? It is a critical part of the starter home package and we really need to see delivery of higher numbers of affordable purchase. I ask the Minister to comment on that please.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_122" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_164">I thank the Deputy and I agree. On the starter homes, affordable purchase is a key element of that. We have significant funding to be able to help deliver affordable purchase. Some local authorities are now delivering a significant amount. Some local authorities seem to be a little bit reluctant to move on affordable purchase. That may be the case because some local authorities probably feel a little bit burned from past experiences as well. We are working with those specific local authorities to find a pathway to maximise delivery of affordable purchase as a housing solution for those who want to avail of it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_123">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_165">I thank the Minister. He knows my views on it. It is a critical part of the starter home package so I would ask that every effort is made to work with the local authorities to ramp up supply.</p>
          <p eId="para_166"> I will turn to something that was touched on by some of the speakers so far. I refer to the limits with regard to the first home scheme, the help-to-buy scheme and the local authority home loan. I have raised this issue with the Minister in the Dáil as well. There are many first-time buyers who find themselves outside those limits. The help-to-buy scheme has a €500,000 ceiling with regard to the price of the property. The first home scheme, in relation to Cork, for example, is €450,000 in the county and so on. Many first-time buyers are simply outside that in regard to the properties available to them to purchase. Similarly, in regard to the local authority home loan, I was contacted recently by someone who has gone through a separation and hopes to avail of the fresh start principle under that but, again, the limit that is on the first home scheme is presenting a problem.</p>
          <p eId="para_167"> Overall, I know the Minister said they are constantly under review. Can we take some optimism that there will be a look at these limits in the very near future?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_124" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_168">Very much so. I appreciate that there are certain areas in this country where the limits, especially near border areas of different local authorities, can have a bit of a negative impact in terms of the supports that are needed, especially where, perhaps on those border areas, prices can be quite similar but the amount of supports can differ as a result of one local authority being considerably lower. It can be. These limits are kept under review. Most of them are kept under independent review. We want to ensure that we maximise the supports people can get without driving inflation or driving up the overall housing cost. I assure the Deputy that all of these schemes are currently under review with a view to ensuring the right balance of supports are there without creating any unintended consequences or driving up the overall price of housing.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_125">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_169">Continuing on the theme of limits and the income limits for social housing, they are quite restrictive at the moment. There is quite a low income limit. I know it varies across the country but the Minister mentioned earlier about closing gaps between individual families who qualify for social housing, and the next step with regard to cost rental, affordable purchase or whatever may be available. It is quite a significant gap at present and part of the solution has to be narrowing that gap through the increase of the social housing income limits. Is it intended that we will look at those income limits in the near future?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_126" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_170">Absolutely. I am looking at those limits. The last time they increased was 2023 and we are now coming into 2026. There has been inflation in that period as well, which will have affected people's ability, that balance and the spectrum where people's certain income limits would come into. We are reviewing all of those at the moment. The first home scheme price thresholds, for example, are being actively reviewed at the moment but I am looking at the social housing thresholds as well to ensure everybody falls within the correct or most suitable housing solution to meet their needs. It increased by €5,000 in 2023 but I am conscious there has been significant inflation since that time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_127">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_171">I would appreciate if the Minister could look at that as soon as possible. In relation to rightsizing, it is in the plan and it is very important. Whenever we talk about rightsizing or downsizing, it is always important to reiterate that it is totally voluntary and up to the individuals in regard to freeing up a family home, if it is something they want to do, but the options have to be there for them. What I am hearing from elderly people is that they do not see the options out there.</p>
          <p eId="para_172">They would vacate their traditional family home but they do not see a place for them to go - somewhere that is attractive to them, that is secure and that is designed appropriately in terms of a single-storey property. The Minister mentioned it in the plan in terms of rightsizing. Some local authorities have embraced it quite well while others have not. What can we do to ensure local authorities embrace it across the country? Some local authorities simply do not have a rightsizing scheme. The scheme needs to be looked at in terms of reform but it also needs to be rolled out across the country and our 31 local authorities. I welcome it in the plan. How can we make it a reality and deliver on it? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_128" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_173">I know a number of local authorities have run these types of schemes, including Limerick and Cork. There is no national scheme to help people rightsize. The Minister of State, Deputy O'Donnell, is working on an plan for older persons of which rightsizing is a key part. Where people want to rightsize, two things very much hold them back. One is bridging finance, while the other is getting a property in their local area. They want to stay in their communities and be close to their families and what they are familiar with. It is about ensuring that staying within the local community is an option for older people, in particular if they want to rightsize. If they want to stay in their existing home, they should be helped to do that as well. It is about what works for them. I find that many older people are willing to rightsize but only where the alternative accommodation meets their needs. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_129">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_174">I totally agree. Regarding the focus on homelessness, on child and family homelessness and the need to acquire larger properties, the rightsizing scheme has the potential to deliver larger properties. There are many four-bedroom properties that people would willingly give up if they feel there is somewhere attractive for them to go. It can certainly help address family homelessness. There are many benefits to a rightsizing scheme and it is important that it is rolled out across the country. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_130">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_175">Our public session next week focuses on homelessness. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasGould" eId="spk_131">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Gould<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_176">I thank the Minister and his officials for being here. The new plan commits to developing a new voids programme. What will this look like? When will it be in place? Will it bridge the funding gap that is there? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_132" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_177">We are looking at a voids programme. We already provide very significant money for voids - €260 million for local authorities in 2026. It is and remains the duty of local authorities to ensure their stock is maintained-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasGould" eId="spk_133">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Gould<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_178">I do not mean to interrupt the Minister but I am asking specifically about the new plan. I am not talking about local authorities. The new plan commits to developing a new voids programme. What will this look like? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_134" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_179">A key part of it is that principle that local authorities are responsible for ensuring that voids, which are vacant social housing, are turned over as quickly as possible and are maintained. I have already said that from next year alone, €216 million will be----- </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasGould" eId="spk_135">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Gould<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_180">To clarify, we are talking about the new plan. Maybe there is another plan that exists that I do not know about for local authorities. I am talking about the Minister's plan. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_136" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_181">That is what I am talking about. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasGould" eId="spk_137">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Gould<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_182">There is nothing specific in it. We are passing the buck to local authorities. Is there anything in the plan? Is there any funding in it? What will it look like? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_138" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_183">Local authorities maintaining their own stock is not passing the buck. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasGould" eId="spk_139">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Gould<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_184">We are back to local authorities. I am asking the Minister a straightforward question. We are here to discuss-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_140" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_185">Voids are local authority properties. The Deputy is asking me to talk about a plan about voids without mentioning local authorities. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_141">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_186">Deputy Gould should give the Minister time to answer the question. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasGould" eId="spk_142">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Gould<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_187">We are not here to talk about local authorities. We are here to talk about-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_143" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_188">Voids. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasGould" eId="spk_144">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Gould<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_189">-----the plan. We are here to talk about the plan. There is no additional funding. I asked the Minister last week or the week before in this committee whether there was any additional funding for local authorities to return voids and he said "No". I thanked him for his honesty. We could clear long-term family homelessness in this State by returning the voids programmes. The Minister is putting that on the local authorities. I asked him what is in the plan to specifically solve that. There are two families in Cork who have been over four years on the list, three families who are over three years on the list, 25 families who are over two years on the list and 73 families who have been on the list for over a year. There are hundreds of boarded-up houses in Cork. Cork City Council had to put up rates this year because it did not have the money. The Minister is saying that local authorities have to do it. Cork City Council had to put up rates on businesses that are struggling and barely hanging on to balance a budget. It also had to put up the local property tax to balance the budget. Where is Cork City Council getting that money? It put up rates and the local property tax. What else is it supposed to put up? It looks like the Minister wants all local authorities to put up rents. That is the only way they can raise their income. </p>
          <p eId="para_190"> We will move on. The Minister's plan commits to 15,000 affordable homes on average. Last year, 7,100 were delivered. The Minister is not delivering on targets for social, affordable and cost rental. We need those targets to be able to monitor how this plan is going. Will he deliver those targets? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_145" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_191">Local authorities will have targets. The target for social housing for next year is 10,200. We are continuing to work with local authorities in terms of their targets to maximise the delivery of social and affordable homes. Our local authorities, which are our housing authorities, are critical to delivering an awful lot of the housing solutions. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasGould" eId="spk_146">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Gould<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_192">I understand that but what are the targets for social, affordable and cost rental for next year? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_147" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_193">For 2026, the target for social housing is 10,200. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasGould" eId="spk_148">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Gould<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_194">What about affordable housing? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_149" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_195">For starter homes, we are looking on average to hit 15,000 units. We have a very good chance of achieving that. I do not have the figure for cost rental in front of me but I can get it for the Deputy. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasGould" eId="spk_150">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Gould<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_196">I would like that because those figures should be in every plan. I must have contacted the Minister's office a half a dozen times if not more looking for data on derelict sites. Normally derelict site figures are produced in the first quarter of every year. It is now December and I still do not have access to them. I have raised this a number of times with the Minister. Are derelict site figures being withheld by the Minister, his Department or someone because every year I have been a TD, I have been able to get those figures at the start of the year or after the first quarter? Here we are in December and we do not have access to them. Why are figures relating to the derelict sites register, levies and the performance of local authorities being withheld? Will the Minister commit to releasing them after today? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_151" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_197">They are not being withheld. We are dependent on local authorities for that information and are working with them to finalise the figures so the figures will be released. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasGould" eId="spk_152">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Gould<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_198">How come it is nine months later? I sent an FOI to every local authority over the summer and again last month. I can get the information. I am a backbench TD from an Opposition party and I can get the information. Deputy Browne is the Minister with a Department. Is he telling me that local authorities are withholding information they are obliged to give him and his Department? I find that hard to believe.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_153" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_199">All I can tell the Deputy is that we are finalising those figures and they will be published. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasGould" eId="spk_154">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Gould<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_200">When will they be published? Will they be published before Christmas? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_155" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_201">I do not have the exact date in front of me.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasGould" eId="spk_156">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Gould<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_202">Can the Minister understand my frustration? These are published at the start of every year. We want to be constructive. We want this plan to work. </p>
          <p eId="para_203">I swear to God we want this plan to work. I held a clinic yesterday. I got out of that clinic at 3 o'clock. We were in there the whole day dealing with people. Housing is the number one issue, as is the number of people who are homeless or at risk of homelessness. We want the plan and we want to be constructive. The Minister's document states that he is committed to the plan of ending homelessness by 2030. The Minister's plan states that we affirm our commitment to the Lisbon declaration "to work towards ending homelessness by 2030" on page 60. At the current rate, there is no way the Government will do that, in this plan that has been outlined. I will ask the Minister a question that I asked his predecessor, the Taoiseach and the Tánaiste. If the Government does not end homelessness by 2030, will the Minister accept that it is a failure of his as the housing Minister?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_157">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_204">We need to move on now.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasGould" eId="spk_158">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Gould<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_205">I would like an answer, Chair.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_159" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_206">I deal with issues as they arise. I have my plan and will speak to it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasGould" eId="spk_160">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Gould<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_207">It is contained in the Minister's document.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_161">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_208">Deputy Aird, who is standing in for Deputy Butterly, is next.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_162">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_209">I have a question for the Minister. I have been in contact with the Minister to ask him about a girl with disabilities. April is the girl's name and I have been working with her for many years. She would now be described as a mature student. She spent a lot of time during her life having operations. She eventually qualified and was on the housing list of Laois County Council. As she has taken up a job for herself, she now finds that she is above the threshold and the council has informed me that she will have to be taken off the housing list. We have social houses that will soon be completed by Laois County Council and one of them that is being built would have been suitable for her needs. This is very wrong. I have spoken to the Minister and his officials. I came to the committee meeting today to see if I could prolong the date because he kept telling me that Laois County Council sets the thresholds. Laois County Council does not set the threshold. The threshold is set for the council by the Minister's Department and the council abides by the rules of that. Surely there is some concession for a person who is confined with disabilities. If this person was on HAP, the income from the little job she got would not have affected her. She could never get HAP because she could never get accommodation to rent suitable for her needs. That is point number one. Number two is that she can never, ever get a loan because she cannot get mortgage protection. Surely there has to be some compassion here.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_163">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_210">I remind members that the discussion today is on the housing plan in general. I ask them to be careful about discussing the specifics of any person. I do not think this is the place to talk about that matter. Maybe the Minister and his officials will talk to Deputy Aird off-site.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_164">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_211">I have already spoken to them and cannot get a result. I am sorry, but it is Christmas time and I am very downbeat over this. It has been going on for a good few years. It was going to be a happy Christmas for this girl. It is a simple thing. There has to be some leeway for people with disabilities. There is no leeway - not a fivepenny piece of leeway - and I think it is so wrong. We cannot compare people with disabilities with any other person who is on the list because those people can go out, seek and get accommodation but this girl could not get accommodation. She could not avail of the HAP because there was no suitable accommodation to be got. There is no accommodation that is suitable to her needs. Laois County Council was going to provide the accommodation suitable to her needs.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_165">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_212">I remind the Deputy that today's discussion is about the housing plan in general and not specific cases</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_166">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_213">This is part of the housing plan. I am not on this committee. I came in because I asked if I could have the time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_167">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_214">I let the Deputy in.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_168">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_215">I know. I did the same thing already today. I chaired the agriculture committee this morning and I let two people in because other people did not come. I am just asking the question. If I cannot get answers at an Oireachtas committee meeting like this, where will I get the answers? I spent an hour yesterday at Laois County Council on this particular subject. I have been at it for years and it is so close to my heart. I am very passionate about it because I think it is wrong. That is all.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_169" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_216">The Deputy is very passionate about this situation and case. I can get one of the senior officials, such as the Secretary General, to talk to the Deputy to see if there is some way of resolving this particular situation. To be fair to the Deputy, he has been raising this issue for a few weeks now or longer.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_170">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_217">I thank the Minister.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_171">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_218">I thank the Minister. I had another question about what he was doing but I will not put them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_172">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_219">The Deputy still has another three minutes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_173">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_220">No, it is all right. I will give it to the other members. I thank the members of the housing committee for allowing me in. That is all.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_174">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_221">Sorry, the Deputy came in. He has three minutes left for other questions. He is taking Deputy Butterly's slot.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_175">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_222">I will give it to the other members who are here. That is all other than to say I was a member of the council for many years. There is a need for joined-up thinking when a local authority makes a submission to the Department of housing saying it is ready to go for planning for more houses. It is taking up to ten years from the time a site - a piece of land - is purchased to the time somebody, whoever it is, cuts the ribbon. That is what I have seen down through the years. It is now worse instead of better. In 1992 Laois County Council bought 8 acres of land and in 1995 - three years later - the 8 acres of land was completely built out. That would not happen now. It would take ten or 12 years before it would happen. I would just like to say-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_176">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_223">I ask the Deputy to let the Minister answer that. Changes have been made during the past 12 months.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_177">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_224">Laois County Council, as the Minister knows, is the best council in the country for delivering housing. We are the very best in the country.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_178">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_225">The Minister to respond.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_179" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_226">Thanks very much Cathaoirleach. The Deputy is right when he says that it is a very good local authority. During the last year, we have abolished the four-stage process and moved to a single-stage one. We have increased the limits under which the local authority can deliver homes from €17 million to €200 million, giving them a huge increased scope. We have issued standardised manual design to make it more straightforward for local authorities to know what needs to be designed and built and how to deliver housing. As these changes wash into the system, I think we will see local authorities being able to move an awful lot more quickly. I want us to remove some of those constraints to assist local authorities, like Laois County Council, that have the capacity to drive on with housing delivery.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_180">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_227">That would solve the housing problem.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_181">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_228">I thank Deputy Aird. I omitted to mention at the beginning there were apologies from Deputy Paul McAuliffe and Senator Pat Casey. The next slot falls to Fianna Fáil again. I think I will let Deputy Ó Broin in as a second speaker rather than having three, to be fair. Deputy Ó Broin is to come back in. I think Senator McCormack is voting in the Seanad.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_182">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_229">She is voting in the Seanad.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_183">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_230">Senator Anne Rabbitte is voting as well.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_184">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_231">Will the Minister tell us when he is going to publish the social, affordable, purchase and cost-rental delivery figures for quarter 3? Will it be before the Dáil breaks for Christmas?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_185" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_232">The aim is to try to do that but I cannot guarantee it. That is certainly the aim.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_186">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_233">Is the Minister in any position to give us any indication as to whether the slow rate of progress in the first two quarters will improve in quarter 3? Has he had sight of draft figures at this stage?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_187" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_234">I have not looked at draft figures yet but our aim is always to increase the delivery.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_188">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_235">The Minister mentioned to my colleague that there is a cost-rental target for next year that he will share with the committee. Will he also confirm if there is an affordable purchase target for next year and share that with the committee if he does not have it with him today?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_189" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_236">In terms of starter homes, that is a broad base.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_190">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_237">My question is specifically about the affordable purchase scheme. Will there be a target for the affordable purchase scheme next year? The Minister told this committee at an earlier session that this year's target for affordable purchase is 2,100. Will there be a target for that scheme for next year?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_191" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_238">I will have to get clarification on that for the Deputy.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_192">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_239">Yes, if the Minister could share it with the committee. When he was with the committee previously he told us that the affordable purchase target for this year is 2,100 and the cost-rental target across the various agencies is 2,350. I am looking for comparable figures for next year.</p>
          <p eId="para_240"> One of the other issues I have raised regularly - it is even more important now - is that the affordable purchase and the cost rental schemes have not only been underperforming in terms of missing the targets and the total number, but the price of both schemes is rising. Deputy Séamus McGrath rightly raised his concerns around affordable purchase earlier. We are being told by the LDA and the approved housing bodies that there is a growing number of people who, when they apply either for cost rental or affordable purchase, are being priced out.</p>
          <p eId="para_241">They earn too much to be eligible for social housing but do not earn enough to be able to access cost rental or affordable purchase. When this was raised with officials previously, we were told this was not an issue being tracked by the Department. Given that cost rental in particular is an important form of tenure for those who fall between the two stools of the private and the social, will the Minister give a commitment that the Department will start tracking the number of households excluded from those schemes solely on affordability grounds? That would give us a sense of the scale of the challenge. In some of the developments I have seen, such as cost-rental developments with the LDA or approved housing bodies, as many as 50% if not more of the applicants who would be deemed eligible on all other grounds are not eligible on the affordability grounds. Therefore, they have no options; neither social, cost rental nor the private market. Will the Minister give a commitment to start tracking that issue in the Department so we can have visibility on the size of that group which is now being excluded?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_193" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_242">It is a group of people I am always very concerned about if they are being excluded from various schemes. I can commit to looking at whether that is viable.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_194">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_243">To be helpful, it is. I have written to a number of AHBs asking if they can provide that data and they can. I am not sure if a couple of the smaller AHBs hold it but for the majority of the properties, the LDA, Clúid, Respond and Tuath can do so. There was a report in the <i>Irish Daily Mail</i> today about the doubling of the number of people in their 60s in the private rental sector. Many of those people have occupational pensions and on retirement their income will fall, they will struggle to pay private rents and also struggle to pay cost rents and may not be eligible for social housing. Will the Minister give a commitment that data will be collated and discussed with committee periodically? That would be useful.</p>
          <p eId="para_244"> Does the Minister have any concerns about the rising prices of the cost rental and affordable purchase schemes? We are seeing prices for two-bedroom and three-bedroom cost-rental units of €1,700 and €1,900 a month. They are 25% below market rent but they are very high rents. Likewise, the use of open market valuation for affordable purchase means the all-in price, if you want one of the units completely, is very high. Is the Department following those upward movements of price? Does the Minister have any concern about the trajectory of where they are going?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_195" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_245">We closely follow them. Any upward trajectory impacts affordability; there is no question. We have sought to take measures to try to address that through, for example, corporation tax changes. It is something-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_196">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_246">Paschal Donohoe was before the finance committee and I asked him specifically about this. He said the reduction in corporation tax would not be passed on to new cost-rental tenants of the LDA in rent reductions. It was solely, as he described it, a viability measure. We had quite a detailed exchange. He said at no stage was the discussion with him around reductions in rents for new cost-rental tenants so the corporation tax exemption will not have any impact on the rents. Does the Minister accept that? He seems to be suggesting something different to the former finance Minister.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_197" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_247">The aim is to maximise the delivery of the number of cost-rental properties made available to us.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_198">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_248">Does the Minister accept it will not have any impact on downward pressure on rents because that is not the purpose of that measure?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_199" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_249">We will work through it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_200">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_250">The former Minister for Finance was much more definitive. The Minister said he got rid of the one-stage process. That is not my understanding - work is still ongoing. Is the new one-stage process now in place and local authorities can apply for it, or are the details of the scheme still being worked out?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_201" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_251">I have made the decision to get rid of it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_202">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_252">Has the Minister got rid of it? Can a local authority today apply under this new scheme or process or is it still being worked through with the local authorities?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_203" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_253">It has been finalised with local authorities and should be fully in place-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_204">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_254">When does the Minister expect it will be open for people to apply?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_205" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_255">It should be in place in the next couple of weeks.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_206">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_256">It is the Minister's intention to publish data on its usage? There was very poor uptake, as the Minister knows, of the previous one-stage process in the number of applications in units. Does the Minister intend to publish information on that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_207" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_257">Absolutely. The previous one-stage process was not availed of too often. That was because the limit was so low and the local authority was responsible if it went above the limit. Understandably, local authorities were risk averse in those circumstances. Unless the delivery was very much at the bottom end, they were not prepared to take that risk.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_208">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_258">Will the Minister forward the figures for 2026 projections for affordable houses?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_209">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_259">It is two schemes - cost rental and affordable purchase. If that can be provided to the committee, it would be very welcome.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_210">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_260">Will the Minister forward those figures? Deputy Gould wanted details of derelict sites for 2024 and 2025. They should be available early in the first quarter of 2026. Local authorities should forward that information. I will call Deputy Hearne because he has to go to speak in the Chamber. I will then call Deputy Séamus McGrath.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_211">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_261">The first area I want to focus on is the issue of starter homes. Are there targets? The Minister said 15,000 but are there targets specifically for affordable purchase and cost rental? I know we have asked for the figures but has the Department set targets for each year?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_212" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_262">Housing action plans are currently being developed. Our overall target remains 15,000 starter homes. Numbers within that will remain flexible. We have to bring flexibility into the system to maximise the use of various schemes. I am always reluctant around actual specific targets because they become an end in themselves rather than the overall purpose which is to maximise housing delivery. That is the overall mission we need to aim towards.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_213">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_263">I was very critical of the lack of annual targets in the plan itself. I feel there in an issue in that. I know the Minister has a different view. If we are trying to get local authorities, not-for-profit housing bodies, which in particular are core, and the LDA to ramp up delivery, whatever about the overall targets - which I still think should be in the plan - does the Minister accept there should be targets for them so they know where they are aiming? I understand what the Minister said about flexibility but surely there is a need to say this is what we need to deliver if we are going to deliver sufficient affordable housing, for example.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_214" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_264">We know what we need to deliver. Our aim is for the LDA, the AHBs and the local authorities to maximise delivery. I do not want anybody to get a sense that there is a target and when we get to that target, that is our job done. When you go back to the core principle of the mission, which is to maximise delivery, that is where I want all the focus on. The overall targets are minimum targets we want people to achieve and focus on.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_215">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_265">On the area of affordable purchase, we had Dara Turnbull from Housing Europe at the committee. The Minister is probably aware of that organisation. He spoke about a missing sector in Ireland in housing which is co-operative housing or community-led affordable housing. I know the Housing Agency has been doing some work on that. There is no ambition or target for delivering that affordable co-operative housing-led sector in the housing plan. It is a gap. Did the Minister explore it and not want to put it in the housing plan? Will he talk about that? Has he considered it?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_216" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_266">I am aware that it is being looked at. It is innovative in the context of Ireland. There will probably be proposals going forward. I am open to seeing how they can be used. They are not far enough advanced to form part of a plan at this stage.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_217">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_267">The Minister, the Department and the Government should promote it more. It is a real solution in places like Copenhagen where people co-own apartment blocks as tenants and renters. They buy equity in it. We have a long history of co-operative housing development in Ireland. There is a need to promote in particular the community land trust model. I would appreciate if the Minister would look into that.</p>
          <p eId="para_268"> On the State savings scheme proposal we made, the Minister said in the Dáil that the Department is looking into it and we discussed it with Ms Timmons as well. It is a real opportunity. I know there is a broad acceptance that we need more funding and finance. The Taoiseach's argument is that this would take years to set up and is not really going to have a material impact now. Surely the longer you make that argument, of course it is going to go on longer. If we start now doing that model like in France, it seems an obvious one. The current models are not that.</p>
          <p eId="para_269">They are not where people can go into any bank, open an account called, let us say, the State savings account, and then that money is being channelled into affordable housing or social housing. There is a real opportunity in Ireland, in particular, to funnel it towards the private affordable housing delivery market. The Minister might give an update on that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_218" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_270">I thank the Deputy very much. I did ask the Department of Finance. I undertook to look at the<i> Livret A</i> measure because it is the Department that would be leading on it. I hear the Deputy on a very specific<b>
						</b><i>Livret A</i>-type measure, but the response from the Department of Finance was that its view is that the National Treasury Management Agency, NTMA, already operates the State savings schemes, which provide a range of products. The total value in the State savings schemes totalled €24.3 billion at December 24. The NTMA in turn provides a source of funds to the Housing Finance Agency, Home Building Finance Ireland, HBFI, and the LDA as well through the Ireland Strategic Investment Fund, ISIF. There are concerns that a <i>Livret A</i><b>
						</b>scheme would detract from the other investment schemes. However, I will certainly ask the Department of Finance to keep it under review.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_219">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_271">I appreciate that. I do think it is a real potential solution.</p>
          <p eId="para_272"> The other area is in relation to rents and student rents. It has been reported in the media that the Department of higher education wants more regular increases of rents allowed in terms of student accommodation. However, it has been reported that the Minister said he wants the situation of every six years to apply to student accommodation. Can he clarify what exactly his position is at the moment in relation to that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_220" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_273">Our position, as stated publicly, is that it is six years for resetting. I am not going to get into any ongoing discussions between the various Departments or what has been reported in the media and what is or is not correct. It is not what we do. The current proposal is not just the six-year resetting, but because sometimes there can be a higher turnover of students within student-specific accommodation, there would be a three-year maximum reset on it so it could only happen once. It is, therefore, an<b>
						</b>additional restriction.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_221">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_274">Yes, because there is that turnover every year, essentially.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_222" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_275">It is an additional restriction, if you like, on student-specific accommodation, but that is currently where we are at.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_223">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_276">Would that apply to private student accommodation?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_224" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_277">No, it will not apply to private student accommodation. I have been very clear on that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_225">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_278">Just student accommodation-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_226">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_279">I thank the Deputy.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_227">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_280">I am sorry.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_228">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_281">We are just-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_229" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_282">It is purpose-built student accommodation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_230">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_283">Both private and public if it is purpose-built.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_231" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_284">If it is on a university. Purpose-built student accommodation has a very specific identifiable approach to it being built, so legally it can be separated out.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_232">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_285">I will turn to the issue of finance for the construction sector. The Minister mentions in the plan additional funding of €400 million for the Ireland Strategic Investment Fund and €200 million for Home Building Finance Ireland. Will he elaborate for us what exactly he intends that funding package will help with?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_233" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_286">Is this the equity fund for smaller builders?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_234">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_287">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_235" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_288">I expect to be launching that in the very near future. It is very important because we have made a number of significant measures to activate large-scale development. However, I am also very conscious that a key element of how we address our housing crisis is by maximising delivery of smaller developments and through smaller and medium-sized developers. They, in particular, have a real challenge right now. I spoke earlier about how we have tried to address one of their challenges through developer-led wastewater infrastructure and then also developing serviced sites. However, the other way is the equity piece. Small and medium-sized developers are struggling to get loans from banks because of the very high equity demand. Their alternative, in some cases, to meet that equity need is to go out and borrow on international financial markets at very high rates. Therefore, what we are attempting to do with the Tánaiste and Minister for Finance, Deputy Simon Harris, with the banks is to try to plug some of that equity gap at a much lower interest rate. That is where we see this fund coming into place. We would expect that fund would be used as property as built and sold. Obviously, there are repayments, and that fund can be continuously reused and replenished.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_236">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_289">That is good because smaller builders and smaller developers have a lot to offer. Affordable finance is certainly one of the key issues for them, so the provision of that fund is very welcome.</p>
          <p eId="para_290"> I will go back to the issue of vacancy. It is widely viewed that there are over 100,000 vacant properties across the State. The Minister's plan has a number of key measures in relation to it. The derelict property tax is a welcome initiative as far as I am concerned. I agree with the Minister that people sitting on properties and not activating them is a major social issue. There are complex reasons in many cases but at the same time, there are others where there are not complex reasons. People are simply letting them lie. If that tax is to work, we need to significantly look at the derelict site register that is there at the moment. It is only capturing a very small number of those derelict properties as far as I am concerned. It is around 3,000 nationally if I am correct. We are looking at 3,000 captured out of a potential vacancy pool of 100,000, although they are not all derelict; I appreciate that. While we are waiting for this tax to be set up - it is taking a long time as far as I am concerned and I am sure the Minister would share my concerns there - we can do a lot to improve the current derelict sites list. We need to work closely with the local authorities to do that to try to ramp up the number of properties that are captured. Perhaps the Minister would take that away. He might comment on it today as well to see how we can dramatically improve that in terms of capturing the properties that are both derelict and vacant.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_237" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_291">I thank the Deputy very much. In terms of local authorities, there is a fair amount of forewarning now that the derelict sites are coming in under the Revenue Commissioners. I would hope local authorities are going to continue and will add to that the number of derelict properties across the country. We will be working with the local authorities to ensure that is the case.</p>
          <p eId="para_292"> It is also looking at the definitions of what is derelict and what is vacant and ensuring that there is no opportunity for properties to slip in between the two. As far as I am concerned, if a person's property is not being occupied and it meets the threshold for being vacant, it is either vacant or derelict. We do need to look at the definitions again, and the Deputy has been very strong on this, and rightly so, in order that there is no opportunity for any properties to slip between the vacant or derelict definitions. It can come down to local authority interpretations, but for some of those, the derelict definition is perhaps a bit dated. We need to look at that definition as part of the reform in terms of the derelict tax that is going to come in as well.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_238">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_293">Absolutely. As a former councillor for a good number of years, I am all for local authorities to be given discretion. At the same time, however, there has to be consistency brought to bear on this issue in terms of the definition of dereliction because as far as I can see, there is too much inconsistency across the country in relation to it. Certainly, looking at that definition is a key part of it, so I would very much welcome that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_239">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_294">The Minister is all for reforming the planning system through the implementation of the Planning and Development Act 2024, providing certainty, clearer timelines and better outcomes. It is very welcome. What can be achieved there? Can we achieve what we would be hoping to achieve in that? We are well aware that all planning applications are taking a long time at the moment, and it is actually putting developers off getting involved in buying land and developing it. I am well aware it is because of all the criteria and red tape they have to go through. Will this achieve the speeding up of planning applications?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_240" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_295">Very much so, and the Minister of State, Deputy Cummins, is doing very good work in this area. We have done a number of things to speed up planning. We set up An Coimisiún Pleanála, and it is now meeting 90% of all of its statutory timelines. Anybody appealing is now getting that turnover very quickly.</p>
          <p eId="para_296"> In relation to the local authorities, we are working with the Minister, Deputy Lawless, in terms of increasing the number of people going into the whole area of planning.</p>
          <p eId="para_297">We are also working with the Minister, Deputy Burke, and planning expertise is now included on the critical skills list. What the Minister of State, Deputy Cummins, is doing through the planning exemptions is a huge body of work that will come in in the first quarter of next year. It will clear off a huge amount of the workload from our planners in our local authorities to allow them to focus on housing delivery. They will no longer be caught up in what they spend an awful lot of their time doing now, namely, enforcing very small planning issues that really should not be needing a planning decision at all. I do not want to prejudge the outcome, but an example would be needing planning permission for a Velux window in the front of your house, for example. A bus shelter also needs planning permission, which seems a bit odd. I think there will be lots of these exemptions. This is the approach. We need more planners. It is quite difficult, however, to find skilled planners now, so we are approaching it from the other end of actually removing some of the workload. We are addressing An Coimisiún Pleanála and huge strides have been made.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_241">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_298">That makes common sense and it will take a lot of the workload off the planners. I am well aware many of them are very stressed with what they have to go through. Have objections and judicial reviews been looked at and can something be put in place there to stop some of those going on, bar their really needing to go forward?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_242" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_299">Our judicial review system is an essential part of our courts system and our courts system is an essential part of our democracy under the umbrella of our Constitution. The nature of judicial reviews has changed in recent years. They have moved away from general principles into being more of a trawling exercise by some people. There is also the length of time appeals to An Coimisiún Pleanála or judicial reviews were taking in and of themselves. This was becoming a justification for bringing an appeal for no other reason than to delay. We have tried to speed it up. Within judicial reviews and planning applications made under the 2024 Act, this legislation significantly tightened up what is known as the <i>locus standi</i>. The grounds under which people can take a challenge are now much tighter. There is a need to have an actual interest. There has also been the removal of the appeal to the Court of Appeal and the removal of the opportunity for someone taking a judicial review to amend their hand, to change the grounds, during the case. There is also a requirement for people to have put their best foot forward and to have exercised all the various opportunities before ending up in court. We are now examining applying the same rules to decisions made under the 2000 Act.</p>
          <p eId="para_300"> We are preserving the opportunity for people to be able to take judicial reviews, which is essential in any democracy, but also tightening up the basis on which this can be done. We are also removing the leave stage. Where the judge finds there is an issue, this does not mean the planning application is struck out. It simply goes back for remittal to allow it to be seen whether that particular issue can be amended or fixed, rather than everybody having to go back to the very start again, thereby reducing the costs. This retains that democratic balance while ensuring the courts are not being weaponised and there is efficiency in the system.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_243">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_301">Some 300,000 houses will be built before 2030. I really welcome this and it is fantastic. Are we going to have the workforce in this country to deliver those houses?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_244" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_302">There are certain challenges with the workforce but modern methods of construction are essential here. This is the case in terms of 2D modern methods of construction, and we are increasing the use of this approach very significantly and trying to increase the use of 3D volumetric units. Increasing the use of modern methods of construction is critical. I am always explaining that I grew up in a family of tradespeople and I would have been on sites when I was younger. When we go onto a site now, it is noticeable how clean it is. This is because a lot of the blockwork uses modern methods of construction as well and some are also starting to develop 3D printing.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_245">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_303">I agree with the Minister, but skilled, trained workers are going to be needed in future, and we need to look more to apprenticeships and getting people involved in the trade.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_246" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_304">I could not agree more with the Deputy. I think there was a trend back in the 1990s and 2000s, and certainly when I was going to school, when apprenticeships were not given the respect they deserved. They continued to be given respect in other European countries, but not in Ireland. I think this has been recognised and the skills needed in apprenticeships are extraordinary. That respect for apprenticeships has now returned. It is an amazing career and one that can be taken anywhere in the world if people want to travel. People who do apprenticeships will always have a job and these jobs are impregnable to artificial intelligence. I encourage anyone to take up what is a very good career.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_247">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_305">I thank the Minister and compliment him on the good work he is doing.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ConorSheehan" eId="spk_248">
          <from>Deputy Conor Sheehan<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_306">I want to go back and ask about the one-stage approval process. There is a line in the plan that refers to the one-stage approval process being implemented where appropriate. In this regard, will the Minister outline, insofar as is possible, how many of the total number of developments for social housing going through at the moment are going through the one-stage approval process? What is the average length of time from application to departmental approval with the one-stage approval process?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_249" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_307">I do not have that detail in front of me but I will get it for the Deputy. Some developments will be going through the existing one-stage process and there is the four-stage process. We want to transition local authorities into the one-stage process as quickly as possible because it is the way to maximise delivery. We will be entrusting our local authorities to deliver those homes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ConorSheehan" eId="spk_250">
          <from>Deputy Conor Sheehan<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_308">Will the one-stage approval process be fully implemented by the end of this year?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_251" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_309">I certainly expect that it will be and certainly our aim is to get it implemented by the end of the year. For me, it is absolutely crucial to drive home delivery.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ConorSheehan" eId="spk_252">
          <from>Deputy Conor Sheehan<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_310">Is the Minister proposing anything to address the increasing unaffordability of cost rental and affordable purchase? Is he going to look at the equity share structure or at tweaking the scheme in any way? In my city of Limerick, some of the houses in the affordable purchase schemes are going for prices well over €400,000. For the cost-rental houses, the price is up near €2,000 a month, albeit slightly below the market rate. I am concerned that, with the Residential Tenancies Board, RTB, amendment Bill is coming next year, if rents rise again, the cost-rental model will continue to become more and more unaffordable. How does the Minister propose to address this issue?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_253" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_311">Cost rental varies across the State in terms of what is being charged, but we are keeping it all under review. I want to ensure the affordable schemes are just that: affordable and available for people.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ConorSheehan" eId="spk_254">
          <from>Deputy Conor Sheehan<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_312">Is the Minister concerned about cost-rental rents rising?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_255" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_313">I am always concerned about any rents rising, and that would include where cost-rental costs may be going up. There are cost-rental units available at various rates. The key thing is that it remains at least 25% below the market rate, and this is what we aim to continue to do. Rents are rising; I do not want rents rising. They are rising too fast. The ultimate solution is maximising housing supply and that is what will get rents back down.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ConorSheehan" eId="spk_256">
          <from>Deputy Conor Sheehan<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_314">In relation to the delivery of social housing and turnkey units versus direct delivery, we know the majority of what the Land Development Agency has delivered and the local authorities are delivering has been coming through turnkey units. When will the body of work be complete in relation to the gearing issue that is there for approved housing bodies, AHBs? What measures is the Minister going to take under this housing plan to wean local authorities and approved housing bodies off turnkey units as a mode of delivery? When I talk to people from local authorities and approved housing bodies at the moment, I know it is easier for them to go down the turnkey route because it is significantly less risky.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_257" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_315">It is easier to go down the turnkey route, but I want those bodies doing direct delivery. There are two different types of turnkey approaches. One is forward-funded and the other is actually turnkey, where the houses are built and potentially sold on the private market and a local authority or AHB moves in to purchase them. I am not as concerned about forward-funding, but it is still not ideal. Whether it is local authorities or affordable housing bodies, I prefer them to identify their own sites and to be doing the designing, planning and building themselves. That is where we want to get to. This is why our new affordable housing body strategy is all aimed towards getting to that point too.</p>
          <p eId="para_316">It is going to require a transition. It is not something that can be done-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ConorSheehan" eId="spk_258">
          <from>Deputy Conor Sheehan<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_317">I want to ask another question because I have only ten seconds left. On the fund the Minister is introducing to get families out of long-term homelessness, is he planning to bring forward additional measures to deal with single adults in homelessness? We know they comprise the biggest group of non-movers, so to speak.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_259" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_318">They are. It can be quite challenging for single people. For the moment, my focus is very much on families, including families in emergency accommodation, because the impact of homelessness, although quite severe on everybody, is severe on children in particular. It affects their development.</p>
          <p eId="para_319"> Regarding single people, the challenge has been that there simply have not been enough one-bedroom and even two-bedroom houses built by our local authorities. That should be addressed by the local authorities at the level of planning permissions, and also through county development plans. We are working with the local authorities. We are considering mandating them, if necessary, to build the housing they need in their areas. In Dublin, for example, we have a shortage of four- and five-bedroom houses. We also have a shortage of one-bedroom houses. In many cases for single persons, appropriately sized properties, be they one-bedroom or two-bedroom, are simply not being built. We need more of them. Directing or mandating local authorities is an essential part of that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_260">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_320">I will ask a couple of questions before the next round.</p>
          <p eId="para_321"> Is it possible to have an audit in local authorities to show how many one-bedroom units there are? It seems that two-bedroom houses are being built where there is not a great need for them. I realise there is some need for them but, in the vast majority of cases, two-bedroom houses are occupied by single people or couples. Would it be more cost-effective to deliver more one-bedroom units than two-bedroom units?</p>
          <p eId="para_322"> One of the members made the point that some local authority areas had a scheme to allow downsizing or right-sizing. I am referring to a scheme whereby those in three-bedroom semi-detached houses and whose children have gone, or who may be widowed, could transfer to smaller properties. That would free up family homes. Coming from a rural area, I hear about many elderly people living in three- or four-bedroom houses, maybe out the country, who would love to move into a one- or two-bedroom house in the village. They wish to either sell the family home or leave it to some of the younger generation as a family home.</p>
          <p eId="para_323"> I happened to be over in Brussels yesterday at a European People’s Party event on housing. There is a housing crisis in most countries in Europe although we do not hear about it here, naturally enough. I found it very interesting to see the different ways countries were addressing it. As a committee, we have asked the secretariat to consider, particularly having regard to best practice around Europe, whether we could identify other ways we feel might make a difference. Is there much discussion among ministers for housing of the various EU countries about coming up with alternative ideas that might not obtain here?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_261" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_324">There is. I was in Copenhagen a few weeks ago and met various ministers from across Europe, including the ministers for housing from France, the Netherlands, Slovakia, Slovenia and Denmark. There is now a housing crisis right across Europe. Certain decisions have been made by the EU. Previously, there was no Commissioner for housing and the impact on housing delivery may not have been considered in making decisions. We now have a Commissioner for housing, Dan Jørgensen, and he is publishing his plan on 16 December. We are looking forward to it. We have had an input, as have various ministers for housing across Europe. Housing delivery and infrastructure have very much become an acute Europe-wide problem. I met the French and Dutch ministers for housing to discuss solutions. In many ways, our schemes in Ireland are far more advanced than many in other countries, and countries are seeking to adopt some of them. Addressing this at EU level is crucial, as is very much recognised. I look forward to the publication of the housing plan from the Commissioner.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_262">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_325">I thank the Minister. I am conscious of time and want to allow Senator McCarthy to contribute. Every time he came in, he had to leave for a vote in the Seanad, so I am going to allow him to contribute now.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AubreyMcCarthy" eId="spk_263">
          <from>Senator Aubrey McCarthy<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_326">I thank the Cathaoirleach.</p>
          <p eId="para_327"> I thank the Minister. The reason I am running in and out is because we are voting on the Finance Bill. Without the finance, it will not be possible to build the houses. I appreciate the presence of the Minister and his team today.</p>
          <p eId="para_328"> The Government is committed to building 300,000 homes and eradicating homelessness by 2030. I visited the Houses in 2016 when Simon Coveney was the Minister. I was sort of innocent and these matters were very new to me. It was agreed that homelessness would be eradicated by 2020. We have had a perfect storm, and in this regard the current Minister has said there is a housing crisis across Europe. I presume that with migration and everything added to it, we have a big issue. We are trying to sort it and I am supportive of the Minister in that regard.</p>
          <p eId="para_329"> Regarding the national targets sent to local authorities, is the Minister satisfied that they have been translated at council level? The feedback I am getting is that not many councils have advanced to the Department meaningful numbers regarding rezoning capacity.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_264" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_330">Rezoning is ongoing in local authorities across the country. We have given them a breakdown, under the new national planning framework, of what we need each of them to be able to deliver. Some are moving quite quickly but others are not moving as quickly as I would want them to or as they need to. I will be writing to every local authority this week to remind them of their duty. While the failure to deliver on housing may appear in national figures, it happens if each local authority fails to do what we need it to do. Some are very proactive in delivering social and affordable housing and facilitating private housing delivery, while some may not be.</p>
          <p eId="para_331"> The local authorities are our housing authorities. The Department of housing does not build houses; it delivers houses through our housing authorities, which are our local authorities, and the Land Development Agency and affordable housing bodies, and also by facilitating people to purchase privately. We are working with local authorities to deliver the housing we need.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AubreyMcCarthy" eId="spk_265">
          <from>Senator Aubrey McCarthy<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_332">Is there a way to encourage local authorities that are not increasing capacity and tell them that now is the time and that the clock is ticking?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_266" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_333">Yes. We will be highlighting the local authorities that are delivering. We have brought league tables to the Government and they have been published. We will be publishing more. The best way is for people in a county or local authority area to be able to see what their neighbours are doing and then ask why their own authority is not doing the same. The disparities between some local authorities are quite stark under various headings.</p>
          <p eId="para_334"> The variation is a reserved function of councillors. <b>
						</b>Through the housing plan, we will be incentivising councils, through financial supports, that meet whatever targets we need them to meet.</p>
          <p eId="para_335"> Planning has become complicated. Our local government task force, whose work will be concluding in the new year, is examining how we can re-empower or give additional powers and supports to councillors. On that, we have gone too far in the other way. I want to see the role of councillors strengthened.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AubreyMcCarthy" eId="spk_267">
          <from>Senator Aubrey McCarthy<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_336">Let me refer to one area in which the Minister knows I am involved: homelessness. I am involved with an approved housing body. When I appeared before a joint committee of the Houses of the Oireachtas in 2016, I brought with me a guy who had been given three houses, including apartments, by the State.</p>
          <p eId="para_337">It all went wrong for him. He ended up losing the key, it was boarded up, he burned one, etc. He gave his story here. He had addiction and mental health issues, so without the proper supports, we could be giving him houses for the rest of his life. The plan is to have 12,000 new social homes per year. What portion of those 12,000 will be ring-fenced for people exiting homelessness and people with complex needs? How will the Minister guarantee that local authorities will ring-fence them for those people? If not, we are going to be constantly giving houses to the same people. They need the supports. It all has to work together.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_268" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_338">Absolutely. Senator McCarthy has identified a very important point around homelessness in the sense that we cannot address the issue as if homeless people are a homogenous group. When we go down to a granular level, we have a lot of families becoming homeless as a result of notices to quit, for example, but there are situations where this is legitimately used. We also have people who have addiction or mental health issues and they need supports when they are put into their first homes. In some cases, they do not need extensive supports, but where they do, they can be put in transition homes as well, which means they can leave homelessness and go into safe and secure homes.</p>
          <p eId="para_339"> Another category in this regard is young people who are leaving care. Tusla and the HSE have a vital role to play for individuals who are going through their own trauma, whether it is addiction, mental health issues or leaving care. Supports must be there to help them to go into a secure home and also to sustain them there, which is crucial. I met Cork City Council today on that very point. I asked what more help it needed from us but also from other Departments. We have a meeting of the Cabinet subcommittee on homelessness coming up next week. We will have various Ministers, for example, the Minister for children, the Minister for Health and also the Minister for Social Protection. We will look at how we can ensure that the additional supports that are needed for the cohort of people who are homeless are being provided and are in place.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AubreyMcCarthy" eId="spk_269">
          <from>Senator Aubrey McCarthy<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_340">The Minister mentioned young people coming out of care. Four years ago, I opened a centre in Naas, called Jigginstown Manor, in connection with Kildare County Council. The council really bought into it from day 1. It has been tremendously successful. We had 84 young people through it and we got them into education, apprenticeships, etc.</p>
          <p eId="para_341"> We run the Lighthouse café in Dublin. We have anywhere between 250 to 500 people there every day. If the Minister came in this evening with €500,000, it would not solve the issue for those people unless they had the proper supports. I appreciate the Minister being on the same page.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_270">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_342">I will put ten minutes on the clock for the discussion so we will finish prior to 5.15 p.m. We will let members back in. I am conscious that Deputy Gould did not get a second chance to speak, so I will him in.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasGould" eId="spk_271">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Gould<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_343">Do I have ten minutes?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_272">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_344">No, it is ten minutes in total. I will give the Deputy three minutes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasGould" eId="spk_273">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Gould<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_345">In his briefing, the Minister outlines how there is €100 million in capital funding to help families exit emergency accommodation. How many houses does he think €100 million will buy?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_274" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_346">It will vary depending on the location. If we buy a house in Dublin, it will be considerably more expensive.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasGould" eId="spk_275">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Gould<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_347">How many, on average?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_276" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_348">I do not want to put a figure on it. The €100 million is available and it is being used by, for example, the Dublin Region Homeless Executive, DRHE, and others to ensure that we get the accommodation we need to get people long-term accommodation. I will not get into numbers. It is a complex matrix. The price varies depending on whether it is a house in Cork, Wexford or Dublin.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ThomasGould" eId="spk_277">
          <from>Deputy Thomas Gould<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_349">If we divide €100 million by 31 local authorities and we say that, on average, a house costs €250,000 - but it would be a lot more in Dublin, so I am really going on the low side – that is 13 houses per local authority.</p>
          <p eId="para_350"> I am not sure if I gave the exact figures, so I just want to correct the record in regard to the information we got from Cork City Council last night. Two families were four or more years on the housing list – that is four Christmases - three families were three Christmases on the housing list; 21 were on the list for their second Christmas, and there were another 67. Some 93 families in Cork city are homeless. That is people who have been consecutively homeless; some people go on and off the list. A total of 496 individuals have been consecutively homeless. Other people go in and out of homelessness. The Minister is giving Cork City Council 13 houses and expecting that to help families exit emergency accommodation. He is giving huge tax breaks to developers who are building apartments that are already built or in the process of being built. The developers would not have started to build the apartments unless they were viable. The Government is giving massive tax breaks and then it is giving a drop in the ocean to help people in emergency accommodation.</p>
          <p eId="para_351"> I am reading from page 6 of the Minister's document. The sum of €100 million is nearly like an insult to people who are homeless. The homeless figures have been going up non-stop for ten years and the Minister expects 13 homes per local authority to solve that. I invite the Minister or his Department to estimate how many homes the €100 million will deliver. I reckon the number will be less than what I have outlined.</p>
          <p eId="para_352"> Moving on to page 7 of the briefing, the Minister talks about the derelict sites tax. Why is the levy not starting on 1 January? Local authorities have been collecting information for 35 years. There is a lot of information there now. I know it is not complete, but expecting to wait another year suggests the Minister is letting land hoarders get away. That is wrong.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_278">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_353">The Minister might answer all the questions together. We will give one minute to each member and then the Minister can sum up.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_279">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_354">I will be brief. I spoke to the Minister before about funding for the regeneration of some of our oldest and poorest quality council flat complexes, particularly in Dublin. At the time, the discussion was that the Department was insisting on increased density to release capital funding. My understanding is that that position has now changed but the Department is still insisting that there can be no reduction in density. Given that this is some of the worst rental accommodation in the State, particularly the flat complexes that date from the 1930s, 1940s and 1950s, I appeal to the Minister to state that there should be no density requirement. The homes should be brought up to contemporary standards, and it is fine if additional density can be provided. Does the Minister have an update on the Department's position on these urgent regenerations and, if not, can he provide it by way of writing to the committee before the Christmas recess? There are some in Cork as well but the bulk of them are in inner city Dublin.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_280">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_355">I will focus on the capacity of the construction sector, which Deputy Cooney touched on earlier as well, and modern methods of construction. There is a specific scheme, built to innovate, by Enterprise Ireland. Is it intended that we would look at that scheme and expand it or revise it to try and incentivise greater use of modern methods of construction? The construction sector is very much up for it. It is great that we are showing leadership in the plan as well in regard to social and affordable properties where our aim is to have 25% of them constructed through modern methods of construction. That is important. Is the built to innovate scheme something that is in the Minister's line of sight to try to look at how we can expand it further?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ConorSheehan" eId="spk_281">
          <from>Deputy Conor Sheehan<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_356">I want to ask about the role of the LDA in the new housing plan and what specific additional powers, if any, the Minister is going to grant it in the area of land management in particular to stop it having to negotiate bilaterally with individual State entities?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_282">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_357">If we buy a group of houses that are run down, as happens on all main streets and offshoots of main streets, it is mind-blowing to think how many times the council goes up and down to Dublin to communicate with the Department in order to get the approval to go ahead. Surely, there is a better way to do it. I gave my life as a councillor requesting information year in and year out, not monthly, on how far we have advanced. I wanted to find out where we were and then we could go on to the next step. That is one area where the Minister could get a huge delivery from local authorities. It is not all the fault of the local authorities. For years, as councillors, we identified the sites. For example, we might ask the council to buy two derelict houses.</p>
          <p eId="para_358">It takes between seven and nine years to get two families into those. That is crazy. There should be two families in them within 15 months.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_283">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_359">What other measures can be put in place to make more affordable housing available for young people who are crying out for houses? Unfortunately, they cannot get into the housing market.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_284" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_360">I turn to Deputy Gould's point. As he knows full well, the €100 million is only one measure. It adds to the €50 million this year already. It is only one measure to get people out of homelessness. Cork allocated 722 homes last year. Social housing and void allocation are also critical to getting people out of homeless accommodation. There is also tenant in situ, second-hand acquisitions and HAP. It is only one measure being used. In particular, we find with families who have been in homelessness for a considerable time that there may be particular situations for those families. That is why we have created this fund to provide an additional solution to the many other solutions in place. Last year, we had record exits from homelessness and also record preventions. Huge work is being done by local authorities to prevent families going into homelessness.</p>
          <p eId="para_361"> I turn to other issues. Everything about what I am trying to do is about simplification. I agree with Deputy Aird that we need to speed up our systems. Trusting local authorities is key. That is why I am using the single-stage process as well. Deputy McGrath mentioned modern methods of construction, MMC. We are working with the Minister for Enterprise, Tourism and Employment, Deputy Burke, and Minister for Further and Higher Education, Research Innovation and Science and the Ministers, Deputy Lawless, and their respective Departments to ensure MMC is being used. That innovation model is critical for smaller medium-size developers to be able to adapt the new skills being developed. The technologies being used are crucial.</p>
          <p eId="para_362"> Deputy Sheehan asked about the role of the LDA within the housing plan. The Government has agreed to massively increase the scope of the LDA and its geographical region. We have also secured additional funding for the LDA. I see a big increase in the role of the LDA in coming years.</p>
          <p eId="para_363"> Deputy Cooney spoke about more affordable housing. It is about maximising the different schemes for starter homes to ensure there are no gaps, people have the opportunity to use the affordable measures and homes are delivered through supply, so people get the benefit of them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_285">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_364">Rather than delaying the committee further, can we get a note from the Minister's officials on the current position of the Department with respect to the capital funding for flat complex regeneration of social housing?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_286" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_365">I will do that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_287">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_366">Will that be forwarded to the Deputy or the committee?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_288">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_367">If it is sent to the committee we can all have it. It is better practice.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_289">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_368">I thank the Minister and his officials for assisting the committee. I know we will be seeing some of them again later in the week and next week to discuss this important matter, the housing plan. We will briefly suspend ahead of our discussion of the planning and development regulations 2025.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_7">
          <i>Sitting suspended at 5.14 p.m. and resumed at 5.20 p.m.</i>
        </summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>Planning and Development (Exempted Development (Act of 2000)) Regulations 2025: Discussion<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:20:00+00:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_290">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_369">The Planning and Development (Exempted Development (Act of 2000)) Regulations 2025 have been referred to the committee for consideration. I am pleased to have the opportunity to consider the regulations with the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage, Deputy Browne, and his officials. The opening statement has been circulated to members. Do we have agreement to publish it? That is agreed. I ask the Minister to read out his short opening statement.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage" eId="spk_291">
          <from>Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage (Deputy James Browne)<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_370">I thank the Cathaoirleach for affording me the opportunity to present to him and the committee these proposed planning regulations on behalf of my colleague, the Minister of State, Deputy Cummins.</p>
          <p eId="para_371"> The Planning and Development (Exempted Development (Act of 2000)) Regulations 2025 amend the Planning and Development Regulations 2001, as already amended by the 2001 regulations, by extending until 31 December 2028 the provisions for change of use from commercial to residential in vacant properties under Article 10(6) of the 2001 regulations. This ensures individuals can avail of the exemption without fear of enforcement as the current provision expires on 31 December 2025.</p>
          <p eId="para_372"> I note the context of these regulations was discussed and approved by the committee on 14 October alongside exemptions regarding agriculture. I advise the committee that the agricultural elements have been removed from this version as an environmental assessment is ongoing regarding those proposals and will take a little more time to conclude. It is important these change of use regulations are in place before the end of this year so they are being relaid separately to ensure continuity and that the exemption for change of use from commercial to residential is not allowed to expire. Once complete, the Minister of State, Deputy Cummins, will relay the agricultural regulations before the Oireachtas and will appear before the committee.</p>
          <p eId="para_373"> With regard to the change of use regulations before us today, the Government is committed to measures that support the delivery of housing units. By extending the exemptions for a further three years, it is hoped more people will consider availing of the exemption and change the use of vacant properties from commercial to residential, thereby increasing the number of housing units available in the State within the next three years.</p>
          <p eId="para_374"> The draft regulation is being prepared under the Planning and Development Act 2000, as amended. When new exempted development regulations are made under the Planning and Development Act 2024, the provisions regarding change of use from commercial to residential will be maintained. It is important to note the planning exemptions are removed where works would materially affect an protected structure or an environmental assessment or appropriate assessment is required. Planning permission is required in these instances.</p>
          <p eId="para_375"> I commend the draft regulations to the committee. Having regard to the need to support the delivery of housing, the regulations are intended to give certainty. If, further to today's presentation to the committee, the draft regulations are approved by positive resolution of both Houses of the Oireachtas, as required under the Planning Act, they will come into force as soon as they are signed by the Minister of State, Deputy Cummins.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_292">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_376">The role of the committee in scrutinising exempted development regulations is a really important one. In the long time I have been on this committee, we have always facilitated Ministers and taken a constructive role. These regulations are no different but what has happened with the first module of exempted development regulations is unprecedented in my time in the Oireachtas. I was hoping the Minister might address it. Given its absence from his opening statement, I will ask him to address it.</p>
          <p eId="para_377"> We were given a set of exempted development regulations and there was significant discussion of the environmental impacts of those. I, Deputy McGrath and others raised questions. We were told the environmental assessment was ongoing and we queried that but to facilitate the Minister of State, we then approved the regulations. The Minister of State wrote back to us some weeks later asking us to do something which is not legal. We know that because the committee had to get legal advice on the matter. We were asked to effectively overturn a decision of the Oireachtas that approved the original set of regulations. That should not have happened. I do not understand why it happened and I hope the Minister can provide an explanation.</p>
          <p eId="para_378"> Now the original regulations, which we spend considerable time discussing, have been split and more committee time is being taken up. Given this is the first of a series of modules, the question I have is why the original cluster of regulations was brought to us before the environmental assessment was complete. We now know it should not have been done. The environmental assessment has clearly raised some issues that mean the regulations removed in relation to slurry tanks and animal shelters will have to be amended. Why was the committee asked to do something not in accordance with the rules? The request did not come from the Minister; however, the Minister of State, Deputy Cummins, is one of his junior Ministers. Ultimately, the Minister is responsible for the overall direction of the Department. What guarantee can he give the committee that it will not happen again? I say this as someone who comes to these regulations in a constructive manner. Can the Minister give us an updated timeframe for the further rounds of regulations? They have obviously been delayed in part by this.</p>
          <p eId="para_379"> For a committee to be asked to do something that is not in line with Standing Orders and to have to seek legal advice to clarify that is quite unprecedented. I want an assurance from the Minister that something like that will not happen again, particularly given how important these kinds of regulations are.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_293" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_380">I thank the Deputy. Everyone always intends to do these things in the appropriate manner. I understand there was some difficulty in terms of the regulations and how they were approached. Clarity was sought in relation to the procedure. I assure the Deputy that is never what is intended. Certainly, it will always be intended that appropriate procedures are followed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_294">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_381">Does the Minister accept, in this instance, that was not the case and that is not a good situation for any of us to be in?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_295" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_382">Our intention is always to ensure appropriate procedures are followed. The regulations were relaid because the committee came to a decision. Anything that has happened will form the basis for future approaches to regulations.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_296">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_383">I have two final questions then. Does the Minister think it was a mistake for that first round of regulations to be brought to the committee before the environmental assessment was complete? Can he give us a guarantee that we will not have a repeat of this with the other modules that are coming through and that we will be able to deal with them in an appropriate manner?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_297" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_384">I have no doubt the Minister of State, Deputy Cummins, will be able to address at a future date why he took a particular approach. I cannot get into the Minister of State's mind in relation to it. It is always the intention to ensure that procedure is followed. If a decision is taken that it was not the correct procedure, then obviously everyone will act accordingly.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_298">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_385">You are the senior Minister. They are your juniors. I appreciate you do not control everything they do, but you have oversight of it. Do you think it was appropriate for the regulations to be brought to this committee prior to the completion of the environmental assessment? Can you guarantee the committee will not be put in the position it was put in the last time, that regulations will be brought to us in an appropriate manner and that we will be asked to deal with them in accordance with Standing Orders?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_299" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_386">It always was and will be the intention to bring regulations to the committee in compliance with the appropriate procedures. That is what will always be the intention.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_300">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_387">Where that does not happen, I ask the Minister to undertake to ensure we do not have a repeat of such an instance. In my ten years on the committee, we have dealt with lots of exempted development regulations but have never had regulations presented, then withdrawn, then a request made of the committee to override a decision of the Oireachtas and then had to have repeat sessions of the committee to deal with these at a time when the planning section of the Department is already overstretched.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_301" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_388">I appreciate the committee has a huge workload. I will make every effort to ensure any regulations brought before the committee are in accordance with procedures. If regulations are brought that are not in accordance with procedures, that is not intentional. Every effort is made. The committee has to reach its own decision and we will act accordingly.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_302">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_389">I welcome this extension to the provision for the change of use for vacant properties from commercial to residential. It is important. I have seen at first-hand where vacant properties, whether they are pubs, former pubs, shops or offices, have been converted into residential units and provided good accommodation for individuals and families. It is very important that certainty is given. The extensions of three years is welcome. As we know, the original provision was to come to an end this year. I welcome this measure and thank the Minister and his team for bringing this before the committee. I commend it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_303">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_390">I concur with the Deputy's comments in support of the measure. It is needed. There are certain timelines required because of the end of the year and the agricultural regulations. That is the intention.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_304">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_391">I welcome the extension. I understand there are challenges from a planning perspective as to how this change is affecting the character of our commercial streets in towns and villages and would not be in line with what the planners would consider the proper planning and sustainable development of an area. Could there be some mechanism within the legislation that would allow the planning section of a local authority to apply some brakes to this extension if it was felt to be needed? That might be to ensure that a whole street does not become totally residential without any commercial units.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JamesBrowne" eId="spk_305" as="#Minister_for_Housing,_Local_Government_and_Heritage">
          <from>Deputy James Browne<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_392">There are guidelines for the use of the exemptions. I will take another look at them and ask the Minister of State, Deputy Cummins, to do the same. They should not be allowed where there are conflicts with development plan objectives, so there is a certain amount of scope there for the planners. This is always about balancing the local authority's development plan and ensuring consistency across the country with respect to who can apply and when permission can be granted. Those matters should not be in conflict. We will engage with the local authorities and planners.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_306">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_393">That concludes the discussion of the matter. No other member is indicating. I propose that the committee request the clerk to the committee to inform the Dáil and Seanad accordingly. Is that agreed? Agreed.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_4">
        <heading>Messages to Dáil and Seanad<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:30:00+00:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_307">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-09T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_394">In accordance with Dáil Standing Order 103, the following message will be sent to the Dáil:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_395">The Joint Committee on Housing, Local Government and Heritage has completed its consideration of the following order in draft:</p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_396">Planning and Development (Exempted Development (Act of 2000)) Regulations 2025</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_397">copies of which were laid before Dáil Éireann on 27 November 2025.</p>
          <p eId="para_398"> In accordance with Seanad Standing Order 79, the following message will be sent to the Seanad:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_399">The Joint Committee on Housing, Local Government and Heritage has completed its consideration of the following order in draft:</p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_400">Planning and Development (Exempted Development (Act of 2000)) Regulations 2025</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_401">copies of which were laid before Seanad Éireann on 27 November 2025.</p>
          <p eId="para_402"> I thank the Minister and his officials for assisting us with our consideration of the matter.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_8"> The joint committee went into private session at 5.33 p.m. and adjourned at 5.38 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Tuesday, 16 December 2025.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
