<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#debates">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_social_protection_rural_and_community_development/2025-06-18/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_social_protection_rural_and_community_development/2025-06-18/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-06-18" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#author" href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/34/joint_committee_on_social_protection_rural_and_community_development"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_social_protection_rural_and_community_development/2025-06-18/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_social_protection_rural_and_community_development/2025-06-18/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-06-18" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_social_protection_rural_and_community_development/2025-06-18/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_social_protection_rural_and_community_development/2025-06-18/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-06-20" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#debates">
        <TLCPerson eId="AnneRabbitte" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Anne-Rabbitte.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Anne Rabbitte"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="CatherineArdagh" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Catherine-Ardagh.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Catherine Ardagh"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JohnnyGuirke" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Johnny-Guirke.D.2020-02-08" showAs="Johnny Guirke"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JohnPaulOShea" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/John-Paul-O'Shea.D.2024-11-29" showAs="John Paul O'Shea"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="LouiseOReilly" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Louise-O'Reilly.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Louise O'Reilly"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MarkWall" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Mark-Wall.S.2020-03-30" showAs="Mark Wall"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="NoelODonovan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Noel-O'Donovan.S.2025-01-29" showAs="Noel O'Donovan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PatTheCopeGallagher" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Pat-the-Cope-Gallagher.D.1981-06-30" showAs="Pat the Cope Gallagher"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="SarahOReilly" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Sarah-O'Reilly.S.2025-01-29" showAs="Sarah O'Reilly"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="WilliamAird" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/William-Aird.D.2024-11-29" showAs="William Aird"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/chair" showAs="Chair" eId="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/vice_chairman" showAs="Vice Chairman" eId="Vice_Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/author" showAs="author" eId="author"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/editor" showAs="editor" eId="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>AN COMHCHOISTE UM CHOIMIRCE SHÓISIALACH, FORBAIRT TUAITHE AGUS POBAIL</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>Joint Committee on Social Protection, Rural and Community Development</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2025-06-18">Dé Céadaoin, 18 Meitheamh 2025</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2025-06-18">Wednesday, 18 June 2025</docDate>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_en">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_ga">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">Tháinig an Comhchoiste le chéile ag 09:30 a.m.</summary>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">The Joint Committee met at 09:30 a.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_3">Comhaltaí a bhí i láthair / Members present:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_1">Teachtaí Dála / Deputies</p>
              </th>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_2">Seanadóirí / Senators</p>
              </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#WilliamAird">William Aird</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#ImeldaGoldsboro">Imelda Goldsboro</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#CatherineArdagh">Catherine Ardagh</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#MariaMcCormack">Maria McCormack</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#PatTheCopeGallagher">Pat the Cope Gallagher</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#NoelODonovan">Noel O'Donovan</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_9">
                  <person refersTo="#JohnnyGuirke">Johnny Guirke</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_10">
                  <person refersTo="#SarahOReilly">Sarah O'Reilly</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_11">
                  <person refersTo="#LouiseOReilly">Louise O'Reilly</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_12">
                  <person refersTo="#AnneRabbitte">Anne Rabbitte.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_13">
                  <person refersTo="#MarkWall">Mark Wall.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_4">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#JohnPaulOShea">Teachta / Deputy John Paul O'Shea sa Chathaoir / in the Chair.</person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
        <summary eId="sum_5">
          <i>The joint committee met in private session until 9.52 a.m.</i>
        </summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Social Welfare (Bereaved Partner's Pension) Bill 2025: Free Legal Advice Centres<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T09:50:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_1">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_14">No apologies have been received. Witnesses and members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice that they should not criticise or make charges against any person or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable, or otherwise engage in speech that would be regarded as damaging to the good name of the person or entity. Therefore, if witnesses' statements are potentially defamatory in respect of an identified person or entity, they will be directed to discontinue their remarks. It is imperative that witnesses comply with any such directive I might make.</p>
          <p eId="para_15"> Members attending remotely are reminded of the constitutional requirement that to participate in the meeting, they must be physically present within the confines of the place where Parliament has chosen to sit. I ask any members participating via Microsoft Teams to confirm before contributing that they are on the grounds of the Leinster House complex.</p>
          <p eId="para_16"> I remind all in attendance to ensure their mobile telephones are switched off or in silent mode. Failure to do so may affect the transmission of proceedings.</p>
          <p eId="para_17"> The purpose of today's meeting is to engage in scrutiny, prior to Committee Stage, of the Social Welfare (Bereaved Partner's Pension) Bill 2025. From the Free Legal Advice Centres, FLAC, I welcome Ms Eilis Barry, chief executive, and Mr. Christopher Bowes, policy and public affairs manager. The committee welcomes the opportunity to engage with the witnesses. I acknowledge FLAC's contribution in advocating in respect of the legislation we are discussing. I invite Ms Barry to make her opening remarks.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_2">
          <from> Ms Eilis Barry<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_18">FLAC is very grateful for the opportunity to address the joint committee as part of its consideration of the Social Welfare (Bereaved Partner's Pension) Bill 2025. As members know, it was intended that the Bill would give effect to the Supreme Court's decision in the O'Meara case. We represented John O'Meara and his children in their successful challenge to the legislation that excluded John from access to a widower's contributory pension following the tragic death of the children's mother, Michelle Batey, who was John's partner of more than two decades. The Supreme Court declared that the legislation, which provides for payments to bereaved families only in circumstances where the parents had been married or in a civil partnership, is unconstitutional by reference to the Constitution's guarantee of equality before the law. The Chief Justice found there is "no relevant constitutional distinction between children in a long-standing non-marital unit such as the O'Meara's and those of a comparable family whose parents were married".</p>
          <p eId="para_19"> The Bill will expand the entitlement to social welfare schemes aimed at bereaved partners and families to qualified cohabitants and their children. We very much welcome the Government's implementation of the O'Meara decision through this legislation. In particular, we welcome the inclusion of bereaved cohabitants who do not have children in the expanded scope of the relevant schemes. While not strictly required by the O’Meara judgment, it represents a compassionate and generous response to its findings. The Bill will have a significant positive impact for cohabiting couples and families who, like the O'Meara family, suffer a bereavement and the emotional and financial impact it inevitably entails. </p>
          <p eId="para_20"> Regrettably, the Bill also contains proposals to remove the current entitlement of people who are divorced or separated to a survivor's pension if their former partner dies. Such an entitlement has been in place for almost 20 years. It was introduced after the second divorce referendum in recognition that the death of a divorced or separated partner can bring about a financial loss for families who may have been reliant on maintenance from the deceased. I am old enough to remember the first divorce referendum, which was rejected on the grounds that it failed to properly provide for dependent adults and children. The Bill proposes to water down protections that were introduced subsequently to shore up the protection for those people.</p>
          <p eId="para_21"> We believe there are strong legal, policy and practical rationales for removing the proposals from the Bill to reduce the social welfare entitlements of divorced and separated people. With the greatest respect, we do not accept the various arguments put forward by the Minister for Social Protection and his Department that attempt to justify the changes proposed.</p>
          <p eId="para_22"> First, the changes are not required by the Supreme Court judgment in the O'Meara case and may, in fact, be inconsistent with that judgment. The reduction in the social welfare entitlements of a particularly vulnerable category of lone parents and their children, namely, those who were reliant on maintenance from a former partner who has died, is in no way required by the O'Meara judgment. Indeed, the proposed changes may be inconsistent with the equality and children's rights principles that underpin the landmark judgment. The Bill proposes to treat the children of separated or divorced parents less favourably than children whose parents are married, in a civil partnership or cohabiting. This is despite the fact that in the O'Meara judgment, the Chief Justice placed an emphasis on "the rights of all children, and obligations of their parents, irrespective of the status of their parents". The approach taken in the Bill seeks to achieve equality by levelling down existing levels of entitlement when it is entirely possible to take a more generous and equitable levelling-up approach by expanding entitlement to include divorced and separated cohabitants. </p>
          <p eId="para_23"> Second, the restrictive new conditions will impact on all future applicants for the payments. The proposed changes will mean all future applicants for a survivor’s pension will be required to prove to the Department of Social Protection that they were living with their partner in an intimate and committed relationship in the two years before that partner's death, even where they were married and living in the same house. There is no similar requirement in other areas of social welfare law for married couples to establish that they have been in an intimate and committed relationship. At present, the existence of a marriage or civil partnership is sufficient to establish entitlement to a survivor's pension, subject to the other conditions being satisfied. The new rules require the potentially invasive examination of the nature of a couple's relationship and whether they were living together. This would occur following a bereavement, when respecting the surviving partner's right to privacy and dignity should be of tantamount concern. </p>
          <p eId="para_24"> Third, the numbers of separated and divorced people who require the payment are small. The Irish social welfare system has long been concerned to protect the particular needs of bereaved people and families and has made special provision for them.</p>
          <p eId="para_25">Since the introduction of divorce in the mid-1990s, the social welfare system has provided a safety net for families where the surviving parent is separated or divorced but has not remarried or begun cohabiting with another person. This safety net is still needed now. Lone parents remain one of the groups most at risk of experiencing poverty and disadvantage and we know that most lone parents are women. Separated and divorced people make up a very small fraction of the number of people seeking widow's or widower's contributory pensions. The Department estimates that there are only approximately 100 newly divorced claimants for this payment each year.</p>
          <p eId="para_26"> It is a significant cause for concern that the Department does not seem to have conducted any human rights, equality or anti-poverty impact assessments concerning the proposals. This is despite the fact that the public sector human rights and equality duty puts a mandatory obligation on the Department to have regard for human rights, equality and anti-poverty concerns when it carries out any of its functions, including matters such as the Bill under consideration by this committee.</p>
          <p eId="para_27"> We have drafted a number of amendments to the Bill that we believe would address our concerns about the legislation and ensure that the relevant social welfare payments remain available to bereaved families where the parents were divorced or separated. These amendments, and the rationale behind them, are outlined in detail in our written submission, which we have provided to the joint committee.</p>
          <p eId="para_28"> With the amendments, we are trying to prevent the introduction of new inequalities for families of divorced or separated parents. We believe that our proposals will not arbitrarily exclude any children of any family based on a committed, stable relationship. It is an opportunity to ensure equal treatment of all children irrespective of the status of their parents. It will align the Bill with the Supreme Court judgment. There are only tiny numbers involved; there are no floodgates to fear. It would be a very fitting tribute to John, who at the very worst time in his life and that of his children had to show enormous courage and resilience and take on the might of the State to secure the rights of his children. Let us not introduce a new inequality and subject another family to what John and his family had to go through. </p>
          <p eId="para_29"> My colleague, Mr. Christopher Bowes, FLAC’s policy and public affairs manager who drafted the amendments, and I would be happy to answer any questions that members of the joint committee may have.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_3">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_30">Go raibh maith agat Eilis for your opening statement. I will now invite members to discuss the matter. I remind members participating remotely to use the raised-hand feature and to cancel it when they have spoken. Deputy O'Reilly has asked to speak first because she has another commitment. Is that agreed? Agreed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LouiseOReilly" eId="spk_4">
          <from>Deputy Louise O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_31">I apologise to our witnesses because I will have to leave to speak in the Dáil. If I leave, I can catch up afterwards with the transcript.</p>
          <p eId="para_32"> It is my intention to submit the amendments that have been given to us by FLAC for consideration. We will have a chance on Committee Stage to discuss them in detail and, I hope, discuss them with members of the Department. Like Ms Barry, I am old enough to remember the original divorce referendum and the phrase, "Hello Divorce ... Bye Bye Daddy". I do not think that going backwards is really a good option. This is very decent legislation. It is progressive and good but there is a tiny piece missing that we need to get right.</p>
          <p eId="para_33"> Ms Barry said that the numbers involved were tiny. Will she give us an estimate? We have been asking the Department and it seems to be a fraction of even the people who will qualify.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_5">
          <from> Mr. Christopher Bowes<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_34">The main payment concerned is the contributory version of the widower's pension. At the moment, there are just under 130,000 people in receipt of that. According to figures we have seen in response to a parliamentary question that was answered by the Minister for Social Protection, there are usually approximately 3,000 people recorded as previously having been divorced who are in receipt of the payment. This figure had remained fairly stable over the most recent five years that the Department was able to provide figures for. This indicates that it is probably 2.5% of the people who are in receipt of a widower's or widow's pension. When representatives of the Department appeared before the committee last year to discuss the general scheme of this legislation, they indicated that there were only about 100 fresh applications from people who were divorced for a widower's or widow's pension each year. The figure remains stable and the number being added each year is quite small.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LouiseOReilly" eId="spk_6">
          <from>Deputy Louise O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_35">We are definitely not talking about opening up any floodgates, given that the numbers are so small. I appreciate that there are some difficulties in terms of the date of the judgment and people who would have qualified before, but I do not think it is anything we should not be able to get over. FLAC's amendments address these issues. In the event that the amendments are not successful and the Government votes them down, which I hope is not the case, has FLAC considered any other form of compensation for people who would otherwise not be captured? Would it be appropriate for the committee to discuss whether it would be in order for another form of payment, if the Department is unwilling to grant access to the pension? Would this be out of the question?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_7">
          <from> Mr. Christopher Bowes<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_36">The Deputy is referring to two groups. For people who are divorced and separated and whose former partner died, they are best dealt with by allowing them to remain within the scheme itself. The ideal situation in that case would be those amendments. There is a possibility in that scenario that someone might be entitled to, for example, the one-parent family payment, but because this is a contributory scheme, it is less likely that he or she would be entitled. The best way forward for that group of people would be to keep them in the scheme through the amendments we are proposing.</p>
          <p eId="para_37"> The other group of people are those who may have an entitlement to the payment on the basis of cohabitation that arose before the O'Meara judgment and might may have since ceased. The way the legislation is framed provides that entitlement only arises from the date of the O'Meara judgment in January 2024. There would be no scope for the Minister to use the backdating provisions in the 2005 Act to make regulations that allow for backdating before that point. That is the way the legislation is framed. The committee may consider the pension entitlements of cohabitants that arose before the O'Meara judgment. People may have applied for the payment and been refused or more likely they were told they were not entitled and did not apply for it. Due to the way this legislation is framed, that would have to be dealt with through some sort of <i>ex gratia</i> scheme outside of the scope of the legislation. The way the legislation is framed at the moment provides that entitlement can only arise from the date of the judgment.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LouiseOReilly" eId="spk_8">
          <from>Deputy Louise O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_38">Is it the case that, for the majority group, the preference is that they would be encompassed by the scheme and that would make sense?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_9">
          <from> Mr. Christopher Bowes<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_39">Exactly.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LouiseOReilly" eId="spk_10">
          <from>Deputy Louise O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_40">FLAC has pointed out in its submission that the group we are talking about here are, for obvious reasons, lone parents and, therefore, the group most likely to have children at risk of poverty. I hope that we as a committee can work to strengthen and improve the legislation. I intend to submit those amendments and we will have an opportunity at that stage to have that discussion. I thank Mr. Bowes and Ms Barry for all of their work.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineArdagh" eId="spk_11">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Ardagh<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_41">Regarding the restrictive new conditions that are being imposed by the legislation, is there a precedent for this in other legislation? Is it saying that parties should have exercised their conjugal rights? Is that how far it is going? I am really flabbergasted by that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_12">
          <from> Mr. Christopher Bowes<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_42">It is quite unusual. Usually within the social welfare legislation, a person is deemed to be married on the basis of his or her legal status as being married. That would be accepted and it is certainly the way the widower's pension has operated for more than 20 years now. This is an unusual condition that stipulates that, as well as being married, people have to prove that they are in an intimate and committed relationship. The members of the committee will be aware that, when a person applies for a social welfare payment, the obligation is on the claimant to establish that he or she meets the conditions. This legislation would effectively put in place a system whereby someone who has recently suffered a bereavement - even if he or she was married or living in the same house as the deceased partner - would have to establish to the Department that, in the two years before the partner died, they were living in an intimate and committed relationship.</p>
          <p eId="para_43">There is scope in the legislation for the Minister to create exceptions. For example, where someone was in a hospital for an extended period, they could still be considered as living together for the purpose of the legislation. An exception is carved out in that regard but as a general rule, there will now be an obligation on not just people who are cohabitants but also those who are married or in a civil partnership to meet these requirements and establish that they were not separated but were living together in an intimate and committed relationship at the point of death of their partner to become entitled to this payment. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineArdagh" eId="spk_13">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Ardagh<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_44">Is there anything in the Schedule to the legislation that gives guidance to the Department? It just seems bizarre. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_14">
          <from> Mr. Christopher Bowes<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_45">The legislation allows for the Minister to introduce regulations that provide for how this will be assessed, but it is certainly a new form of investigation and adjudication for the Department to look at the relationship of married people to decide whether it is an intimate and committed relationship. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatTheCopeGallagher" eId="spk_15">
          <from>Deputy Pat the Cope Gallagher<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_46">I thank the witnesses for their presentations on this very important issue of the bereaved partner's pension. Did I understand correctly that the witnesses said this only pertains to the contributory pension rather than the non-contributory? In the past, those who had become widows or widowers, as we knew it then, could apply for non-contributory pension schemes. Can someone in this situation who does not have the contributions apply for a non-contributory scheme?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_16">
          <from> Mr. Christopher Bowes<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_47">There is a non-contributory version of the widow and widower's pension but only approximately 700 people are on this at any given time. It is a much smaller scheme in terms of take-up because it has been overtaken to a significant degree by the one-parent family payment. There are specific rules for entitlement of people who are widowed to the one-parent family payment. Anyone who has dependent children who come within the age range of those payments, for example, would be able to get an increase for a qualified child on the one-parent family payment, which they are not able to get on the non-contributory widow and widower's pension. For that reason, and for the most part when it comes to the non-contributory and social assistance side, people who have a bereavement of a spouse or civil partner will end up on the one-parent family payment rather than the non-contributory version of the widow and widower's pension scheme. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatTheCopeGallagher" eId="spk_17">
          <from>Deputy Pat the Cope Gallagher<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_48">Would it make much of a financial difference if this were to include non-contributory? Has anyone been at a loss as a result of not being included in non-contributory schemes?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_18">
          <from> Mr. Christopher Bowes<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_49">These amendments also apply to the non-contributory version of the scheme. This legislation will entitle people who are qualified cohabitants, if their qualified cohabitant dies, to the non-contributory version of the scheme. As I said, however, if dependent children are involved, the entitlement ends up being the one-parent family payment. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatTheCopeGallagher" eId="spk_19">
          <from>Deputy Pat the Cope Gallagher<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_50">If no children are involved, it is the non-contributory element of the scheme. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_20">
          <from> Mr. Christopher Bowes<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_51">Exactly. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarkWall" eId="spk_21">
          <from>Deputy Mark Wall<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_52">I welcome our guests. It is good to speak with them again after our previous conversation.</p>
          <p eId="para_53"> I have a couple of questions. I apologise for missing the start of the contributions. My first question may have been addressed earlier. How much communication or queries has FLAC had about this pension? We have all had queries, and I have had them from throughout the State. As a body, what kind of questions have been asked of FLAC and how many people have contacted FLAC on this?</p>
          <p eId="para_54"> I have had concern for a while surrounding who qualifies for this and who does not, which has been mentioned and gone through. I queried the Minister on an <i>ex gratia</i> payment and he said he would look at it. Obviously, it will have to be looked at by the Department. Does FLAC have any idea what that payment will look like or what it would like it to look like? How much should that payment be? Are we talking about a contributory pension? It is a concern for many people I deal with who are worried they may not qualify. </p>
          <p eId="para_55"> My final question relates to the regulations the Minister will have if this Bill passes. It is a very progressive Bill, as has been said, and it is welcome and timely. Again, we remember the O'Meara family, who have been involved in this. This question has arisen time and again, but does FLAC have any idea what "intimate and committed" means? In the regulations the Minister will bring forward subsequent to this Bill's passage, what would FLAC like to see as "intimate and committed" and are there timeframes or anything else FLAC would like to see involved there? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_22">
          <from> Mr. Christopher Bowes<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_56">As I think we said the last time, we get regular queries on this. Every couple of weeks or so, we get something new into our telephone information referral line. The question that is currently coming in most often is when this legislation will be enacted. My sense is there is fairly good awareness of this. There should be some take-up scheme undertaken by the Department once these changes are brought in to ensure the new groups captured under the expanded scope of the schemes are made aware of their entitlement, particularly because there will be scope for backdating going back to the date of the O'Meara judgment. People may have significant entitlements to a backdated payment at the stage the legislation is enacted.</p>
          <p eId="para_57"> On the <i>ex gratia</i> scheme, there will be two groups of people. There will be those who became entitled before the date of the O'Meara judgment and the scheme will cover them from the date onwards but they may have had a period before the judgment took effect and, therefore, the scheme will also capture that period. There will also be people who became entitled at some point before the O'Meara judgment and are now no longer entitled for some reason. They may be cohabiting with or married to someone else so their entitlement may have ended. That could be someone who no longer has an ongoing entitlement but who had a period when they could have got the payment and effectively did not or, under O'Meara, would have got the payment but did not because it was not in place at that point. </p>
          <p eId="para_58"> On the shape of that scheme, we will need to look at whether people were able to access other social welfare payments during that time, whether they did access those payments, the number of qualified children and so on. I mentioned in my response to Deputy O'Reilly that if there was a scheme like that, it is important that we would not restrict it to people who had applied for the payment before the O'Meara judgment, even though they were not entitled. As we have said, most people who were cohabiting and lost their former qualified cohabitant partner would have been aware they were not entitled, so may not have applied or may have attempted to apply to the Department or the citizens information office. If they had contacted FLAC, we would have told them that, unfortunately, they were not entitled under the scheme at that point. It is important we would not restrict it in this way were a scheme like that to be put in place. The legislation as drafted only provides for entitlement after the date of the O'Meara judgment, so a scheme like that would have to take place on an administrative basis rather than under regulations relating to the 2005 Act. </p>
          <p eId="para_59"> On intimate and committed relationships, this concept arises in two ways in the 2025 Bill. First, it is for the purpose of establishing whether a person is a qualified cohabitant. In that context, it uses the same definition of qualified cohabitant as that in the 2010 civil partnership and cohabitation legislation. A pre-existing legal definition is already being applied by courts, so we have guidance and precedent for how this can be used. We believe this is a positive aspect of the 2025 Bill. It is assessed by reference to factors such as whether the couple were living together, for how long, whether there is financial interdependence and whether they own assets together. It is quite a high threshold for someone to be considered a qualified cohabitant. The intimate and committed relationship is just one factor. </p>
          <p eId="para_60"> The other side of where this concept arises in the 2025 Bill is for the purpose of establishing whether people who are married or are in a civil partnership, as Deputy Ardagh discussed earlier, are not separated but are in an intimate and committed relationship. When it arises in that context in the legislation, it is a lot more nebulous. It does not mirror the 2010 Act in the same way. It is all left up to ministerial regulations, which we do not have sight of yet. The amendments proposed by FLAC would remove this aspect of the scheme. This will not create a new entitlement for people who are married or are in a civil partnership and are divorced or separated. It just maintains the existing entitlement, which has been there since 1996. As far as we can see, it has given rise to no difficulties in administering the scheme. It has not made it unnecessarily complex and people have been able to access the payment. </p>
          <p eId="para_61">We would very strongly push for the use of this idea of intimate and committed relationships insofar as married and civil partnerships are concerned. We would very strongly push our amendments to remove this new element of the scheme that is being proposed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NoelODonovan" eId="spk_23">
          <from>Senator Noel O'Donovan<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_62">I thank FLAC for being here this morning. Social protection legislation is quite complex and technical. I thank FLAC for its work on ensuring end users get the protections they need. I have just two quick queries. The first is on the nature of the presentation on the removal of the entitlement of divorced and separated people. In the first instance one could say that there may well be reasons for separation and divorce and continuation of funding. One can see why it may well not be. The point was made by witnesses about lone parents and maintenance payments that would have been available. Has the Department given any justification as to why this is in the legislation given that it was not requested in the O'Meara report? Ultimately, we will have the Department officials before us here do the witnesses have any view on that, or what has the Department been saying back to them?</p>
          <p eId="para_63"> My second question is on cohabitation, which is another complex area. There is legislation on property rights and all of that, which is thankfully in place. With regard to the social protection system and the State finances, and I accept that at the stage of bereavement there are emotive concerns at times, there have to be protections to prove cohabitation for two years prior to cohabitation. The witnesses mentioned that the Department will introduce guidelines on that. Has FLAC asked the Department what those guidelines may be at this stage? Would it be beneficial to see those guidelines being drafted as part of this legislation?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_24">
          <from> Mr. Christopher Bowes<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_64">Ms Barry made clear in her presentation that we are quite strong in that we believe these changes are not required by the O'Meara judgment and in fact are inconsistent with it. We do not accept that. The Department has at various times put forward the idea that these changes are to bring the scheme in line with the O'Meara judgment to create greater consistency. The result of the changes it is proposing is that this would create a situation similar to the O'Meara case where one group of families, those where the parents were divorced and separated, are treated differently from cohabiting families, families where the parents were married and families with parents who are in a civil partnership. As the Chief Justice pointed out, no matter the status of the parents, their obligations to their children are still the same. That applies whether the parents are divorced or separated. We believe a situation is being created where another group of families is being arbitrarily excluded. We do not accept the idea being put forward that this is somehow consistent with the O'Meara judgment.</p>
          <p eId="para_65"> Another rationale being put forward for it by the Department-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NoelODonovan" eId="spk_25">
          <from>Senator Noel O'Donovan<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_66">Has FLAC this information in written correspondence from the Department?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_26">
          <from> Mr. Christopher Bowes<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_67">Yes. This has come up in both their appearances before the previous iteration of this committee and in the Minister's statement when the legislation was introduced in the Dáil on Second Stage.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NoelODonovan" eId="spk_27">
          <from>Senator Noel O'Donovan<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_68">Perhaps Mr. Bowes will share that with us. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_28">
          <from> Mr. Christopher Bowes<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_69">We recap all of that in our submission as well. It is in section 2 of the submission, just at the start, but not the opening statement. It is contained in our full written submission.</p>
          <p eId="para_70"> Another idea put forward by the Department officials is that they do not want a scenario where a single death could give rise to two claims for a widow's or widower's pension. It has been the case for more than 20 years that if people die and they are married at the time of their death but they were previously married to someone else, and if their first spouse has not remarried or is not cohabiting with someone else, then that person could have an entitlement to a widow's or widower's pension similar to the spouse at the time of the death. There would be two entitlements but there is no indication that this has created any difficulties in administering the scheme. It seems quite arbitrary to pursue this policy whereby the Department is seeking to have a situation where death can only give rise to one claim.</p>
          <p eId="para_71"> Another issue that has been put forward-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NoelODonovan" eId="spk_29">
          <from>Senator Noel O'Donovan<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_72">Does FLAC have a view as to how we would stop that situation occurring where a previous partner and a current partner were recently bereaved? That is the Department's issue with this. Is there a view from FLAC as to how to get around that situation?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_30">
          <from> Mr. Christopher Bowes<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_73">We would not take issue with it. It may well be that the former spouse might be reliant on maintenance from the person who died, and the children may have been reliant on that maintenance. The spouse at the time of death could also have been reliant on the person. We just view that as a scenario where the scheme is working as it is intended to work to address the gap that has arisen in entitlement or dependence on the person who has died, and in trying to address the need that has arisen as a result of the person's death.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NoelODonovan" eId="spk_31">
          <from>Senator Noel O'Donovan<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_74">I am not saying that paying two previous partners should not be the case but understanding the reasons the Department may have issues with it would be beneficial for us. What number of families may be in that position at present? It would be beneficial if we could get those numbers.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_32">
          <from> Ms Eilis Barry<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_75">We are meeting the Minister tomorrow. He has agreed to meet with us and he may be able to throw further light on his reasons for some of the amendments.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyGuirke" eId="spk_33">
          <from>Deputy Johnny Guirke<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_76">I thank Ms Barry and Mr. Bowes. I have a couple of questions although some may have been asked. How can the two-year cohabitation requirement for a partner to be a qualified cohabitant be justified? What evidence is there to suggest that this duration adequately reflects the emotional and financial independence that may exist in shorter relationships?</p>
          <p eId="para_77"> On the transition period, given that the Bill includes amendments that will affect existing pension recipients, what transitional arrangements will be made for individuals who were previously receiving benefits under the old system.</p>
          <p eId="para_78"> How does the Government plan to fund a bereaved partner's pension and the bereaved parent grant in the long term? What assurances can be provided that benefits will remain sustainable and not subject to cuts in the future? Will there be a regular review mechanism to assess the impact of this Bill on bereaved partners and families? How will the Government incorporate feedback from stakeholders and beneficiaries into future amendments or improvements to this legislation? The Bill is a good step forward.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_34">
          <from> Mr. Christopher Bowes<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_79">That two-year time period is for families with children. It comes from the 2010 civil partnership and cohabitation legislation. This has been in place for a good while. I should point out that it is two years where there are children and five years where there and no children. This is the length of time used in the legislation for effectively establishing that people are in an intimate and committed relationship.</p>
          <p eId="para_80"> On the transition provisions, it is important to highlight that there are what we call "saver clauses" within the legislation. People who are divorced and separated who have been claiming the payment up to now, and up to the point until the 2025 Bill is enacted will maintain their entitlement. There will not be any further new claims from people who are divorced or separated. Those saver clauses would capture those people.</p>
          <p eId="para_81"> With regard to funding in the long term, as I mentioned in reply to Deputy Gallagher earlier, most people claiming these schemes come under the contributory side of the scheme. There is less take up of the non-contributory version. Most of the funding of it would be through the social insurance fund. This is my understanding of where the funding is coming from for the contributory version of this scheme.</p>
          <p eId="para_82"> I agree with the Deputy that the impact of these changes should be reviewed. Our hope is that the amendments will be accepted, existing entitlement will be maintained and separated cohabitants will be brought within the scope of the scheme. This is what our amendments are trying to achieve and instead of bringing it down, to level it up to include those separated cohabitants, and then maintain this existing entitlement that has been there for divorced and separated people. In her opening statement, Ms Barry pointed out that the Department needs to be looking at the potential impact of this now so they are subject to the public sector human rights and equality duty. This brings in a requirement to make sure they are trying to prevent any sort of extreme form of poverty, and that this would be encapsulated within that. We actually want the reviewing and the assessment done now by the Department to make sure that officials fully understand the potential impact of the changes they are proposing. Unfortunately, answers to a number of parliamentary questions that were submitted to the Minister for Social Protection indicate that those sort of assessments have not been undertaken to date. We are looking at engaging further with the Minister and the Department on this.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyGuirke" eId="spk_35">
          <from>Deputy Johnny Guirke<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_83">Will there be a public awareness campaign on this to make people aware of the changes?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_36">
          <from> Mr. Christopher Bowes<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_84">Yes. When the Minister introduced the legislation on Report Stage he mentioned that the Department would seek to make cohabitants who are included in the expanded scope of the scheme aware of this new entitlement they will have under the 2025 Bill. Making sure that people are aware of their legal rights under the social welfare legislation and are able to avail of their entitlements is very important from an access to justice perspective.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_37">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_85">I thank the witnesses for being here. I am encouraged by what I have heard. As a former long-serving county councillor, I thank them for their work and involvement with citizens information. They do an awful lot of good work in that regard. I know that from my years as a councillor. I am glad to have the opportunity to thank them very much for the work they do throughout the country.</p>
          <p eId="para_86"> I welcome the outcome of the O'Meara case. I have been reading into it. Most of the questions I was going to ask have been answered. From where does the requirement to prove you are in a relationship come? Is it from civil servants? Is that where it originated? Are they afraid that something in the Bill is going to cost the State an awful lot more money? It beggars belief that people are being asked to prove something in order to qualify. That makes matters very complicated. As a county councillor over the years, I helped people in circumstances such as these in the context of filling out forms. This is another layer, which is difficult. Are these requirements coming from civil servants? These are the questions I would have loved to ask in all the time I was a councillor, and now I have the opportunity to ask them as a TD. Is this coming from civil servants and are they asking for a reason? Who is flagging this? It certainly did not come about as a result of a Minister seeing something and asking for a change. I need some clarity on that point.</p>
          <p eId="para_87"> All of the other questions I wanted to ask have already been answered. It is encouraging that the O'Meara family did what they did. To prove a point, the matter had to go in direction it did in order for us to be here today discussing it. Perhaps the witnesses would answer my question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_38">
          <from> Mr. Christopher Bowes<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_88">We very much agree that this is going to introduce new complexity to the legislation, which could result in delays and appeals. It could create a barrier to accessing the payment because people must establish that they meet the new criterion for access, which is that they are in an intimate and committed relationship with their husband or wife, or were at the time of his or her death. Our amendments would remove this proposal from the legislation and restore how the legislation has worked over decades, which is that to prove you are married, you must simply demonstrate that you are legally married, which is a more straightforward approach. I do not think there is anything to suggest that has not worked well for as long as the scheme has been in existence.</p>
          <p eId="para_89"> Insofar as where the proposal came from, there is potential here of an overcorrection in light of the O'Meara judgment. As we mentioned, cohabitants will have to establish that they are qualified cohabitants under the definition used in the 2015 legislation. Part of that is establishing that you are in an intimate and committed relationship by reference to other factors, such as the length of the relationship, as we mentioned, and financial interdependence. The issue arising here is that people who are married or in a civil partnership are also being asked to establish they are in an intimate and committed relationship. Looked at one way, that is equality of treatment, but it is an overcorrection. There is a reason that qualified cohabitants must establish they meet those criteria, which is that they cannot show they are married or in a civil partnership by reference to paper records in the same way that people who are married or in civil partnerships can. In our view, it is not necessary at all. It is effectively creating more restrictive conditions for accessing the payment and, as the Deputy said, bureaucratic barriers to accessing it. The situation is difficult. We do not accept in any way that this comes from the O'Meara judgment. Our view is that it should be removed from the legislation, and we have proposed amendments to do that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_39">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_90">May I ask one further question? I know it was sort of asked already but I want to make it clear in my own head. Consider a single parent who has been getting maintenance all his or her life. When the person from whom they have been getting maintenance dies, what is the situation?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_40">
          <from> Mr. Christopher Bowes<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_91">It depends on the relationship with the person who has died. Under the existing legislation, if they were married or in a civil partnership, still are in such a partnership and have separated, or were previously in such a relationship, as long as that lone parent has not remarried, entered a new partnership or begun cohabiting with someone else, when their former partner dies, they become entitled to a widow's or widower's pension. That entitlement, which is under the current legislation, would be removed by the 2025 Bill. People who are divorced and separated from a former partner who has since died would no longer be entitled to the payment. That is the issue we are highlighting.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_41">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_92">They would no longer, under this Bill, be entitled to the payment.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_42">
          <from> Mr. Christopher Bowes<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_93">That is correct. Under the current legislation, cohabitants are not covered. If they had never been married or in a civil partnership but had been qualified cohabitants, they would not, under the current legislation, have an entitlement in the same way as someone who was previously married or in a civil partnership.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SarahOReilly" eId="spk_43">
          <from>Senator Sarah O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_94">I thank Ms Barry and Mr. Bowes for coming. They are very welcome. I say "Well done" on the O'Meara case.</p>
          <p eId="para_95"> I have the same questions as everyone else. On the attempts to remove the pension entitlements from divorced and separated people, what was the rationale in the proposed legislation? Was there any legal basis to it? Is there legislation similar to this in other European countries?</p>
          <p eId="para_96"> My second question relates to the proof that you are in an intimate relationship. What level of proof is required? What are they looking for in those cases? What constitutes proof?</p>
          <p eId="para_97"> There is a matter that nobody else has brought up and that is not covered by the Bill. There is an anomaly in situations where a widow is working and receiving the pension of her deceased partner. If that widow falls ill, she cannot claim illness benefit. That affects some women, especially young widows. I understand the double jeopardy rule but the contributory pension is the result of the deceased spouse's PRSI. The widow who is working and falls ill should be able to claim for illness from their own PRSI. Do the witnesses have any thoughts on that? Have they come across such a situation?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_44">
          <from> Mr. Christopher Bowes<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_98">I will start with the Deputy's question about the rationale for the changes in the 2025 Bill. We touched on a few of them already. I highlight that one rationale which has been raised is that there is an attempt to achieve equality. Because divorced and separated people have the entitlement at the moment, the intention is to add cohabitants. However, the Bill is not adding separated cohabitants. The suggestion is that if separated cohabitants are not added, there is an equality between separated cohabitants and divorced and separated people who are married or in civil partnerships. Our response to that is to put in separated cohabitants. It would not be as complex to adjudicate as one might expect because the threshold is so high to establish that one is a qualified cohabitant and there is a system for assessing it. We think it would be possible to introduce that.</p>
          <p eId="para_99"> On legislation around widow's and widower's pensions in other European countries, and their approach to cohabitation, we might have to come back to the Senator.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SarahOReilly" eId="spk_45">
          <from>Senator Sarah O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_100">Okay.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_46">
          <from> Mr. Christopher Bowes<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_101">I know that different approaches are taken in different jurisdictions. We might come back to the Senator on how those things operate in other places.</p>
          <p eId="para_102"> The illness benefit point is a good one, and we have received queries in that regard to our telephone information and referral line. Senator Rabbitte raised the matter with the Minister last week, and there is an issue.</p>
          <p eId="para_103">As Senator O’Reilly said, there is a general rule against a person claiming two social welfare payments at the same time.</p>
          <p eId="para_104"> The issue regarding illness benefit could be resolved through regulation. The Minister has the power to make exceptions to the general rule with regard to double entitlement and the preference that people get only one payment. The issue that arises regarding illness benefit is that when someone is in receipt a widower's or widow's contributory pension, he or she is able to work and can therefore have two forms of income. However, someone who may be sick or disabled, who may also be entitled to illness benefit is not entitled to the two forms of social welfare income. There is a differentiation in treatment, which raises issues from a disability rights and equality perspective.</p>
          <p eId="para_105"> The rules, legislation and regulations regarding double entitlement are extremely complex. They have been amended heavily over time and the schemes have been consolidated. A piece of work should be done to review the rules on double entitlement to make sure they are consistent and coherent in how people are being treated. They have developed a lot over time. When that happens, there can be irrationalities and inconsistencies in how people are treated. In addition to looking at regulations, that whole area of overlapping entitlements should be reviewed.</p>
          <p eId="para_106"> The rules, legislation and regulations regarding double entitlement are extremely complex. They have been amended heavily over time and the schemes have been consolidated. A piece of work should be done to review these rules on double entitlement to make sure they are consistent and coherent in terms of how people are being treated. They have developed a lot over time. When that happens, there can be irrationalities and inconsistencies in how people are treated. In addition to looking at regulations, that whole area of overlapping entitlements should be reviewed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnneRabbitte" eId="spk_47">
          <from>Senator Anne Rabbitte<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_107">I apologise for being late. I do not see it as a double entitlement. First, as Senator O'Reilly and Mr. Bowes have rightly said in their remarks, a lot of the people who pass away already have contributory entitlements. The widow or widower is actually only claiming off his or her late spouse's entitlement. If a person becomes ill, he or she becomes ill in his or her own right. That is what a person is contributing to in his or her own right. It is not a double entitlement; there has been a loss. The compensation of the loss is covered within the PRSI contribution as a person has contributed all his or her life. A working person is contributing to his or her own entitlement for illness benefit in the event he or she gets sick. It is not a double entitlement at all. They are two separate entitlements to which both persons have contributed in their lifetime while working.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SarahOReilly" eId="spk_48">
          <from>Senator Sarah O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_108">I raise the proof required to prove someone is in an intimate relationship. Do the witnesses know what that entails? I have no idea. What is it that the Department is looking for?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_49">
          <from> Mr. Christopher Bowes<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_109">Insofar as it relates to people who are married or in a civil partnership, it is less clear what the Department is looking for in that scenario because the factors are not set out in the legislation in the same way as they are for cohabitants, but there is a commitment to introduce regulations in that area. I think Deputy Aird mentioned that it would be useful to see those draft regulations as soon as possible.</p>
          <p eId="para_110"> The regulation for qualified cohabitants is more straightforward than the Senator might think. It is usually based on the length of time lived together, whether there are children in the relationship, financial interdependence in the relationship and shared assets. It is possible and has been done for quite a while under the 2010 cohabitation and civil partnership legislation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_50">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_111">There is an overall welcome for this Bill in the House across all parties. It is something that should be welcomed. I thank Ms Barry and Mr. Bowes for their contributions today and for their proposed amendments to the Bill. It is important that members go through the amendments. We got a fair understanding today of some of the amendments that have been put forward for very good reasons. There are significant complexities associated with a few of them and they have to be teased out more. It is good that they will meet the Minister tomorrow and that there is direct engagement with FLAC.</p>
          <p eId="para_112"> I give them a particular thanks to them for bringing this forward and for helping John O'Meara and the O'Meara family. I acknowledge that family as a committee because this Bill would not be before us if not for John O'Meara and the O'Meara family.</p>
          <p eId="para_113"> We have discussed the 2010 qualifying criteria for cohabitants a lot today. Do the witnesses think that legislation or regulation is still to the fore? Could it be updated in terms of those obligations? I assume the Bill will pass at some stage because there is overall support for it, whether the amendments are included. Whenever this Bill is passed, a public awareness campaign should be undertaken to encompass everybody who should have been included in it from the date of the judgment. That would be very important. People who would have applied but were told not to as they did not qualify would be in a position to apply retrospectively. In some cases, people may have received some other social welfare support during that time, which will have to be considered. There needs to be some level of individual circumstances applied as part of this whole application process. Will the witnesses comment on this in terms of the qualifying criteria for the 2010 Act? Are they still happy with how that is reviewed and looked at? Do they have any further comments?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_51">
          <from> Mr. Christopher Bowes<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_114">The system under the 2010 legislation provides that people who meet the threshold of being qualified cohabitants can, after the end of the relationship, apply for maintenance and for provision out of the estate of a deceased qualified cohabitant. It is not the same sort of obligation that a person would have to a spouse if he or she were married or in a civil partnership. It is a lower level of entitlement, but it does address a gap that is there.</p>
          <p eId="para_115"> There are two elements to that legislation, namely, the definition of "qualified cohabitant" and the entitlement people have when they meet the threshold of being a qualified cohabitant. The 2025 Bill complements the provisions in the 2010 legislation because it is an add-on. It is not just an entitlement of one party to another. The social welfare system then steps in and provides for people who meet the threshold of qualified cohabitant. If we were to look at how the 2010 Act is functioning, there are two areas to look at. The first is the definition, of which I certainly have not seen any criticism that people are not able to establish that they meet that threshold. It is quite accessible and people are able to provide the proof. It seems they do meet that threshold. The other area is the level of entitlement or obligation that arises when people satisfy that they meet the definition of "qualified cohabitant". That is something that would be trickier to review, but 15 years on it is worth re-examining.</p>
          <p eId="para_116"> We agree with the Cathaoirleach's point about a take-up scheme. Our hope is, as the 2010 legislation seems to function fairly well in terms of proving cohabitation, that the 2025 Act will function in a similar way and that people who are qualified cohabitants will be able to establish that they will be entitled to what will be called the "bereaved partner's pension".</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_52">
          <from> Ms Eilis Barry<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_117">The Scottish social welfare legislation places an obligation on its Department of social protection to carry out benefit take-up campaigns with regard to all payments. That is something that should be incorporated into Irish legislation, not just in this regard, but to make sure that people are getting what they are entitled to.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_53">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_118">Regarding a date, the legislation allows for payments to be backdated to the date of whenever the judgment was made. Do the FLAC representatives think that this date is satisfactory? Would they like an alternative date?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_54">
          <from> Mr. Christopher Bowes<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_119">That is the date set out in the judgment. As a matter of the requirements of the judgment, legally that date complies with the judgment. The Government is therefore entitled to set it there. Deputy Wall and organisations such as Treoir have brought up that people have been excluded in the past but because the O'Meara judgment was not in place at that time, it meant the definition of "qualified cohabitant" and "provision" were not in the legislation. The legislation does not provide for those people prior to the date of the O'Meara judgment in January 2024. It is something that is definitely worth examining from the Minister's perspective. As we said, the way the legislation is structured at the moment, it would look to us as if it would have to be dealt with through some sort of administrative scheme. I suppose it would be helpful if there were some clarity on what the Department's approach to that whole area will be as the legislation progresses.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_55">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_120">As there are no further questions from members, I thank Ms Barry and Mr. Bowes for contributing to the meeting. We are grateful that they provided their briefing materials in advance of our discussion, which assisted the committee in its deliberations. We will suspend until 11 a.m. to facilitate the exchange of witnesses.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_6">
          <i>Sitting suspended at 10.50 a.m. and resumed at 11 a.m.</i>
        </summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>Effect of Child-related Benefits on Child Poverty and Deprivation: ESRI<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:00:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_56">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_121">Witnesses and members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice that they should not criticise or make charges against any person or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable, or otherwise engage in speech that would be regarded as damaging to the good name of the person or entity. Therefore, if witnesses' statements are potentially defamatory in respect of an identified person or entity, they will be directed to discontinue their remarks. It is imperative that witnesses comply with any such direction I might make.</p>
          <p eId="para_122"> Members attending remotely are reminded of the constitutional requirement that to participate in a public meeting, they must be physically present within the confines of the Leinster House campus. This is due to the constitutional requirement that to participate in a public meeting, members must be physically present within the confines of the place where the Parliament has chosen to sit. In this regard, I ask any members participating remotely online via the MS Teams platform to confirm that they are on the grounds of the Leinster House campus if they wish to contribute to the meeting. I remind all in attendance to ensure their mobile telephones are switched off or in silent mode.</p>
          <p eId="para_123"> I welcome the witnesses from the Economic and Social Research Institute, ESRI: Dr. Karina Doorley, associate research professor; Mr. Bertrand Maître, senior research officer; and Ms Simona Sándorová, research assistant. The committee welcomes the opportunity to engage with them on the ESRI’s output and publications on many areas relevant to its work. The issue we are addressing today is pressing and one that featured prominently at the National Economic Forum on Monday last. I now invite Dr. Doorley to make her opening remarks.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_57">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_124">I thank the Chair for the invitation to appear before the committee. I am joined by my colleagues<b>
						</b>Bertrand Maître and Simona Sándorová. We are grateful for the opportunity to appear before the committee today to discuss our recent report, The Effect of Child-related Benefits on Child Poverty and Deprivation in Ireland.</p>
          <p eId="para_125"> Child poverty is of growing concern in Ireland and internationally due to the growing body of evidence on the detrimental effects of childhood socioeconomic disadvantage on children, both in the short term and the long term, through the loss of education, earnings and health. In Ireland and in many other countries over the past few years, the rate of child poverty has typically been higher than the rates of poverty among other age groups of the population, according to many poverty metrics. Our research aims to understand the effectiveness of current policies and explore potential reforms to further reduce child poverty.</p>
          <p eId="para_126"> Measuring child poverty is complex due to its multidimensional nature. Ireland’s current national poverty target, as defined in the Roadmap for Social Inclusion 2020-2025, is based on the concept of consistent poverty, which combines income poverty and material deprivation to identify the most vulnerable groups in society. Income poverty is measured using the at-risk-of-poverty, AROP, rate: individuals living in a household where the income is lower than 60% of the national median income, adjusted for household size and composition, are considered at risk of poverty. Material deprivation is measured by self-reported answers to survey questions about the household’s ability to afford essentials. People are considered to experience deprivation if they live in a household that cannot afford two or more of the 11 basic deprivation items. Those who are at risk of poverty and materially deprived are considered to be in consistent poverty.</p>
          <p eId="para_127"> The 2025 target consistent poverty rate for the population as a whole is 2% or less. There is currently no specific target for the child consistent poverty rate, though the national policy framework in Better Outcomes, Brighter Futures set a target to lift 70,000 children out of consistent poverty, with a deadline of 2020. The deadline has since been extended to 2025.</p>
          <p eId="para_128"> Using the SWITCH tax-benefit model, we investigated the impact of Ireland’s current system of child-related benefits on child poverty and deprivation. Our findings show that these benefits significantly reduce child poverty rates. Specifically, in-cash child-related benefits reduce the child AROP rate by 10 percentage points, while in-kind child-related benefits reduce the child AROP rate by 1.5 percentage points. Without child-related benefits, child poverty rates would be considerably higher. For instance, we estimate that, for 2025, the child AROP rate would increase from 13.9% to 27%, the child material deprivation rate would increase from 19.5% to 23.3%, and the child consistent poverty rate would rise from 5.6% to 13.6%. These benefits lift approximately 157,000 children out of income poverty, 45,000 out of material deprivation and 94,000 out of consistent poverty.</p>
          <p eId="para_129"> There are a number of ways that policy can tackle child poverty. One such way is increasing the earnings of families with children by reducing barriers to work. Another is the provision of more free services or in-kind child benefits. A third is to increase targeted welfare payments to low-income families with children. Our research focused on the latter channel and we considered several reforms to the tax benefit system that could further reduce child poverty. These include increases to child benefit, child support payments, CSPs, and the working families payment, as well as the introduction of a means-tested second tier of child benefit. Among these, we found the second tier of child benefit to be the most cost-effective reform. This reform would integrate CSPs with a modified working family payment, allowing all households with children to receive an amount determined by their means. For an annual cost of €773 million, it would reduce the child AROP rate by 4.6 percentage points, the child material deprivation rate by 0.7 percentage points and the child consistent poverty rate by 2.1 percentage points. Our analysis suggests any such reform should be designed carefully to avoid income losses for some households. The effects of a second tier of child benefit on work incentives should also be investigated to ensure they do not overly discourage employment.</p>
          <p eId="para_130"> I thank the members for their attention. We will be happy to answer any questions they have.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_58">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_131">I thank Dr. Doorley. Several members have indicated they wish to contribute, the first being Deputy Aird.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_59">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_132">I thank our guests for coming here today. I have put a few questions together that I would like them to endeavour to answer, if they can. How effective are existing child-related benefits at reducing poverty in Ireland? Which specific ones have the greatest impact?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_60">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_133">The research we did investigated the current system of child benefits, both in kind and in cash. We examined anything related to children, not the things specifically targeted at children but those that change depending on the presence and number of children. We investigated the system as a whole, distinguishing only between in-cash benefits and in-kind child benefits. We found that in-cash child benefits have the largest effect, having reduced the AROP rate by 10 percentage points. I am referring to the likes of child benefit, the one-parent family payment and the working family payment – all of those measures that represent an actual cash transfer to households. In-kind benefits, such as free school meals, free schoolbooks, GP visit cards and childcare subsidies, also have a measurable effect on child poverty, reducing the AROP rate by 1.5 percentage points.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_61">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_134">That is grand. Does the report highlight any gaps in current supports, such as for children in one-parent families, migrants or low-income working households?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_62">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_135">It depends on what the Deputy means by a gap. What we identified is that the current system is doing a really good job. It is lifting a considerable proportion of children who would otherwise be poor above the poverty line, but there is still a problem with child poverty. It is not a problem that is specific to Ireland. There are many European and other OECD countries where child poverty rates are higher than the rates among the rest of the population.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_63">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_136">That is lovely. What evidence does the ESRI provide on long-term impacts of increased child benefits and education and health outcomes?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_64">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_137">I do not believe we have anything on the long-term effects for Ireland specifically.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_65">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_138">That is grand. I just wanted to know the effect on young children.</p>
          <p eId="para_139"> How does Ireland compare with other EU countries on spending efficiency and child poverty reduction via social welfare protections?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_66">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_140">We have some work under way on that exact question. It is not finished yet, so I cannot give the Deputy a final answer. We are comparing Ireland’s expenditure with that of all other EU countries. I might have more to say on that in a couple of months.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_67">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_141">What policy changes does the ESRI recommend based on its analysis and what are the fiscal implications of these changes?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_68">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_142">Broadly speaking, there are three ways to reduce child poverty. What we focused on in the report were transfers to the welfare system. That is not to say that is necessarily the best route.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_69">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_143">I understand.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_70">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_144">It all depends on policy objectives. If we are to use the welfare system to target child poverty, the most cost-effective way to do so is through a second-tier child benefit because it is targeted and reaches all children, regardless of whether their parents are receiving welfare or are at work. With regard to cost-effectiveness, that would be a recommendation. That is obviously not the only consideration.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_71">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_145">I thank Dr. Doorley.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarkWall" eId="spk_72">
          <from>Deputy Mark Wall<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_146">I thank the witnesses from the ESRI very much for coming in. Unfortunately, we have to use statistics and percentages even though we are talking about children, and obviously one child in poverty is one child too many. I know the witnesses would accept this point too. Regarding what was put before us today in respect of there being a cost of €773 million for a second tier of child benefit, that is to be means-tested, according to what the witnesses told us, so could they break down that means test for us? Where would it start and finish and how many people would that €773 million assist?</p>
          <p eId="para_147"> Turning to the statutory targets, and I am returning to the statistics, should we have statutory targets here like those that exist in Scotland and other countries? I know the witnesses said they are only looking at other countries now, but a lot of emphasis seems to be being placed on this aspect in other countries now. In Ireland, however, we do not seem to have statutory legislation on child poverty. I would like to get the witnesses' opinions on this point.</p>
          <p eId="para_148"> Going back to the means test, if it was introduced, does the ESRI think there will be a significant reduction in child poverty? I ask this question given it was said that the rate would go from 13.9% to 27% without the existing child benefit. I am again using percentages, unfortunately, but this is what we must use. If the second tier of child benefit was introduced for a cost of €773 million, by what percentage does the ESRI think we could reduce child poverty? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_73">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_149">On the means test, we designed this proposed reform - and it is definitely not the only way it could be designed - by piggybacking on the working family payment. All this means is that we would remove the work requirement from the working family payment. It then becomes a means-tested payment for all families with children. The means-testing itself is exactly the same as what is done in the context of the working family payment. This means a family gets 60% of the difference between their weekly income and the income threshold, and that income threshold depends on how many children they have. That is how we do the means-testing. If a policy like this was introduced, we estimate it would reduce the child-at-risk-of-poverty rate by 4.6 percentage points. This is a fairly sizeable decrease and higher than what we estimate for any of the other proposed reforms that cost the same. </p>
          <p eId="para_150"> On whether we should have statutory targets for child poverty, we are not hitting our targets now. I do not know if having a statutory target in this area would make it more important to hit the target. I do not know what it would depend on, but perhaps Mr. Maître would like to comment.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_74">
          <from> Mr. Bertrand Maître<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_151">The only target, as Dr. Doorley mentioned, is based on lifting a certain number of children out of poverty. I refer to lifting 70,000 children out of consistent poverty from the base that was designed in 2011. There were 111,000 children in that position at the time. This is the only target that exists, but it is not exactly the same as the one that has been designed for the total population, where the target is just to have a rate of consistent poverty of 2% or less by 2025. We have not, however, been going in this direction recently. The latest CSO figures show the rate of consistent poverty for children increased from 5% to 8%. More than 45,000 extra children were in consistent poverty, so we are not going in the required direction.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarkWall" eId="spk_75">
          <from>Deputy Mark Wall<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_152">In the context of the working family payment, it was mentioned – not by the ESRI – that a decision by a government to introduce a second tier of child benefit payment could impact people's ability or desire to go back to work. Has any work been done on this aspect and what the impact might be? I would also like the witnesses to comment on the not trying effect. Obviously, many people do want to get back to work. If a second tier of child benefit were to be introduced, then, how would it impact people's desire to get back to work?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_76">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_153">We have had a look at the work incentive impact of all these reforms. It is not published work but work in progress. I think this is the next step here. When designing a measure to reduce poverty or child poverty, we will always have a tension between providing a safety net that is adequate and incentivising people to work and to take themselves out of poverty. The policy mix chosen in this regard really depends on which is more important. If the overarching goal here is to reduce child poverty at all costs, then maybe we can live with the work incentive effects. These policies do damage work incentives, but there are ways in which you could try to mitigate those impacts, such as changing taper rates or allowing people to keep some of their benefits for a certain time after they go back to work, in the same way as is done for things like medical cards. There is never a perfect solution to something like this, so it is really all about the trade-offs.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MarkWall" eId="spk_77">
          <from>Deputy Mark Wall<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_154">I thank the witnesses.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyGuirke" eId="spk_78">
          <from>Deputy Johnny Guirke<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_155">I thank the witnesses for coming in. How many children in Ireland are in poverty now? How many children would a second tier of child benefit lift out of poverty? What are some examples of in-kind child benefits mentioned in the report and how do they contribute to reducing child poverty? Why do the authors suggest that tracking at-risk-of-poverty rates based on household income, including in-kind benefits, could be beneficial? What long-term effects are associated with childhood poverty, as highlighted by the ESRI? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_79">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_156">The in-kind benefits we looked at were free schoolbooks, free school meals, age-based GP visit cards, medical cards and means-tested GP visit cards, the national childcare scheme subsidies and the free preschool year. I think that is everything. The primary policy goal of those in-kind benefits is not to reduce poverty, but to improve school attendance or bring about better child outcomes or better child health. Those in-kind benefits, though, also have a measurable effect on living standards. This is why we suggested it might be worth keeping track of this aspect. In recent years, the Government has moved more towards the provision of these free services, so it is worth tracking them to see their impact. If we put a lot of money into this area, it is nice to see how it shows up in things like poverty statistics. We would suggest, therefore, that this is something that could be an alternative poverty measure. We already track after housing costs measures of poverty, so this would just be another sort of metric along those lines. I ask Mr. Maître to comment on the number of children in poverty.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_80">
          <from> Mr. Bertrand Maître<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_157">I have those numbers. Based on the latest CSO release, based on the SILC survey for 2024, the poverty rate for children in 2024 was 15%. This is the equivalent of 185,000 children in Ireland being below the poverty line. When we look at the measure of deprivation Dr. Doorley mentioned earlier, namely, a household lacking basic necessities, the deprivation rate for children is just above 21%. This represents 256,000 children in Ireland living in households unable to afford the basic necessities. In terms of consistent poverty - the overlap between being below the poverty line and experiencing basic deprivation - 8.5% of children are living in consistent poverty, or just over 100,000 children. Quite a large number of children are living in those conditions.</p>
          <p eId="para_158"> Also mentioned earlier was the increase between 2023 and 2024 in consistent poverty. The increase saw the total go from 58,000 children to more than 100,000 children. It was a very large increase. We do not know exactly what is behind the increase. We will have to wait to see with next year's survey if this was just a peak and it will have gone down. Additionally, very often there are some people living just above the poverty line who are deprived. If there is any change in their household income, then they fall into consistent poverty. Those households that were just above the poverty line and then fell into consistent poverty could be another aspect of the situation too.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyGuirke" eId="spk_81">
          <from>Deputy Johnny Guirke<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_159">Would the witnesses like to see a situation in the context of child benefit where there was a certain budget that could go a lot further? I refer to a situation where child benefit was means-tested and an awful lot more being available for the people who need it the most. What is the witnesses' opinion in this regard? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_82">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_160">On the subject of universal child benefit, there is a case for it. All means-tested benefits have a take-up issue. This means that if the rules of a particular benefit are opaque or something like that, then there will not be full take up. Not everyone eligible will actually apply for it.</p>
          <p eId="para_161">Sometimes there is as stigma associated with means-tested benefits as well. Households feel like it is not for them or do not want to be claiming that. There is an issue when you means-test something, where not everybody who is entitled to a benefit will take it up. Sometimes the households that do not take it up might be those that are the most vulnerable because the administrative burden for them to apply is quite high and they do not have the capacity. There is still a case for a universal child benefit. One of the things that came out of some research we did over the financial crisis was the fact child benefit is systematically paid to the mother actually reduced the gender discrepancy in how policy affected men and women over time because that child benefit acted as a buffer to women's income. There are a number of reasons why we might want to keep a universal payment and add a means-tested payment. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnneRabbitte" eId="spk_83">
          <from>Senator Anne Rabbitte<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_162">I really welcome this Economic and Social Research Institute report. A bespoke piece of work like this gives us a great understanding and a wider context. At the end of the day, it helps us form policy and a direction when it talks about €773 million, because the budget last year for social protection was about €2.5 billion. I was doing a bit of research to see if there is money in the pot, and that is what has been consistently in the pot. When we look at how the report has been done, income poverty and material deprivation are used as the two measures or the two tools. When we look at the income poverty aspect, the witnesses touched on that relating to the single parent and also talked about the female. In our previous contributions we were talking about widows' pensions. If a widow is receiving a widow's pension they cannot get sick because they cannot have illness benefit or they cannot have a second contribution, that means that family is severely impacted. That heightens our conversations around that. In situations where a parent is disabled, and the associated poverty within that family, how does that impact on the children? One can only guess. Have witnesses broken down the categories that makes up the low-income families?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_84">
          <from> Mr. Bertrand Maître<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_163">Every time we look at the profile of the households who are more likely to experience income poverty or deprivation, we find is always lone parents or households where someone has a disability. For example, as the Senator just mentioned, we can see children living in a household where someone has a disability are much more likely to be at risk of poverty and to experience material deprivation. There is a cost associated with disability which means people might have a certain level of income, but they cannot translate that into a decent standard of living because of that cost of disability. Very often, as the Senator mentioned, it is lone parents, or, for example, people with a disability or people with a lower level of education. Those are really strong predictor factors for experiencing poverty and deprivation. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnneRabbitte" eId="spk_85">
          <from>Senator Anne Rabbitte<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_164">I want to tease that out a little bit further. There is the figure of 195,000 children, and then there is a figure of 100,000 children in consistent poverty. Have the witnesses the data behind that research to say it is X number of families of lone parents that fall into that category? Or, it is X number of families that are in receipt of the disability allowance, for example. The disability allowance is means-tested as well. Do witnesses have those statistics?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_86">
          <from> Mr. Bertrand Maître<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_165">I do not have those numbers but we can extract them. It is possible to do that. To look at the set in terms of composition and the exact profile of family type but also, what kind of income they are in receipt of and so on. It is something that can be done. I do not have any numbers here to provide the Senator with. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_87">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_166">The last piece of work we did on profiling people in poverty found half of children in poverty were either the children of people with a disability or of lone parents. That is the ballpark. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnneRabbitte" eId="spk_88">
          <from>Senator Anne Rabbitte<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_167">Straight away that is an identification as to where we should be, at a very minimum, raising the bar. That is very important and I thank the witnesses for their contributions. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineArdagh" eId="spk_89">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Ardagh<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_168">The statistics and the research the ESRI has done show how important the in-cash child benefit model is. This is a position paper, a research paper. How quickly do witnesses think this can be introduced? Is there draft legislation? I know they have to work with the Minister, but it seems like something we have to prioritise as a matter of urgency.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_90">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_169">The Deputy would have to talk to her colleagues. Our job is to provide the evidence. We have no other role in terms of legislating or anything like that. This is a suggestion. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineArdagh" eId="spk_91">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Ardagh<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_170">People are watching. When we hear discussions in the media around child benefit, people think some of it is going to be taken away from some people. Obviously, there is anxiety around that given the history of the child benefit payment in Ireland. To be clear, the proposition is that the universal child benefit will remain. This is a second, top-up child benefit to those families who really need it. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_92">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_171">Absolutely. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineArdagh" eId="spk_93">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Ardagh<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_172">I am following on from my colleague's question about the profile of recipients. Does the research take into account the urban and rural divide, the age of the children, whether they are lone parents, or if someone in the family or that child has a disability when assessing who is eligible for the second tier?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_94">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_173">The way we have modelled the second tier of child benefit is purely based on income. Implicitly, that will take into account the urban-rural divide but not explicitly. It is purely based on income and based on the number of children, so not on the age of children, either. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LouiseOReilly" eId="spk_95">
          <from>Deputy Louise O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_174">I apologise for not being here at the beginning. I was speaking in the Chamber, but I did read the submission. There is some very interesting information in it. It references the need to reduce the barriers to work. I am sure I am not the only person grossly offended by Simon Harris telling people to just get off their backside and get a job and that will get them out of poverty, which, of course, we know it will not because the rates of in-work poverty are actually increasing. When the report refers to barriers, is it talking about the cliff edge or are there other barriers that we, as a committee, should be aware of?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_96">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_175">There are lots of things we could consider a barrier to work. The ones that we have worked on in the past, and we have evidence they really do hinder peoples' ability to work, are the provision of affordable, available, good-quality childcare and the same for elder care. There are lots of people who are either caring for children or caring for an elderly person or a relative. That is a barrier to them working if they want to do so. Things like joint taxation provides a disincentive for secondary earners to work, meaning, the household's lower earner's potential to work. They typically tends to be women. There are other aspects in the tax and welfare system that could be considered cliff edges and disincentives to work. Those would be a little bit more specific They could be things like the four and seven rule for social welfare payments, and things like that. Things that are fairly straightforward to address and other things that are quite complicated to address. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LouiseOReilly" eId="spk_97">
          <from>Deputy Louise O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_176">There is a range of issues there. The one around childcare is really important because that is a big consideration for people who need to go to work. There is no variability. If you are on a low income or you are a multimillionaire, you are likely paying the same for childcare. There is absolutely no distinction made there. In terms of assessing the at risk of poverty and the levels of poverty, there is an important piece of work. It is not being missed by the witnesses but it is being missed in general, namely, the difference between young children and teenagers. We know the households most at risk of poverty are lone parents with teenagers in the family. How can we isolate that?</p>
          <p eId="para_177">Would it become overly complicated to have a tiered form of additional means-tested child benefit, gradated first? It is an issue everywhere. It is an issue with the school meals programme. Clearly a four-year-old does not eat the same amount as a 16-year-old but they all get the same allowance. I understand that it might be complicated. On the one hand, we have a hungry child but on the other hand we have food waste and there has to be some way to balance that out. Would be possible or would the complications actually turn people off applying? I am aware that people can sometimes get anxious about having to fill out large forms and provide massive amounts of information. It is also right to say that there is a stigma surrounding means-tested benefits in particular. Is it possible or would it just be overly complicated to try to do something like that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_98">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_178">I think it is certainly possible. In the same way that the CSPs are designed for under- and over-12s, something similar could be worked out for a means-tested child benefit payment. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LouiseOReilly" eId="spk_99">
          <from>Deputy Louise O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_179">Does Dr. Doorley think that would be worth doing or is it not as significant a factor? I know the at-risk-of-poverty rates are higher for one-parent households that have teenagers in them but is the difference not enough to warrant the complexity that might be created or would it be worth exploring?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_100">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_180">I have not worked on this topic and I do not think Mr. Maître has either.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_101">
          <from> Mr. Bertrand Maître<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_181">No, I have not but it would be very complicated, depending on the number of in different age groups and so on. It is feasible of course, but I presume it would be very difficult to implement.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LouiseOReilly" eId="spk_102">
          <from>Deputy Louise O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_182">I am conscious that anything that requires a ten-page brochure is not really going to do it at the end of the day. I have read the ESRI report and I have read plenty of others and understand people are in poverty because they do not have enough money and in-cash transfers are really the only way. It is as basic and as simple as that. It is a question for us, as a committee, to consider how best we can achieve that goal. </p>
          <p eId="para_183"> My last question relates to the Government's child poverty strategy. The date on it has been pushed out. We were due to have results by 2020 but the date on it has been pushed out again. On the current track, if nothing changes and we just have Government policy exactly as it is now, are the rates of children in consistent poverty likely to stay the same, get worse or get better? We all envisage and hope that there will be a change in the budget, specifically to tackle child poverty which is something that this and the previous Government have shown themselves not to be massively interested in. If nothing changes, what are we looking at in terms of rates of consistent child poverty?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_103">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_184">We need to get out our crystal ball here. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_104">
          <from> Mr. Bertrand Maître<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_185">We are definitely not going to reach the targets anyway so I presume the Government and the Department of Social Protection are thinking of setting out new targets. The framework, as the Deputy said, was for between 2020 and 2025. We will be at the end of that in six months so I presume the Department is trying to set out a new target for children. We have one for the total population but we are not going in the right direction. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LouiseOReilly" eId="spk_105">
          <from>Deputy Louise O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_186">We are not going in the right direction.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_106">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_187">On my own behalf, I very much welcome the report that was published last week demonstrating that cash in kind benefits significantly reduce child income poverty and deprivation. I am interested in core welfare payments and the need to look at everything in the round, including the hot school meals programme, the free books scheme, free GP care for children under eight, the medical card scheme, the increased funding for a national childcare scheme and so on. How does the ESRI measure the impact of all of those broader programmes on child poverty?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_107">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_188">For the first time last year when we did our post-budget analysis, we included free school books and free school meals. We have always had the national childcare scheme in there, since it was introduced. We have the option to put in the medical card as well, based on our model.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_108">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_189">Was that included?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_109">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_190">We do not tend to include the medical card because there are so many ways to measure the value of a medical card. There is the cost to the State versus the value to the individual. Those are two very different things so we tend to not include that because depending on the option one chooses, it can have vastly different effects.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_110">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_191">Obviously without a medical card, the costs are quite high for a family. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_111">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_192">Yes, the value to a family can be very different from the cost to the State, depending on things like age and the amount of healthcare they actually need. It depends on how we measure it. Whether it is based on cost or value can drastically change the profile so we tend to not put that in as standard. However, the Department of Health does have access to that model and can run its own analysis using that. We tend to put in in-kind benefits that we are confident we are measuring robustly and that make sense in terms of how we value them. Valuing in-kind benefits is complicated but once we are sure that we are doing a good job of valuing them, we do that. Last year we did a five-year profile of the effect of the last five budgets compared with a scenario in which everything had to have kept pace with wage inflation. The free schoolbooks and school meals actually stood out there. They were turning everything from very negative to slightly positive for the lowest income groups and then negative throughout. It is worth measuring and keeping track of that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_112">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_193">One thing that has come back to us regarding the hot school meals programme is the cost savings for a family. The free book scheme has allowed families to have that extra bit of income too. </p>
          <p eId="para_194"> In terms of data from the CSO, often there is a time lag. A lot of the figures released by the CSO did not take into account items introduced in budget 2024, for example, or budget 2025. How does the ESRI take that into account as part of its report?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_113">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_195">Our analysis is based on a simulation for the current year, 2025. We are using the same data that the CSO has but when we put it through our model, it accounts for updates to the tax and welfare systems since then. That is why our simulated poverty rates are different from the most recent ones from the CSO. They are for 2025 rather than 2024 and are simulated rather than being based on actual data. We are simulating the tax and welfare system. The report that we have been discussing is based on a simulation of 2025.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_114">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_196">Finally, on the proposal for a second child benefit scheme, the ordinary child benefit payment is €140 per month, which is €1,600 per year. Added to that is the child support payment, which is €50 for children under 12 and more than €60 for children over 12. How does the ESRI envisage a second tier child benefit payment would fit in with all of those schemes? I refer not just to child benefit itself but the child support payment, working family payment and so on. How would a second payment fit in with those schemes?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_115">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_197">It is complicated because of the number of schemes. If we take things like the carer's allowance and disability allowance, there are different means disregards for those two payments. Adding on another means-tested payment for two families on those two different payments does make things a bit complicated. In some cases, families would lose out.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_116">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_198">Is it too complicated? As Deputy O'Reilly and others have mentioned, if things are too complicated, people will not apply. Often, it is the people who really need to apply who find it too complicated and just do not bother. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_117">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_199">I completely understand that. We estimate that the working family payment at the moment has a take-up rate of just over 50%, which is not great if we are trying to use that as an anti-poverty tool for the working poor. It is complicated to fit something else into the system which is why we piggybacked on something else that was already there. Rather than introducing another payment and trying to fit it in, we just modified an existing payment. We also took out the CSPs when we were modelling this because our idea was that all children should get the same payment, rather than children of families on social welfare getting one thing and children of families in work getting another thing. That is the way we have modelled it but there are, of course, other ways to model it. There are other ways to take into account policy objectives, whether they be really maintaining incentives to work, in which case we might want to keep that distinction between social welfare and work, or something else. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_118">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_200">In terms of the cost, it is estimated to be in excess of €700 million. How did the ESRI come up with that costing? Where does it see the means test sitting? Does the ESRI have a figure in mind for the means test, such as, let us say, anyone with more than €50,000 does not qualify? What is the ESRI suggesting in that regard?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_119">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_201">For the costing our switch model is for the whole population. It is based on representative survey data.</p>
          <p eId="para_202">That allows you to simulate the income distribution, like how many children are in poverty at the moment. Then you can change the rules of the tax-benefit system and apply those changes to the same population and see how things change. That automatically spits out a costing. You have a certain number of families getting a certain percentage more, and grossing that up to the population level gives you the costing €773 million. We did the same for the other policy reforms we modelled.</p>
          <p eId="para_203"> There was a second question about the means-testing. Because it is the same as the working family payment means-testing, there probably is a specific income limit beyond which you would get nothing, but it depends on the number of children you have. For example, a family with eight children has its own income limit in the working family payment means-testing.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_120">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_204">It is good to see that the programme for Government commits to examining this and it is important that this committee would flesh that out in more detail.</p>
          <p eId="para_205"> Do any other members have any comments or questions? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SarahOReilly" eId="spk_121">
          <from>Senator Sarah O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_206">On the point of the poverty rate, or the target, it is set by the Irish Government, in the Department. Is there a European target, or how do we compare? Has the ESRI done comparisons with other countries?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_122">
          <from> Mr. Bertrand Maître<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_207">There is no European target for children. The only target we have in Ireland is to lift a certain number of children out of consistent poverty, not in terms of rates. There is no EU target.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SarahOReilly" eId="spk_123">
          <from>Senator Sarah O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_208">I am interested in the tax-benefit system. Has the ESRI done any work on looking at the potential of tackling tax individualisation? The system penalises one-income families.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_124">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_209">We are looking at that at the moment. We should have a report out this year on it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SarahOReilly" eId="spk_125">
          <from>Senator Sarah O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_210">Has the ESRI engaged with Mary Reader's work? She has published in the <i>Journal of Health Economics</i>. She found that a small child benefit sum paid to mothers during pregnancy resulted in infant health gains. The cost-of-living survey also made interesting points about this and how a drop in income during pregnancy can impact the child poverty rate of other children. Has the ESRI looked into that or done any research on it?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_126">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_211">We have not specifically, no. Something might come out of our European work on this because we are working with a bunch of international partners, and there would be some country-specific studies. There may be something in that, but it is not something I have worked on.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SarahOReilly" eId="spk_127">
          <from>Senator Sarah O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_212">I had a question about the means test as well and how the witnesses would implement that, but they have answered it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_128">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_213">I call Senator Rabbitte.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnneRabbitte" eId="spk_129">
          <from>Senator Anne Rabbitte<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_214">Thank you, a Chathaoirligh, for letting me in for just a quick question. Going back to the figure of 100,000 children, is the €770 million cost solely for the 100,000 children? Is it the cost for the 195,000 children? I am just trying to work out that figure of €770 million. What does it equate to in the number of children?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_130">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_215">The €770 million would lift 55,000 children out of income poverty and 25,000 out of consistent poverty, so it would reduce that 100,000 figure by 25,000.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnneRabbitte" eId="spk_131">
          <from>Senator Anne Rabbitte<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_216">It would cost €770 million. That is an important one for us to know, Chair, as to what we have to benchmark against when we are looking at making submissions to the Minister. That €770 million is to take 25,000 children out of consistent poverty.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_132">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_217">And 50,000 out of income poverty.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_133">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_218">Yes, 55,000 out of income poverty.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnneRabbitte" eId="spk_134">
          <from>Senator Anne Rabbitte<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_219">That income poverty could also be looked at on the means side of things or on disregards because it puts more money, on whatever basis, back into the parents' pockets.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_135">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_220">I have a supplementary question. Has the ESRI done any research on the child support payment or the follow-up on that? Has there been a take-up on that? For example, it was mentioned that the 50% take-up on the working family payment is quite low. Has the ESRI done any research on the child support payment? I know many people might not be aware that there is an additional payment on top of the child benefit payment that could be available to them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_136">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_221">No, I have not done any work on the take-up on that. I would have assumed that it came automatically with the core payment, whatever welfare payment the person was on, but maybe the application is different or more complicated than that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_137">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_222">We might research that ourselves and take it on board on the committee.</p>
          <p eId="para_223"> Are there any other questions or queries?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_138">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_224">May I just ask one simple question? It is a follow-up. I thank the witnesses for answering the questions earlier. When there is no take-up, is there a reason for that? Has the ESRI ever fleshed out the reason?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_139">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_225">There is a lot of literature on this because if money is on the table, you would assume people would apply for it. Stigma is a big reason. Some people do not apply for welfare because they feel like they should not or that welfare is not for them. They do not want to be tarnished by that welfare stigma. It might be complicated. The rules might be complicated. For example, I think the means test for the medical card is different from a lot of other things because you can deduct a lot of your expenses in order to qualify. You can deduct childcare expenses, housing expenses and things like that, and then that is the income that is assessed for eligibility for a medical card. Many people just do not know that so they do not know they are eligible. Finally, the process itself may be arduous. With the old family income supplement, I think you used to have to get a signature from your employer to validate your claim. Maybe some people did not want to go to an employer for a signature or that made it overly complicated. There are a number of reasons. I do not think we have separated out how much of it is due to which reason. We have done some work-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_140">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_226">On the question then, we will go back to the employer. What is Dr. Doorley's opinion on that? Should they have to do that? Should they have to go and personally talk to their employer about what they are doing? I ask for Dr. Doorley's answer on that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_141">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_227">Ideally not, but they do not have to do that any more, which I think has helped.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_142">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_228">They do not have to.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_143">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_229">No.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_144">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_230">That is grand. That answers my question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_145">
          <from> Dr. Karina Doorley<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_231">I think that has helped the take-up.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_146">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_232">If today proves anything, it is that a lot more research is needed to try to see if we can address the issue of child poverty. Certainly, from a social welfare or a social protection point of view, a lot of discussion needs to happen as to how we try to improve these situations. We have the example Deputy Aird just gave of the family income supplement, which is now the working family payment. There is a stigma associated with applying for a lot of these.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SarahOReilly" eId="spk_147">
          <from>Senator Sarah O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_233">It is a matter of information as well, Chair. You mentioned a payment there. What payment were you talking about, may I ask?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_148">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_234">It is the child support payment. It was the qualifying child payment before. Now it is the child support payment, which is, I think, €50 for under-12s and €62 for over-12s. That is in addition to your child benefit, but that is per week.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnneRabbitte" eId="spk_149">
          <from>Senator Anne Rabbitte<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_235">That is only for a person who is in receipt of the widow's or widower's pension.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_150">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_236">Or a number of other-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnneRabbitte" eId="spk_151">
          <from>Senator Anne Rabbitte<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_237">Are there others as well?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_152">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_238">Yes, but I suppose-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SarahOReilly" eId="spk_153">
          <from>Senator Sarah O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_239">More information about that needs to be-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_154">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_240">Disseminated.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SarahOReilly" eId="spk_155">
          <from>Senator Sarah O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_241">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_156">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_242">To be fair to the witnesses-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnneRabbitte" eId="spk_157">
          <from>Senator Anne Rabbitte<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_243">They are doing very well.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_158">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-06-18T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_244">-----there is an awful lot of detail involved in the social protection system. It is good to have the research from them but it is also good to see the continued research.</p>
          <p eId="para_245"> I thank you for your time and your interest in this matter because it is something on which this committee is very anxious to follow up over the coming years to try to make the system more public-friendly, child-friendly and family-friendly. Thank you to Dr. Doorley, Mr. Maître and Ms Sándorová for their contributions today and for providing the various briefing materials in advance for the committee's deliberations. I thank you all. I know you have another commitment at 12 o'clock so I thank you for coming in and taking up our invitation at such short notice last week.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_7"> The joint committee adjourned at 11.48 a.m. <i>sine die</i>.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
