<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#debates">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_and_food/2025-07-02/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_and_food/2025-07-02/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-07-02" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#author" href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/34/joint_committee_on_agriculture_and_food"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_and_food/2025-07-02/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_and_food/2025-07-02/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-07-02" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_and_food/2025-07-02/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_and_food/2025-07-02/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-07-10" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#debates">
        <TLCPerson eId="AindriasMoynihan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Aindrias-Moynihan.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Aindrias Moynihan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="DannyHealyRae" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Danny-Healy-Rae.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Danny Healy-Rae"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="EileenLynch" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Eileen-Lynch.S.2025-01-29" showAs="Eileen Lynch"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ErinMcGreehan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Erin-McGreehan.S.2020-06-29" showAs="Erin McGreehan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JoanneCollins" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Joanne-Collins.S.2025-01-29" showAs="Joanne Collins"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JoeCooney" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Joe-Cooney.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Joe Cooney"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MartinKenny" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Martin-Kenny.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Martin Kenny"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MattieMcGrath" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Mattie-McGrath.D.2007-06-14" showAs="Mattie McGrath"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MichaelFitzmaurice" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Michael-Fitzmaurice.D.2014-10-10" showAs="Michael Fitzmaurice"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ParaicBrady" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paraic-Brady.S.2025-01-29" showAs="Paraic Brady"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaulDaly" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paul-Daly.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Paul Daly"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaulLawless" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paul-Lawless.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Paul Lawless"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="WilliamAird" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/William-Aird.D.2024-11-29" showAs="William Aird"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/chair" showAs="Chair" eId="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/vice_chairman" showAs="Vice Chairman" eId="Vice_Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/author" showAs="author" eId="author"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/editor" showAs="editor" eId="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>AN COMHCHOISTE UM THALMHAÍOCHT AGUS BIA</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>Joint Committee on Agriculture and Food</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2025-07-02">Dé Céadaoin, 02 Iúil 2025</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2025-07-02">Wednesday, 02 July 2025</docDate>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_en">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_ga">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">Tháinig an Comhchoiste le chéile ag 03:30 p.m.</summary>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">The Joint Committee met at 03:30 p.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_3">Comhaltaí a bhí i láthair / Members present:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_1">Teachtaí Dála / Deputies</p>
              </th>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_2">Seanadóirí / Senators</p>
              </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#WilliamAird">William Aird</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#VictorBoyhan">Victor Boyhan</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#JoeCooney">Joe Cooney</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#ParaicBrady">Paraic Brady</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#MichaelFitzmaurice">Michael Fitzmaurice</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#JoanneCollins">Joanne Collins</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_9">
                  <person refersTo="#DannyHealyRae">Danny Healy-Rae</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_10">
                  <person refersTo="#PaulDaly">Paul Daly</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_11">
                  <person refersTo="#MartinKenny">Martin Kenny</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_12">
                  <person refersTo="#EileenLynch">Eileen Lynch.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_13">
                  <person refersTo="#PaulLawless">Paul Lawless</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_14">
                  <person refersTo="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan">Natasha Newsome Drennan.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_4">I láthair / In attendance: Deputies Mattie McGrath and Erin McGreehan.</summary>
          <summary eId="sum_5">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#AindriasMoynihan">Teachta / Deputy Aindrias Moynihan sa Chathaoir / in the Chair.</person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Dog Control and Sheep-Worrying: Discussion<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T15:30:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_1">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T15:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_15">We have received no apologies. Before we begin, I remind witnesses giving evidence from within the parliamentary precincts that they are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to the committee. This means a witness has a full defence in any defamation action in respect of anything said at a committee meeting. However, witnesses are expected not to abuse this privilege and may be directed, at the Chair's discretion, to cease giving evidence on an issue. Witnesses should follow the direction of the Chair in this regard. </p>
          <p eId="para_16"> I remind witnesses of the long-standing parliamentary practice that, so far as is reasonable, no adverse commentary should be made against an identifiable third person or entity. Witnesses who give evidence from a location outside the parliamentary precincts are asked to note that they may not benefit from the same level of immunity from legal proceedings as witnesses giving evidence from within the parliamentary precincts do. They may consider it appropriate to take legal advice in this regard. Privilege against defamation does not apply to the publication by witnesses outside the proceedings of the committee of any matters arising from the proceedings.</p>
          <p eId="para_17"> Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the Houses or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p>
          <p eId="para_18">Parliamentary privilege is considered to apply to the utterances of members participating online in the committee meeting where their participation is from within the parliamentary precincts. Members may not participate online in a public meeting from outside the parliamentary precincts. Any attempt to do so will result in the member having his or her online access removed.</p>
          <p eId="para_19"> Cuirim fáilte roimh na finnéithe go léir inniu. They are very welcome. The committee wants to focus on dog control and sheep worrying. We will hear from representatives of the Irish Natura and Hill Farmers Association, INHFA: Mr. John Joe Fitzgerald and Mr. Pheilim Molloy. Cuirim fáilte rompu. From the Irish Creamery Milk Suppliers Association, ICMSA: Mr. Michael O'Connell and Mr. Brian Delaney. Cuirim fáilte rompu. From the Irish Farmers' Association, IFA: Mr. Adrian Gallagher and Mr. Tomás Bourke. They are welcome. Cuirim fáilte rompu. From the Irish Cattle and Sheep Farmers' Association, ICSFA: Mr. Hugh Farrell and Mr. Willie Shaw. They are welcome here today. From the National Association of Regional Games Councils, NAFGC: Mr. Dan Curley and Mr. John Butler. They are very welcome.</p>
          <p eId="para_20"> We will start with the INFHA, followed by the ICMSA, the IFA, the ICFSA and the NARGC. The witnesses have provided opening statements. I take it that members have had an opportunity to read through the statements. I will give the witnesses two minutes to synopsise their statements and then we will go to members to ensure we have the maximum amount of time available for questions and answers.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_2">
          <from> Mr. John Joe Fitzgerald<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_21">Go raibh míle maith agat, a Chathaoirligh, as an seans a thabhairt dúinn teacht agus labhairt. Thank you, Chair, for giving us this opportunity. The Irish Natura and Hill Farmers Association welcomes the opportunity to highlight concerns farmers have about dog control and to outline clear solutions. This is an ongoing issue for our members, as detailed in a number of member surveys we have held over the last three years. In addition to these surveys, we have been inundated with calls from farmers about the risk to their livestock following attacks from dogs and the stress caused by dogs that are not controlled. We have seen increasing levels of concern and complaints from farmers about recreational walkers bringing their dogs onto farmlands, including our hills. When asked to remove them, the walkers become highly abusive and threatening, which in some instances has led to physical violence. As a result, the INHFA in Kerry has put together a petition and has submitted it to the European Parliament with the ambition of having this issue addressed and stamped out, both in Ireland and across Europe. A copy of this petition has been sent to the clerk of the committee and we understand all members have received it. The petition, which includes a book of evidence on dog attacks and farmer feedback, outlines a number of proposals that, if followed, will deliver much better outcomes in dog control and, by extension, reduce and, I hope, eliminate dog attacks on sheep and other livestock.</p>
          <p eId="para_22"> A summary of what we are advocating is as follows: a national database collating all information on dogs, including dog licence, microchipping and DNA samples from each dog; a Government-funded, time-limited subsidy for DNA sampling-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_3">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_23">I thank Mr. Fitzgerald. The submission has been circulated. We want to keep things moving.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_4">
          <from> Mr. John Joe Fitzgerald<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_24">I will keep it short. I will move to the conclusion.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_5">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_25">I must move on to the next witness.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_6">
          <from> Mr. John Joe Fitzgerald<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_26">I am sorry, a Chathaoirligh.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_7">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_27">The statement has been circulated and members have had the opportunity to read it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_8">
          <from> Mr. John Joe Fitzgerald<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_28">That is fine.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_9">
          <from> Mr. Michael O'Connell<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_29">I thank the Chair for the opportunity to address the Joint Oireachtas Committee on Agriculture and Food. Dog control is a major issue at the moment for livestock farmers, sheep and cattle. We believe a similar initiative is required to the awareness campaign that was launched in 2024. The ICMSA believes that a number of areas should be highlighted in such a campaign. I refer to the damage done to sheep and other stock. There is an economic effect due to the cost of it. There is also a psychological effect on the farmers involved. The repercussions should be made known to dog owners as to what will happen if their dogs are found to have worried or killed sheep.</p>
          <p eId="para_30"> It is important that all dogs be microchipped and licensed and that this be enforced. Without microchipping, there is no traceability, which, in fairness, is a major issue.</p>
          <p eId="para_31"> The impact on farmers should not be underestimated. It is traumatic on any farmer to see that his or her animals have been attacked by dogs. The committee should be mindful of that as well.</p>
          <p eId="para_32"> The enforcement of dog controls must be rigid and swift. In recent months, we have seen in media outlets coverage of the legislation banning XL bullies. There is a way around it and the loopholes must be closed. The powers of dog wardens need to be reviewed. Will they come in under the Department of agriculture and be supervised by it? That is more or less a synopsis of what we have proposed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_10">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_33">Gabhaim buíochas le Mr. O'Connell.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_11">
          <from> Mr. Adrian Gallagher<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_34">I thank the committee very much for the invitation. More than any other sector, sheep farmers are affected by the irresponsible behaviour of some dog owners. As chair of the IFA sheep committee, I hear more and more stories about irresponsible incidents involving dog attacks, livestock worrying and, at times, the aggressive behaviour of dog owners. Lack of enforcement of obligations on dog owners and low levels of sanction in this area are allowing this behaviour to continue, with sheep farmers having their flocks savaged by dogs on an almost daily basis at this point.</p>
          <p eId="para_35"> We also do not hear often enough about the emotional and long-standing consequences dog attacks have on farmers, farm families and the remaining flock, most particularly where multiple incidents occur, which is not all that rare.</p>
          <p eId="para_36"> Lack of meaningful action in this area has led us to taking the step of introducing a campaign whereby we do not allow any dogs on our lands. The campaign, which is now in its fifth year, is an attempt to protect the health and welfare of our animals. This must stop.</p>
          <p eId="para_37"> Under the Animal Health and Welfare Act 2013, owners and persons responsible for protected animals are legally obliged to prevent unnecessary suffering and to safeguard their welfare. This includes providing adequate food, water, shelter and veterinary care. Offences such as cruelty, abandonment, neglect, poisoning and illegal procedures carry severe penalties of up to €250,000 in fines and-or five years' imprisonment. Courts may also disqualify offenders from keeping animals. These types of sanction must also extend to cases where dogs have been found worrying or savaging sheep.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_12">
          <from> Mr. Willie Shaw<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_38">I thank the committee for the opportunity to talk to it today. I agree with previous speakers. It is basically the same thing that we are all after here today, that is, stronger controls for dogs and more traceability for the dogs that are doing the harm. It is a very small percentage of dog owners who let their dogs do what they like. Unfortunately, it only takes a few percent. Thousands of sheep are killed every year in Ireland. Millions of euro worth of livestock is destroyed. An awful lot of sheep farmers are leaving the sector and we do not need yet another reason for them to leave. We appreciate that legislation is to be introduced but there must be backup financially and in terms of dog wardens and even something as simple as microchipping.</p>
          <p eId="para_39">When that dog is sold again as an adult it needs to be registered with its new owner. The microchip registration cannot go back to its old owner. Small common-sense measures like these could make a huge difference.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_13">
          <from> Mr. John Butler<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_40">Dog control and sheep worrying are issues the National Association of Regional Game Councils, NARGC, takes very seriously. We have a large cohort of dog ownership in the country, with more than 25,000 members who have an average of two to three dogs each. They are game hunting dogs and by their very nature they are highly trained to find, flush and retrieve game. As part of this training, we try to ensure, and we do ensure, the animals do not interact or interfere with domestic animals such as cattle and sheep. We have many expert trainers in our association and we take pride in how our dogs perform.</p>
          <p eId="para_41"> Having said this, we acknowledge and accept there is a problem and we want to be part of the solution. We are willing to help the farming community and landowners. We do so and we have done so in the past. Some of the measures we strongly support have been alluded to by other speakers. We feel strongly there should be a database of all dog ownership in Ireland. When we look at the fact that we know where every cow, calf and sheep is in Ireland, we should also know where every dog is in Ireland.</p>
          <p eId="para_42"> The old saying is that there are very few bad dogs out there but there are an awful lot of bad owners. We believe the responsibility for dogs being off a lead or out of action solely lies with the owner. This is where the buck should stop. It is where a database would come into its own. It, along with microchipping, would mean we know precisely who is at fault, the nature of the animal and the owner.</p>
          <p eId="para_43"> I ask that legislation be considered on the point that while a landowner is allowed to dispatch a dog worrying sheep, sometimes they may not have the facility to do so. They should be able to call on a local gun club member or a local licenceholder to do it on their behalf. We would like to see this acknowledged as part of the legislation and included as part and parcel of it. We are here to help and we will do so in any way we can.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_14">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_44">I thank all of the witnesses for giving us concise presentations. Their documents have been circulated. We want to have as much discussion as we can on this. The documents, including the photographs, were circulated earlier and anyone involved in any way with sheep farming will, unfortunately, be all too familiar with the violence and damage done by dogs on sheep. If there are ways to progress the situation let us try to get onto them as quickly as we can.</p>
          <p eId="para_45"> Seven members are offering to speak. I suggest that each person has four minutes and if there is an opportunity afterwards, we can have another round of questions. Our first speaker will be Deputy Martin Kenny.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_15">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_46">Is it four minutes for questions and answers?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_16">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_47">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_17">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_48">I thank the Cathaoirleach and all of the witnesses for coming before the committee and for their opening statements. There is a single trend through all of this, which is traceability. It is about who owns a dog, where the dog is and how it can be traced and followed up. There are issues with neighbours' pets that escape and get out. It could be a dog that gets out and damages sheep. There are also people who go walking in the country for recreation and who jump out of the car, open the boot and let the dog out with no lead. Away they go as if it is free and open countryside. It may be free and open countryside but if there are domestic animals in the fields nearby they are in danger. They may not always be attacked and ravaged by a dog as they may be just run. If pregnant ewes are chased around a field there will be miscarriages and big losses. This may not be as evident as it is where animals are attacked. We have seen some of the graphic pictures that have been sent in and we are all conscious of this.</p>
          <p eId="para_49"> Today, if we can, we need to focus on what can be done. A trend running through this meeting is discussion of a national database, microchipping and licences. Do the witnesses feel, as I do, that there are not enough resources for the dog wardens? Half of them do not have wands to read the chips even if they do come across a dog, and there are not enough of them in place to ensure it is followed up on. I have come across situations where people have been contacted and it is three days later before someone comes from the local authority to speak to them about what happened. I would like to get the views of the witnesses on this and what level of additional resources they think is needed to police the somewhat inadequate legislation that exists at present. I will throw this open, perhaps to the INHFA first as they were the first to present.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_18">
          <from> Mr. Pheilim Molloy<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_50">On the issue of dogs being let run wild, we must remember that a farm is a place of work for the farmer. Under health and safety legislation, farmers are responsible for their own safety. This is a very important point to remember. With regard to resources, they are scarce on the ground and there is no doubt that the powers the dog wardens and An Garda Síochána have is a problem. If we look at the Control of Dogs Act 1986, a garda or a dog warden is prohibited from following a dog into a residential premises. This is in the legislation. This is an area that seriously needs to be addressed. There is an issue with the number of dog wardens and the powers these officers enjoy. Unless this is addressed we will not make any progress on this problem.</p>
          <p eId="para_51"> Unfortunately, I can relate a situation whereby I spent two hours in the company of a farmer in west Donegal one night whose stress and anxiety were displayed because he had 30 sheep killed. The dog was chased back to a premises but because of the provision in the legislation nobody could go in. The fear was that the dog would repeat the attack on a later date. This is where a big problem exists. I have seven or eight points on the Control of Dogs Act 1986, which has great weaknesses and this is only one example. If I get an opportunity at a later stage I will cover more of them. This is something that needs to be addressed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_19">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_52">If Mr. Molloy wishes he can send in the seven or eight points to the clerk to the committee and they will be considered.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_20">
          <from> Mr. Pheilim Molloy<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_53">I thank the Cathaoirleach.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_21">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_54">Four minutes is a very short time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_22">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_55">It is tight. We may have an opportunity afterwards for more questions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_23">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_56">Perhaps the other witnesses can speak about the issue of resources for local authorities at other points during the meeting.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_24">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_57">I thank Deputy Kenny for his co-operation. We are trying to cram a lot into a short time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DannyHealyRae" eId="spk_25">
          <from>Deputy Danny Healy-Rae<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_58">I am very glad to have an opportunity to speak on this highly emotive issue. I welcome each and every one of the organisations before the committee. Their members are very welcome. As a unit the committee, under our very able Cathaoirleach, promises to do our best for them. I was upset one morning when I heard people saying no one in Ireland was listening to them and that they would go to Europe. By all means they can go to Europe but we are, and have been, listening to them. We have been out in the fields where the damage has been done. We know what is involved and what happens when little lambs and sheep are torn and mangled. We know all of this. We support most of what the witnesses have said. There should be microchipping. I am worried about how the DNA sampling would work. As Mr. Molloy has said, we cannot go into houses.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_26">
          <from> Mr. John Joe Fitzgerald<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_59">The biggest problem we see with microchipping and dog licences is that when the farmer gets to the field there is no trace of the dog.</p>
          <p eId="para_60">That is the biggest problem I hear from every farmer in the country. DNA sampling is a very easy system. It is either a swab, a blood sample or a skin nick. If it is a viable sample we put it back into the database. When a kill happens after that and if the farmer gets to the field the dog is gone he can test the saliva on the tears and cuts on the dead or torn animal and go back to the database and find the dog's owner.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DannyHealyRae" eId="spk_27">
          <from>Deputy Danny Healy-Rae<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_61">I must save my time because-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_28">
          <from> Mr. Willie Shaw<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_62">Apologies Deputy, but approximately 50% of dog attacks are not actually kills, the dogs are running the sheep. What kills the sheep is only around 10% of the problem. The problem is sheep being run, pregnant ewes especially. The DNA does not work in that case but it is a help. Everything is a help but DNA is not the silver bullet.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DannyHealyRae" eId="spk_29">
          <from>Deputy Danny Healy-Rae<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_63">All right, my understanding is that either the farmer himself or someone on his behalf can shoot a dog on his property. Is that right?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_30">
          <from> Mr. John Joe Fitzgerald<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_64">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_31">
          <from> Mr. Willie Shaw<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_65">Yes. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DannyHealyRae" eId="spk_32">
          <from>Deputy Danny Healy-Rae<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_66">That is very important and this is the only way I believe we can teach these fellas a lesson. Framers should have cameras up as well. I know it costs farmers money to do this but if a farmer is lambing sheep he should have cameras up. As Dan Michael Muldoon once said, shoot at sight. We know that when these dogs taste blood at all they are never satisfied until they go back for more. It is not about chasing sheep it is about the taste of blood. We will raise what we can for the witnesses through parliamentary questions and in different ways and we appreciate their horror at what is happening. It is happening all around me, in Kilgarvan, Kenmare, Sneem and any place that a dog can meet you in the flesh, it has happened. It is a very serious issue and we are very concerned about it. We are glad the witnesses came to the committee. I know all of the members have different ideas but I believe that with the walkways and all of these things coming on stream now, sheep will be more exposed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_33">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_67">Go raibh maith agat, a Theachta.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DannyHealyRae" eId="spk_34">
          <from>Deputy Danny Healy-Rae<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_68">So farmers need to assure themselves they can shoot dogs on their property and that should be maintained.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_35">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_69">Gabhaim buíochas leis an Teachta. Bíonn scrios ar fad á dhéanamh ag gadhair in áiteanna. Bíonn an-bhaol do chaoirigh. An bhfuil céim amháin faoi leith gur féidir a thógáil chun dul i ngleic leis an bhfadhb? An bhfuil aon chéim amháin faoi leith a bheadh an-chabhrach? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_36">
          <from> Mr. John Joe Fitzgerald<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_70">Is í an chéim amháin a mholaim ná database nó ionad sonraí a chur le chéile a thiocfadh faoi bhráid an Aire talmhaíochta agus na Roinne talmhaíochta. Ní mór ceadúnas madraí a bheith ag daoine. Ní mór ceann amháin de na cinn seo a leanas a bheith ag daoine: dog licence, microchipping nó sampla DNA. Caithfidh na cinn seo ar fad a bheith faoi bhráid an Aire talmhaíochta agus na Roinne talmhaíochta. Caithfidh duine éigin a bheith freagrach as seo nó commissioner a thabhairt isteach le gur féidir le daoine dul chuige i gcónaí. D’oibreodh sé sin go maith. Roimhe seo, bhí beirt Aire ag déileáil le cúnamh madraí le blianta fada. Bhí duine amháin ag rá rud amháin le duine amháin agus rud eile le duine eile agus é ag imeacht ar fud na háite. Ní mór é sin a bheith faoi bhráid Roinne amháin. D’oibreodh sé sin go maith. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_37">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_71">Gabhaim buíochas as sin. Leanfaidh muid ar aghaidh leis an gcéad duine eile, is é sin an Seanadóir Paul Daly. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_38">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_72">Go raibh maith agat, Cathaoirleach. I know time is limited but that exchange reminded me of an uncle of mine who was training a sheepdog one time and it was not going well. The reason he gave for his lack of success was the dog had come from the Gaeltacht and did not understand him.</p>
          <p eId="para_73"> The witnesses are all very welcome and I think we are all on the one side of the fence on this one. We will have to follow this meeting up with the other side of the fence, which is the Department and the people who have the power to make changes. Today is about the committee becoming armed with the information to go to that meeting. I had a couple of people who were meant to attend today and unfortunately they could not. They have done a lot to highlight this issue and they are Eamonn and Niamh Monahan from Iniskeen, Monaghan. They will appear on "Crimecall" to get the message out to a different audience that would not usually watch this. We would all watch "Ear to the Ground" if this issue was featured on it but the whole country watches the likes of "Crimecall" and I do not think enough can be done to highlight the issue to the public because they are the dog owners. The big issue here, the problem, is dog owners. As was mentioned already it is not savagery but the number of people out there who say their dog is only a little poodle and is the loveliest dog in the world and would not do a bit of harm, he would run after a ball, a stick and a sheep. It is the worrying and chasing of ewes that are heavily in lamb. It does not have to be savagery. There is some savagery but the chase can do every bit as much damage with lambs being thrown and all of that. </p>
          <p eId="para_74"> There needs to be more highlighting of the issues as Eamonn and Niamh have done so that the public and not just the farming community see it. Your heart would go out to them. They have a pedigree Texel herd and do not know when they go to bed any night what they will wake up to the next morning. It is completely out of their control. There is a body of work to be done. I compliment the people who are working on this issue. </p>
          <p eId="para_75"> Another colleague of mine, Councillor Fionnán Fitzgerald, informed me that Kerry has done a map of reported dog attacks. Every county should do that and we as politicians should encourage all local authorities to do that because when one sees a map and list of how many attacks there are, there are a lot more than one would imagine. I am a firm believer and have been hammering the drum for a long time that the owner of any breed of dog should not be allowed to chip a dog or get a licence without doing a theory test. Anybody can have a dog and he or she might not have a clue about the consequence of having a dog. There should be a theory test before a person is allowed to own a dog and that is something I will keep pushing for. </p>
          <p eId="para_76"> I do not have any questions because we received the witnesses' documentation. I have a minute and a half remaining, if anyone would like to comment. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_39">
          <from> Mr. Hugh Farrell<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_77">I thank the Senator for his questions. He remarked on the good work being done by the people in question, and rightly so. The Senator referred to the map of each county. That is a brainwave, in fairness, because if that issue was identified on a map of the counties and put out to the local media, including local papers, it would leave everyone who owns a dog wondering and worrying if their dog was part of it or could be part of it. This could send a bigger message than we think it could, bigger than us just discussing it here today. I would like to see that followed through as a national study of reports that come in and are formed in that way and the maps are distributed throughout the counties. I thank the Senator for his input. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_40">
          <from> Mr. Tomás Bourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_78">I will comment on a number of the points made by members. They question has been asked, what can the committee do? The key to all of this is we do not need to reinvent the wheel to a large extent. Five years ago we commenced a no dogs allowed campaign. To be brutally honest, the only way we can ensure the safety and well-being of our animals on the hills is if dogs are prohibited from being taken on to hills. It does not matter, Deputy Kenny, how many dog wardens we have, we cannot police that. That is why the IFA's position is that all hills should be a no-go area for dogs because hills are frequented by livestock and it cannot be guaranteed those dogs will be retained under effective control when their owners go up hills. That is something simple and straightforward that can be done immediately.</p>
          <p eId="para_79"> The centralised database has to be the bedrock this is built on but we do not need a lot of new legislation. We have an Animal Health and Welfare Act 2013 and in that Act, Part 3, section 12 that deals with animal welfare clearly sets out what the criteria and sanctions are if someone is found to impact on the health and welfare of a protected species. Dogs and sheep are protected animals. We have a situation where if a farmer is found to be non-compliant with that, he or she is prohibited from owning animals in the future. We need an amendment to this Act to recognise that the dog owner is no longer allowed to own a dog if he or she has been found to be non-compliant with responsibilities and that recognises the trauma and severity of the welfare and psychological impact on the farmer their dog has caused. We do not need to reinvent the wheel but to amend what we already have.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_41">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_80">I thank Mr. Bourke but we need to move on. Senator Brady is next.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_42">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_81">I thank all the associations here. Last weekend, I made a request for them to attend, especially the NARGC. To make it known, I am a member of the NARGC and keep hunting dogs at home. Everybody is responsible for their own dog, just to make that clear. Every dog is a pet until the pets get together and then become killing machines. Unfortunately, I keep sheep as well. I have some questions that someone can maybe answer. Physical violence to any landowner is unacceptable. Most people condemn it at all costs.</p>
          <p eId="para_82">Have we any figures on the cost to farmers of sheep-worrying and the loss of sheep last year?</p>
          <p eId="para_83"> On dog wardens, how many prosecutions have there been over the last 12 months by local authorities? Have we figures on that?</p>
          <p eId="para_84"> Anybody who is eligible to carry a firearm is licensed to protect his or her own property or livestock but I do not know whether the legislation allows a farmer to bring someone who has a licence onto his or her land, if there has been sheep-worrying, to shoot a dog. I am not sure whether the legislation is strong enough. Maybe the witnesses would like to comment on that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_43">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_85">I would like to give the witnesses a chance to answer a few of the questions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_44">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_86">Yes. Whoever wants to take them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_45">
          <from> Mr. Dan Curley<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_87">I will take the one about firearms. It is our understanding that it is only the owner who could do it. The owner could not invite a gun club member to do it. The law only says the owner. That may be something this committee could look at and possibly change. It would allow the farmer to get a gun club member down the road who may have a far more powerful rifle. The member may shoot deer or foxes and would have the necessary equipment to do it far better. The average farmer might only have a shotgun, with which someone would have to get within 30 or 40 yards of a dog to dispatch it. It would only be a small amendment but it could be an important one.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_46">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_88">Yes. What would Mr. Curley say in regard to the other questions?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_47">
          <from> Mr. Pheilim Molloy<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_89">On the amount of compensation that would be paid, I will mention the 1986 Act, and section 21(1), which is around the burden of proof that is placed on the farmer with regard to damage done to his or her stock. There is a burden of proof there. That is another area of the legislation that needs to be looked at. If a farmer decides to bring a court case, there is a huge burden of proof placed on that farmer. In a lot of cases, there would be a reluctance on the part of the farmer because of costs and so on that would be logged against him or her.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_48">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_90">Has anybody a costing of what it cost farmers last year in general, and how many prosecutions were there?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_49">
          <from> Mr. John Joe Fitzgerald<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_91">The cost must be gone into the millions of euro.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_50">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_92">Before we finish up, an area no one has touched on yet is that of the illegal hunting of hares and rabbits, or coursing, from a certain cohort of people who go in on land-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_51">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_93">We will stick with the sheep, Senator.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_52">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_94">The illegal coursing is the problem because people are going onto lands where there are sheep and worrying them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_53">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_95">Our business here is to deal with sheep-worrying.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_54">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_96">It is sheep-worrying.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_55">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_97">Let us stick with it. We need to move on.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_56">
          <from> Mr. Hugh Farrell<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_98">I want to come back in on the cost. There may be figures there for it but the real figure is unknown, with the amount of animals that have been damaged, left with stillbirths or whatever else comes along with it. It would be multiples of it. I do not know how we would get a real figure on it because it would not be reported to the level we would love it to be.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_57">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_99">We have five more speakers offering, so there should be opportunity for people to get another go at it in a little while. Deputy Lawless is next.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_58">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_100">I welcome all the farm organisations and thank them for attending. This matter is one of the key priorities for me with respect to the work programme. That is because I recently attended, with some of the witnesses, a public meeting in Roundfort in south Mayo. Following the meeting, I walked the fields belonging to some farmers who had been terrorised by what was happening. This is happening in south and north Mayo. It is important that this committee recognise that, in pockets of the country, a huge part of this problem is down to illegal hare coursing, where groups of people are travelling-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_59">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_101">Deputy,-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_60">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_102">No, a Chathaoirligh, we cannot talk about-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_61">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_103">-----it is important that we focus on the business of the meeting with regard to sheep.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_62">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_104">I want to be very clear. It is absolutely relevant to talk about one of the key issues in my constituency that is-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_63">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_105">Deputy, the business of the meeting relates to sheep-worrying. There are so many other things we would love to talk about but the business of the meeting regards sheep-worrying.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_64">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_106">My point is that there is an issue around illegal hare coursing in the country. It has a knock-on effect where groups of people are coming onto farmers' lands and letting their dogs off. This is a huge issue in south and north Mayo and I want to register it here in the committee. We need to do a significant amount of work on this and if we cannot talk about some of the key issues on it-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_65">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_107">Our focus today - and we can take the other issue on another day - is on sheep. We can follow up with the other issues another day if the meeting-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_66">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_108">The focus of the committee is on sheep and the perpetrators, which are dogs.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_67">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_109">Deputy, the business of today's meeting is sheep-worrying. If there are other issues the committee needs to look at, it can choose to do that another day but today, our business regards sheep.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_68">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_110">It is very relevant. I want to move on because my time is going.</p>
          <p eId="para_111"> I want to work with the farm organisations on this. There are major issues around the legislation from 1986. It is very weak, as was alluded to. It is resulting in a lack of prosecutions. That is the reality. The other factor is not only do we have very weak and loose legislation that is vague and one of the reasons there is such a lack of prosecutions, particularly around the sheep-worrying offence, but we also have a lack of enforcement. In Mayo, for example, there are just three dog wardens to cover the entire county. When we have breakouts of hare coursing in north and south Mayo, it is a major challenge.</p>
          <p eId="para_112"> The other point I want this committee to focus on is providing An Garda Síochána with the equipment to manage this problem. It is shocking that the Garda in Mayo does not have the ability to scan with respect to microchipping. I understand that scanners were sent by the Department to the Garda across the country some years ago and some gardaí in stations were unfortunately unable to use them because that was not sanctioned by the justice Minister and senior management within An Garda Síochána.</p>
          <p eId="para_113"> Addressing these major issues will have a big, positive impact. The reality is that there are people losing pedigree flocks overnight as a result of this issue and we need to address it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_69">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_114">Can anyone comment in the brief time that is there?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_70">
          <from> Mr. Hugh Farrell<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_115">I have one line or two. I understand where the Deputy is coming from with regard to the hunting. I was a victim of that. There were dogs in hunting, plus quad bikes, and we lost a lot of lambs over it. It is simple as that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_71">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_116">I need to move on. Senator Lynch is next.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EileenLynch" eId="spk_72">
          <from>Senator Eileen Lynch<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_117">I thank all the organisations for their briefings. It has been very informative. I did not realise the number of non-microchipped pet dogs there was in the country. With regard to my background, I keep greyhounds. It is an incredibly regulated sport. We have to microchip our dogs if we want to register them and if we want them to compete. It is incredibly lax that the same does not apply to pet owners. We sometimes have a case here where we are putting pets ahead of agricultural animals. I do no think that is good enough because, as has been said by Senator Daly, people should have some kind of training or test in order to have a dog. I have dogs. Do I know what they are up to every night? Absolutely not.</p>
          <p eId="para_118"> Something that I do not think has been raised by any of the groups today is the issue of dog insurance. We have insurance for our dogs for any damage they carry out. I appreciate there is a burden of proof in terms of proving whose dog is inflicting the damage. Do the witnesses think insurance for dog damage is an area we need to be focusing on? Hunting paths and greyhound owners have it. It is not a thing that is, to me, as prominent with actual pet owners and I think that is an issue we need to focus on.</p>
          <p eId="para_119"> My second point - I know it has been raised by the previous two speakers, and I am not trying to take away from the meeting - is that looking at the books of evidence and the photos from the INHFA, I find it hard to believe that all those attacks are carried out by pet dogs. I know, at the end of the day, a dog is a dog and a dog can turn. Do the witnesses think there is a higher proportion of these attacks coming from illegal hunting groups? I am not specifying what kind.</p>
          <p eId="para_120">Hunting groups and coursing groups are going through land with the landowner's permission. Without the landowner's permission, those sports cannot continue. Is it the case that groups of people illegally going through lands are causing a higher proportion of the damage? I appreciate a dog can turn on a person in a second. I am well aware of that and have experience of it. Whether it is a poodle or a bulldog, anything is possible. As I said, I find it hard to believe that more of these attacks are by pet as opposed to illegally held or illegally owned dogs.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_73">
          <from> Mr. Hugh Farrell<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_121">The Senator hit a good point. As far as insurance goes, I feel our dogs would be covered as a hazard under public liability. The point on the other end is access to hunting. Maybe we should look at that. There needs to be consent for people to come in to hunt on the land or to be on the farm, whether it is walking or hunting. Maybe that needs to be looked at to could control a lot of what we are discussing today. It is something I would like to see brought forward.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_74">
          <from> Mr. John Joe Fitzgerald<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_122">It is not all coming from pet dogs. Let us be exact about that. It is happening in all of society and among all types of dogs. To give the Senator a good example of it, Deputy Danny Healy-Rae lives down in the Sneem area. I visited a farmer there two years ago. More than 100 of his ewes and lambs were driven off the cliff by marauding dogs that were let loose from holiday homes. When people come out of towns and cities and go to these places, they think it is like the Wild West or an old cowboy film. I have spoken to another man in Galway who had the same thing happen to him on 8 December. He called me at 10 p.m. and told me his sheep had been driven off the cliff. They are in the book of evidence. I advise every member to look at the graphic photos in the book of evidence. If they think those are bad, I will supply them with even worse ones.</p>
          <p eId="para_123"> At the end of the day, there is no accountability. Nobody is taking responsibility. The reason we had to go to Europe with this petition is that nobody is listening. I have heard at this meeting that everyone is listening, but I have been told by one good politician in Kerry that nobody is listening because there are no votes in it for us. It is as simple as that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_75">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_124">I know there are-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DannyHealyRae" eId="spk_76">
          <from>Deputy Danny Healy-Rae<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_125">I have to stand up for myself. I am listening to Mr. Fitzgerald anyway, and I have always been doing my best about it. He can name the rest of them, but he cannot name me anyway.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ErinMcGreehan" eId="spk_77">
          <from>Deputy Erin McGreehan<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_126">Likewise.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_78">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_127">I am listening. It is not about votes. I was a farmer before I was a politician. I am listening and I will be.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_79">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_128">Based on the intensity with which members have raised this issue in recent meetings, I can say they are fairly keen on and interested in it. I support members in that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_80">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_129">Solutions are what we want. I propose that the committee does a report on this problem to give to the Department of agriculture.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_81">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_130">I second that proposal.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_82">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_131">Will the members and witnesses tell me if they do not disagree with something? We need to take note of what we will do and include it in a report. Does anyone object to the recommendation for dog DNA collection to be included in the report? Agreed. Is it agreed that we recommend all dogs in Ireland be microchipped? Agreed. Is it agreed that if a dog goes wild, as Mr. Bourke said earlier, that a person will not own a dog again? Agreed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_83">
          <from> Mr. Pheilim Molloy<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_132">Can we broaden that out a wee bit? That is fine as a statement, but how will that be incorporated into legislation if we do not have the personnel on the ground to actually monitor-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_84">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_133">Hold on.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_85">
          <from> Mr. Pheilim Molloy<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_134">-----that non-compliance?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_86">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_135">Just one second. We know that not everyone who goes around stealing will be caught by gardaí. The same goes for dog wardens. There will not be a dog warden up every road in Ireland. What we need is a DNA test and all the tools to identify something and have the databases for it. That is the best we can do. We will not have a dog warden in Mr. Molloy's place, my place and every other place flying around to get this sorted.</p>
          <p eId="para_136"> A good point was brought up earlier. Is it agreed that, in the event that a farmer does not have a gun licence, with the consent of the farmer or the landowner, a person who owns a gun licence would be allowed to use it? Is it agreed to include this in the report? Agreed.</p>
          <p eId="para_137"> If a person trespasses - a person or dog - a farmer has the right to shoot the dog. Is it agreed to include that? Agreed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_87">
          <from> Mr. Hugh Farrell<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_138">Any dog off a lead on its own.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_88">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_139">Provided the farmer has a licence. These are things we need to put into a report if we are going to try to change things. All databases and equipment should be a joined-up measure between the Department of justice and the Department of agriculture and the whole lot should be together in the event of dogs doing harm. Is there anything else that should be included in that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_89">
          <from> Mr. Tomás Bourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_140">I thank Deputy Fitzmaurice. He has, to a large extent, identified some of the key issues. The key area in enforcement is that the deterrent has to be awareness of the significance of the sanctions. I welcome the Deputy's proposal with regard to preventing any future ownership of a person found to not be meeting their legal obligation to maintain their dog under their effective control. We must also look at extending the sanctions for what damage they cause on farms with regard to potential custodial sentences and significant fines. We can achieve that.</p>
          <p eId="para_141"> The issues of enforcement and clarity about the roles of An Garda Síochána, authorised officers or dog wardens have come up. The Animal Health and Welfare Act 2013 clearly defines roles and responsibilities. We need to include in the report the recommendation that the worrying of livestock and savaging of sheep be included in this Act and the sanctions within the legislation should apply. That gives the correct authorities to An Garda Síochána-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_90">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_142">Will Mr. Bourke send his submission to us?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_91">
          <from> Mr. Tomás Bourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_143">I will, of course.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_92">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_144">Will Mr. Fitzgerald be quick?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_93">
          <from> Mr. John Joe Fitzgerald<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_145">Just a quick point-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_94">
          <from> Mr. Tomás Bourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_146">There is one point I want to finish on because I did not get in earlier.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_95">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_147">We will give Mr. Curley a chance to speak.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_96">
          <from> Mr. Dan Curley<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_148">No, I am okay.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_97">
          <from> Mr. John Joe Fitzgerald<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_149">Roaming patrols in tourist hotspots would help out the west of Ireland in dealing with dogs on hills.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_98">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_150">I ask Mr. Fitzgerald to send in his submission. Mr. Bourke may make whatever other points he wishes to make.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_99">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_151">I ask members and witnesses to bear with me. If witnesses want to answer questions and there is not enough time, they should write down the answers and send them to the secretariat. They will be sent to members-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_100">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_152">Did the Cathaoirleach take note that Senator Daly seconded a proposal that we do on a report on this?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_101">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_153">That is agreed. Do members have any views on doing a report?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_102">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_154">I fully support Deputy Fitzmaurice's suggestion to do a report.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_103">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_155">We will take the opportunity to follow up on that. Two standing members are offering and a non-member has written in and asked to contribute. She has asked to go. At the discretion of the committee, I call Deputy McGreehan.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ErinMcGreehan" eId="spk_104">
          <from>Deputy Erin McGreehan<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_156">I thank the Cathaoirleach and Deputy Aird for his indulgence and for allowing me to speak. I do not have any questions. This is something I am very passionate about.</p>
          <p eId="para_157"> I brought forward a Bill in the previous Seanad that encompasses an awful lot of the stuff the witnesses want and need. It beggars belief, day in and day out, to hear of the ignorance of people who traipse around with their dogs in the countryside like they have a free pass and allow their dogs to roam and attack sheep, whether by mouth or by running. The bad manners of people in society are appalling. The support here is absolutely necessary. I hope this committee can bring the Department's officials before it because they know what the issues are. They have been told what they are. Many Members in this room, including me, have raised the issues and what needs to be done over and over. This is a serious issue. Thousands of euro have been lost. The mental health of farmers and their families has been affected.</p>
          <p eId="para_158">People cannot go to bed at night without worrying about their sheep and livestock. It is about time the Minister, the Department and the officials started listening to farmers, the committees and the farming organisations and acted on it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_105">
          <from> Mr. Tomás Bourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_159">There is one point I wish to add to Deputy Fitzmaurice’s proposals. It is timely and can happen immediately. We need to announce a ban on all dogs on all hills and commonage grounds because it cannot be policed. We are now at the height of the period when people and walkers walk through our lands and bring dogs with them. We have our campaign. Farmers are having their signs torn down and are being abused. The violence has been referenced already. We need to ban dogs from hills because those are where livestock are kept. It cannot be policed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_106">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_160">I have one other question and I know-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_107">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_161">There will be another opportunity. Bear with me. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_108">
          <from> Mr. Hugh Farrell<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_162">One thing that must be remembered, and which seems to have been missed all the way, is that this is private property. Everyone else is treating it as their property. We have to change that. This is where consent to enter and different things need to be looked at. That ties into what Mr. Bourke said because it is on all land.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_109">
          <from> Mr. John Joe Fitzgerald<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_163">Education and awareness in schools are another issue. Niamh Monahan and AgriKids have been mentioned. They are doing great work to educate the youth, from primary school level up to secondary school level. If that happens and is encouraged by the Government, hopefully those small kids will grow up to be responsible dog owners in years to come. That will help everyone.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_110">
          <from> Mr. John Butler<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_164">I wish to make an observation. When we speak about going onto land, we need to be aware that there are two types of people, namely, those people who go onto land with permission and then those who trespass. It is those who trespass that we need to highlight. Hunting has been mentioned once or twice today as part of the problem. I am not saying that was intentional. It is illegal hunting that is part of the problem. Hunting, by its very nature, is done with the permission of the landowner. Hunters gain access to the land with the permission of landowners. </p>
          <p eId="para_165"> The other thing mentioned was insurance.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_111">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_166">I ask Mr. Butler to be brief because I need to move on to Deputy Aird.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_112">
          <from> Mr. John Butler<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_167">Insurance was mentioned. Our association, since its inception, has a solid, sound compensation fund package for all landowners who are members if they fall foul to an unfortunate accident. We have never failed to look after our landowners in that respect.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_113">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_168">I thank all the witnesses who have come in. I am delighted to be here. One good thing that has happened, on which I have campaigned for more than 40 years as a member of Laois County Council, is that the control of dogs be handed over to the Department of agriculture. That has happened now for the first time, although it should have always been the case. It should have been the case for horses too, but I will leave that matter aside. We have teeth now. We can bring in the Minister for agriculture, Deputy Heydon. We can get on to the Department of agriculture to establish new rules for all dog owners and get a path forward.</p>
          <p eId="para_169"> I maintain that no dog should be around without being microchipped. Every person has a responsibility in that regard. The Department of agriculture will have a dedicated budget, whereas the local authorities were operating on a shoestring. From that point of view, dog wardens will have all the equipment to just stop a person and seize a dog. All the wardens must do is run the yoke along the dog and if it does not give a whistle, that means there is no tag and the dog must be taken away. People will know that quickly.</p>
          <p eId="para_170"> On dog worrying, my view is that no dog should be let off a lead. That has to be provided for in legislation. We can do that in this country. We do not have to go to Europe; we can have our own set of rules. No one is allowed should be let a dog off a lead. There is a difference where farmers give permission for gun clubs to go in to shoot. You will see that up at farms throughout the country. That is a completely different thing. Those people have permission. There are other places where no one is allowed. You will see that in places as well. No matter what happens, no dog should be allowed off a lead. It does not matter whether someone is coming down from Dublin for a week out or coming from wherever, no dog should be allowed off a lead. If we had that in legislation, at least we would be moving forward in some way.</p>
          <p eId="para_171"> While I agree with everything Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice said, there is one thing I wish to say. I live right in the middle of a town. I certainly would not encourage anyone to go out to confront three or four people in their field this evening with four or five dogs to tell them to get out or to pull out a gun and shoot them. Who would come out the worst of that? It would be the farmer. We saw what happened in Dublin when that poor man went over and asked the people to keep their dogs on a leash and to go out to the ditch because he had sheep next door. Look what happened to him. We have a lot of work to do to ensure people respect the person who confronts them as the owner of the land. I am serious in that regard. I am telling the committee here and now that I would not encourage any farmer to confront these people. There is a difference in the people out there. That was alluded to today. There is the person who lets their dog off and the dog gets away from them and runs at the sheep. A dog will run at anything that moves, from the smallest to the biggest dog. </p>
          <p eId="para_172"> We have an awful lot of work to do. We have it now in the right place in the Department of agriculture. Deputy Fitzmaurice is here a lot longer here than I am. I promise that real changes will now be seen because we are in a position to do so. We have this matter under one umbrella, namely, the Department of agriculture. We were all members of a local authority at some stage. The local authorities all had different rules and regulations. Now, however, we will have one guiding path forward for dealing with this. We have a lot of work to do before people will be able to go out to ensure no one is on their land with dogs. That is all I can say.</p>
          <p eId="para_173"> This matter is so urgent that we should be addressing it with the same urgency as we address TB. I honestly believe that. Farmers have left the industry because of dogs, which is natural enough. What farmer tonight could go to bed with 100 sheep lambing out in the field without the worry of it? You could do not do it because there are too many dogs running wild. We politicians are always on the roads late at night coming and going from meetings. How many times do we pass two dogs going at it on a rural road? Every time I go to rural meetings at night, I will not come home without passing and seeing a dog.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_114">
          <from> Mr. Pheilim Molloy<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_174">I fully concur with what Deputy Aird said. He encapsulated all the concerns we have and gave a great summary. I have one or two points.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_115">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_175">Mr. Molloy can make one point.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_116">
          <from> Mr. Pheilim Molloy<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_176">Pet owners and pet dogs were mentioned earlier. A huge number of different types of dogs are kept as pets. As the Deputy said, if you go into a field in which there is an Alsatian, you are not going to stay in it too long because the danger is that you will be attacked. That is an issue that needs to be looked at. Dogs are allowed to run wild. While there is a lot of talk about dogs on hills, many of the attacks originate from these so-called pet dogs.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_117">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_177">I thank all the witnesses for coming in and highlighting their concerns. In fairness, they have highlighted a lot of concerns of which we are well aware. We have witnessed what has gone on in the past. Dogs are the responsibility of the owners. I agree with the Deputies sitting beside me that laws need to be put in place in order that owners are held responsible if their dogs are out of control. A law needs to be in place to take them to court, fine them and name and shame them. If we do not do that, we will not solve this problem.</p>
          <p eId="para_178"> I have a couple of questions for the witnesses. When it comes to locations, I presume there are different parts of the country worse affected than other parts. Am I correct? Can someone answer that? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_118">
          <from> Mr. Willie Shaw<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_179">It is mainly the sheep areas. Where sheep farming predominates, there is a greater chance of dog attacks. There is less of a chance in the counties with fewer sheep. Flashpoints tend to be in rural areas where there are hillwalkers and where one comes into contact with the other.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_119">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_180">I see the ratio of dog wardens to dogs is 1:10,000. That makes it impossible. There should be more dog wardens put into those areas for a start. We all know this will not happen overnight. Legislation will not come in overnight but that is one thing that should be looked at. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_120">
          <from> Mr. John Joe Fitzgerald<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_181">Tourist hotspots on the west coast are a concern. We have a serious issue anywhere where there is tourism, walks and trails. This is an issue in my area of west Kerry and Mount Brandon.</p>
          <p eId="para_182">On the August bank holiday weekend last year, there were four dogs per hour going up the side of the mountain. The signs were at the bottom of the mountain, but no one was looking or listening. Even when they were told to turn around and go back down, they were highly abusive. That is why I am asking for roaming patrols by An Garda Síochána, NPWS rangers and some dog wardens. They do not have to be in the same place all the time. They can be roaming around. That would cure a lot for us.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_121">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_183">It is important to look at the different locations. We are all well aware of the areas in the country where sheep farming is going on. The sheep need to be protected first. I go back to the responsibility of the dog owners. We have to give credit. There are some fantastic dog owners and we cannot forget that. Is there enforcement as regards dog owners? Can they be taken to court? Can court cases go ahead? Is it up to the IFA or the farmer? Who is responsible?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_122">
          <from> Mr. John Joe Fitzgerald<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_184">I will give one example. I spoke to a retired dog warden last week who told me that he had lost a lot of the cases he brought to court because the judge felt pity for the dogs. That is just one person. Every part of society needs to be included in this. They all need to stand up and say they have had enough of this. That is from the bottom up, from dog owners on the street to people in courts dealing with the cases that come before them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_123">
          <from> Mr. Hugh Farrell<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_185">Identifying the owner is the biggest problem. I walked two or three fields back to the house from where a dog had attacked my sheep. I was lucky that there were men working on a roof who identified where I walked from. The dog owner said the dogs had only just been let out, that they had just been given meat and that was why there was blood around their mouths. I had witnesses, but in a lot of cases farmers do not have a witness or backup. That is the big problem. It is one person's word against another's until we can really identify the dogs. This is why we are talking about having DNA and other means of identifying them. This is where we are at a loss.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_124">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_186">The most important thing is having more resources-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_125">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_187">We will have another opportunity.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_126">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_188">-----in the affected areas. It is vital going forward</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoanneCollins" eId="spk_127">
          <from>Senator Joanne Collins<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_189">I thank all the witnesses for attending. It is great to see so many organisations agreeing on one important point. To go back to the controlling powers, it is not possible to have 100,000 dog wardens, but prevention is definitely better than cure. Do the witnesses agree that we need to increase the number of dog wardens? Looking at them county by county, apart from in Dublin and Cork, the maximum number of wardens in a county is three. County Limerick-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_128">
          <from> Mr. Willie Shaw<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_190">We definitely need to increase the number of dog wardens, but it is also about education. Many people with dogs go onto private and public lands and just let the dogs off their leads. They do not know. Many people do not even think of sheep. It is the last thing on their minds. They are on their holidays and they just go.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoanneCollins" eId="spk_129">
          <from>Senator Joanne Collins<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_191">They are giving their dogs a good run of the land.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_130">
          <from> Mr. Willie Shaw<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_192">The campaign about it not being the dog's fault, but the owner's fault was one of the best I have seen in a long time. That needs to be-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoanneCollins" eId="spk_131">
          <from>Senator Joanne Collins<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_193">It always comes back to the owner of the animal, as the animal does not know any better.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_132">
          <from> Mr. Tomás Bourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_194">Senator Collins is correct - the point was also made earlier - that there will never be enough dog wardens to police all the dogs. This is why, in the first instance, the level of sanction for non-compliance must be the deterrent so that people are acutely aware of the impact or repercussions if they are non-compliant.</p>
          <p eId="para_195"> There are other opportunities. It is compulsory for vets to use the national veterinary prescription system, NVPS, when prescribing products for farm animals. It will cover virtually all products and treatments animals get in the next few months - it currently covers antibiotics - but pets are outside its remit. A lot of dog owners are prepared to invest a significant amount of money in the health and welfare of their animals, yet the vets prescribing for those animals are not compelled to use the NVPS. We need a situation wherein if dogs are presented to a veterinary practitioner, their treatment must be recorded on the NVPS. This would require that the dogs be microchipped, which would require them to be on the database and the responsible person to be identified. That does not necessitate an additional layer of bureaucracy at all.</p>
          <p eId="para_196"> If I want to become a farmer, I have to fill out a 14-page document and submit it to the Department of agriculture. I will be assessed for suitability to own the farm animals. However, anyone can go and fill his or her car boot with dogs, open the boot and let them out to run amok between the animals whose health and welfare I am legally responsible for. It is not credible that we have to jump through so many hoops as farmers to be given permission to own these animals, yet anyone can decide to drive out into the countryside and open up a boot of animals for which they have not been assessed as being suitable owners. They are not meeting the legal obligations they have in the first place and are creating havoc. There has to be an assessment of suitability to own a dog in the first instance. It would not be easy to police, but if sanction was levelled for being found with a dog without the licence that had to be given to own the dog in the first place, it may help with the level of compliance.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoanneCollins" eId="spk_133">
          <from>Senator Joanne Collins<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_197">I have never been asked at the veterinary practice whether my dog is microchipped or whether I have a licence. It is not something people are asked, so it would be a good to-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_134">
          <from> Mr. Tomás Bourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_198">As farmers, when veterinary practitioners are servicing our farms, they have been legally required since the start of this year to prescribe all antibiotics on the NVPS. From later in the year, virtually every medicine that will used on a farm animal will be on the NVPS. We know the volume of work and interaction veterinary practitioners have with pets, yet those animals are sailing under the radar. The point we are making is that there are ample opportunities within existing legislation, now that we are under the remit of the Department of agriculture, to tighten up these controls.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_135">
          <from> Mr. Pheilim Molloy<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_199">May I come in with one point on that? There is also an issue with dogs being brought across the Border. We have a problem in County Donegal, where people come from Northern Ireland with their dogs and let them roam wild. How will that aspect of the problem be dealt with? It is a critical issue that needs to be looked at.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_136">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_200">We have the COMs to deal with after 5 p.m. so we have a few minutes left. Do members want to take two minutes each?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_137">
          <from> Mr. Hugh Farrell<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_201">I would like to come back in on the dogs.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_138">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_202">Bear with me for a moment. I want to give members the maximum amount of time. We have done the rounds with members.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MattieMcGrath" eId="spk_139">
          <from>Deputy Mattie McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_203">I apologise. I wanted to come in but I was delayed at other meetings. There are a lot on a Wednesday.</p>
          <p eId="para_204"> My son is a hill sheep farmer. The committee is discussing dogs and it is a huge issue. We have been fortunate in our area of the Knockmealdown Mountains, but neighbouring farmers have been annihilated. When the sheep are chased and attacked by any dog, but especially bigger dogs, they are all worried and harried and they do not thrive. It is the height of cruelty. It is hard to prove which dog it is even where the dogs are identified. Some people have shot dogs and got in trouble over that. It is an issue that needs to be dealt with because it is pretty widespread. The problem is that people in ordinary houses - I am not naming anyone - are ordinary people, but they have big, dangerous dogs. If one reports it to An Garda Síochána, the response is that the Garda cannot really deal with it. There is only one dog warden in south Tipperary. It is impossible and is a quite serious situation. It is unfair. The animal cruelty is horrific, but it is unfair on families as well because farmers, especially sheep and cattle farmers, tend to their animals and engage in animal husbandry, and they do not want this happening.</p>
          <p eId="para_205"> I thank the witnesses for their presentations. I am sorry I did not hear them. Perhaps I can get it after the meeting. The issue needs to be dealt with.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_140">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_206">I will follow the same rota we had earlier.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_141">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_207">It has been an interesting discussion. Everyone is singing off the same hymn sheet. We know where the problems are and what some of the potential solutions are. One of the big solutions is that owners need to be more responsible.</p>
          <p eId="para_208"> On trusting education to make owners more responsible, I remember an ad on television years ago where a dog went out worrying sheep. We do not see those ads any more. That is just one thing. Some responsibility needs to be put on dog owners so that, before they can own a dog, they have to have a fair knowledge of the responsibility attached to it and know that, if they drop the ball, there are consequences for them as the owners.</p>
          <p eId="para_209">That is ultimately what needs to happen.</p>
          <p eId="para_210"> I asked whether there are enough dog wardens. We clearly need more of them. We need to improve legislation. We need to do a whole range of things. Right now we need to follow up with the Department and the local authorities. We need to talk to them to ensure we can get progress on all of this. That is really all I need to say.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_142">
          <from> Mr. Hugh Farrell<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_211">I would like to follow up on an issue. We need one point of registration for all dogs, in the same way as with animals and everything else. Then they can be traced and monitored. That information has to be fed back to the local dog wardens. That is the only way they can be sure that what they are monitoring is in the right place. They can scan a dog and the scanner will be beep if it has a tag. However, if it is registered to somebody five counties away, that is where the problem lies. We need a proper registration system in place so that they are moved on. As was said earlier in the week, it would be the same as registering a car or an animal. That goes to the new owner. This is not happening now. We find a lot of problems with families or farmers who get a dog that is registered to somebody unknown to them and not living in the vicinity.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_143">
          <from> Mr. Adrian Gallagher<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_212">Some counties do not even have a full-time dog warden, but only a part-time dog warden in the county. In a big county, there may be only one part-time warden. There was €2 million allocated by the previous Government to spend on recruiting additional dog wardens. That has not been done. It is time that money was spent. It is time there were new staff on the ground. It takes a while to get that person trained up to be capable and confident enough to go out as a full-time dog warden.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_144">
          <from> Mr. Brian Delaney<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_213">Everyone is on the same wavelength when it comes to dog wardens. The powers of the dog warden need to be reviewed and dog owners' responsibilities as well. We spoke about the responsibilities but in cases of attacks or worrying, the repercussions need to be looked into. Fines and potential prosecutions need to be followed up on. If an example is not made of someone, things are not going to change.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#DannyHealyRae" eId="spk_145">
          <from>Deputy Danny Healy-Rae<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_214">We know dog wardens are employed by local authorities. We need to have one authority, either the Department of agriculture or the local authorities, to be responsible for the farmers and ensure they are doing their job. It cannot be the case that the Department of agriculture is over it but the dog wardens are not responsible to the Department. That is an anomaly that must be straightened out by us. It is absolutely ridiculous to hear Deputy Willie Aird saying that we cannot challenge people on our own land. That tells us where the problem is at. That is the truth and it should not be the case. If we are responsible for our own farms and property, there should be no one else able to surmount that or take no notice of us. Farmers must get assistance and the only one that can deal with situations like this is An Garda Síochána. A lot of work needs to be done, as Deputy Aird said. We need to get our act together and ensure it will be just the one authority in charge of the dog wardens because they have a role to play when someone reports that their sheep or other animals are being worried. I have seen dogs going after cows, calves and horses. They can do so much damage to those valuable animals. All sheep are valuable to the farmers who have them. Other animals can be far more expensive. If a farmer confronts someone, he should be safe in doing so and in taking the number of their car or whatever and it should have to be followed up by the Garda. I can see no other way of doing it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_146">
          <from> Mr. John Joe Fitzgerald<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_215">The Deputy raised a good point there. I have seen it and I have been speaking to farmers from Donegal down to west Kerry. The older generation of farmers have given up going into the hills on bank holidays and weekends because of the serious issue of run-ins with people. They have been abused and shouted at. Those people stayed here in the 1970s, 1980s and 1990s when the rest of us emigrated and they are now treated like dirt at this time of life. They are afraid to go and check their animals on bank holidays and at weekends. That is totally outrageous in this day and age.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_147">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_216">I agree that is unacceptable in this day and age. Let us be quite clear on this. I hunt on horseback and I shoot. We are registered and licensed. We have dogs that are under control. They are doing what they are meant to do. They are not the problem here. Let us be quite clear on that. The National Association of Regional Game Councils, NARGC, sees that members' dogs are licensed. They go where they are meant to go and do what they are meant to do. They are not the problem. I would not like them labelled as having anything to do with this.</p>
          <p eId="para_217"> Before we go any further, as was said already, the problem is in black spot areas where the dogs are being let off. The farmers have co-operated to put these walkways and cycleways through their land. Permission has been given. I have been involved in many of them. Our walkways are always fenced off with sheep wire and should have been all fenced off with sheep wire. Any dog that is on a walkway that has not got permission to be there should be on a leash. If it is not on a leash, it should not be out on a walkway on any hill, any day. Legislation needs to be firmly tightened up on this. Going forward, this committee, with the witnesses' suggestions and feedback, will put policy together. We will firm this up and hopefully it will alleviate some of the problem. I would like to be associated with the view that the problem concerns not all owners of dogs. I am a pet owner. I control my dogs. I am in a hunters' association and go horseback riding. We do not cause problems. If a problem arises, and you often have a problem, let us be quite clear that we are insured for any problem that is caused out there. If a dog runs out in front of a car and a car is damaged, we are insured by the NARGC or by the hunters' association. We are legalised for doing what we do.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_148">
          <from> Mr. John Joe Fitzgerald<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_218">I want to make the point that I have no problem with hunts or these people coming onto our lands. They have been there forever, are well behaved and do their best. However, the problem is with the recreational user, the walkers who are coming onto our land. That is why we need to see legislation brought in that bans the recreational user from bringing dogs onto our farmland. There needs to be a strong statement put out from this House to say those words, that this cannot happen any longer.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_149">
          <from> Mr. Tomás Bourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_219">Senator Brady is talking about the responsible people with permission or indeed the people who are keeping their dogs under effective control at all times. Unfortunately, and this is the reason we had no choice five years ago but to commence our campaign of no dogs allowed, the behaviour of a small minority is going to impact on the access that the responsible people are going to have to our farmland. We cannot continue to have dogs allowed on hills.</p>
          <p eId="para_220"> Deputy Kenny referenced an accidental breakout from the dog of somebody doing everything right. These things happen and can be addressed. However, the majority of attacks on our sheep and our livestock fall under one of two headings of owners, either arrogants or ignorants. The arrogants are the people who, for the various examples given, maybe illegal activities, assume entitlement and assume right. Then we have the ignorants, people who just do not appreciate. I would give some hop of the ball to the ignorant aspect of it. However, the arrogant aspect of it is in no way acceptable. A member of ours was physically abused on his own farmland not many miles from here, only a couple years ago. He was one of the first people to give access to his lands for recreational users.</p>
          <p eId="para_221">When he merely asked for the person to keep his dog off his land, he was physically abused on his own farmland. We have to get to a situation where there can be no more confusion around that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_150">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_222">This is really important because if we do not address it, we are going to see great difficulty in the future for greenways and walkways. Farmers will not engage with councils. Greenways have been a massive lifeline for rural Ireland. It is critically important for the tourism sector that we address this issue. I agree with all the points made and the report we have committed to doing. However, in regard to enforcement, it is an oversight that some counties have no dog wardens, while other counties may have part-time dog wardens. In cases where dog wardens are on holidays or sick, there are gangs who realise what is happening and are able to roam the country. The report should investigate the ability of members of An Garda Síochána to carry out their function regarding this as well. For example, every squad car in the country should have the ability to scan a dog. Currently that is not the case. That is something we should look at seriously.</p>
          <p eId="para_223"> On sanctions, while we are going to catch everyone, we should make an example out of a number of perpetrators. Currently, the fixed penalty notice is €300. That is not good enough. The committee should recommend an increase in the penalty to the Minister.</p>
          <p eId="para_224"> Mr. Bourke made a key point on accessibility and suitability. We should examine that, particularly in examples where we know there is a suspected offender or, for example, where there are cases - going back to the topic of gangs - where the dogs are possessed and are microchipped. Those gangs are moving the dogs on because they are now traceable. That is what is happening. We know that where dogs are microchipped, owners are more vigilant. Mr. Bourke raised an important point on suitability and I will be recommending to the Minister that a suitability plan be developed, particularly for offenders or people known to the warden.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_151">
          <from> Mr. Tomás Bourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_225">I welcome the Deputy's comments. This is where there is potential because the Department of agriculture is taking over control of this area. Within the Animal Health and Welfare Act 2013, effectively every power, clarity, sanction and qualification required is available if we attribute it to dogs in the same way as we do to livestock. If the same obligations, criteria and sanctions were applied to dog owners as they are to animal owners, we would have a lot more responsible ownership. There is the huge potential, without reinventing the wheel, to incorporate dog ownership and responsibilities of dog owners in the requirements of the Animal Health and Welfare Act.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_152">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_226">I have one issue that I wish to be clear on. There is some agreement with farm organisations that people can walk hills. Is that correct?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_153">
          <from> Mr. Pheilim Molloy<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_227">There is permissive access. In a situation where an individual wants to walk the land, it would be up to the farmer to grant that permission.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_154">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_228">Are there some walking trails for which agreements have been done already? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_155">
          <from> Mr. Hugh Farrell<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_229">Not that I am aware of.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_156">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_230">There is permissive access around the country.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_157">
          <from> Mr. Hugh Farrell<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_231">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_158">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_232">We want to watch that we do not cut off our nose to spite our face. Are there any dogs on the lands that have to be on a lead? Mr. Bourke said no dogs should be on a mountain.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_159">
          <from> Mr. Tomás Bourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_233">The Deputy has hit the nail on the head. It is the inconsistency of approach. This is what is leading to some of the interaction between landowners and walkers. People go to one hill and the dog is allowed, but on another walkway the dog has to be on a leash and on another one there are no dogs allowed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_160">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_234">Just to be clear, is Mr. Bourke saying all dogs should be on leads?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_161">
          <from> Mr. Tomás Bourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_235">Our campaign for five years is that there should be no dogs.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_162">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_236">No dogs on mountains. Do all the farmer organisations agree with that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_163">
          <from> Mr. Tomás Bourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_237">It cannot be policed, particularly on the hills. We just cannot allow them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_164">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_238">It is just so we know.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_165">
          <from> Mr. Willie Shaw<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_239">I apologise; I do not agree with that. There are a lot of people using the hills for recreation. We are not going to able to stop the general public from going up to these places. It is about leads and controlling their dogs. That is the message here today. If a person is responsible for their dog and have the landowner’s permission, whether it is from a friend, neighbour or whoever it is, then use the hill, but use it responsibly if the person has the permission of the owner.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_166">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_240">I am not going to take up any more time because I want to let other members speak. There are all the points put down that the witnesses have agreed on and after that we will talk as a committee. We are not going to be making the law. There is no point codding the witnesses. We can put report together as a committee and give it to the Department. The Cathaoirleach will hand in the report to the Minister. That is how it works. We are not going to tell the witnesses that we will guarantee everything they have brought up today. With the help of our Chair and secretariat, we will bring in the Minister and his officials on this. All of the ideas raised are common sense; they are not over the top. The interesting point we should include is the one on the Animal Health and Welfare Act.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_167">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_241">We are talking about a very small cohort of people. The majority of people look after their dogs well. There are an awful lot of dogs. None of us knows what happens, but some say we come back as animals. I often say to myself if I came back, there are certain people that I would love to be minded by as a dog. There is care and attention taken, but it is a problem when it is not done. We are in limbo at the moment because responsibility for this area has only been handed over to the Department of agriculture. Other members and the witnesses may know about this, but I do not know if the dog wardens, dog pounds and all of that are going to be shifted over to the Department of agriculture. We are going to have a huge problem if that happens because we will have officials from Department of agriculture liaising with the dog warden who is under the offices of Laois County Council. Who will run the pound? We may have a lot of work to do yet to convince the Minister. There is one way this is going to work, and that is to have it all under one umbrella. We will then have huge success. </p>
          <p eId="para_242"> We can ask the witnesses to come back to the committee again when we have more work done on this. Things are going wrong in two ways at the moment. The first is when a person lets their dog off the lead and the dog sees sheep or cattle and takes off. You would want to have a very good dog. There are people here today with hunting dogs that are well trained. My father had these dogs. If you call a dog that has travelled in the car and has run off, there is not a hope in hell that it will come back to you. That is me being straight. That is what I have seen anyway.</p>
          <p eId="para_243"> The second issue is that many of the sheep attacks are taking place at night, after dark. I am a farmer. From that point of the view, farmers get up in the morning or someone rings to say there is a problem. All of the damage is done and the dog is gone. That is why all this talk about dog wardens is no good if the damage is done and the dogs are gone. There is no point ringing the council in the morning to say I want the dog warden to come out and look at dead sheep everywhere. It is no good. That is not working. We have to move on from that. The witnesses may have suggestions about what we can do when we put all of these points together.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EileenLynch" eId="spk_168">
          <from>Senator Eileen Lynch<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_244">I have one point relating to how dogs are getting on lands. It is not so much the night attacks, but the attacks during the day when people are leaving dogs loose. Dogs should not be on a farmer's land if it is private property. There is a slightly different issue if it is mountain land or commonage in certain places. In 2021, there was a proposal that all rights of way, which were rights of way through long use, would have to be registered. That was subsequently dropped. Would something like that be worth looking at? It would mean that rights of way that are currently open would be registered in the name of a person or a property. That would probably prevent walkers accessing farms because the rights of way to them would be cut off. The legislation proposed on rights of way in 2021 was subsequently dropped because it was felt it was too cumbersome with regard to rights of way of long use.</p>
          <p eId="para_245">I do not know if that is something the witnesses feel would make a difference in terms of people out walking, etc., accessing lands.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_169">
          <from> Mr. Tomás Bourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_246">To be clear, we have no problems with walkers and recreational users. The problem we have is with them bringing their dogs. I know to an extent the point the Senator is making, but the difficulty as touched on by Deputy Fitzmaurice is the mixed messaging around what is acceptable. That is why we talk about one clear and concise message. If someone is going walking on hills around open land, then he or she should not bring a dog. We cannot police it. There could be 500 dog wardens. Someone can police and watch dogs with the lead on at the gate and when they cross the stile, but who is going two miles up the hill to see where that dog has gone over the far side of the hill? It is impractical, so there is only one solution, which is consistency of messaging. This has to be fair to the dog owners and the walkers as well. If someone wants to bring a dog for a walk, then go in a controlled area where the dog can be kept on a leash and the land is not on, or in any contact with, farmland. If someone wants to walk the hills, then leave the dog at home.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_170">
          <from> Mr. Willie Shaw<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_247">Rights of way have caused, and will cause, trouble over the years. A lot of people have access to other properties and other land further in. To register that in one name is not going to happen and will not work. I do not mean that to be biased, but we have to be practical because everybody is entitled to access. Let us take the proper approach so that people have access under consent. This is a big issue that the ICSFA wishes to raise. If nobody else can go into someone's property without consent, why should this be any different? These lands are easily accessed if people really want to get to them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_171">
          <from> Mr. John Joe Fitzgerald<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_248">I agree 100% with what Mr. Bourke said. There can be no ambiguity around dark-shaded or any other type of area where bringing dogs onto farmland, especially hills, is concerned. It is a no-no, and that message has to come out from here. The biggest problem we have is that, if a guy or girl brings a dog onto a commonage and a farmer approaches to tell that person to bring the dog home, that guy or girl tells the farmer that he or she got permission from the landowner. How can someone get permission from 20 landowners? That is why we are saying we need a total ban on recreational users bringing their dogs onto our hills and farmlands, bar the hunts, dogs for the blind and stuff like that. If we do that, it will be a better society and give farmers more of an opportunity if they feel they want to open up for walks and schemes. The biggest hindrance at the moment to these walk schemes is recreational users with dogs. That is what I have been told. Before I came here today, I was on the phone to someone named Vincent. There are a lot of landowners out there who are thinking of closing the walks down unless the serious issue with dogs is dealt with.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_172">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_249">There have been many questions, so if there are points the witnesses want to forward on, they should please send them to the secretariat for the consideration of the committee.</p>
          <p eId="para_250"> I have one brief question about the database. There are a number of databases operated by different organisations. They are not co-ordinated. Who would the witnesses see holding and managing a database and who would carry the costs of it?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_173">
          <from> Mr. Tomás Bourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_251">The Department of agriculture has extensive experience of running the animal identification and movement system, AIMS, database for our bovines and is building the sheep one. That is the logical place for it, but the Chair should also be reminded that there are amendments to the European regulation on traceability for dogs and cats that we also need to ensure we align with.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_174">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_252">There are two questions. Where is the database and who would pay for it?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_175">
          <from> Mr. Tomás Bourke<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_253">The dog owner when he or she registers.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_176">
          <from> Mr. Hugh Farrell<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_254">The dog owner, and I will follow up on what Mr. Bourke said. We agree totally because if they are being chipped by the vet, there is a native system they can be registered on. They are automatically transferring into the database. That whole facility is already set up except for maybe a bit of tweaking on the IT side. It is up and running, so this is not impossible. It will not take a long time to do it. Now, in the beginning, is the time to make it happen before there is more harm done.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_177">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_255">Before we go, may we ask the organisations to submit a summary of what was discussed to the Chair?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_178">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_256">They will be sending in their responses to the unanswered questions anyway.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_179">
          <from> Mr. Hugh Farrell<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_257">Will we get a chance to see the review paperwork the committee will present or put together?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_180">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_258">The witnesses can make submissions to the committee. The committee is talking about doing a report and that will be a public document once published, but not before then.</p>
          <p eId="para_259"> On behalf of the committee, I thank the witnesses for taking part in the meeting, preparing for it and for the great deal of information.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_6">
          <i>Sitting suspended at 5.15 p.m. and resumed at 5.24 p.m.</i>
        </summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>Scrutiny of EU Legislative Proposals<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:20:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_181">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_260">I draw witnesses' attention to the fact that witnesses giving evidence from within the parliamentary precincts are protected by absolute privilege in respect of the evidence they give to a committee. This means a witness has a full defence in any defamation action for anything said at a committee meeting. However, witnesses are expected not to abuse this privilege and may be directed to cease giving evidence on an issue at the Chair's discretion. Witnesses should follow the direction of the Chair in this regard and are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that, as is reasonable, no adverse commentary should be made against any identifiable third person or entity. Witnesses who are to give evidence from a location outside the parliamentary precincts are asked to note that they may not benefit from the same level of immunity from legal proceedings as witnesses giving evidence from within the parliamentary precincts and may consider it appropriate to take legal advice on the matter. Privilege against defamation does not apply to the publication by witnesses outside of the proceedings held by the committee of any matters arising from the proceedings.</p>
          <p eId="para_261"> The agenda for the second session is to focus on two legislative proposals. The first is COM (2024) 576, proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council on co-operation among enforcement authorities responsible for the enforcement of EU Directive No. 2019/633 on unfair trading practices, UTPs, in business-to-business relationships in the agricultural and food supply chain. The second is COM (2024) 577, proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council amending EU Regulations Nos. 1308/2013, 2021/2115 and 2021/2116 as regards the strengthening of the position of farmers in the food supply chain.</p>
          <p eId="para_262"> The committee will now hear from officials from the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine as follows: Ms Maria Dunne, assistant secretary general; Ms Angela Robinson, principal officer; Mr. Ultan Waldron, principal officer; and Mr. Damien Ward, assistant principal officer. Tá fáilte romhaibh. I will give you five minutes to present the details and then we will have a-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_182">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_263">Chair, will we give them ten minutes?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_183">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_264">We will give them five minutes to do their presentation on these proposals and we will have an opportunity then to ask about them. We need to be out by 6 p.m., so we are constrained on time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_184">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_265">I thank the members of the committee for the opportunity to appear before them to discuss the European Commission's proposal for a regulation on co-operation among enforcement authorities responsible for the UTP directive, and the European Commission's proposal to amend the CMO regulation with regard to strengthening the position of farmers in the food supply chain. I welcome the committee's engagement on these two important matters.</p>
          <p eId="para_266"> I am the assistant secretary general in the Department with responsibility for agrifood sectoral policy and strategy development. Mr. Waldron is the principal officer in the meat and milk policy division with responsibility for policy relating to the livestock sector, which includes relevant elements of the CMO regulation, and Mr. Ward works with Mr. Waldron. Ms Robinson is principal officer in the food industry development division with responsibility for the UTP directive.</p>
          <p eId="para_267"> I wish to give the committee a very brief overview of the current position of both proposals. Starting with proposed regulation No. 576 of 2024 concerning a proposal on co-operation among enforcement authorities responsible for the enforcement of the UTP directive, the UTP directive covers unfair trading practices in business-to-business relationships in the agricultural and food supply chain. This legislation has been in place in Ireland since 2021, and since 2023, the UTP enforcement authority function is performed by the Agri-Food Regulator. The UTP directive required the enforcement authorities to co-operate effectively with one another and the Commission and to provide one another with mutual assistance in investigations that had a cross-border dimension. Following consultation by the European Commission, however, it was found that the experience of enforcement authorities was that gathering information, finding infringements and imposing and enforcing penalties could be difficult when the buyer was in another member state.</p>
          <p eId="para_268"> The proposed regulation aims to improve and increase co-operation between enforcement authorities. Specifically, the proposed rules aim to ensure that a legal basis is provided to enable exchanges of information and requests for enforcement measures between member states. By providing tools to enable enforcement authorities to gather information and investigate non-compliances against buyers located in another member state, the proposed powers will help to further protect suppliers in the agricultural and food supply chain against unfair trading practices.</p>
          <p eId="para_269">The Department, in close consultation with the Agri-Food Regulator, engaged with the EU Presidency, the European Commission and other member states on the draft text of the proposals to ensure that the provisions would work well, from an Irish perspective. On 7 April 2025, the special committee on agriculture approved the Council's negotiating mandate for negotiations with the European Parliament. The negotiations are expected to commence the plenary stage in September 2025. </p>
          <p eId="para_270"> Turning to the proposal to amend the CMO regulation, Regulation 1308/2013, in December 2024 the Commission published a proposal to amend this regulation. The proposal responds to the Commission's March 2024 non-paper and recommendations from the strategic dialogue on the future on EU agriculture, published in September 2024. The Commission proposal and subsequent amendments are aimed at strengthening the position of farmers in the food supply chain. The key elements include strengthening EU-level provisions on contracts involving farmers with other actors in the supply chain, including food industry and retail, across all sectors covered by the CMO and strengthening producer organisations to allow farmers to co-operate and act collectively in a more effective way. The Department also consulted key stakeholders on the proposals, following which it engaged with the EU Presidency, the European Commission and other member states on the draft text of the proposal. The Council is now ready to start negotiations with the European Parliament, once the latter adopts its position. The Committee on Agriculture and Rural Development is expected to vote on its report in September, while approval of the mandate and plenary session is expected to take place in October. </p>
          <p eId="para_271"> I conclude by stressing that the Department is focused on ensuring that Ireland's position is reflected in EU legislation, while acknowledging that generally, a compromise text will emerge. We start that process by consulting key stakeholders to ensure a cohesive, informed position. We have done that in relation to both the proposals being discussed today. We are happy to take any questions on the details of the two proposals. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_185">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_272">The witnesses probably recognise as well that the regulator has stated that it does not have enough teeth or enough power. Would that be fair to say? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_186">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_273">To clarify, the regulation relates to the unfair trading practices powers of the Agri-Food Regulator. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_187">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_274">I have heard Joe Healy say that he would like more powers. Is that recognised by the Department? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_188">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_275">I will explain a little bit of the background. The independent Agri-Food Regulator was established under the Agricultural and Food Supply Chain Act 2023. It performs two key functions. It enforces the law on unfair trading practices and it performs a price and market analysis and reporting function. The Commission proposal being discussed today specifically relates to the first of those, namely, the law on unfair trading practices and the ability to share information across member States. On the price and market analysis function, over the last year, the regulator has published welcome analysis on the egg and horticulture sectors. Such reports are important to assist food suppliers in their decision-making. However, while there has been much positive engagement with the regulator from operators that have voluntarily responded to request for information, a few operators did not provide the requested data. As a result, the two reports concerned were published using only publicly available data. In light of its experience with these reports, the regulator has reported to the Minister that it requires enhanced powers to compel businesses to provide financial information that is not in the public domain. The Act itself does not permit the regulator to compel such data. However, the Act provides that the Minister may make regulations on price and market information. I want to stress that there are very strong powers regarding the unfair trading practices regulation. The price and market analysis and reporting function is separate and is not covered by the legislation being discussed. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_189">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_276">Is Ms Dunne saying that, for the regulator, the Minister can put in more regulations and is the Minister looking at that to help it? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_190">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_277">The Minister, Deputy Heydon, has clearly stated that he is fully committed to ensuring that the regulator is equipped with the necessary powers to fulfil its statutory function, subject to the necessary consultative and legislative process. That is necessary to ensure that the additional powers granted are proportionate. This process is under way in the Department. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_191">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_278">While what we are on about is in relation to European legislation, when a company is outside, say in Brazil or another country that sends beef to us, do they come under this in any way or are they totally separate once they are outside the EU? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_192">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_279">I will ask my colleague, Ms Robinson to respond to this question. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_193">
          <from> Ms Angela Robinson<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_280">The UTP directive applies to suppliers and buyers, where at least one of them is located in the European Union. In practice, the intention of the directive is that if there is a supplier in the European Union selling to a buyer outside of the European Union, it is open to the enforcement authority-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_194">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_281">What if it is <i>vice versa</i>? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_195">
          <from> Ms Angela Robinson<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_282">If the buyer is in the European Union and the supplier is outside, yes, it equally applies that the enforcement authority has powers. The supplier could make a complaint-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_196">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_283">Has there been any case opened on that yet? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_197">
          <from> Ms Angela Robinson<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_284">Across Europe, I stand to be corrected but as regards the Agri-Food Regulator, no query or complaint has come in respect of any outside-of-Ireland UTP issue arising. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_198">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_285">As was said, the regulator has dealt with the egg and the horticulture sectors to date. When do the witnesses see the regulator having the teeth to deal with the beef sector? In this sector, we have a fifth quarter, regarding the offal and the tongue, that is sold into Asian markets that a farmer in this country does not actually get paid for. There are unfair practices within the beef sector, when we see the fifth quarter being sold globally and yet the farmer in this country has not been paid for it. Do the witnesses see the regulator engaging with Meat Industry Ireland, MII, and processors regarding the meat sector in the future? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_199">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_286">To be clear, there are two functions. One is the UTP legislation and the other is market transparency and price reporting. Under the unfair trading practices legislation, which the regulation being discussed relates to, there is not an unfair trading practice relating to price. There are 16 unfair trading practices but they do not relate to price. If we are talking about the other function, which is about market transparency and reporting, I refer to my previous answer that the Minister has stated that it is a priority for the Department but I cannot give timelines on when we will have concluded the consultative and legislative consultation processes. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_200">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_287">Will it be in the lifetime of this Government? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_201">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_288">There is a commitment under the programme for Government to give the Agri-Food Regulator additional powers. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_202">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_289">I thank the witnesses and Ms Dunne for her presentation. What we are talking about is a directive that gives a little more method for the regulator in this State to work with regulators in other states, mainly within the EU, in respect of how they can co-operate better to ensure a level playing field for the farmer and, we hope, the consumer at the other end. An issue that comes to mind in that regard is that regulators in other states in the EU have been much longer in existence and have in many cases done a lot more work in this field. I met the food regulator recently and it is taking baby steps. It has only been in place for a short while and has a lot of work to do. It has done a couple of reports into the poultry sector and eggs. It has looked at other sectors but has not done reports. It probably needs more resources to do that. Will the regulator's co-operation with regulators in other states mean that it will require more resources to be able to work in that context? That is one of the big problems it has. There are approximately 16 staff members and the regulator has a lot of work to do domestically. When its remit is broadened internationally, it will put more strain on the regulator. Perhaps that is not a question related directly to the directive but would be an impact of it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_203">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_290">Within the existing UTP directive, there is provision for co-operation between enforcement authorities. This directive is to provide a legal basis for that co-operation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_204">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_291">Pardon?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_205">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_292">The directive provides a legal basis for that co-operation because enforcement authorities were finding it difficult.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_206">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_293">Ms Dunne mentioned in her opening remarks that the food regulator has stated that one of its issues relates to compellability, particularly with regard to information it wants to get from various players in the field. When the regulator asks for information, many of the players co-operate but if a couple of the big players do not co-operate, it skews the whole thing and makes it very hard to do an accurate report. The regulator would like a situation whereby it could compel these people to give them the information it requires. Many are hesitant because of competition, etc. We understand that and there must be a level of guarantee that any information that flows is going to be handled in a sensitive and proper manner, as would be necessary. Does this directive give the Minister the ability to put in place compellability to allow the food regulator to get the information it requires?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_207">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_294">No. The regulation we are discussing refers to the unfair trading practices. It does not refer to the market transparency and price reporting function of the Agri-Food Regulator, which is entirely different from its unfair trading practices function. This legislation in Europe only refers to its unfair trading practices function. The function the Deputy is talking about came out of primary legislation in Ireland.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_208">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_295">Is there any part of the legislation in Europe that deals with the pricing aspect of the market?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_209">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_296">There are market transparency regulations in Europe. Under that market transparency function, the Central Statistics Office, CSO, and the Department report into Europe on an ongoing basis on a number of different prices at a number of different points in the supply chain for a whole range of commodities. There is regulation in place but the Agri-Food Regulator does not have a role within those regulations.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_210">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_297">I know I am drifting slightly off target here, but do the regulators in other states have that power of compellability to require players to give them the information they require? The regulator here does not have that power yet.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_211">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_298">I do not have information on that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_212">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_299">That is fine. I understand.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_213">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_300">I can say that the Department has powers to compel under the market transparency regulations.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_214">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_301">I want to talk about the Agri-Food Regulator. One of the key tasks for it is that there is a significant mark-up on the price of beef in supermarkets. The farmer keeps the animal for over three years, or thereabouts. He receives €7.50 per kilo. Supermarkets at the moment are selling at a price in the region of €23 per kilo. What role does the Agri-Food Regulator have in respect of identifying the significant mark-up and producing data or a report in respect of the profits taken from a slice of that particular pie?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_215">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_302">To be clear, the regulator has two functions. One is enforcing the law on unfair trading practices. That is not relevant to the scenario the Deputy raised because it is not an unfair trading practice. The other function is that it performs a price and market analysis and reporting function. As I said, it has reported it does not feel it has enough powers to conduct that function completely at the moment. The Minister has stated he is fully committed to ensuring the regulator is equipped with the necessary powers to fulfil its statutory function.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_216">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_303">In its current form, it is a charade. It does not have the ability to quantify or extract that data from the companies in its current form.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_217">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_304">It has access to all the publicly available data and the data that is given to it voluntarily under the Act. That is what the Act currently provides for.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_218">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_305">If the companies tell the Agri-Food Regulator that their data are none of its business, the regulator says "Okay".</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_219">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_306">As it stands, the regulator is entitled to the information on a voluntary basis. That is what the Act provides for. It also has the information on market transparency, as I outlined, that the Department can compel under the legislation. That is published by the EU market observatories and the Department in its weekly meat market reports and on its meat and dairy dashboards. Bord Bia does a market tracker that came out of the beef task force agreement. There is a lot of publicly available data to which the regulator has access.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_220">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_307">The regulator has two functions. One is around unfair trading practices and the other relates to transparency. It is ironic that those are its core functions but it does not have any teeth to address transparency and the slice of that pie. It is a major oversight. Would Ms Dunne agree?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_221">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_308">All I can say is that it has two key functions. It enforces the law on unfair trading practices and performs a price and market analysis and reporting function. It is able to carry out analysis and reporting on a vast range. There is a lot of publicly available data on the markets.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_222">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_309">The other function is around unfair trading practices. As Senator Brady alluded to earlier, there is a fifth quarter of offal that is sold by meat factories but the farmer receives nothing. How is that not an unfair trading practice?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_223">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_310">For clarity, I can tell the Deputy what the unfair trading practices are. They include: payments later than 30 days for perishable agricultural and food products, payment later than 60 days for other agrifood products, short notice cancellations of perishable agrifood products, unilateral contract changes by the buyer, payments not related to a specific transaction, the risk of loss and deterioration being transferred to the supplier, the refusal of written confirmation of a supply agreement by a buyer despite requests from the supplier, misuse of trade secrets by the buyer, commercial retaliation by the buyer and transferring the costs of examining customer complaints to the supplier. There are six further unfair practices that only come into-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_224">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_311">Could Ms Dunne send those to the committee?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_225">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_312">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_226">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_313">The Agri-Food Regulator has two core functions in relation to unfair trading practices and transparency. It cannot achieve either. How is it the case that for a valuable commodity such as offal, the farmer cannot receive anything? The Agri-Food Regulator says, "There is nothing to see here."</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_227">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_314">We need to get Deputy Aird-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_228">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_315">The other point-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_229">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_316">No, Deputy Lawless.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_230">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_317">-----is around the fact that transparency without the power to compel is a major oversight.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_231">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_318">Deputy Aird should be allowed an opportunity.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_232">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_319">We as a committee need to write to the Minister about these key points.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_233">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_320">No, Deputy. I call Deputy Aird. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_234">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_321">I thank the officials for attending and clearing up our concerns. I very much welcome food regulation. It is something that we all sought for many years.</p>
          <p eId="para_322"> I wish Mr. Joe Healy well and he is Chair of the board. The office of the Agri-Food Regulator is only in its infancy and getting off the ground. There is a lot more legislation to be put in place so that the people with the responsibility can carry out their duties. I have no doubt that once the legislation is passed and the Minister confers responsibilities upon them then we will be able to get exactly what everybody has talked about here today because at the moment it can only ask and if you voluntarily do not contribute the information to the regulator then it cannot actually get it out of them.</p>
          <p eId="para_323"> The situation will change rapidly because the Minister has given a commitment that he is going to do that and we will see huge change, and rightly so. Prices have escalated for beef and butter, which is what we are all talking about at the moment, but there are reasons and blame cannot be pinned on farmers. Until we can see exactly where supermarkets, etc., make their profits then we will not have a true answer. The Minister has promised that change will happen. In the meantime, we must address all of the associated issues.</p>
          <p eId="para_324"> We are talking about the offal from cattle. There was a time when pigs were killed and the owner was not paid for the pig's head and crubeens but an Act or whatever was passed which meant that payment for both items had to be made because the pigs' heads and crubeens were for sale to the public. I hope this is what all the regulator is about.</p>
          <p eId="para_325"> The Agri-Food Regulator will have a wide brief. I look forward to when the regulator gets down into the nuts and bolts of it and sees what has happened, the profits, and where profits were made and where they went. On the other hand, it is regrettable that there is so few cattle. I am sure Deputy Fitzmaurice will agree with me because he can see the same in Roscommon and several counties. Without question, everywhere one drives it is obvious because one sees an ever decreasing number of cattle, which I think will be a huge problem down the line. I am sure everyone will agree with me that it would have been preferable if all these regulations had been put in place because we would not have nearly 200,000 suckler cows gone out of the national herd. We will not have them back, which is shameful and terrible. It really hits me, as a farmer, to see all the finest of stockmen having had to let go all their good cattle because they could not make a profit. One generation after the other saw that a farmer's life is not for them because there is no profit to be made. That is what happened and is why a lot of people changed market and went into milk production.</p>
          <p eId="para_326"> I ask the officials to help us by telling us what extra powers the regulator should get than what has been proposed by the Minister. I ask because I do not know but the officials will know because of their years of experience working in the Department. I would love if that information could be sent to the clerk to the committee as it would benefit us all.</p>
          <p eId="para_327"> I am not saying that we just get one bite of the cherry. When the Minister does sit down to look at what he can do to strengthen the power of the regulator we need to be able to say please include A, B, C and D. I know that he will include the pricing provision so the regulator will be able to say, "We want to know how much you are charging for a product and how much was paid for it," which will be eye-opening information.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EileenLynch" eId="spk_235">
          <from>Senator Eileen Lynch<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_328">I thank the officials for their attendance and their briefing. Has the 2023 Act been commenced in its entirety?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_236">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_329">Yes, absolutely. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EileenLynch" eId="spk_237">
          <from>Senator Eileen Lynch<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_330">On unfair trading practices, I understand that this is a regulation to enforce the existing directive to allow greater co-operation between enforcement bodies within the various member states. What actual power will the regulator have when it comes to legal cases being taken? I appreciate that co-operation exists and information is shared. Also, if a general unfair trading practice emerges at a Union level, the Department looks at different elements such as conformity of language, etc. in terms of notification and highlighting these things. If there is an unfair trading legal case at either a national or European level then what are the powers of compulsion here from one enforcement to another? In particular I mean from the country where the enforcement Act originates. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_238">
          <from> Ms Angela Robinson<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_331">The Senator has asked a very relevant question. She has also outlined the core functions provided in the regulation that we are discussing today and it was following consultation by the European Commission with the enforcement authorities. The directive does provide for co-operation on enforcement authorities across Europe but what its experience was, in talking to the enforcement authorities, was that it was difficult to get some engagement on that and the enforcement authorities themselves were not sure what information they could share in respect of certain activities within their area. So if there was a supplier based in Ireland, for example, that had a difficulty with a buyer in another member state then there were questions about what information could be taken or what activity should be taken. The regulation sets out the parameters for the enforcement authorities and for the member states to be able to say, "These are the things that we can do." That includes the sharing of information, requesting another enforcement authority in another member state to investigate a suspected UTP that involves, perhaps, a supplier in one member state and a buyer in another member state. So we might call that a cross-border type of UTP.</p>
          <p eId="para_332"> On the Senator's question on the legal powers for enforcement, the regulation provides for the enforcement by one member state at the request of an enforcement authority in another member state of a fine, a decision or a penalty that has been imposed in that requesting member state. There is also provision for co-ordinated actions where there is a cross-border UTP that involves at least three member states.</p>
          <p eId="para_333"> It still is not been finalised and has to go to the European Parliament. The Council's mandate is to make sure that there are very strong powers to allow enforcement authorities to co-operate across that, and that includes the legal basis for those interventions and investigations. It also includes, for example, that authorised officers of an enforcement authority in one member state can accompany an investigation in respect of an enforcement in another member state. That is the current proposal.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EileenLynch" eId="spk_239">
          <from>Senator Eileen Lynch<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_334">So the regulation would allow for obligatory enforcement if, say, an Irish buyer takes an action against a French suppler and the decision is made here but the two enforcement authorities work together to enforce that in the second country.</p>
          <p eId="para_335"> On the other COM proposal, I note that the Department's briefing on the implications for Ireland sets out that the Department is concerned about any potential increased administrative burden on farmers as a result of these new rules in relation to the contracts. What administrative burden is foreseen? What is the extent of that? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_240">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_336">Mr. Waldron will reply. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_241">
          <from> Mr. Ultan Waldron<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_337">At the time when the regulations came out it could have been around having to engage and having written contracts in advance. That would have been the concern about the administrative burden and that is the way the regulations are currently phrased at the moment.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EileenLynch" eId="spk_242">
          <from>Senator Eileen Lynch<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_338">Do the officials think that issue will be resolved, as negotiations are ongoing? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_243">
          <from> Mr. Ultan Waldron<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_339">The way the legislation is at the moment, the Council has adopted their general approach. As Ms Dunne outlined in her opening statement, the European Parliament's Committee on Agriculture and Rural Development, or the AGRI committee, is due to vote on its position in September, the plenary will take place in October and then trilogues will commence thereafter. We do not have the final set of regulations and there is a transition phase. Again, it has not been set but it normally takes two years between the time the regulations are adopted and published in the journal and entering into force. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_244">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_340">I have one very quick question on COM (2024) 576. There is consultation being conducted with the Agri-Food Regulator. Has the consultation concluded? Has the Agri-Food Regulator made any recommendations on that COM proposal? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_245">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_341">This is on the unfair trading practices. Yes, we have worked closely with it all the time. The regulation has now been agreed by Council and will be subject to agreement by Parliament and then trilogue discussions. So, yes. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_246">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_342">There has been quite a bit of conversation about the Agri-Food Regulator. While our focus today is on the COM proposal, it is a topic the committee should look further towards and possibly put it on our programme of work. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_247">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_343">I propose we bring in the Agri-Food Regulator in the future. It is not something for today.</p>
          <p eId="para_344"> The second proposal, COM (2024) 577, concerns the protection of the primary producer. Reference is made to farmer co-operatives or producer groups. Is there more protection for producer groups or is there anything to ensure they have a greater status? That would be important as we move forward.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_248">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_345">There are a couple of things in the CMO. It is about strengthening EU level provisions on contracts, strengthening the economic producer organisations and a framework for fair trading voluntary schemes. Specifically on producer organisations, it is about trying to simplify the process for registration. There is increased financial support for producer organisations where they are implementing operational programmes under the strategic plans regulation. There is some increased co-financing. It is about making things simpler for them and there are more finances under the CAP strategic plan.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_249">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_346">At the moment, where they would bite the hand off you for cattle or sheep because they are stuck for them, producer organisations do not really hold sway. Is it a requirement for factories to deal with producer organisations under any of the legislation? More paperwork for a farmer was mentioned. Under this COM proposal, will a farmer have to have a contract with someone or is that up in the air at the moment? If we start implementing a system whereby someone with ten cattle has to have a contract, that would bring us into fairly difficult water.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_250">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_347">On the first question, it is primarily about encouraging producer organisations. The real advantage is collective bargaining in terms of price and imports. What we have done and have been asked to do is to make it easier for them to set up and give them more financial support. There is financial support under the current CAP strategic plan for the first three years of a producer organisation, as well as some administrative support. As it stands, the CMO regulation provides for compulsory written contracts for each delivery of agricultural products, with certain exemptions. A range of derogations can be availed of by member states or a member state can put in place in its own system. That is what the CMO is aimed at.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_251">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_348">Is the Department fighting that? It is crazy to have to have documentation if you, as a small operator, are buying fertiliser or selling sheep or cattle. The paperwork involved in this will be horrendous.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_252">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_349">It is for written contracts between the farmer and their buyer.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_253">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_350">Would the officials be able to forward us on those derogations?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_254">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_351">Chair, you have opened up an awful can of worms, if you do not mind me saying that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_255">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_352">Is the Department concerned about potential problems with the COM? A large producer group will have a contract or whatever. I am referring to farmers who sell ten or 15 cattle or 40 or 50 sheep. How will such contracts work? Does this refer to merchants selling farmers fertiliser or meal? Does that have to be a contract under all of this?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_256">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_353">No, it is the farmer when the farmer is selling it. There is a list of processors, including processors, wholesalers or retailers-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_257">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_354">There will have to be a written contract.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_258">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_355">When he is selling it, subject to a number of derogations which member states can put in place.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_259">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_356">Do we know what they are yet?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_260">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_357">There is a range of derogations referring to existing co-operative structures, producer organisations and the size of the buyer-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_261">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_358">An ordinary farmer------</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_262">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_359">-----and the financial level of the transaction.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_263">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_360">Are we not going down a certain road with the word "derogation"? I have read about derogations for years. Sooner or later, a derogation comes along and there is a battle with Europe. We have seen that happen with animal medicines, the dairy side and many other derogations. There were so-called derogations for bogs. Are we kicking the can down the road in respect of derogations? In five, six or ten years' time will some Minister, through no fault of his or her own, have to say we are no longer getting a derogation, meaning the whole job is up in a heap? Are we walking ourselves into things that we should not agree to now? Should we instead put the boot in? Should we instead contact our MEPs? What is the advice from the Department? Can the Council of Ministers block some of the contracts to which the officials have referred? I am worried about ordinary farmers who will have to become involved in this. Farmers are not accountants; they try to farm the best they can. I do not want to put more stuff on top of them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_264">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_361">To clarify, we are talking about contracts between farmers and processor, distributor or retailer organisations across all of the sectors covered by the CMO. It covers beef, most of the meats, dairy, etc., subject to exemptions that are specified in the regulation. We consulted on this with farm bodies and stakeholders. The key thing stakeholders wanted was an assurance that any legislation would not inhibit their ability to negotiate the best price. In our discussions at European level, we sought to have as many exemptions as possible which Ireland can avail of.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_265">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_362">Can Ms Dunne answer one question I am trying to get to grips with. Maybe she has said it and I did not hear it right. Will an ordinary farmer selling 20 cattle or 40 or 50 sheep have an exemption whereby they do not need to have this contract? Are farmers bound by the regulation if they are not a purchasing group?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_266">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_363">The initial regulation proposed that it not apply to contracts of less than €10,000. That figure has now increased to €20,000, if I am correct.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_267">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_364">That is only seven or eight cattle.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_268">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_365">The officials will send us on a list of exemptions or derogations. We are over time and need to wrap up.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_269">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_366">I can send the Cathaoirleach the links to the draft regulation, which will list the exemptions and Council mandate.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_270">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_367">Thank you.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_271">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_368">It is stated that this refers to a contract of the duration of no longer than six months.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_272">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_369">It was in the briefing document circulated earlier. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_273">
          <from> Mr. Ultan Waldron<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_370">We can send on the link to the latest text. The six months referred to is for a revision clause. In the latest draft, that is out to 12 months.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_274">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_371">Can we block this if we are not happy? Can the Minister block this? I have concerns about some of this. I am worried about derogations.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_275">
          <from> Mr. Ultan Waldron<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_372">The way the regulation is currently written means that the member state in question, depending on the sector or commodity concerned, can avail of the derogation. We have to notify the Commission if we are availing of a derogation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_276">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_373">How long is the derogation for?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_277">
          <from> Mr. Ultan Waldron<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_374">I presume it would be exercised for the lifetime of the legislation or until such time as that might be changed. The list is available. For example, there are traditional and customary practices in respect of contracts under €20,000, as Ms Dunne said, relating to co-ops etc. They are listed in the regulation. One is for the milk sector and the other is for all other sectors.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_278">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_375">Could we get more information on that? The committee would be interested in examining this. The value of €20,000 today might include seven cattle if they are fit for killing. Could that be increased to €100,000 or whatever?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_279">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_376">We do not have to close off the conversation today. Once the officials send the details to us, we will be able to discuss this.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_280">
          <from> Ms Maria Dunne<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_377">We sent a briefing note before Christmas on it and we can update it. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_281">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_378">I thank the Chair. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_282">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-02T18:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_379">We can come back on it. </p>
          <p eId="para_380"> As there are no further matters for discussion, the meeting stands adjourned. </p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_7"> The joint committee adjourned at 6.10 p.m. until 3.30 p.m. on Wednesday, 9 July 2025.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
