<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#debates">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_public_petitions_and_the_ombudsmen/2025-05-20/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_public_petitions_and_the_ombudsmen/2025-05-20/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-05-20" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#author" href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/34/joint_committee_on_public_petitions_and_the_ombudsmen"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_public_petitions_and_the_ombudsmen/2025-05-20/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_public_petitions_and_the_ombudsmen/2025-05-20/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-05-20" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_public_petitions_and_the_ombudsmen/2025-05-20/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_public_petitions_and_the_ombudsmen/2025-05-20/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-05-21" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#debates">
        <TLCPerson eId="LouiseOReilly" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Louise-O'Reilly.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Louise O'Reilly"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/chair" showAs="Chair" eId="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/vice_chairman" showAs="Vice Chairman" eId="Vice_Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/author" showAs="author" eId="author"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/editor" showAs="editor" eId="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>AN COMHCHOISTE UM ACHAINÍOCHA ÓN BPOBAL AGUS NA HOMBUDSMAIN</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>Joint Committee on Public Petitions and the Ombudsmen</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2025-05-20">Dé Máirt, 20 Bealtaine 2025</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2025-05-20">Tuesday, 20 May 2025</docDate>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_en">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_ga">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">Tháinig an Comhchoiste le chéile ag 11:00 a.m.</summary>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">The Joint Committee met at 11:00 a.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_3">Comhaltaí a bhí i láthair / Members present:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_1">Teachtaí Dála / Deputies</p>
              </th>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_2">Seanadóirí / Senators</p>
              </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#PatBuckley">Pat Buckley</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#ChrisAndrews">Chris Andrews</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#AlbertDolan">Albert Dolan</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#ParaicBrady">Paraic Brady.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#MichaelMurphy">Michael Murphy</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#BrendanSmith">Brendan Smith.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_4">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#LouiseOReilly">Teachta / Deputy Louise O'Reilly sa Chathaoir / in the Chair.</person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Business of Joint Committee<recordedTime time="2025-05-20T11:00:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#LouiseOReilly" eId="spk_1">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-05-20T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_9">Apologies have been received from Deputy David Maxwell.</p>
          <p eId="para_10"> Before we proceed, I have a few housekeeping matters to go through. The first is that I make the following declaration. I do solemnly declare that I will duly and faithfully engage and, to the best of my knowledge and ability, execute the office of Cathaoirleach of the Joint Committee on Public Petitions and the Ombudsmen without fear or favour, apply the rules as laid down by the House in an impartial and fair manner, maintain order and uphold the rights and privileges of members in accordance with the Constitution and Standing Orders.</p>
          <p eId="para_11"> I remind members of the constitutional requirement that in order to participate in public meetings, members must be physically present within the confines of the Leinster House complex. Members of the committee attending remotely must do so from within the precincts of Leinster House. This is due to the constitutional requirement that in order to participate in public meetings, members must be physically present within the confines of the place where Parliament has chosen to sit. In this regard, I ask that, prior to the meeting, members participating via MS Teams confirm that they are on the grounds of Leinster House. This is not a very onerous thing to do but it is done for the sake of housekeeping. We will ask once, so we do not need to keep asking people.</p>
          <p eId="para_12"> Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice that they should not criticise or make charges against any person or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable or otherwise engage in speech that might be regarded as damaging to the good name of the person or entity. Therefore, if their statements are potentially defamatory with regard to an identifiable person or entity, I will direct them to discontinue their remarks. It is imperative that members comply with any such direction. I say that in full anticipation that it will not be needed.</p>
          <p eId="para_13"> I start by welcoming members of the committee and the secretariat. I know some of them while I will get to know others. I have served on many committees. I was elected in 2016 and have served on a good few committees such as the Oireachtas Committee on Health; the Oireachtas Committee on the Eighth Amendment of the Constitution; the Oireachtas Committee on the Future of Healthcare; the Oireachtas Committee on Enterprise, Trade and Employment; and the Oireachtas Committee on Members' Interests of Dáil Éireann. As such, I know the challenge ahead. This is my first time to be appointed as a committee Chair. It is a great honour to take up this appointment and I genuinely look forward to working with members.</p>
          <p eId="para_14"> I remind members present of the importance of this committee and the fact that we will hear from people who have most likely been through a few hoops - possibly more than a few hoops - and around the block before they get as far as us.</p>
          <p eId="para_15">Some will be weary from the battle that brought them to this committee. It is our job to make sure their experience here is a good one. While we will not be able to right every wrong, although we might want to, we should try to make sure people feel heard and seen.</p>
          <p eId="para_16"> I do not know whether I am unique among Members of the Oireachtas, but before I was elected I appeared before a number of committees, including the Committee of Public Accounts. It can be quite a gruelling experience for people to give evidence, and it is daunting. We will be in these committee rooms day in and day out. It is easy to breeze in and breeze out. We must remember that for those who come to give evidence, it might be their first time to ever set foot in the Leinster House complex. They might never come back again, so it is our job to make sure they get the most out of their hearing and that we get the most out of it on behalf of our constituents and the committee.</p>
          <p eId="para_17"> I thank the members of the secretariat. I am looking forward to working them. To members, this committee has done very good work in the past. It is our job as committee members to build on that and ensure we use all the resources at our disposal to make sure our work is thorough and relevant. We can all agree that is important.</p>
          <p eId="para_18"> If we so choose, we can elect a Leas-Chathaoirleach who will exercise my duties in the event that I cannot be here. I request nominations for the position of Leas-Chathaoirleach. Members might wish to consult one another - that is generally how it happens - and should get the nominations to the clerk by 23 May. Ideally, the election of the Leas-Chathaoirleach will take place at our next meeting. That is in order.</p>
          <p eId="para_19"> Given that we have done the required business for the public session, I suggest that we go into private session. Is that agreed? Agreed.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_5"> The joint committee went into private session at 11.07 a.m. and adjourned at 11.24 a.m. until 11 a.m. on Tuesday, 27 May 2025.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
