<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#debates">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_and_food/2025-09-24/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_and_food/2025-09-24/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-09-24" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#author" href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/34/joint_committee_on_agriculture_and_food"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_and_food/2025-09-24/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_and_food/2025-09-24/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-09-24" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_and_food/2025-09-24/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_and_food/2025-09-24/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-10-01" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#debates">
        <TLCPerson eId="AindriasMoynihan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Aindrias-Moynihan.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Aindrias Moynihan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="GillianToole" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Gillian-Toole.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Gillian Toole"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JoanneCollins" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Joanne-Collins.S.2025-01-29" showAs="Joanne Collins"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JoeCooney" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Joe-Cooney.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Joe Cooney"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MichaelFitzmaurice" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Michael-Fitzmaurice.D.2014-10-10" showAs="Michael Fitzmaurice"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="NatashaNewsomeDrennan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Natasha-Newsome-Drennan.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Natasha Newsome Drennan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaulDaly" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paul-Daly.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Paul Daly"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaulLawless" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paul-Lawless.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Paul Lawless"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="WilliamAird" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/William-Aird.D.2024-11-29" showAs="William Aird"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/chair" showAs="Chair" eId="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/vice_chairman" showAs="Vice Chairman" eId="Vice_Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/author" showAs="author" eId="author"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/editor" showAs="editor" eId="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>AN COMHCHOISTE UM THALMHAÍOCHT AGUS BIA</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>Joint Committee on Agriculture and Food</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2025-09-24">Dé Céadaoin, 24 Meán Fómhair 2025</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2025-09-24">Wednesday, 24 September 2025</docDate>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_en">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_ga">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">Tháinig an Comhchoiste le chéile ag 03:30 p.m.</summary>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">The Joint Committee met at 03:30 p.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_3">Comhaltaí a bhí i láthair / Members present:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_1">Teachtaí Dála / Deputies</p>
              </th>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_2">Seanadóirí / Senators</p>
              </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#WilliamAird">William Aird</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#JoanneCollins">Joanne Collins</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#JoeCooney">Joe Cooney</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#PaulDaly">Paul Daly.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#MichaelFitzmaurice">Michael Fitzmaurice</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#PaulLawless">Paul Lawless</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_9">
                  <person refersTo="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan">Natasha Newsome Drennan.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_4">I láthair / In attendance: Deputy Gillian Toole.</summary>
          <summary eId="sum_5">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#AindriasMoynihan">Teachta / Deputy Aindrias Moynihan sa Chathaoir / in the Chair.</person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Nitrates Derogation: Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:30:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_1">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_10">Apologies have been received from Deputies Kenny and Healy-Rae and Senators Brady and Lynch. Before we begin, I wish to bring to the committee's attention that witnesses giving evidence from within the parliamentary precincts are protected by absolute privilege in respect of the evidence they give to the committee. This means a witness has full defence in any defamation action for anything said at a committee meeting. However, witnesses are expected not to abuse this privilege and may be directed to cease giving evidence on an issue at the Chair's discretion. Witnesses should follow the direction of the Chair in this regard and are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that, as is reasonable, no adverse commentary should be made against an identifiable third person or entity. Witnesses giving evidence from a location outside the parliamentary precincts are asked to note they may not benefit from the same level of immunity from legal proceedings as witnesses giving evidence from within the parliamentary precincts and may consider it appropriate to take legal advice on the matter. Privilege against defamation does not apply to the publication by witnesses outside of the proceedings held by the committee of any matters arising from the proceedings. </p>
          <p eId="para_11"> Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that members should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the Houses or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable. Parliamentary privilege is considered to apply to the utterances of members participating online in a committee meeting when their participation is from within the parliamentary precincts. Members may not participate online in a public meeting from outside the parliamentary precincts. Any attempt to do so will result in the member having their online access removed. </p>
          <p eId="para_12"> Tá fáilte roimh na finnéithe chuig ár gcéad chruinniú poiblí tar éis an tsamhraidh. The agenda for our first session today is to examine the nitrates derogation. We have one hour and 15 minutes for this discussion. The committee will hear from the following officials from the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine: Mr. Bill Callanan, chief inspector; Mr. Ted Massey; senior inspector; and Dr. Daire Ó hUallacháin, principal officer and ecologist. The opening statements have been circulated to members. I will allow five minutes for the witnesses to read their opening statement into the record, or they can take two minutes to give a brief synopsis of it. We will then proceed to questions. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_2">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_13">I will take the time to read the statement into the record. I thank the committee for affording us the opportunity to attend today to discuss the important topic of the nitrates derogation. Securing a further nitrates derogation is a key priority for the Minister and the Government and is set out as such in the programme for Government. The current EU implementing decision granting Ireland a derogation concludes at the end of the year. Securing a renewal involves a detailed process, including developing a nitrates action programme, which sets down the basic requirements for all farmers. While responsibility for the nitrates action programme lies with the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage, the Department of Agriculture, Food and Marine plays a significant role. The derogation process also includes making a number of presentations to the EU nitrates committee, which is made up of all member states, securing its support and finally agreement, along with that of the Commission on all aspects. It is the Commission that proposes the implementing decision granting a derogation. </p>
          <p eId="para_14"> The derogation is contingent on measures to reduce the impact of agriculture on water quality. The legal provisions underpinning the derogation lay down parameters that include a long growing season, crops with high nitrogen requirements and high precipitation or rainfall levels. Ireland’s pasture-based system satisfies these criteria.</p>
          <p eId="para_15"> The derogation is also dependent on improving water quality. There continues to be an unprecedented and significant level of engagement and support right across the Government, farmers and the broader agrifood industry, who are all focused on the one common objective of improving water quality. Last year, the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine published its plan, Water and Agriculture - a collaborative approach, which underpins the work of the Department towards improving water quality - a precursor, as identified, to the delivery of a derogation.</p>
          <p eId="para_16">This plan includes supporting farmers in a very targeted way through a free on-farm advisory service whereby approximately 50 advisers are visiting farmers under the ASSAP programme. This is coupled with a €60 million European Innovation Partnership which grant-aids farmers to implement targeted actions above regulatory requirements to improve water quality. Additionally, there are many actions under the ACRES agri-environment scheme supporting this objective. Finally, the plan includes a commitment to introduce an exempted development threshold for stand-alone manure storage under the planning regulations and members will note significant progress to this end recently.</p>
          <p eId="para_17"> Ireland will have to demonstrate compliance with the habitats directive. The Minister, Deputy Heydon, met Commissioner Roswall yesterday regarding Ireland’s nitrates derogation and this follows a visit by senior officials from the Directorate-General for Environment, DG ENV, in recent weeks. By way of update on the process required in securing a derogation, Ireland has now made three presentations at the EU nitrates committee in Brussels, the most recent of which was last Friday.</p>
          <p eId="para_18"> Engagement with national stakeholders has also been a key component of our approach. Since this committee’s meeting in late May, the agriculture water quality working group has met a further four times. From the start of this year, the group has been very much involved in developing the measures for the next nitrates action programme. We are now at the stage where the Ministers, Deputies Heydon and Browne, are reflecting and finalising the proposed measures that Deputy Browne will bring forward for public consultation in the coming weeks under the nitrates action programme alongside the draft Natura impact statement and the draft strategic environmental assessment that must accompany it.</p>
          <p eId="para_19"> Over the coming months, the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine, the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage and the broader Government will continue to work together and to engage with stakeholders at a national and European level on the next nitrates action programme and the nitrates derogation. That will ensure we get the best possible outcome for Ireland post 2025. </p>
          <p eId="para_20"> My colleagues and I are happy to answer any questions members may have about progress being made on this important issue.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_3">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_21">The whole issue around the nitrates directive is hugely concerning for many farmers. They want to ensure every effort is made to hold on to that derogation for us.</p>
          <p eId="para_22"> In relation to the habitats directive, the Minister proposed river catchment analysis done by ecologists within the Department. Are there many people in the Department to do the likes of that? How long will it take?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_4">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_23">I will bring the Chairman back to the beginning. The nitrates derogation is contingent on having a nitrates action programme. That has to be agreed and when in place, from a regulatory point of view, the opportunity to secure a derogation is available to a country. It has always been a requirement for us to comply with the habitats directive. That has been the case since the instigation. I have been involved since 2010 and that has been done at plan level. The overall nitrates action plan is accompanied by a Natura assessment and an appropriate assessment under the habitats directive.</p>
          <p eId="para_24"> Case law has evolved since then, particularly driven by the 2018 Dutch nitrates case, which identified we need to consider this at a more granular level to ensure we are compliant. Its direction was that agricultural activity may constitute an impact in terms of Natura. We are challenged by that requirement and are looking to develop a plan to generate compliance with that specific requirement for habitats compliance at a more granular level than just the plan. We propose to do it at a catchments level. We have engaged Daire Ó hUallacháin, who is originally from Teagasc. We have also engaged an external consultant on how to design that.</p>
          <p eId="para_25"> The next stage, which the Chairman is talking about, is conducting such assessments. That is a job of work yet to be determined in terms of how it is constructed, the requirements involved and the time period it will take to deliver it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_5">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_26">So there is an unknown all the time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_6">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_27">There is an element of work to be done on that. The Minister has been clear we will need time do that and do it robustly. It is important that all farmers are treated equally as a result of that and that we do not have, for example, outcomes for a particular catchment area that was selected early being known before everybody else's. All farmers should receive outcomes regarding assessments of catchments at the same time. That is our objective.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_7">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_28">So one catchment will be done at a time but all the results will be published at the end.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_8">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_29">Correct.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_9">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_30">Has the Department not taken a measure of how much work will be involved or how many people will be needed to do it?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_10">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_31">It will be significant. We are scoping out how much work it will take. It will certainly take some time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_11">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_32">How many ecologists does the Department currently have?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_12">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_33">We have a significant number of ecologists in the Department working on afforestation licensing. That is a combination of in-house and people being procured for that work. For this action, we will have to scope out how many ecologists will be needed for detailed assessment to be done.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_13">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_34">So there is not a measure taken of that yet.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_14">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_35">Not at this point.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_15">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_36">The decision times are at the end of the year. It is getting tight.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_16">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_37">Certainly. We are identifying to the Commission the need for a plan to deliver that. It cannot be constructed or delivered by the end of the year in any sort of robust way. That is our position.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_17">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_38">Okay. I will be brief as I want to give members an opportunity. Mr. Callanan could not cover everything in his opening statement but one big ingredient recently was the EPA report. That was not helpful to Ireland's case and will be a significant player. What happened there? Where is the move? How can that case be-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_18">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_39">Does Mr. Massey want to start in terms of dealing with the report?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_19">
          <from> Mr. Ted Massey<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_40">Yes. Last week the EPA published early insight data covering 20 rivers we know to be representative of the national situation. The report was solely focused on nitrate concentration in those rivers and showed an increase on last year. The report for last year was very positive in that it showed our levels were the lowest they had been since about 2016. This year, concentration had gone up but the EPA report states that requires further investigation because there are a number of things that influence the concentration in water. They are weather, agricultural land management and the nutrient or source load present in the environment.</p>
          <p eId="para_41"> When we consider the EPA data, we must first set it in context. While it is obviously disappointing the levels went up, they are only marginally higher than in 2022 for the same rivers and well below the same period in 2023. We should also think back to the weather in the first six months of the year, which was relatively dry. In many of those rivers, the rate of flow was less than it would have been historically in a normal year. The rate of flow will have an influence on the concentration of nutrients and on how nutrients move through the soil, in terms of rainfall.</p>
          <p eId="para_42"> There is a job of work to be done to identity what has happened there. One thing I would take from the report is nitrates concentration increased in all those rivers in all areas of the country. It was not just in areas which tend to have more derogation farmers; it was in all areas. That, to my mind, points to the weather having a greater role to play.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_20">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_43">Trends in water quality have to be looked at over a period. We had an improving trend until 2015-16; then there was a period a negative trend in water quality.</p>
          <p eId="para_44">Certainly over the past couple of years, that has reverted to an improving trend overall, although we all remain disappointed in terms of the initial data for 2025.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_21">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_45">I thank Mr. Callanan. I have two speakers offering and I am sure everyone wants to come in. We will keep to seven minutes each and try to keep tight to the time. I call Deputy Aird.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_22">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_46">I welcome the witnesses. They are not coming with the positive news we would hope to have as regards what was done in the rivers and all of that scientific evidence. I hope the next time around the news might be better. I cannot understand how we, or some people, are talking about the end of the year. We do not have a hope of doing all that work by the end of the year. I presume we will get an extension to the derogation. I presume the Minister and his officials have discussed all that.</p>
          <p eId="para_47"> As a farmer, I know how important the derogation is to the Irish food industry and the wider community that feeds off the farming community. The derogation allows us farmers to maximise the advantages of our grass-based system, about which we have all spoken over the years. I have written down six questions that I would like the witnesses to answer. I will go through them quickly. Will the Department provide an account of the engagement with the European Commission around the reduction in the derogation limit from 250 kg N/ha to 220 kg N/ha? Will the Department confirm that all possible political and technical avenues have been exhausted to maintain the 250 kg N/ha limit?</p>
          <p eId="para_48"> What scientific basis did the Commission refer to when requiring Ireland to reduce the derogation limit? Will the Department publish the assessment it has made of the economic impact the derogation cut will have on all farmers in Ireland, according to the main commodity, and on the rural hinterland, particularly in the high-production counties to which the Cathaoirleach alluded a moment ago?</p>
          <p eId="para_49"> Has the Department proposed alternative compliance tools to the Commission to demonstrate Ireland's environmental progress, such as neutral catchment, precision fertiliser use, which we are doing, and the considerable investment we all made in slurry management? That investment was made on every farm that was involved in any way with cattle throughout the Twenty-six Counties.</p>
          <p eId="para_50"> In the interests of transparency, will the Department publish all documentation and correspondence it has had with the European Commission in respect of the nitrates derogation? Will the Department outline how often it has engaged with Irish MEPs, the permanent representation in Brussels and the Commission on our behalf during this process? Could more political pressure be applied before we come to an outcome? Those are the questions I present today.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_23">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_51">In general terms, we must recognise that we are all on the one page in respect of the importance of the continuance of the derogation and the availability. It is recognised within the programme for Government. As I set out in the opening statement, it is a priority indicated by the Minister in terms of all engagements.</p>
          <p eId="para_52"> On political pressure, the simple reality is that this matter has been raised by the Taoiseach with the Commission President, Commissioner von der Leyen, and I do not think you can get any higher in terms of bringing political pressure to bear to highlight the importance to Ireland of a continued derogation.</p>
          <p eId="para_53"> The Deputy asked about correspondence. The Department always has an open policy in respect of its correspondence.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_24">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_54">Will Mr. Callanan answer the questions in the order they were asked? I thank him.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_25">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_55">I have taken a note. I hope I have done so faithfully.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_26">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_56">That is grand. I will remind Mr. Callanan if he has not. I thank him.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_27">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_57">The Deputy asked about the reduction from 250 kg N/ha to 220 kg N/ha. In negotiating a nitrates derogation, we must recognise that the process is very detailed. It requires presentations to the nitrates committee. It also comprises engagement with the Commission, which ultimately proposes the derogation for vote and require confidence that it will not have a negative impact. As part of that, in the decision of 2022 there was the inclusion by the Commission quite late in the day of a caveat stating that water quality had disimproved. The Commission wanted evidence to ensure we were going to get back on the right track in that regard. Let us call a spade a spade: cow numbers had expanded significantly in the previous period. Water quality had generally declined. The Commission wanted comfort that Ireland was on the correct path to improve water quality. That was the key driver in terms of the-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_28">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_58">Drop.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_29">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_59">-----drop from 250 kg N/ha to 220 kg N/ha. We must recognise that, going way back to 1992, the same principle of declining water quality across the Benelux countries was the rationale for the introduction of the directive at that time. It became a clear request and demand from the Commission in terms of the granting of a derogation. That was the basis for the reasoning. It was quite linked to an interim review, with specific conditions identifying those areas where water quality was declining.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_30">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_60">I am watching the time. Will Mr. Callanan answer the second question? I only have a limited time. What scientific basis did the Commission refer to when requiring Ireland to reduce the derogation? What did it say to us?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_31">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_61">There were four criteria. They were published. I will ask Mr. Massey in a moment to go through where those areas that were the subject of a drop from 250 kg N/ha to 220 kg N/ha should apply. The criteria were specific and direct. They were based on water quality data.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_32">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_62">My third question related to the assessment made.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_33">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_63">We have already published the request. We have asked Teagasc to do five pieces of work, including an economic assessment, and that document has been published on the Teagasc website for a number of weeks.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_34">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_64">My next question was about the Department's proposal of alternative compliance tools to the Commission.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_35">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_65">Let us call a spade a spade: the ultimate arbiter here is water quality. That is ultimately how one is adjudicated in terms of compliance.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_36">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_66">I asked whether in the interests of transparency the Department would publish all documentation and correspondence it had with the European Commission in respect of the nitrates derogation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_37">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_67">Yes, in time, but let us be clear-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_38">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_68">When?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_39">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_69">I want to be clear. There is a reality here that as policy is in progress and engagement with the Commission is ongoing, etc., it is not appropriate to publish. Thereafter, it will be a matter for the Commission in terms of any letters it would have sent to us and a matter for the Department in respect of any letters that would have been sent to the Commission. There is a process there.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_40">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_70">I am coming to my last question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_41">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_71">All policy, until it is concluded, complies with those principles. It is a matter for the Commission to decide about any engagement material it has sent to us. Generally, there would not be a decision on that until after the conclusion of the whole process. It is the same with any policy.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_42">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_72">The Commission would not be able to share it while the process is under way. It seems that afterwards, we should be able to see correspondence.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_43">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_73">I can come back. My time is up.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_44">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_74">I welcome the officials. They are often here in an us-and-them scenario. However, I accept, as I think everybody out there does, that we are all on the one side on this issue. There is nothing to be gained from us arguing with them or telling them what they already know. I accept the bona fides of the Department and Minister. I have discussed the issue at length with the Taoiseach and Mr. Callanan is quite right that he has taken it to the highest level with Ms von der Leyen. We are all on the one page on the issue. How we get it over the line is the question. We need to show that united front. If can play around with a Winston Churchill quote, never before were so many dependent on so few. This is not just about derogation farmers. Let us consider the amount of money invested in stainless steel in creameries and processing plants that will not function without milk. Let us consider the amount of jobs that those processors have created. There are people out there who probably do not know what a derogation is but whose jobs are in jeopardy if we do not maintain the derogation. With that in mind, I am not going to give the witnesses a hard time but they must keep up the battle.</p>
          <p eId="para_75"> I have a few questions that are mainly based on correlation and what has happened with us being requested to do the appropriate assessment. Deputy Aird has covered the time issue. This derogation ends on 31 December. We are in the mouth of October now. There is no way all the appropriate assessments in the catchment areas are going to be done. Are we talking to the Commission about an extension? What do the witnesses see?</p>
          <p eId="para_76">There has to be a plan B for 1 January. Is there a plan B? What if somebody out there, in his or her wisdom, decides that this has to be done before we can get our next derogation and there will be no extension in the interim? Common sense will say that will not happen but we all know where common sense comes into a lot of these things.</p>
          <p eId="para_77"> How much of this has been influenced by the An Taisce case, if the witnesses can comment? I appreciate that they probably cannot.</p>
          <p eId="para_78"> On the EPA results last week, Mr. Massey rightly said that this needed to be looked at over a period of time. It does not make sense from an agricultural perspective to say the nitrates content in the water is up when we have proof that the use of artificial fertiliser is down. Has anybody ever shown correlation between stocking density and water quality in the specific areas where there are derogations and the stock numbers are high? I do not think that correlation has been shown. Is that not a case we have to make, in that there are more pollutants than agriculture and dairy farming?</p>
          <p eId="para_79"> The witnesses might comment on those questions and if I have time left, I have another couple. I want to hear their comments on what I have said. I know they cannot disclose during the negotiation process much of the communication that has happened, but surely to God there is conversation at this stage about an interim extension while we are doing what we were asked to do. We have never said we will not do what the Commission has asked us to do.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_6">
          <i>Deputy William Aird took the Chair.</i>
        </summary>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_45">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_80">On the bigger general question about our approach, the Commission has been clear in its request of us. We have to provide assurances of compliance with the habitats directive. Is this linked to the An Taisce case? Not particularly, as the Commission side is very clear. Effectively, the 2018 Dutch nitrates case saw a ruling, which has subsequently been reaffirmed in quite a number of other rulings, about the requirement to assess where it may have an impact. In that situation, the Commission's request of Ireland - it is naturally a matter for Ireland to demonstrate compliance - is to prove we are taking account of that ruling within our process and procedure of granting derogations. Quite simply, a derogation process requires us to grant consent. When we are granting consent, we have to comply with the habitats directive. Ultimately, that is what this plan has to address.</p>
          <p eId="para_81"> I will be clear. We have articulated very clearly about the reality of having all that work done by 1 January and what is needed to do that level of work. We have a lot of experience in the Department about appropriate assessment, particularly in light of the requirements on the forestry side. We are identifying the need for a plan in terms of generating compliance and how that might be done; we can articulate how that is based on a catchment approach. Those are conversations we have been having about demonstrating the approach to it.</p>
          <p eId="para_82"> In terms of pressures, the reality is agriculture is identified by the EPA as a significant pressure in locations. That is a factor of all farming types. It should not just be identified as simply an issue of high stocking rates. There is no doubting that in our minds. When we grant a derogation, we have additional conditions and requirements that are placed on farmers in derogation to effectively mitigate some of that. All sectors will have to contribute towards that objective of improving water quality. That is demonstrated in the collaborative approach we have taken and the engagement with all the various sectors on what can be done by all of them. However, there is a pressure associated with agriculture and we have to mitigate that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_46">
          <from> Dr. Daire Ó hUallacháin<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_83">I can come in on water quality and this reiterates what Mr. Massey said. While the results were disappointing for the first six months, they need to be taken into a longer trend context but we also must take flow into account. Water flow was significantly reduced for the first six months of the year, particularly for March and April. We could have more or less the same number of nutrients moving in the system as we had last year, but because the flow has been a lot lower, the concentration could be higher. Ultimately, the load might be smaller or lower but the concentration is higher. That could be one of the-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_47">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_84">Sorry to interrupt but my time is nearly up. Would that not be taken into consideration? For want of a better phrase, let us call them laboratory conditions. I remember from my own college days that, if one is doing a test, one takes the variables into consideration. If there is low flow, one factors that into the results. We seem to blame the farmer and it does not matter whether there was a low flow, high flow, what the weather conditions were or whatever. There seems to be a little bit of that going on.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_48">
          <from> Dr. Daire Ó hUallacháin<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_85">I cannot really comment on how the EPA report its results but for a long time now, it has been reporting in relation to the concentration of water bodies. To allow comparison with previous data, it still needs to report on concentration. In more recent years and towards the end of year, it reports on the load from our 20 major catchments. It might be useful to wait until the end of the year to see what the load for this year is relative to last year and compare that to longer term trends. By providing both concentration and load, one gets a better overall picture of the amount of nutrients moving through the system.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_49">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_86">I thank the witnesses for coming in today and making their presentation. Water quality is important and vital, as is protecting the farming community going forward. That is why it is important to try to see if it is at all possible to at least maintain what we have. On water quality in the EPA report, from 2024 to 2025, was there a massive change in water quality or was it small? The EPA was happy in 2024 but there now seems to be more of a concern in 2025. Will someone outline how much of a change there was and was it major over that period?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_50">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_87">I will give an overview. We are getting fixated on one year. The reality is the Commission looks at this over a period and at the overall trend. We need to reflect on that because, ultimately, that is the arbiter of whether we are going in the right direction in terms of water quality. Post 2024 and 2025, the water quality trend was not moving in the right direction. That has improved over recent years, albeit we accept that the preliminary finding for 2025 is not positive.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_51">
          <from> Mr. Ted Massey<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_88">To build on that reply, the data published last week by the EPA shows a 16% increase in nitrate concentration in those rivers involved in its monitoring compared to 2024. In 2024, however, it was down 10% on what was a much higher level in 2023. As Mr. Callanan has said, it is very important not to become fixated on short periods of time when we are talking about water because we know nitrate levels will fluctuate. The Minister, Deputy Heydon, has been very measured in his response to the EPA data for 2024 because we knew weather and other factors could lead to data going the other way but it is important to look at the long term trend, as Mr. Callanan has said. If one looks at the EPA reports of recent years on nitrate concentration, they confirm there is a declining number of rivers with elevated nitrate levels overall. While our data for the first six months of this year is obviously a concern, we have to look at the longer term data because that is what will count.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_52">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_89">Very good. The other side of it is the question of whether agriculture is totally responsible for the water quality issues. Could there be some other issues out there that are affecting water quality? We are well aware of wastewater. Could that be an issue, with the farmers maybe getting blamed for its effects? Will one of the witnesses respond to that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_53">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_90">In its reporting, the EPA has identified where the pressures are modelled and coming from. Agriculture is the largest but there are also wastewater, forestry and other impacts that have to be taken into account. That depends on the river catchment that is impacted. In broad terms, the EPA has identified that there are pressures from various sources. That is clear. Agriculture is not the sole pressure in terms of water quality but the evidence highlights that agriculture has a part to play in improving water quality. That is undeniable.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_54">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_91">It has a part to play but my belief is other organisations have a part to play as well to get water quality up to a good standard.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_55">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_92">There is no doubt. We all agree with that as a principle in terms of the contribution from the various sectors where improvement is needed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_56">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_93">As regards the public consultation, when is that taking place? Is there a date for it and what way is it being done throughout the country?</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_7">
          <i>Deputy Aindrias Moynihan resumed the Chair.</i>
        </summary>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_57">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_94">The public consultation to which the Deputy is referring is about the nitrates action programme, which comprises the actions that apply to all farmers and not just derogation farmers.</p>
          <p eId="para_95">That will commence in a matter of weeks. It is currently with the Ministers, Deputies Browne and Heydon, regarding what measures are being put out for public consultation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_58">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_96">So we are not exactly sure what measures are going out at the moment.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_59">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_97">That is a matter for decision regarding what goes for public consultation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_60">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_98">Is it going to be possible to maintain what we have - the 250 kg N/ha and 220 kg N/ha rates - as they are?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_61">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_99">All I can articulate is what Ireland's ask is in relation to it. It is very much around maintaining the 220 kg N/ha and 250 kg N/harates. Naturally, there is an engagement process here with the Commission. I cannot pre-empt its side of it. It is clearly Ireland's ask regarding the continuation of derogation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_62">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_100">We know it is going to be important for the farming community going forward to try to maintain what we have. We do not want to see rural parts of the country suffering again because of more restrictions put on them. There are a lot of concerns among the farming community. I hope that will not be the situation going forward, so I hope we will be able to maintain what we have while keeping our water qualities at a high standard as well, which is important.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_63">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_101">The only thing I wish to bring to the Deputy's attention is the level of engagement we have had with stakeholders through the water quality group. We have had 28 or 29 meetings at this point with that group in relation to ensuring that all stakeholders are engaged with the process of improving water quality and being kept up to speed on the work we are doing, the engagement we are having, and the necessary evidence we are collating in terms of underpinning Ireland's application for derogation, as well as how we progress on compliance with the habitats directive. It has been unprecedented in my history, and I was involved in the 2010 negotiations on derogation, so I have been around for a while in relation to this. We are hugely engaged with all stakeholders, including industry, processors and farmers, to ensure that everybody is fully cognisant of the work that needs to be done and the work we are doing.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_64">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_102">We are also well aware, in fairness, of what the stakeholders have invested in trying to the meet criteria that are required and the big investment that has gone in.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_65">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_103">It is a bit like school buses. As we get back to school, it is the first morning of school that we find out whether we have a got a ticket. I understand and we all agree that we have to do our best to keep this. It is all about water quality, which we need. On the 20 rivers, which I presume are spaced out, do we have information on what rivers are tested and at what positions they are tested? Is it one point in each river? Is it numerous points on each river? It would be handy to know if they were on the back of a large farm or industrial sites and to have an idea of where the data is being collected. How far back do these reports go? Are they done every six months? Is it a six-month data collection or what way do the reports come out?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_66">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_104">The caution I have is that a number of the questions the Deputy is asking are more relevant to the EPA, which is responsible for the reporting. However, we can draw attention to what is in the reports that have been published. More recently, the EPA has moved towards that six-month timeframe indicative reporting on foot of requests for more timely reporting. That is what has prompted that change. That has only happened in the past couple of years. Last year and this year were the first years that had those six-month reports.</p>
          <p eId="para_105"> Are the rivers identified? Yes, they are, and they are right around the country. The question of the frequency of sampling is more detailed. Does Dr. Ó hUallacháin wish to come in?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_67">
          <from> Dr. Daire Ó hUallacháin<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_106">I will let Mr. Massey comment first. I will then come in.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_68">
          <from> Mr. Ted Massey<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_107">To answer the question what rivers these are, the report published by the EPA last week and which is on its website contains a map clearly showing the location of the 20 rivers. The agency makes the point that it is looking at the monitoring stations located at the most downstream available sites on these rivers. That is the most accurate place to get a true picture of what is happening in that catchment overall. In terms of the frequency of monitoring, I am not sure if the EPA report mentions that. As Mr. Callanan said, that is a question for the EPA.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_69">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_108">It would be good to get a better picture weather-wise if that report was done more frequently. It is easy to out and collect a little bit of water. The figure of 16% may not be 16% on another day if we have heavy rain - that is the idea I am getting. For example, if there is heavy rainfall, are the waters flowing more quickly and is the concentration therefore lower?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_70">
          <from> Dr. Daire Ó hUallacháin<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_109">I will answer some of these questions. There are thousands of sampling points throughout the country. On the 20 major rivers, as Mr. Massey said, they reflect what is going on in the full catchment because we are now at the outlet. There is continuous data that are capturing flow for every day in these major catchments. They are collecting data on nutrients monthly, typically. For other sites throughout the country, it is being collected quarterly. There are sites throughout the country that are sampled but they are not being sampled for nutrients. However, they are being sampled for ecology because ecology is a reflector or indicator of the water quality.</p>
          <p eId="para_110"> The EPA would be in a better position to give the full suite of measures. All of these data are available on the EPA website. We should not get overly bogged down on the indicator report it has given. That is reflective of the 20 major rivers for the first six months. It is about the longer term trends for the wider suite of rivers and other parameters. The publication from last week related to nitrogen. There are other reports going to come out relating to phosphorus and ecology as well. We will then get a better full picture of the potential stressors that are in these systems.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_71">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_111">Until we got those levels down, we are in a bit of bother when we are trying to fight our case.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_72">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_112">The way I have described it to farmers is that we have a unique production system in the EU in Ireland as a grass-based grain-fed system without outdoor grazing, etc. With the likes of the UK having left, that is not commonplace across Europe. Many of them are housed system. However, as a member of the European Union, we are not unique in our commitment to the achievement of water framework directive, which requires the achievement of good status. Neither are we unique in our requirements to comply with the habitats directive. That is universal. We have to charter a pathway to ensure compliance with the requirements of those directives. That is common to all, but not in how we do it because we have an outdoor-based system in Ireland.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_73">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_113">If we use France as an example, is it doing the same testing as Ireland? Are we the better boys in the class than France is? Where do we rank in the world?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_74">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_114">Generally speaking, our water would be in the top third of European member states. I think we are number 13. It depends on whether it is ground water, river water, etc. We are not best in class, but we are certainly a long way from worst in class for our overall water quality. I have been involved in this since 2010. At that time, Germany was applying for derogation. At one point, the Po Valley of Italy applied for derogation. Belgium, Denmark, Holland, Ireland and the UK, including Northern Ireland, were all applying for the availability of a derogation. Most of those countries have now moved away from applying for a derogation. Germany no longer applies. At this time, Ireland and the Netherlands are the only countries with a derogation. The Dutch one concludes at the end of this year. It has written to the Commission but it has not moved at the pace Ireland is at with presentations to the nitrates committee, which is a necessary precursor to securing a positive vote.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_75">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_115">There was recently a meeting. When is the next presentation the witnesses have to make?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_76">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_116">There are four meetings in the year.</p>
          <p eId="para_117">We have done the three presentations, which are necessary requirements. It remains to be seen as to whether we face a vote, effectively, in December at the next meeting. That is effectively contingent on a proposal from the Commission in relation to a continuation of the derogation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_77">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_118">I thank Mr. Callanan very much.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_78">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_119">The witnesses are very welcome today. It is such an important issue. Like Senator Paul Daly said, I appreciate their work in relation to this. I appreciate a lot has been answered, and I will keep it brief. Perhaps this is for the EPA really, but there is a huge amount of energy and focus on farmers when it comes to water quality. In all of the reports and so on, it is all focusing on farmers and talk about agricultural catchment areas and the monitoring of farmers, etc. Is Mr. Callanan satisfied that industry and the EPA is monitoring industry and other sectors as well as it is monitoring farmers? A several pronged approach is necessary here. My fear and concern is that it seems we are focusing nearly exclusively on farmers in relation to it. What engagement, contribution, work and collaboration has the Department with the Department of housing in respect of other areas, particularly around industry?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_79">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_120">In terms of our engagement with stakeholders, this is a question that arises. We have added the EPA into the water quality working group to identify how it has come up with its modelling and how the water quality stats are being compiled so that it is very open and transparent. As we have set out, there are many pressures, and industry is one of them. Agriculture is also a pressure. However, we do have to recognise that the evidence and data that is being collected at catchment level is growing exponentially. That has to be understood by farmers as well.</p>
          <p eId="para_121"> If the Deputy looks at our objectives in terms of engaging with farmers, they have been around a number of clear targets that we wanted to do. Number one was whether we have the right actions in the right place. We divide that into three categories. First, have we the right legislation in place, which is the action programme and the requirements of derogation farmers? Have we the right support, that is, the advisers, etc., as I put out in the EIP? Have we the support structures, such as, for example, the Teagasc advisory programme to assist farmers? However, we have to remember that there is scrutiny by the EPA in relation to the other pressures as well, such as licensed units. There is a hell of a lot of scrutiny for those in terms of the licensing conditions in which they operate as establishment. There is also scrutiny by the EPA of wastewater treatment plants, etc. There is, therefore, increased scrutiny on all sectors, and agriculture cannot deny its responsibility in terms of ensuring what is done in our sector is towards that objective of improving water quality rather than asking what other sectors are doing.</p>
          <p eId="para_122"> I describe that in many ways the nitrates action programme is around almost ensuring that the best practices are applied by all farmers. When we look back, committees like this would have debated the instances of calendar farming, by way of example, which was very emotive as everybody will recall. Now, the reality is that there is a recognition by the vast majority of farmers of the value of slurry and that it should be applied at the right time, and they are quite annoyed, let us say, when they see non-compliance by others in terms of poor practice. That is the reality of the action programme. It is effectively ensuring that the best practices are applied by all farmers. That is the way we would look at it. I described it at one stage as a backstop, effectively, from a legislative point of view. We know a lot of our best farmers are ahead of the standard in terms of whether it is the use of their slurries, nutrient management on their farms, ensuring there are no losses coming from farmyards in terms of management of rainwater, etc. In simple terms, all sectors are being scrutinised now like never before. The data is at a greater granularity now than ever before.</p>
          <p eId="para_123"> I spoke at an EPA conference last year, and the Local Authority Waters Programme, LAWPRO, did a presentation afterwards. The level of data and knowledge at catchment level is growing exponentially. Farmers need to be aware and educated of water quality locally to understand how their practice on their farms impacts on water quality locally. That is where the likes of the Teagasc programme for water is very beneficial, the signpost series, etc., in terms of that education piece.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_80">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_124">I appreciate that this may have already been asked as I was in the Dáil at the start of the meeting, but can Mr. Callanan give farmers an outline of the timeframe over the next few months in terms of engagements with the Department, the Commission, etc.? When will farmers have an update on this?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_81">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_125">We are meeting the water quality group very regularly. That is under the chairmanship of Mr. John Comer, who is an independent chair. As we said, eight meetings have been held this year. We constantly update the stakeholders in terms of our level of engagement and where we will step out this process from here until the end of the year, and that will continue.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_82">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_126">What about the Commission and the extension?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_83">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_127">By way of example, as the Deputy will note, the Minister issued a press release that Commissioner Roswall will in the months ahead come on a visit to Ireland. We already had a visit from the Commission officials last week, including the visit to a derogation farm, to ensure there is a very good understanding on that side of the table in terms of what our ask is and what the conditions are in Ireland. Equally, however, it is asking us for assurances in relation to compliance with the habitats that we will have to address.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_84">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_128">I thank Mr. Callanan.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_85">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_129">We have about a quarter of an hour. Members may have two minutes each.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoanneCollins" eId="spk_86">
          <from>Senator Joanne Collins<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_130">I have one very quick question. I thank the witnesses very much for being here and for giving up their time. Mr. Callanan said that this has to be decided by 31 December. Is there a chance that it is going to be extended or are farmers going to have a situation come 1 January where this could be completely pulled until everything is put together, if that falls after 31 December?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_87">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_131">We have been very clear that a lacuna or a period without derogation is not an option here in relation to it. In terms of voting, to remind people, there are four meetings in the year and, previously, we did not have a vote until March. That is not the end of the world in terms of availability of a derogation because it covers the year in question. We have never gone beyond March, but it has happened that we have had a March vote rather than a December vote.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoanneCollins" eId="spk_88">
          <from>Senator Joanne Collins<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_132">Therefore, Mr. Callanan will be pushing for an extension if it is a thing that-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_89">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_133">Our objective here is to secure a four-year derogation period. That is in line with the directive in terms of provision in that it is a four-year cycle here.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoanneCollins" eId="spk_90">
          <from>Senator Joanne Collins<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_134">Okay. I thank Mr. Callanan. I just wanted to check for the farmers if there was going to be a possibility come 1 January that it was not in place, and we are pushing to make sure. It is great that we are all heading towards and have the same goals, which is amazing. It is just that we will have those farmers who are going to be waiting for the news and the stress it will cause waiting just to know that-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_91">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_135">We all agree. We understand that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoanneCollins" eId="spk_92">
          <from>Senator Joanne Collins<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_136">That is great. I thank Mr. Callanan so much.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_93">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_137">I will ask a question on the habitats. There were a couple of issues that arose. We can work to get down to test the quality of the water and we can identify the source eventually, and we will get there. However, a habitat is something that I cannot get my head around because a habitat is something that if we touch it, we have broken the habitat. Can Mr. Callanan just explain that when he gets a second?</p>
          <p eId="para_138"> We are talking today about free flow and rivers. Looking back at this country 50 or 60 years ago, I can remember the dredger as a little boy. We used to love to see the dredger coming. The dredger is gone; it has ceased operation. The rivers are all overgrowing. There are trees lying in the rivers. The debris and sludge in the rivers and everything are nearly up to the top of the banks at this stage.</p>
          <p eId="para_139">The flow in rivers is nearly gone completely. Anybody will tell you that; just ask any old person about the depth of the bank. I spoke to an 84-year-old man the other night while walking the river with him where he was getting flooded. He told me that, at one time, if someone slid in off the bank, he or she would have to get pulled up out of it. Now, if one is not careful, one could walk off the bank into the river. The water is level with it. Is the likes of that making a difference?</p>
          <p eId="para_140"> I will say one other thing at this stage. We all know about the number of roads and estates that have been built and all the different developments that have taken place. We also know about all the run-off from the roads. I see it myself when it rains. All of that is going into the one river as well. There is only one river in most towns and villages in this country. In my case, the River Triogue takes every drop of water out of the town of Portlaoise until it joins the River Barrow at two places. Surely, we have to take that into consideration. As was said, it cannot be just the farmer on his own.</p>
          <p eId="para_141"> Will the Department outline how often it has engaged with Irish MEPs and the permanent representation in Brussels? They will make the decision at the end of the day. That is fierce important. They will vote on this, the very same as us in the Dáil Chamber. Are the officials happy enough that all of that engagement has taken place?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_94">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_142">It is not the MEPs who vote on this. To be clear, it is member states that vote on derogations.</p>
          <p eId="para_143"> I will draw people's attention to another thing. It is important that farmers understand that the actions they are taking to improve water quality are exactly the same actions that would be required for compliance with the habitats directive. We have to make sure that we are not giving conflicting messages to farmers. A good habitat in terms of water impact is also improved by good actions that are done to improve water quality. Dr. Ó hUallacháin will speak on the other part of that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_95">
          <from> Dr. Daire Ó hUallacháin<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_144">The area of focus we have relates to designated habitats. These are habitats that have been identified-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_96">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_145">In a river.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_97">
          <from> Dr. Daire Ó hUallacháin<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_146">Not just in a river. It is any designated habitat identified by the NPWS, which includes special areas of conservation and special protection areas because those are what are protected under the habitats directive. There are 600 or so of these designated habitats throughout the country. Each habitat is designated for a certain species, or it could be multiple species, with all the qualifying interests. Some river habitats may be designated for salmon, for example, or for otter. Some of our special protection areas are designated for certain bird species. The area of focus we are interested in is those designated habitats that have these sensitive species that are sensitive to nutrients, for example, or pressure from grazing. As Mr. Callanan mentioned, the actions to improve water quality, for example, to reduce sediment, which the Deputy mentioned, or nutrients, will be beneficial from a water quality point of view, but they will also be beneficial for these designated species, such as salmon. We need to consider not just the aquatic habitat. It is also those other habitats that are designated under the habitats directive.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_98">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_147">I mentioned the correlation between stocking numbers when we were finishing up previously; we just ran out of time. I accept the point about the different flow and everything but with the previous derogation - I am possibly blinkered on this at times because I am a farmer - we had a mid-term review done in 2023 that resulted in people being reduced from a derogation of 250 kg N/ha to 220 kg N/ha or whatever. The nitrates content of the water was then up. That would nearly say to me there was no correlation between stocking densities and water quality. The figures are there. The EPA has almost proved a point that maybe it did not intend to prove. The officials might comment on that.</p>
          <p eId="para_148"> My next question was kind of answered in response to Deputy Aird. I know civil servants do not do politics but, going forward from here, who puts what proposal to the Commission? Where does science end and politics begin, or <i>vice versa</i>, in the final decision being made on this? I am asking this based on the officials' experience in 2010. I know they will not break the mould of civil servants saying politicians do politics and they do-----</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_8">(Interruptions).</summary>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_99">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_149">-----but there has to be somewhere where the science becomes political or the politics becomes science. Will the final decision be political? With the support of 26 or 27 states needed to get this over the line, there has to be an amount of politics involved. Will the officials give us an indication as to where that line is between the science and the politics?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_100">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_150">The Senator answered the question himself, which is civil servants do not get ahead of-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_101">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_151">I am asking the witnesses based on their experience.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_102">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_152">The reality here is it is important that there be political engagement. All levels of political engagement are happening in relation to engagement with the Commission and its officials, including the invitation to Commissioner Roswall to come to see for herself the circumstances in Ireland. As the Senator knows, Commissioner Hansen was also over here last year. Last week, and also last year, officials engaged with all the stakeholders. We had a very positive engagement at that time.</p>
          <p eId="para_153"> Let us call a spade a spade, however. To facilitate that political engagement, we must also comply with the required directives. That means the water framework and habitats directives. There is an ask of us in terms of providing assurances, which is something we have conveyed to stakeholders, around compliance with the habitats directive that effectively enables that political engagement, too.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_103">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_154">I thank the witnesses for taking the time to be here for this discussion. "Water quality" is the big term we are using here. Deputy Aird asked a question about cleaning rivers and I do not think he got a reply to it. The witnesses might give him a reply on that.</p>
          <p eId="para_155"> I asked about this previously. My belief is more stakeholders are responsible for what is happening with water quality than agriculture. Is that the officials' view? Is it their view that what is going on is totally down to farming and agriculture?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_104">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_156">We have never suggested that this is down to farming. However, there has been detailed modelling of the various contributions from sectors such as wastewater, forestry, agriculture, etc. All have a part to play in improving water quality and all have a responsibility. I am not sure it will be productive in achieving that objective of improving water quality if there is a kind of blame game of saying "It is not us, it is them" and so forth. Everybody is going to have to play his or her part. Every sector within farming, not just derogation farming, has to play its part.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_105">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_157">I will add to that. It is my honest belief that wastewater is also a big issue throughout the country.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_106">
          <from> Dr. Daire Ó hUallacháin<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_158">I will try to answer a little in relation to dredging. That falls under the works of the OPW, but it is important to get a balance. While dredging may improve the flow, it damages the habitat. Some of the assessments the EPA undertakes relate to the insects that are living in these habitats. While one might increase the flow and there could be some benefits in relation to concentration, that would potentially damage the habitat that some of these other species, for example, insects, salmon or the like, are depending on. It is not as simple as just increasing the flow to make sure that our concentration is reduced.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_107">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_159">In fairness, it is equally reasonable to assume it is nutrient content and sediment we are looking at in relation to a nitrates action programme, particularly nutrient content, which is really unimpacted by dredging, etc. It is rather about looking at what the flow is from land into watercourses that arise there. The overall action programme is about managing that, making sure farmers are using their slurries most efficiently and there is no leaking from the land into watercourses around the total volume of nutrient, or load, that is arising in agriculture.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_108">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_160">I have one very quick question. I will return to that question about catchment and the analysis of the different catchment areas. Some farms will straddle different catchments. They may have an outside farm or, for example, farms in the Bandon-River Lee area may run across the top of Newcestown-Templemartin. The farm could be in both catchment areas. Could farms end up with different outcomes for different catchment areas? How would they handle that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_109">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_161">I will ask Mr. Massey to deal with that question. That is an issue we have had to grapple with in respect of the 250 kg N/ha to 220 kg N/ha drop as well, where farmers are straddling both areas. Some of the farm may be eligible to apply at 250 kg N/ha and others at 220 kg N/ha. Mr. Massey will go through how we have dealt with that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_110">
          <from> Mr. Ted Massey<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_162">It is important to bear in mind that the catchment boundary is defined by what is happening below ground as well as above ground. It may not necessarily follow the topography of what we might expect but, as Mr. Callanan said, we have already had to grapple with that. Following the two-year review under the current derogation, some parts of the country remained at 250 kg N/ha while other areas moved to 220 kg N/ha.</p>
          <p eId="para_163">The approach we took was that once part of a LPIS parcel, effectively a field at farm level, remained at the higher stocking rate allowance, then the field remained at the higher allowance. We tried to keep it as simple as possible for farmers. Having mapped the country and categorised each parcel, we then wrote to the farmers who would potentially be impacted by that and set out exactly how each parcel they had applied for, in terms of our direct payments, was going to be impacted by the change. They could see exactly how they would be impacted going forward. We did that in 2023 in advance of the changes that became applicable in 2024. We have done it again this year because a small number of people are moving to 220 kg N/ha with effect from December this year, so we wrote to them as well.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_111">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_164">Thank you. Deputy Fitzmaurice is next.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_112">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_165">For Dr. Ó hUallacháin, the cleanest river in Ireland is the Islands River. About ten diggers cleaned it 12 to 14 years ago. It is one of the best rivers in Ireland. To anyone who talks rubbish about cleaning rivers and says that things will not come back, I say that rivers were cleaned for years and all the different things came back. This myth has to be got rid of. If you do not allow water to flow, you are going to have problems and backlogs.</p>
          <p eId="para_166"> On the derogation, the feeling, and what we are hearing, is that there is a fair possibility that it will not stop at Christmas and that there will be a two-year thing. I understand what the officials are facing on the habitats directive side of matters. It would probably take four or five years to do what is required on the basis of what they are looking for. If that happens, what will be the strings attached? Can Mr. Callanan explain this to me. There is a change in Europe at the moment. I do not understand it, but Mr. Callanan will know about it. I think it is called RENURE - manure redone. Is that giving scope for something? Is it that we are not counting the slurry in the tank now or what is it? A few years ago, the considerations relating to year-old cattle were changed. The weight for heifers came down to about 55 kg, while it went up to 60 kg for bull weanlings. What was that based on? Everyone is on about nitrates, but no one is talking about phosphates at all. The spread of the latter is caused by sewage treatment plants blasting out stuff into the water in the west of Ireland. We cannot distinguish between human sewage and cattle slurry for phosphorous. The west of Ireland is down as an area that is high in phosphorous. Farmers are being crippled for a reason that the EPA and Irish Water are not tackling. How can we separate that and get accurate figures?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_113">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_167">The first matter was dredging. That is really not of interest to us. We just expressed a response here in relation to habitats, but let us call a spade a spade. Principally, the assessment of habitat compliance here will revolve around that issue of nutrient load, not dredging and so on. It is nutrient load that is controlled under the nitrates action programme. That is what we will be assessing in terms of compliance with the habitats directive.</p>
          <p eId="para_168"> On what RENURE is, under the nitrates directive there is a limit regarding the organic manure that is applied to land. It is not about the manure that is present, because every pig farmer or large intensive unit can have a lot more nitrate than 170 kg N/ha; it is the amount of manure applied to land. Under RENURE, which was recently positively voted on, nutrient from animal manures that have been converted effectively into a chemical equivalent will not to be counted.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_114">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_169">What does that mean?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_115">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_170">I will attempt to explain. About ten years ago, I visited a plant in Holland where slurries were going in the front end and were divided into three components. One was a solid fraction that was going into an anaerobic digestion plant. The second was the liquid fraction which was then going through a process called reverse osmosis to take the nitrates out of it, creating a liquid that was a fertiliser. The third component was water. The water was basically allowed back into the streams and ditches. RENURE facilitates that conversion of organic manure into a processed fertiliser. It will not be counted against the 170 kg N/ha.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_116">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_171">Will it help us? If an ordinary farmer has 100 cows and RENURE is coming in, how will it help?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_117">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_172">We are not at that level of processing in Ireland that I would suggest RENURE is going to be of any great advantage to us. There are opportunities in terms of the progression of that technology, the development of anaerobic digestion and the consequent further processing which, I understand, has to apply.</p>
          <p eId="para_173"> In terms of the changes that were brought in and why they were brought in, the nitrates action programme specifies technical calculations that are done in terms of, for example, the excretion level for every type of animal you can think of - ducks, geese, sheep, cattle, livestock, horses and so on. The excretion data for calves up to 90 days old was recalculated, as was that for those in the two-year-old category. As the Deputy described, the weight for the male went up and that for the female went down. That is all based on a calculation process done by Teagasc based on scientific assessment and the most recent science data. We had also that in respect of dairy cow excretion rates based on the introduction of banding. In other words, we are updating to take account of new science.</p>
          <p eId="para_174"> On phosphorous, the Deputy is correct that wastewater treatment tends to be a phosphorous issue rather than a nitrates issue. That is modelled by the EPA in terms of where the relevant sources of phosphorous that are going into the system are emanating from. Does Mr. Massey want to comment on RENURE?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_118">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_175">We will need to finish up. I will allow one very brief response.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_119">
          <from> Mr. Ted Massey<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_176">To explain RENURE in simple terms, the acronym stands for recovered nitrogen from manure products. The amendment to the nitrates directive that was voted on last week in Brussels related to three processes that had been deemed to create product that will behave very similarly to chemical fertiliser nitrogen. They are three very capital-intensive processes and we do not have a manure processing industry here. Our system is based on animals out on grass and nutrient recycling within a holding, which is a very sustainable system. In the short term at least, I do not foresee us having the capacity or the volume of nutrients to justify the level of investment that would be required to create processed manure products in terms of that RENURE amendment.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_120">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_177">Would a by-product of anaerobic be worth considering?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_121">
          <from> Mr. Ted Massey<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_178">It could be, but it would be subject to significant further processing.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_122">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_179">Would it have to be animal manure?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_123">
          <from> Mr. Ted Massey<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_180">In terms of RENURE, it is recovered nitrogen from animal manure.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_124">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_181">Right.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_125">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_182">To be clear, the nitrates directive limits the amount of organic manure from animals. If you have digestate that is coming from non-animal sources, that is countable as the equivalent of the fertiliser component but not subject to the 170 kg N/ha limit.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_126">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_183">Who keeps track of that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_127">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_184">In what way?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_128">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_185">Who keeps track of the overall thing?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_129">
          <from> Mr. Bill Callanan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_186">In general, it would be licensed facilities managed by the local authorities and the EPA.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_130">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_187">What about the river that was clean, the cleanest river we have? That is contradiction as regards what was said to me.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_131">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_188">Could I ask one question?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_132">
          <from> Dr. Daire Ó hUallacháin<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_189">Can I just reply there? I said I am unfamiliar with the river in question. I stand by the fact, as I said at the time, that while you may increase the flow, you can damage the habitat by dredging. You can impact the insects that are in that habitat, and insects are one of the indicators that are used by the EPA.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_133">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_190">Every river recovers. That is what I am saying. I saw it happen with the Islands River. Anyone can look it up under the EPA and what it is. One question I have----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_134">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_191">No, we have gone over time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_135">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_192">It is about exported slurry.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_136">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_193">We have another group coming in. I want to thank members for keeping it tight as regards the time. On behalf of the committee, I thank the officials for their preparation and for their answers and discussion today.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_9">
          <i> Sitting suspended at 4.49 p.m. and resumed at 4.56 p.m.</i>
        </summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>Impact of Trade Deals on Agriculture: Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:50:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_137">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_194">Before we begin, I wish to bring to the committee's attention that witnesses giving evidence within the parliamentary precinct are protected by absolute privilege in respect of the evidence they give to the committee. This means a witness has full defence in any defamation action of anything said at a committee meeting. However, witnesses are expected not to abuse this privilege and may be directed to cease giving evidence on an issue at the Chair's discretion. Witnesses should follow the direction of the Chair in this regard and are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that, as is reasonable, no adverse commentary should be made against an identifiable third person or entity.</p>
          <p eId="para_195"> Witnesses giving evidence from a location outside the parliamentary precinct should note they may not benefit from the same level of immunity from legal proceedings as witnesses giving evidence from within the parliamentary precinct and may consider it appropriate to take legal advice on the matter. Privilege against defamation does not apply to the publication by witnesses outside of the proceedings held by the committee of any matter arising from the proceedings.</p>
          <p eId="para_196"> The agenda for this session is to examine the impacts of trade deals on agriculture, such as Mercosur - the EU trade agreement - and US tariffs. The joint committee will hear from the following officials from the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine: Ms Sinéad McPhillips, assistant secretary, EU, UK and international affairs; Mr. Paul Whelan, assistant principal, UK and international trade division; and Ms Margaret O'Boyle, assistant principal, EU and international trade division.</p>
          <p eId="para_197"> Before we proceed, on behalf of the committee and myself, I extend congratulations to Ms McPhillips on her promotion to the position of Secretary General in the Department. We look forward to engagement with her and with her officials. Tá fáilte romhaibh agus comhghairdeas as an ról nua. The opening statements have been circulated to committee members and I will allow five minutes if Ms McPhillips wishes to read it into the record or two minutes if she wishes to give a brief synopsis. We will then move onto questions and answers.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_138">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_198">My appointment does not take place until next week, so I am here in my current role. I thank the committee for the opportunity to discuss the impacts of trade deals on the agrifood sector. The agrifood sector has a strong export focus, and it benefits significantly from good two-way trading relationships with other countries, as well as from the EU’s Single Market. Last year, agrifood exports were a record €19 billion, to over 180 countries.</p>
          <p eId="para_199">Our exports have increased by almost two-thirds in value over the past decade. That increase was driven more by increasing value rather than volume. Our export markets are reasonably well balanced between the UK, at 38% of export value, and EU markets, at 34%, while international markets outside of Europe account for the remaining 28%. Our membership of the EU means that we are part of a growing network of EU free-trade agreements. This presents new opportunities, for example, Irish agrifood exports to Japan have doubled since the implementation of the EU-Japan free trade agreement, to €172 million in 2024.</p>
          <p eId="para_200"> However, it is important that such agreements also take account of sectors which may be vulnerable to increased imports into the EU. The EU-Mercosur agreement is one where concerns have consistently been raised on its impact on the agrifood sector in Ireland, particularly in relation to the beef sector. The committee will be familiar with the programme for Government commitment to work with like-minded EU countries to stand up for Irish farmers and defend our interests in opposing the current Mercosur trade deal. The recent announcement from the Commission of its proposed approach to ratification of the agreement includes a number of measures which look at reinforcing safeguards on sensitive agricultural products, increasing the number of sanitary and phytosanitary, SPS, checks in third countries and strengthening controls, measures relating to production standards and supports for farmers who may be negatively impacted. Our Department is working with the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade, which has lead responsibility for trade policy, to examine the detail of these proposals. The Minister, Deputy Heydon, has in the meantime engaged regularly with his counterparts from other EU member states to discuss common areas of concern in relation to Mercosur, including a meeting with his French counterpart in Brussels earlier this week. </p>
          <p eId="para_201"> In regard to EU-US trade relations, the US is the second-largest market for Irish agrifood exports. Last year, exports to the US were valued at almost €2 billion. Therefore, the trade tensions this year have created challenges for our agrifood sector. In August we saw the EU and US agree a joint statement on transatlantic trade and investment. The statement confirms that a tariff ceiling of 15% will now apply on the majority of goods exported from the EU to the US, with the exception of where the pre-existing most-favoured nation, MFN, tariff rate is higher. This can be seen as a positive outcome for agrifood exports which had higher pre-existing tariff rates, as from 2 April onwards they will be back in the same position they were in before the tariff announcements. For example, butter exports will revert to the pre-existing tariff rate of 16% which was in place before April, having faced a 26% tariff between April and August. The new 15% tariff rate poses major challenges for exports that had lower pre-existing tariff rates. For example, our spirits sector will face a 15% tariff for exports to the US following years of EU and US exporters enjoying a mutually beneficial zero-for-zero tariff arrangement. The EU and the US have committed to work on expanding a list of exemptions included in the joint statement. Obviously, we would like to see spirit drinks included in this. </p>
          <p eId="para_202"> In relation to the UK, Ireland's main trading partner for agrifood products remains the United Kingdom. In May this year the EU-UK summit produced a commitment on both sides to work towards an SPS agreement, as well as securing an important agreement to extend the current arrangements for fisheries until June 2038. The commitment to establish a common SPS area is to be based on dynamic alignment by the UK with all EU rules. A comprehensive SPS agreement would significantly reduce the administrative on Irish agrifood businesses trading with Great Britain, potentially eliminating the need for export certification and for import controls at ports for most products. </p>
          <p eId="para_203"> The EU's negotiating mandate is currently being finalised and my Department will monitor these negotiations closely once they formally commence. Of course, the EU has many other free trade agreements in place or under negotiation with third countries. We will be happy to discuss those also.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_139">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_204">There will be six or seven minutes each, which will gives us an opportunity to do another round if we need it. I call Senator Paul Daly. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_140">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_205">I welcome the officials this evening. I want to be associated with the congratulations to Ms McPhillips. I wish her the best of luck going forward and look forward to working with her.</p>
          <p eId="para_206"> It is likely that Mercosur will dominate proceedings here this evening. I will start there also. I am not opposed to Mercosur. I am not opposed to any trade deal. We are an open economy and Ms McPhillips rightly said how much we need to do free trade with as many people as possible. However, I am also a beef farmer and I have problems with the beef sector of the Mercosur agreement. I have more of a problem with the standards to which beef is produced than I have with anything else. We have to have an equivalence of standards. I would like to hear Ms McPhillips's comment on that. Can Ms McPhillips give us an indication, because we all get carried away on the beef side, of what the Mercosur deal might be worth to our agriculture sector, aside from beef? There are massive positives for our dairy sector. Our spirits sector, as she mentioned, might struggle in America with a 15% tariff. There is a massive opportunity there which would in turn be a benefit to our tillage sector in the production of malt, barley, etc. Has Ms McPhillips any idea of what Mercosur might be worth, on the positive side, to the other sectors? Will she also comment on the equivalence of standards of production of beef to give us a better idea of that? In doing so, she might give us an indication as to what the EU-Canada Comprehensive Economic and Trade Agreement, CETA, is worth to agriculture. It had the same objections. I do not want to use the word "scare-mongering" but, because I cannot think of an equivalent, I will use it to explain what I mean. At the time, CETA was not acceptable at all. What is it worth to us now, having been accepted? Is there any progress on a carve-out for the spirits? I am from Kilbeggan, the home of Kilbeggan whiskey, so I have a keen interest in the American tariffs on whiskey. Is there any progress or update on the potential carve-out of spirits to a zero tariff? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_141">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_207">Obviously there is concern about the impact on the beef sector and that has been the position of this Government and the previous Government for many years. The 99,000 tonne beef quota for the Mercosur countries was agreed in 2019. That has not changed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_142">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_208">That is prime cuts, though. It is not just 99,000 tonnes of beef. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_143">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_209">It is divided between prime cuts and lesser cuts. However, assuming the additional imports are in the high-end cuts, an economic analysis was carried out, commissioned by the Department of Enterprise, Trade and Employment in 2021, which forecast that beef imports from Mercosur to the EU as a whole would increase by around 53,000 tonnes as a result of the agreement. It is important to acknowledge that there are existing imports from Mercosur countries that are facing a tariff at the moment. They would benefit from the reduced tariff arrangements being phased in over a six-year period. The net result was estimated to be that imports would increase by 53,000 tonnes and the impact of the additional imports on Ireland, assuming they were high-end cuts, would be that producer returns in Ireland could fall by around 2%, which at the time was estimated as between €44 million and €55 million of an impact on beef sector incomes. That is a serious concern.</p>
          <p eId="para_210"> The other side of it, which the Senator alluded to, is the standards to which farmers are held in Mercosur countries as opposed to in the EU. As we understand it, two separate sets of standards are being talked about. SPS standards are non-negotiable. They relate to food safety and animal and plant health standards that apply equally to EU production and to imports from all around the world. In its recent proposal the Commission has committed to stepping up the audits and inspections in third countries to ensure that those standards are upheld. There is no change in standards and no difference in standards, however. The other standards are the standards of production, the sustainability standards that our farmers are held to in terms of their production and how they farm.</p>
          <p eId="para_211">Of course we would like to see those same standards applied to producers in other countries. However, we have to bear in mind, not just with Mercosur but with other third countries, that as an exporting nation, if we apply EU standards to our imports, then equally we could be held to different standards when we export so that is a consideration. What we want is a level playing field but we do not have it. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_144">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_212">I do not think there is a higher standard of production of beef in the world than the EU standards, so we cannot lose on that one. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_145">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_213">Absolutely, but the point I am making is that different countries have different standards and requirements. When we export to Asian markets, for example, we go through, as the Senator is aware, a lengthy market-access process. This is to prove that our standards are equivalent to the specifics of those markets, so it cannot really be a one-size-fits-all scenario. We have those concerns in relation to sustainability, and they have been a key part of the further discussions with Mercosur since the original agreement in 2019, that additional sustainability standards were added to the agreement and an additional protocol was added last December. There are further reassurances from the Commission in what it has produced now, but all of those assurances are still being examined by us and by the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade to see how well they stand up. </p>
          <p eId="para_214"> CETA, the agreement with Canada, has been provisionally enforced since 2017. It allows Irish and Canadian companies to take advantage of the beneficial terms of the agreement. Ninety nine percent of goods now have access to the Canadian market tariff-free and EU beef and sheepmeat access into Canada has been fully liberalised. Irish agrifood exports to Canada have increased by 58% in value since 2017, and that is largely driven by an increase in spirit drinks exports. This shows the benefits of some of these free trade agreements, while obviously acknowledging that Mercosur is a significant cause for concern. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_146">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_215">I wish Ms McPhillips the best of luck in her new role. She has a tough job ahead, with all of the different things, but she is well-seasoned, in that she knows the job inside out, so the best of luck. On Mercosur, I want to say I am opposed to it, unlike Senator Daly, for this simple reason. If we look at the backstops that have been put into it, the so-called cushions, the first thing is we are not on a level playing field in the way an Irish farmer has to adhere to animal welfare regulations and the different EU regulations, compared to what they do in Brazil and all the other countries. It is a totally different ball game, so no one can tell me it is a level playing field. In Ireland, regarding the CAP and EU inspections what percentage of the 130,000 farmers get audited? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_147">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_216">I could not put a figure on it but I will follow up on it. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_148">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_217">I imagine it would be 1% or 2% and when we talk about farmers in Brazil being audited, it is going to be like a fly on a wall. To be quite frank, it is going to be the very minimum. On the backstop, am I correct in saying that they are talking about basically a 10% drop in European meat prices before they put a brake on it? However, my understanding is, and correct me if I am wrong on this, that if it was 9% for five years in a row, the brake does not stop. Is that correct? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_149">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_218">I think the Deputy is correct. The proposal is for enhanced monitoring and reporting of imports, allowing for quick adoption of provisional safeguard measures in urgent cases, and to enable the launch of investigations where imports increase from Mercosur by at least 10% and import prices are at least 10% lower than domestic prices. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_150">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_219">It can be 9% for five years in a row, which is 45%, and there is nothing we can do about it, to put it simply. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_151">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_220">I not sure whether that is cumulative or not. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_152">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_221">From my understanding it is yearly on the price. Regarding the tonnage coming in at the moment with the tariff that is on it, am I correct in saying that tariff would be lowered completely, along with the 50,000 extra tonnes? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_153">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_222">The tariff would be lowered for 99,000 tonnes over a six-year period. I could be wrong, and we will check this, but I think at the moment about 200,000 tonnes is coming in in most years from Mercosur countries. Where the 55,000 tonnes comes from is that the economic modelling assumption is that we continue to have 200,000 tonnes coming in and rather than that increasing by 99,000 tonnes, it increases by roughly 53,000 tonnes. In other words, the South American exporters get a benefit from the reduced tariff on the 200,000 tonnes and the increase so they get 253,000 tonnes of total exports rather than 200,000 tonnes. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_154">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_223">In fairness, the Department has been tic-tacing with Europe on the Mercosur deal. Will it be down to a vote in the Parliament and the Council of Ministers? The way it is looking at the moment, I want to call it out straight. My reading of it is that if France gets more money, Italy will throw in the towel and the veto is gone with the Lisbon treaty and all of that. It looks like it will go through the Council of Ministers and that the only hope that Irish people have is of blocking it or the only hope for Ireland is through the European Parliament. Is that fair to say? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_155">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_224">The Commission's recent proposal gives some clarity on the legal approach it is taking to the agreement. It foresees a split agreement, whereby the trade elements-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_156">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_225">Sorry for interrupting, but am I correct in saying that by doing that split, they have now eliminated the national parliaments from having a vote? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_157">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_226">Yes, on the trade elements. They have taken out the trade elements and split those. The trade elements require adoption by a qualified majority vote in the EU trade Council and then by a simple majority vote in the European Parliament. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_158">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_227">When the Department is tic-tacing with them, who is allowing them to split this deal? Does a Council of Ministers not block them, or is it von der Leyen or is it the Commissioner or who? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_159">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_228">The Commission has the power to propose legislation, so it has the right to propose how they would go about adopting----- </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_160">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_229">So unelected bureaucrats have proposed this? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_161">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_230">The Commission has competence for trade matters and then obviously there are joint competencies----- </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_162">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_231">They are not MEPs. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_163">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_232">No, but in relation to competence, there is legislation governing whether competence is a matter for the Commission in some cases, for the Commission and Council in other cases, so a lot of issues would be joint competence. Trade is an exclusive EU Commission competence so therefore, if it is exclusively the trade elements of the deal, the Commission has the power to propose that it is ratified. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_164">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_233">Has Ms McPhillips ever seen this done before? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_165">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_234">The Canadian deal, CETA, that we referred to earlier was done as a provisional agreement only on the trade elements. As the Deputy knows, the whole CETA has not yet been ratified by member state parliaments, so it is definitely not unprecedented. There will be a qualified majority vote at the EU trade Council, and then a simple majority-----... </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_166">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_235">What does that mean? Is that the ministers? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_167">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_236">Yes, that would be the trade ministers, so in our case the Tánaiste. For the qualified majority vote, a blocking minority would be required to prevent adoption of the agreement by the Council of trade ministers. That requires at least four member states representing more than 35% of the EU population either voting against or abstaining on the proposal. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_168">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_237">Voting against or abstaining? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_169">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_238">Yes, voting against or abstaining. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_170">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_239">It is either that or then it goes to the Parliament, is that it? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_171">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_240">The Parliament is a simple majority vote, "Yes" or "No".</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_172">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_241">I have never met Ms McPhillips before but I wish her well in her new role. She is going in at a very challenging time when there is the nitrates directive, the CAP and Mercosur. On a good day you will win all three but on a bad day you will lose all three. Ms McPhillips has a very exciting time in front of her.</p>
          <p eId="para_242"> I want to make it very clear that I am totally opposed to Mercosur. Totally opposed to it. Maybe I will stand in here like Senator Daly in a few years' time and say that it is over, or whatever, but I have a huge and deep commitment to the beef farmers in this country. I stood idly by and saw nearly 200,000 sucklers gone. It makes me very tearful that I knew. I followed my father to many farms and I saw the very best of stock people, old stock people, where traditions were carried down from father to son or daughter. I saw a lot of those farms being forced into milk, which they did not want to do but they could not sustain a family farm any longer. Now, at least we see a situation where those people are getting well rewarded for the cattle they are producing. Anything out there, like Mercosur, to harm that at this time is not worth the risk. I am totally opposed to Mercosur.</p>
          <p eId="para_243"> I will be very brief on the following points and perhaps Ms McPhillips can answer them. Has the Department conducted an up-to-date impact assessment on the implications for the Irish beef sector of increased beef imports from Mercosur countries? What specific protections are being followed for the Irish suckler and beef farmer in light of these potential market distortions? How will this deal affect beef prices? What contingency plans are in place? If Ms McPhillips could please answer that question first and then I can judge my time and maybe go down through the rest of them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_173">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_244">As I mentioned, an impact assessment was carried out in 2021 by the Department of Enterprise, Trade and Employment. That was specifically on the trade aspects of Mercosur. As I have explained to the other Deputies, those trade aspects have not changed since the agreement was originally negotiated in 2019.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_174">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_245">What of the effect on beef prices?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_175">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_246">All the assessments are economic models and are subject to a set of assumptions. They found that the additional imports, assuming they were in high-end cuts, would reduce producer returns in Ireland by about 2%, or €55 million.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_176">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_247">By 2%, all right. That is what we have said but let us see what happens there. What guarantees has the Department received that the meat and the agrifood products entering the EU under this agreement will be produced to equivalent environmental, animal welfare, and traceability standards? We are all asking this question but we are not being told. Is Ms McPhillips happy that these regulations are going to be met?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_177">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_248">As I have said to other members, there is a distinction between the SPS food safety standards, which are a prerequisite for any food entering the EU - the Commission has committed to further audit and inspection on those - and then the environmental and animal welfare standards, as the Deputy has mentioned, which are different in the EU and are higher in the EU than in other countries. The Commission has included certain reassurances in its proposals and those additional assurances are currently being examined by our Department and the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_178">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_249">I will ask another question for whoever wants to answer. Why is the EU prioritising access to beef from South America at a time when Irish and EU farmers are being asked to do more sustainability? In other words, has Ireland used enough influence to slow or oppose the ratification of this deal? We met people on this already and I asked the very same question of representatives who came over here from the EU.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_179">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_250">As the Minister, Deputy Heydon, has frequently said, the Government position is that there are significant concerns around the Mercosur agreement and particularly around its impact on beef farming in Ireland. The Minister has repeatedly raised those concerns in discussions with his EU counterparts and has raised them consistently at meetings of the AGRIFISH Council.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_180">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_251">That is fair enough. I will ask a direct question now. In the event that Irish beef farmers are negatively impacted by this deal, and I mean starting now with the price of beef going down, will the Department seek EU-level compensation funds for market adjustment from this time now?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_181">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_252">In bringing forward the proposals the European Commission has said to us that there will be a market support fund for farmers who might be negatively impacted. That is one of the things-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_182">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_253">That is great news. Will the Department set the guidelines for what farmers get for their cattle? For example, if I sell cattle in any part of the country today weighing in at €4.50 per kg or whatever it is, will the Department give me the same price when this beef comes in and if it has a negative effect on the market? That is where it is. It is around the ring when I produce. Ms McPhillips is telling me today that we will go in at that price and I am happy with that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_183">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_254">The European Commission has given that assurance of a market protection fund-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_184">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_255">That is grand; sure it is all we want.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_185">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_256">-----but we need to-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_186">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_257">There is the news for everybody here today: what you are getting for the cattle today - this is no laughing matter - you will be guaranteed that if anything negative comes out of this-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_187">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_258">I am sorry, Deputy-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_188">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_259">Let Ms McPhillips answer the question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_189">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_260">That is not correct. If it drops 9%-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_190">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_261">Let her answer the question, please.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_191">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_262">In fairness, if it drops 9%, you are not-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_192">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_263">Deputy Fitzmaurice, please let her answer the question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_193">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_264">What I am trying to say is that the Commission has assured us there is a market support fund there but the terms and conditions of what would apply to that market and how we would access that funding are far from clear. That is one of the issues we need to get further clarification on.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_194">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_265">At the minute, it is not clear. We are at a situation in this country where we have been trying desperately hard to get here. It has been very hard to get here but we are getting returns for the cattle. Everybody can see it out there now for the first time in 20 years or 25 years. I can see it on farmers' faces that the confidence is there in everything. This Mercosur deal has now come like a cloud over our heads. If that dampens everything and the price of cattle drops again dramatically, we have to have a guarantee from the EU, or else what are we doing in the EU? Let us clear the hell out of it. Sorry, I have gone over my time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_195">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_266">As Deputy Fitzmaurice said, there is a very high bar for those safeguard clauses to be triggered and for any compensation or support for farmers to come into being.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_196">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_267">I thank the Department officials for coming in. I wish Sinéad McPhillips all the best in her new job. I look forward to working with her over the years ahead.</p>
          <p eId="para_268"> I am totally opposed to the Mercosur trade deal. It is incredible really. It has been a masterclass in political doublespeak from the European Union in many ways. Over the last hour we have been talking about the nitrates derogation and we have been talking about all of the stringent regulations that pertain to farmers in relation to water quality and so on. We are fighting for the nitrates derogation with our European colleagues and meanwhile the Commission is seeking to sign a trade deal with the Mercosur countries that will see thousands of hectares of forestry removed. It does not make any sense. I am actually in shock in many ways with the level of detail and the level of analysis that we spoke about in the last session of this committee in relation to the nitrates derogation. In this session we are talking about almost 100,000 tonnes of beef coming in from the Mercosur countries. Ms McPhillips is only reporting what is coming from Europe but she has said that environmental standards will not be the same and that there may be some parity in relation to food quality or food safety but not in relation to environmentalism. Does it make sense to Ms McPhillips? What is her sense on it? To me, the two do not make any rational sense. A lot of this is really incredible and it is doublespeak. What is Ms McPhillips' sense on it?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_197">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_269">Throughout the negotiations Ireland has consistently highlighted that the agreement with Mercosur should include legally binding commitments on sustainability standards, including climate, biodiversity and deforestation protections. What the Commission would say to us, and I am just repeating what it would say, is that additional protections have been included in the protocol that was agreed last December and that will be kept under review but-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_198">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_270">I am sorry to interrupt Ms McPhillips, but what are the legally binding environmental commitments in this deal?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_199">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_271">One, for instance - I suppose we would say it is not necessarily an extensive protection - is that if one of the Mercosur countries was to leave the Paris climate agreement, then the EU-Mercosur agreement would be suspended for that country. There are certain references also to deforestation protections and so on.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_200">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_272">What level of deforestation is allowable under the deal?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_201">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_273">There are commitments on the part of the Mercosur countries - I might come back to the Deputy on this to give him the detail of it - to honour international deforestation agreements.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_202">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_274">Are those commitments on the number of hectares of rainforest that are allowed to be removed?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_203">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_275">There is a commitment to enhance efforts to stabilise or increase forest cover from 2030 onwards. I will come back to the Deputy with the exact wording of that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_204">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_276">It is very vague. We all live under the same sky. What is the difference between emissions produced in Mayo, Dublin or Donegal and those produced in Argentina or Brazil?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_205">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_277">The trade element of this deal was agreed in 2019. There were significant concerns voiced then by many EU member states about the sustainability impacts of the agreement. That is why the Commission has gone back and added additional safeguards, as it would call them. We need to test those. It is clear from the Government position that intensive engagement is needed by the Commission to explain and justify the details of the final package to member states.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_206">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_278">Farmers are going to be hurt significantly by this deal, especially beef farmers. What analysis has been done? Analysis was done, as Ms McPhillips mentioned, on the potential reduction of beef prices in Ireland. Who are the beneficiaries of this deal? Has there been analysis done on German and French car manufacturing? By what percentage of sales are they due to benefit from the deal?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_207">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_279">Again, I can give the Deputy the details of the EU Joint Research Centre report that has been done on the total impact of EU-Mercosur, which overall I think is seen as economically beneficial for EU and Mercosur countries. In the agrifood sector, there are significant benefits for EU exporters in certain sectors as well, while many countries have vulnerable sectors they wish to protect. The analysis I referenced previously that was done in Ireland in 2021 found there were opportunities for the Irish spirits drinks sector and the dairy sector to increase exports to Mercosur countries as well.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoanneCollins" eId="spk_208">
          <from>Senator Joanne Collins<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_280">I thank the officials for giving of their time to be here. We have gone around the floor and these questions have probably been asked and answered already, but I will try to ask them in a different format to make it more interesting.</p>
          <p eId="para_281"> I am going to touch on the standards side of this, which has been asked about plenty of times. Our farmers pride themselves on the standard of our beef. We are world-renowned for the standards we have. Ms McPhillips is saying that, within the agreement, the EU is looking to have some type of standards for the Mercosur countries. If they are not to the same standards as what we have to export to, then what is stopping Irish farmers from decreasing our standards in protest if the Mercosur countries can do it more cheaply? I mean the likes of injecting hormones into livestock in Mercosur countries, which we cannot do here because it is not allowed under EU regulations. It takes the fairness out of the deal and the trade, so it does not turn out to be a fair trade.</p>
          <p eId="para_282"> The other side I wish to touch on, which colleagues across the floor have spoken about, is the environmental impact. We have a plant in Edenderry that used to be fuelled by Bord na Móna peat. Bord na Móna had to be shut down because of our emissions, so we now ship the rainforest into Shannon Foynes Port, which takes 52 days, shunt it up and down a pier with trucks and cranes, and then take it up to Edenderry by truck again. Think of the emissions of that alone. I do not know if the Department, or whichever body needs to, has ever done a study on that, but surely that is not cutting emissions. Emissions are emissions regardless of what country they come from. As my colleague said, we all have the same sky. What is the point of us bending over backwards to cut our emissions if we are going to incentivise another country to cut down a rainforest so we can hit net zero, or try to hit it, when that country is going to create huge emissions?</p>
          <p eId="para_283"> This does not seem to make sense on the environmental or standards side. What if I was at the end of line where I was selling our cattle for beef and I was depending on that price yet I knew that another farmer doing the exact same thing on the other side of the world was selling into the same market but did not have to go through the same cost? Do not get me wrong - the farmers in this country are willing to do it because we have such good-quality produce, but if it is costing us one thing and costing other countries something else, then it is not very fair. There is going to be a kick back somewhere along the line. The population is going to suffer because the beef is not going to be as good. That is going to be an awful shame because we have such a good name for our beef.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_209">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_284">I thank the Senator. I fully understand the points she is making. On the SPS standards - the food safety animal health and plant standards - they are EU standards and are there to protect EU consumers. They apply to all food, be it produced in the EU or imported. The Commission has committed to increasing the number of SPS audits and checks in third countries and to strengthening controls on the ground to ensure those standards are upheld. On production standards, which are environmental standards of production and animal welfare standards, the Commission has also committed to rolling out initiatives to better align the production standards of imported products with EU production standards. That is somewhere we would like to see more detail from the Commission on what that means in practice.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_210">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_285">I thank the officials for coming in. We are beef farmers at home and I am totally opposed to this. Beef farmers are being thrown under the bus for the sake of Germany and its big fancy cars. It is absolute madness. Can we get a copy of the environmental structures Ms McPhillips was talking about? I understand dairy is going to increase by a small bit. It will not be huge. The officials are saying the effect on Irish beef farmers is €55 million and the pot of money that is being dangled in front of us is €63 billion for the whole of Europe. That pot of European money is a fund in case of us falling on hard times. How will that be split up throughout Europe? What piece of the pie are we going to get? That is all right for next year, but what about the year after, the one after that and the next generation of farmers? I cannot see that money still being there.</p>
          <p eId="para_286">Nothing is telling me that it will be there. I would not trust this Government, never mind the European Parliament, to do right by us when we are such a small piece of the jigsaw. Ireland is tiny in comparison with the whole of Europe.</p>
          <p eId="para_287"> Others have spoken about rainforests being cut down. It is okay for them to have a black hole over their skies but our skies will be clear. We will have to pay huge fines for not meeting our targets. We will not meet them. Every Government building should have solar panels on it. Not enough is being done. Most of it was blamed on farmers, from what I can see. There is huge anger out there, especially among beef farmers. The whole thing baffles me.</p>
          <p eId="para_288"> On the environmental structures, who is going to monitor Brazil? It was stated there will be more checks on meat coming in. Can we trust that there will be more checks in place? It will cost money to do that. Is that a hit on the Irish Government? Will it have to fork out that money? All these things need to be taken into consideration. I will leave the witnesses with that for a minute. Plenty of anger.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_211">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_289">I will speak to the question on crisis supports. In 2019, when the trade elements of the deal were done, the Commission committed to a dedicated €1 billion market disturbance fund which could be-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_212">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_290">For Ireland.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_213">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_291">No, for the EU as a whole. It could be used for farmers impacted. The recent MFF or EU budget proposals for the period 2023 to 2034 came out in July. They include a €6.3 billion crisis reserve to deal with all aspects of crisis in the EU over that period. There was a specific reference in that to trade agreements, and, I think, to Mercosur in particular. There was not a ring-fenced amount for Mercosur. It is likely there will be a high bar in the context of accessing any of the funding from that crisis reserve. It would only become available if the safeguard measures that we have talked about and that are included in the agreement in terms of price and volume of imports were found to have been met. That is when that safeguard would trigger.</p>
          <p eId="para_292"> Another point to consider is the full impact of those market concessions would be phased in over the six years of that tariff rate quota introduction. The 99,000 tonnes will not arrive in one big bang; they will be phased in over six years from adoption.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_214">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_293">On the environmental structures, can we get a copy of-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_215">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_294">We will get the Deputy the specific additional-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_216">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_295">Brilliant. We had a Chinese delegation in here last week. The dairy sector in their country has exploded. I asked if the beef sector was going in the same direction. They did not give me a yes-no answer, but I knew the answer was "Yes" because they spoke about food security. To us, it does not matter because we do not export that much beef to them. However, they import a lot of beef from Mercosur countries. If the Chinese become self-sufficient and no longer need as much beef, will that Mercosur beef need to go somewhere else? Will it flood into Europe? Can we trust that the beef that will come in will be capped for evermore? I do not think we can.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_217">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_296">That is a complicated question. The point is that the EU is open to imports from third countries. That is necessary because the EU is a major net exporter of food, so has to keep two-way trade going. We have seen from trade tensions elsewhere that European farmers, particularly Irish farmers, can be vulnerable to impacts where there are blockages to trade. We need to keep that in mind.</p>
          <p eId="para_297"> Mercosur countries can already export beef to the EU, and they do so. I will come back with exact figures for exports. The free trade agreement would, after the six-year phase-in, allow 99,000 tonnes of beef imports to come in at a low tariff rate. That is the concession in terms of the Mercosur agreement with the EU.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_218">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_298">That is for the 99,000, but it is not to say that more will not come in.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_219">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_299">More could come in but it would pay the full tariff rate.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_220">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_300">I thank the witnesses for coming in. I wish Ms McPhillips the best of luck in her new role. She will need it. The first thing she might do is get rid of Mercosur. Any time there is change, there is a concern. I am 100% opposed to it because I have been listening to farmers up and down the country and can understand their concerns. I will not stay too long on this because Ms McPhillips has been grilled on it for the past hour. The concern is the standard of the beef. Some 99,000 tonnes of beef will come into the country. Will it be up to the standard of the beef we have here in light of the cost of producing beef in this country? We have a great thing going at the moment. We have never seen the trade better placed here. Are we going to upset that? If we do, it would be a total disaster. I am delighted Ms McPhillips said a support fund will be put in place. That would need to be a condition. If we plough ahead with this, my belief is that support fund will be needed.</p>
          <p eId="para_301"> I do not want Ms McPhillips going back over what she has said a number of times. We are well aware that farmers have been affected by TB. Some of those farmers are suffering in a major way now and we do not want them to go through the same thing in the future. If this deal is going to go ahead, make sure good conditions are put in place to support farmers in our country.</p>
          <p eId="para_302"> Ms McPhillips's referred at the end of her opening statement to the EU having many free trade agreements in place and that is in talks with third countries. Will she give us an update on what they are about and what is going on there?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_221">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_303">To clarify, the 99,000 tonnes are for the EU market as a whole rather than just the Irish market. Obviously, however, we are-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_222">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_304">How will we determine how much will come into our country?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_223">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_305">Any imports into the EU market could potentially impact on the average EU price. That is our main concern, rather than what comes into Ireland. The EU has an ambitious trade agenda. It is in the process of negotiating other trade agreements, many of which have potential significant benefits for the Irish agrifood sector and which we support. We have spoken of the Canadian free trade agreement, which is in place and which has given rise to significant increased agrifood exports to Canada. We have doubled the value of agrifood exports to Japan, which is a very good and high-potential market. The protected geographical indication for Irish grass-fed beef has potential in that market. We have a free trade agreement with Korea and beef access to Korea, so there is potential growth there.</p>
          <p eId="para_306"> In terms of negotiations, we heard yesterday in Brussels that there is provisional agreement on trade with Indonesia. That is a significant potential market for dairy exports. Negotiations are ongoing with Thailand, Malaysia and the Philippines. In some of those markets, there are pluses and minuses that we need to be careful of as negotiations continue.</p>
          <p eId="para_307">Overall, as an exporting country, there is a lot of potential there. EU-India negotiations have been going on for many years but seem to be gaining some momentum now. For the spirits drinks sector, India is a significant target market for exports. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_224">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_308">Without going into much detail, what are the pluses and minuses that could affect us going forward?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_225">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_309">For any free trade agreement, as I said to other Deputies, the Commission has competence for trade negotiations but in the course of those negotiations, it will consult with member states to see what the sensitivities are. Obviously, in examining the detail of any Commission proposals, we would look at whether we are sensitive to imports from those countries, whether they could disrupt the EU market and whether there are significant potential export markets there. There is always a balance to be struck in relation to trade. It is very rarely either fully good or fully bad so we need to have the opportunity to assess and to input when the Commission is negotiating on behalf of the EU.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_226">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_310">The most important thing is to protect agriculture and our farmers as much as possible. I hope to work with the witnesses to achieve that, if possible. I wish Ms McPhillips the best of luck in her new role.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_227">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_311">Deputy Toole is next.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GillianToole" eId="spk_228">
          <from>Deputy Gillian Toole<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_312">Thanks for letting me sneak in. I have a few questions and apologise if I am duplicating what colleagues have already asked. In the context of imports and exports from Ireland and Europe <i>vis-à-vis </i>Mercosur and other trade agreements, at what stage is Ireland's land use review at? I ask this for two reasons, one of which is self-sufficiency for future food production and the other is the distribution of land for the location of renewable energy infrastructure. I come from east Meath where the best of tillage land is being used, in the absence of guidelines, for solar, battery storage, gas peaking plants and so on, which I completely acknowledge is necessary but I am wondering if there is an overall plan. If not, why not? It is important, in my humble opinion, in the context of the bigger picture involving Mercosur, CETA and any other trade agreements.</p>
          <p eId="para_313"> On the CETA agreement, there will be corporate compensation for loss of business going forward but is there any reciprocity there? I am thinking in particular of the example of Irish agriculture. Depending on how Mercosur and other trade agreements play out, the Irish farming community, as a business, may be facing potential losses. Is CETA done and dusted and agreed or is there any chance of incorporating reciprocity for potential Irish agrifood losses going forward? </p>
          <p eId="para_314"> Finally, in terms of potential developing markets in far flung places like Indonesia, the Philippines and so on, in the context of the transportation of goods and the net carbon output of that, what overall planning is taking place <i>vis-à-vis </i>the potential loss of domestic food production and inter- and intra-European transfers? It seems to me that we have climate hypocrisy here. On the one hand, the trade deal makes everything hunky-dory from a carbon perspective and we negate that and yet we have different levies on the citizen, domestic businesses and the farming community through the nitrates derogation, the water framework directive and so on. I just wonder if there is anybody, anywhere doing an overall balancing exercise on the net carbon tonnage. I hope that makes sense. When I saw this meeting on the board I decided I would drop in. I would say the Chair is sorry he let me in.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_229">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_315">You are very welcome to take part.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_230">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_316">Does the Deputy have a farming background?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GillianToole" eId="spk_231">
          <from>Deputy Gillian Toole<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_317">Yes, I have.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_232">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_318">I do not have an update on the land use review but I can come back to the Deputy on that, if needed. In relation to CETA, the agreement with Canada, the trade aspects of that agreement are already provisionally in force since 2017, allowing Irish and Canadian companies to take advantage of the beneficial terms of the agreement. That has been beneficial in terms of our agrifood exports to Canada. Several member states, including Ireland, have yet to fully ratify the full agreement, which is wider than trade. </p>
          <p eId="para_319"> The Deputy mentioned the potential loss of food production and while obviously that is a concern, Ireland is fully self-sufficient in food production. We rank as the first or second most food secure country in the world when those studies are done. We export about 90% of what we produce because of our comparative advantage, particularly in grass-based livestock production. On the issue of trade and carbon costs, we export food to 180 countries around the world. I would say that is done in a reasonably low-carbon way in that most of those exports go by sea; there are no air miles, so to speak. The benefits of that trade both for ourselves and others - and trade is always a two-way street between importers and exporters - is significant and keeping that trade going is really important in terms of the economic and social sustainability of rural Ireland. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GillianToole" eId="spk_233">
          <from>Deputy Gillian Toole<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_320">I thank Ms McPhillips.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_234">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_321">Most of my Mercosur questions have already been asked but I have one or two quick questions that I want to put to our guests. Mercosur has raised real concerns for farmers both in terms of the price they are going to get but also in terms of the quality and standards. As we mentioned earlier, a lot of questions are being raised on the environmental front as well as with regard to animal welfare standards. Safeguards have been proposed but they are not fully defined or fleshed out at this point. At what stage will they be defined and who will be dealing with that? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_235">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_322">I thank the Cathaoirleach. What Ireland has said consistently is that those standards and safeguards, particularly in relation to environmental standards, are really important and that intensive engagement by the Commission is needed to explain and justify the details of the final package to both member states and stakeholders. It is really important that there is an understanding of what is in scope and what the Commission has now offered. At official level we continue, with our counterparts in the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade, to interrogate what has been put on the table. Certainly, at political level, the Minister, Deputy Heydon, and the Tánaiste have asked for further engagement. We understand that the Commissioner for Trade and Economic Security, Mr. Šefčovič will visit Ireland in early October and there will be an opportunity then for engagement and further understanding of the Commission's interpretation of those safeguards.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_236">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T17:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_323">I will move the goalposts a little now and move on to pigmeat products and the tariffs being imposed on EU pigmeat products by China. It is claimed that this is an anti-dumping measure. Investigations have been going on for some time at this stage but is evidence emerging of this? In the meantime and looking to the future as well, this is important because a large proportion of our agrifood exports into China are pigmeat products. What efforts are being made by the Department to find alternative markets for Irish pigmeat products?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_237">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_324">This was something that was raised by the Minister at the Agriculture and Fisheries Council, AGRIFISH, yesterday, with serious concerns about the Chinese attitude. Clearly, our view is that EU and Irish exports of pig meat and pig meat by-products to China could in no way be characterised as dumping. There is no breach of WTO rules, which is what has been alleged by the Chinese authorities. We have asked the Commission to take this case very seriously. We received assurances yesterday from Commissioner Hansen that would be done and that the EU would make every effort to defend EU exports to China and get those tariffs lifted. Although China calls them something other than tariffs, that is their effect. We have seen a series of different investigations of different European products by the Chinese authorities. That is a worrying trend for the value of the market. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_238">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_325">Is the focus solely on the tariffs, or is there effort into finding alternative markets as well? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_239">
          <from> Ms Sinéad McPhillips<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_326">There is an ongoing effort to find new markets for Irish products and build the markets we have. We have a meat market access unit within the Department whose focus is on maintaining and building access to those markets. We work closely with Bord Bia to develop those markets. We have a series of ministerial trade missions to various markets every year with intensive engagement. I will try to find the specific section on pig meat, but there are intensive engagements. It is not just necessarily about finding new markets; it is about finding the best market for each product and product category. That is what we are trying to do. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_240">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-09-24T18:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_327">We are limited with our time. If Ms McPhillips has details on the efforts to find alternative markets, I ask her to forward those on to the committee. On behalf of the committee, I thank the witnesses for their extensive answers and contributions, and for going back and forth with members today. Go raibh míle maith agaibh. As there are no further matters for discussion today, our meeting stands adjourned. </p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_10"> The joint committee adjourned at 6.02 p.m. until 3.30 p.m. on Wednesday, 1 October 2025.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
