<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#debates">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_disability_matters/2025-05-15/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_disability_matters/2025-05-15/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-05-15" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#author" href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/34/joint_committee_on_disability_matters"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_disability_matters/2025-05-15/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_disability_matters/2025-05-15/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-05-15" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_disability_matters/2025-05-15/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_disability_matters/2025-05-15/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-05-20" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#debates">
        <TLCPerson eId="MauriceQuinlivan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Maurice-Quinlivan.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Maurice Quinlivan"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/chair" showAs="Chair" eId="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/vice_chairman" showAs="Vice Chairman" eId="Vice_Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/author" showAs="author" eId="author"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/editor" showAs="editor" eId="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>AN COMHCHOISTE UM NITHE A BHAINEANN LE MÍCHUMAS</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>Joint Committee on Disability Matters</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2025-05-15">Déardaoin, 15 Bealtaine 2025</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2025-05-15">Thursday, 15 May 2025</docDate>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_en">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_ga">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">Tháinig an Comhchoiste le chéile ag 09:30 a.m.</summary>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">The Joint Committee met at 09:30 a.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_3">Comhaltaí a bhí i láthair / Members present:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_1">Teachtaí Dála / Deputies</p>
              </th>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_2">Seanadóirí / Senators</p>
              </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#MartinDaly">Martin Daly</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#MariaByrne">Maria Byrne</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#SeamusHealy">Seamus Healy</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#TomClonan">Tom Clonan</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#KeiraKeogh">Keira Keogh</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#MargaretMurphyOMahony">Margaret Murphy O'Mahony.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_9">
                  <person refersTo="#ClaireKerrane">Claire Kerrane</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_10">
                  <person refersTo="#LiamQuaide">Liam Quaide</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_11">
                  <person refersTo="#GillianToole">Gillian Toole.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_4">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#MauriceQuinlivan">Teachta / Deputy Maurice Quinlivan sa Chathaoir / in the Chair.</person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Business of Joint Committee<recordedTime time="2025-05-15T09:30:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#MauriceQuinlivan" eId="spk_1">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-05-15T09:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_12">Apologies have been received from Senators Bradley and Harmon. Before we proceed, as this is the first meeting, I have a number of housekeeping matters. In accordance with Standing Orders, I make the following declaration. I do solemnly declare that I will duly and faithfully and to the best of my knowledge and ability, execute the office of Cathaoirleach of the Joint Committee on Disability Matters without fear or favour, apply the rules as laid down by House in an impartial and fair manner, maintain order and uphold the rights and privileges of members in accordance with the Constitution and Standing Orders.</p>
          <p eId="para_13"> I remind members that in order to participate in public meetings, members must be physically present within the confines of the Leinster House complex. Members of the committee attending remotely must do so from within the precincts of Leinster House. Members must be physically present within the confines of the place where the Parliament has chosen to sit, and that is Leinster House. Members are also reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice that they should not criticise or make charges against any person or entity by name, or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable, or otherwise engage in speech that may be regarded as damaging to the good name of the person or entity. Therefore, if their statements are potentially defamatory in relation to an identifiable person or entity, I will direct them to discontinue their remarks. It is imperative that they comply with any such direction I may make.</p>
          <p eId="para_14"> As this is the first meeting I will make a brief introduction. I welcome everybody here congratulate everybody who has been elected for the first time, or re-elected. It is a difficult job, so I say well done to everybody who has done that.</p>
          <p eId="para_15">I intend my remarks this morning to be brief. I am delighted to welcome all the members of the committee and I look forward to working with them all over the course. I have no doubt our committee's work will be watched closely by many individuals and families across the State - the families of those in care, the families of children awaiting a diagnosis, teachers engaged with students who have a disability and of course those citizens who live, study and work every single day with disabilities. The 2022 census recorded in excess of 1 million people reporting they have, to some extent, a long-lasting condition or difficulty. That represents 21.5% of the population of this State, a huge number of people who will be looking to us and counting on us to stand up with them and fight for them. We have a responsibility to serve the people to the best of our ability and I am extremely confident we will do that.</p>
          <p eId="para_16"> Given the importance of the work we will undertake, I am sure that we can do so in a collective and collegial way. For my part, I assure every member that I will chair these meetings in an honest and non-partisan manner. I am always open to feedback, and I urge any member with a concern or query to contact me. I will do my utmost to accommodate all requests. I am conscious too that we have Senators of long-standing tenure and some with a shorter tenure on our committee. If I can assist any member of the committee with anything at all they should please let me know. I believe we all want to delivery on disability matters and I will focus my energy on ensuring we can do so.</p>
          <p eId="para_17"> I take this opportunity to thank and welcome the staff assigned to the committee and I look forward to working ever more closely with them as we advance the committee schedule. I am sure we all have disability matters we will be eager to have discussed at this committee and following meetings. For myself, the priorities I would like to see debated, discussed and worked on include the assessment of needs process, school places for children with additional needs, employment opportunities and challenges for those who have a disability and the services and supports available to those with a disability, including an autism diagnosis.</p>
          <p eId="para_18"> The role of the Joint Committee on Disability Matters also includes monitoring the implementation of the United Nations Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities. The UNCRPD is a mechanism that ensures people with disabilities enjoy the same human rights as everybody else. I look forward to working with members in a genuine spirit of partnership and co-operation as we undertake important collaborative work to ensure a positive impact on the lives of people with disabilities.</p>
          <p eId="para_19"> I thank members for their time. Would anybody like to make a brief contribution or comment? No. We will move on.</p>
          <p eId="para_20"> As members are aware, the committee may choose to elect a Leas-Chathaoirleach who can perform the duties and exercise the authority of the Cathaoirleach in his absence. I propose requesting nominations for the position of Leas-Chathaoirleach. Members may wish to consult with one another and send nominations to the clerk by close of business on 19 May 2025. Ideally, the election of the Leas-Chathaoirleach will take place on 21 May, the second meeting of the committee. Is that agreed? Agreed.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_5"> The joint committee went into private session at 9.38 a.m. and adjourned at 10.11 a.m. until 9.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 21 May 2025.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
