<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#debates">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/select_committee_on_finance_public_expenditure_public_service_reform_and_digitalisation_and_taoiseach/2025-07-09/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/select_committee_on_finance_public_expenditure_public_service_reform_and_digitalisation_and_taoiseach/2025-07-09/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-07-09" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#author" href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/34/select_committee_on_finance_public_expenditure_public_service_reform_and_digitalisation_and_taoiseach"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/select_committee_on_finance_public_expenditure_public_service_reform_and_digitalisation_and_taoiseach/2025-07-09/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/select_committee_on_finance_public_expenditure_public_service_reform_and_digitalisation_and_taoiseach/2025-07-09/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-07-09" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/select_committee_on_finance_public_expenditure_public_service_reform_and_digitalisation_and_taoiseach/2025-07-09/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/select_committee_on_finance_public_expenditure_public_service_reform_and_digitalisation_and_taoiseach/2025-07-09/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-07-12" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#debates">
        <TLCPerson eId="CianOCallaghan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Cian-O'Callaghan.D.2020-02-08" showAs="Cian O'Callaghan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ColmBurke" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Colm-Burke.S.2011-05-25" showAs="Colm Burke"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="EdwardTimmins" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Edward-Timmins.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Edward Timmins"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ErinMcGreehan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Erin-McGreehan.S.2020-06-29" showAs="Erin McGreehan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="GeraldNash" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Gerald-Nash.D.2011-03-09" showAs="Ged Nash"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MaireadFarrell" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Mairéad-Farrell.D.2020-02-08" showAs="Mairéad Farrell"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MichaelMartin" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Micheál-Martin.D.1989-06-29" showAs="Micheál Martin"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PearseDoherty" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Pearse-Doherty.S.2007-07-23" showAs="Pearse Doherty"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/chair" showAs="Chair" eId="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/vice_chairman" showAs="Vice Chairman" eId="Vice_Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/author" showAs="author" eId="author"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/editor" showAs="editor" eId="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>AN ROGHCHOISTE UM AIRGEADAS, CAITEACHAS POIBLÍ, ATHCHÓIRIÚCHÁN SEIRBHÍSE POIBLÍ AGUS DIGITIÚCHÁN, AGUS AN TAOISEACH</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>Select Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure, Public Service Reform and Digitalisation, and Taoiseach</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2025-07-09">Dé Céadaoin, 09 Iúil 2025</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2025-07-09">Wednesday, 09 July 2025</docDate>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_en">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_ga">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">Tháinig an Roghchoiste le chéile ag 04:00 p.m.</summary>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">The Select Committee met at 04:00 p.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_3">Comhaltaí a bhí i láthair / Members present:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_1">Teachtaí Dála / Deputies</p>
              </th>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_2"/>
              </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#ColmBurke">Colm Burke</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#PearseDoherty">Pearse Doherty</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#MichaelMartin">Micheál Martin (The Taoiseach)</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#ErinMcGreehan">Erin McGreehan</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#GeraldNash">Ged Nash</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#CianOCallaghan">Cian O'Callaghan</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_9">
                  <person refersTo="#EdwardTimmins">Edward Timmins.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_4">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#MaireadFarrell">Teachta / Deputy Mairéad Farrell sa Chathaoir / in the Chair.</person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Estimates for Public Services 2025<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>Vote 1 - President's Establishment  (Revised)<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_4">
        <heading>Vote 2 - Department of the Taoiseach (Revised)<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_5">
        <heading>Vote 3 - Office of the Attorney General (Revised)<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_6">
        <heading>Vote 4 - Central Statistics Office (Revised)<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_7">
        <heading>Vote 5 - Office of the Director of Public Prosecutions (Revised)<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></heading>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_8">
        <heading>Vote 6 - Office of the Chief State Solicitor (Revised)<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_1">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_10">Tá leithscéal faighte againn ón Teachta Dála Shay Brennan. Is mian liom na riachtanais bhunreachtúla seo a leanas a mheabhrú do chomhaltaí agus páirt á glacadh acu i gcruinnithe poiblí. Caithfidh comhaltaí a bheith i láthair go fisiciúil laistigh de theorainneacha shuíomh Theach Laighean. Ní cheadóidh mé do chomhaltaí páirt a ghlacadh i gcruinnithe poiblí nuair nach bhfuil siad ag cloí leis an riachtanas bunreachtúil seo. Mar sin, má dhéanann aon chomhalta iarracht páirt a ghlacadh ó lasmuigh den suíomh, iarrfaidh mé orthu an cruinniú a fhágáil. Maidir leis seo, iarraim ar chomhaltaí a dheimhniú go bhfuil siad i láthair laistigh de phurláin Theach Laighean sula ndéanann siad aon ionchur sa chruinniú ar MS Teams.</p>
          <p eId="para_11"> Fiafraítear de chomhaltaí cleachtadh parlaiminte a urramú, nár chóir, más féidir, daoine nó eintiteas a cháineadh ná líomhaintí a dhéanamh ina n-aghaidh ná tuairimí a thabhairt maidir leo ina ainm, ina hainm nó ina n-ainmneacha ar shlí a bhféadfaí iad a aithint. Chomh maith leis sin, fiafraítear díobh gan aon rud a rá a d’fhéadfaí breathnú air mar ábhar díobhálach do dhea-chlú aon duine nó eintiteas. Mar sin, dá bhféadfadh a ráitis a bheith clúmhillteach do dhuine nó d'eintiteas aitheanta, ordóidh mé dóibh éirí as an ráiteas láithreach. Tá sé ríthábhachtach go ngéillfidís don ordú sin láithreach.</p>
          <p eId="para_12"> I advise members of the constitutional requirement that they must be physically present within the confines of the Leinster House complex to participate in public meetings. I will not permit a member to participate where he or she is not adhering to this constitutional requirement. Therefore, a member who attempts to participate from outside the precincts will be asked to leave the meeting. In this regard, I ask any member participating via MS Teams that prior to making their contribution to the meeting, they confirm that they are on the grounds of the Leinster House campus.</p>
          <p eId="para_13"> Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice that they should not criticise or make charges against any person or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable or otherwise engage in speech that might be regarded as damaging to the good name of the person or entity. Therefore, if their statements are potentially defamatory in respect of an identifiable person or entity, they will be directed to discontinue their remarks. It is imperative that they comply with any such direction.</p>
          <p eId="para_14"> For the context of today, the Select Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure, Public Service Reform and Digitalisation, and Taoiseach is meeting to consider the Revised Estimates Votes 1 to 6, inclusive, for the Office of An Taoiseach. The Revised Estimates Volume for public services, REV, provides considerably more detail at subhead level as well as performance metrics. Revised Estimates are the revised, final proposed spending for the next year and form the basis for parliamentary scrutiny of allocated expenditure. I welcome An Taoiseach and his officials to today's meeting. I invite An Taoiseach, Micheál Martin, to make his opening statement.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_2">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_15">A Chathaoirligh agus a chomhaltaí an chomhchoiste, gabhaim buíochas libh as an deis seo chun teacht os comhair an roghchoiste agus sibh ag déanamh machnamh ar Mheastacháin 2025 do ghrúpa Vótaí Roinn an Taoisigh. Tá sé Vóta i ngrúpa Vótaí Roinn an Taoisigh, is iad sin: Vóta 1 - Arás an Uachtaráin; Vóta 2 – Roinn an Taoisigh; Vóta 3 – Oifig an Ard-Aighne; Vóta 4 – Príomh-Oifig Staidrimh; Vóta 5 – Oifig an Stiúrthóra Ionchúiseamh Poiblí; agus Vóta 6 – Oifig Phríomh-Aturnae an Stáit. Soláthraíodh doiciméad faisnéise le haghaidh gach ceann de na Vótaí seo don choiste roimh an gcruinniú seo. Cé go bhfuil freagrachtaí ar leith orm don Oireachtas mar gheall ar chúrsaí riaracháin i gcuid de na hoifigí seo, oibríonn siad go neamhspleách ó Roinn an Taoisigh.</p>
          <p eId="para_16"> I appreciate the opportunity to appear before the select committee as it considers the 2025 Estimates for the Vote group of the Department of the Taoiseach. I have already outlined as Gaeilge the six Votes that make up the Department of the Taoiseach. A briefing document for each of these Votes has been supplied to the committee in advance of this meeting. While I have certain responsibilities to the Oireachtas for administrative matters in some of these offices, they operate independently of the Department of the Taoiseach.</p>
          <p eId="para_17"> The gross funding allocation sought for the Vote group for 2025 totals just over €292 million, an increase of 7% on 2024. I will now give a brief overview of the 2025 funding allocations for each individual Vote.</p>
          <p eId="para_18"> In respect of Vote 1 - President's Establishment, the purpose of the Vote allocation for this Vote is to support the President’s Establishment to deliver its high level goal to provide high quality, timely support services to the President in the execution of his constitutional, legal and representational duties and responsibilities and to provide for payment of the centenarians’ bounty in a timely and expeditious manner. The 2025 gross Estimate for the President’s Establishment is €5.5 million; an increase of 4% on 2024. The increase in this Vote reflects the increase in administrative subheads for pay and operating expenses.</p>
          <p eId="para_19"> In respect of Vote 2 - Department of the Taoiseach, the purpose of the Vote allocation is to support the Department to deliver its high level goals of helping the Taoiseach and the Government to ensure a sustainable economy and a successful society, pursuing Ireland’s interests abroad, implementing the Government’s programme and building a better future for Ireland and all her citizens. The 2025 gross Estimate for the Department of the Taoiseach is €38.2 million, a decrease of €581,000 compared with 2024. A total of 67%, or €25.42 million, of the Vote allocation relates to salaries, wages and allowances. Administration costs for the Department account for 16%. The remaining 17% provides non-pay funding for the National Economic and Social Development Office, the COVID-19 evaluation, Citizens' Assembly and a number of independent inquiries.</p>
          <p eId="para_20"> On Vote 3 - Office of the Attorney General, the purpose of the Vote allocation is to support the Office of the Attorney General to deliver its high level goal of providing the highest standard of professional legal services to Government, Departments and offices as economically and efficiently as possible and to support adherence to the rule of law. The 2025 gross Estimate for the Office of the Attorney General is €26.3 million, an increase of 6% on 2024. A sum of €3.35 million of the Office of the Attorney General’s 2025 Estimate is allocated to the Law Reform Commission, an increase of 10% on 2024. A total of 78%, €20.36 million, of the Office of the Attorney General’s Vote allocation relates to salaries, wages and allowances. The 2025 provision for pay is €20.362 million, an increase of 13% on 2024. This reflects the increase in costs for current staff in addition to the need to increase staff numbers, which is required to support the timely implementation of the programme for Government. This increase is partially offset by savings in non-pay expenditure.</p>
          <p eId="para_21"> On Vote 4 - Central Statistics Office, the purpose of the Vote allocation is to support the office to deliver its high level goal to describe Ireland, its people, economy, society and environment through verifiable data and accurate information while providing impartial insight. The 2025 gross Estimate for the CSO is €94.8 million, an increase of 14% on 2024. A total of 76%, which is €72 million, of the CSO’s Vote is pay related, with the remaining 24% split across the non-pay subheads. The 2025 gross Estimate includes €1.2 million national recovery and resilience plan funding for the provision of an online census platform.</p>
          <p eId="para_22"> On Vote 5 - Office of the Director for Public Prosecutions, the purpose of the Vote allocation is to support the office to deliver its high level goal to provide, on behalf of the people of Ireland, a prosecution service which is independent, fair and effective.</p>
          <p eId="para_23">The 2025 gross Estimate for the Office of the Director of Public Prosecutions is €73.1 million, an increase of 9% on 2024. The 9% increase on 2024 is principally made up of an increase of €3.96 million in pay, an increase of €1.08 million in fees to counsel and an increase of €800,000 in the local State solicitor service. This increased funding allocation will provide for the additional staff required to deal with the increase in the volume and complexity of file activity levels in recent years. It will also allow for the development of the prosecution service in key areas such as financial crime and sexual offences in addition to the core legal work of the office, including a significant increase in court sittings in the Central Criminal Court and Circuit Courts in particular.</p>
          <p eId="para_24"> On Vote 6 - Office of the Chief State Solicitor, the purpose of this Vote allocation is to support the office in delivering its high level goal to provide the highest standard of professional legal services to Government Departments and offices as economically and efficiently as possible and to support adherence to the rule of law. The 2025 gross Estimate for the Office of the Chief State Solicitor is €54.5 million, an increase of 2% on 2024. This increase in funding is primarily attributable to funding higher staff and operational costs at the office.</p>
          <p eId="para_25"> I welcome the opportunity to engage further with the committee on the 2025 Revised Estimates for the Vote group of the Department of the Taoiseach. I will endeavour to provide any further information required. Given the breadth of the Vote group in terms of activities, functions and responsibilities and the independent status of a number of the offices in the group, I may not be able to provide all information requested by members in the room today. If that proves to be the case, I will revert to the Chair in writing as soon as possible thereafter with the relevant information. I thank the members for their attention and commend the 2025 Revised Estimates for Votes 1 to 6 to the committee.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_3">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_26">I now invite members to discuss these Estimates. I remind members participating remotely to use the "raise hand" function. I also remind members that there is a tight timeline for this meeting. I ask people to be as succinct as possible. Members will have a maximum of five minutes each.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GeraldNash" eId="spk_4">
          <from>Deputy Ged Nash<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_27">The Taoiseach and his officials are very welcome. He has said that he is going to prioritise addressing child poverty. That is a worthy ambition and one all of us should share. An office has been established in the Taoiseach's Department to address that issue on the well-being of children. How many whole-time equivalent staff are engaged in that unit?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_5">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_28">The Deputy is correct; the programme for Government commits to retaining the child poverty and well-being programme office in the Department of the Taoiseach. I have decided to retain that with a view to breaking down silos across Government and driving the delivery of measures aimed at reducing child poverty. There are six full-time equivalent staff. This comprises one principal officer, two assistant principal officers, two administrative officers and one Irish Government Economic and Evaluation Service, IGEES, intern.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GeraldNash" eId="spk_6">
          <from>Deputy Ged Nash<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_29">Is that the same as under the previous administration or are there additional staff compared to-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_7">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_30">There are no additional staff. An assistant secretary oversees the office.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GeraldNash" eId="spk_8">
          <from>Deputy Ged Nash<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_31">I will put a couple of questions, if I may. I appreciate that we are under time pressure. On subhead A.6, relating to citizens' assemblies, I note that €1.547 million was allocated last year. It is €500,000 this year. I know there was a very active series of citizens' assemblies during the previous administration. What are the plans for citizens' assemblies for this administration? My understanding is that there may only be one, a citizens' assembly on the future of education. What are the plans for future citizens' assemblies? Why has there been a reduction? There are none this year. Is this €500,000 to clear up some of the outstanding work of the previous assemblies? What are the plans for the assembly on education?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_9">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_32">The Deputy is correct that provision has not been made for citizens' assemblies this year. On education, we envisage a national convention-type approach. This is different from the model of a citizens' assembly. The Deputy might recall a similar national convention on education being convened by the then Minister for Education, the late Niamh Bhreathnach, in the mid-1990s. I happened to be the Opposition spokesperson at that time. The Minister agrees with the programme for Government commitment to create a national conversation on education more generally, in which stakeholders could engage. It is a better model in terms of public representatives and stakeholders involved in education all contributing.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GeraldNash" eId="spk_10">
          <from>Deputy Ged Nash<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_33">There are no plans for citizens' assemblies as we knew them in the previous administration or for constitutional conventions. It will be a different model.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_11">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_34">Yes, but I am not ruling out the potential for future citizens' assemblies on other topics.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GeraldNash" eId="spk_12">
          <from>Deputy Ged Nash<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_35">There are none committed to in the programme for Government.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_13">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_36">There are none committed to but I am not ruling it out in the event that someone comes forward with an idea. We need to review the methodology and model of citizens' assemblies, particularly in light of the last two. We also have to work through the recommendations of the last number of citizens' assemblies and get some traction on them, which is also important, rather than just allowing them to build up on top of each other.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GeraldNash" eId="spk_14">
          <from>Deputy Ged Nash<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_37">On the Attorney General's Vote, I understand that it is an independent office. That is well accepted. The Taoiseach may not have this material available to him but he might engage with the committee if he does not. Under subhead A.6, which relates to the consolidation and revision of planning legislation, the Estimate last year was €250,000 but nothing has been allocated this year. I assume that €250,000 was for the engagement of consultants and outside advice on the planning Bill.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_15">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_38">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GeraldNash" eId="spk_16">
          <from>Deputy Ged Nash<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_39">Does the Taoiseach know who provided that advice? Was it a number of different firms or individual barristers?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_17">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_40">I do not have that-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#GeraldNash" eId="spk_18">
          <from>Deputy Ged Nash<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_41">Could it be forwarded to the committee?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_19">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_42">Yes. It would obviously fall under the remit of the Attorney General's office. We do not have a role in that. I do not have a role as regards the specifics of who is retained. Over the period of the work on the planning Act, given the enormity of the legislation, external legal advice was sought. What the Deputy is witnessing is the winding-down of that as the Act has now been passed. The respective Departments are now actually dealing with it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CianOCallaghan" eId="spk_20">
          <from>Deputy Cian O'Callaghan<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_43">I thank the Taoiseach and his officials for their attendance. On Vote 2 and section C of the briefing note, which is on sustaining the economy and investment, it is reported in today's <i>Business Post</i> that Irish banks are earning substantially more on mortgages than their UK counterparts. Research from RBC Capital Markets shows that Irish retail banks, AIB, Bank of Ireland and PTSB, are earning higher margins on mortgages than lenders in the UK. The average spread on Irish mortgages, the difference between the interest banks charge and the interest they pay, was almost 2% in quarter 2 of this year. The comparable figure in the UK was less than 0.6%. That has particular economic impacts in respect of people's ability to access and afford housing. What is the Taoiseach's view on this? Does something need to be done about it? What sort of action or approach could be taken?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_21">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_44">I have not read that article. I would like to read it before offering a detailed view. Because of the various housing schemes we have introduced, particularly the help-to-buy and first home schemes, there has been exponential growth in the number of new mortgages drawn down by first-time buyers. The banks have an obligation to make sure they give fair and equitable treatment to those mortgage holders, who are predominantly younger people starting out in life. I also believe the banks should be lending more to the construction industry in the Republic. I do not believe the lending is of sufficient scale given the huge issue housing represents and the pent-up demand. In my view, there would be an adequate return. Lending is far too conservative at the moment. The cost of financing is an issue in construction. The banks could play a stronger role on that. The banks are doing well out of the mortgage market. They have two responsibilities. They must be fair and equitable to those taking out mortgages but they must also lend more to smaller builders and construction companies on economic terms. That would aid the more rapid construction of houses and apartments.</p>
          <p eId="para_45">I will examine this and I will also revert to the Minister for Finance. I have not read the report in detail. I appreciate that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CianOCallaghan" eId="spk_22">
          <from>Deputy Cian O'Callaghan<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_46">Given credible analysis has reported the margin on mortgages in Ireland is more than three times that of the UK, with respect to the gap in the interest rates, that is very serious. It has very serious impacts on people trying to get somewhere to live. That then has very serious knock-on impacts for the economy in terms of housing supply, wage growth and pressures there.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_23">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_47">I would prefer to have a broader read of not just the article but the full background with regard to comparisons between the UK and our market. The Minister for Finance obviously deals regularly, via the Central Bank, with the commercial banks. That is an issue that will be examined by the Government, but again I have not seen the article.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CianOCallaghan" eId="spk_24">
          <from>Deputy Cian O'Callaghan<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_48">Would the Taoiseach be happy to come back to the committee on it after that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_25">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_49">I would. It is not relevant to this budget but I have no problem coming back.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CianOCallaghan" eId="spk_26">
          <from>Deputy Cian O'Callaghan<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_50">It is. The Taoiseach has a larger briefing note on Vote 2 about sustaining the economy and investment and I think this is absolutely relevant to that. If the Taoiseach is going to produce the briefing note-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_27">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_51">But I have not read the article.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CianOCallaghan" eId="spk_28">
          <from>Deputy Cian O'Callaghan<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_52">He might come back to the committee on it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_29">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_53">I thank the Taoiseach and his staff for coming in here. It is great to have them here. It is my first time meeting the Taoiseach here at committee and I thank him for that. My questions are technical. They are on the budget and the numbers. I have a couple of more general questions that I will ask in the next session. I thought this was more confined to the numbers.</p>
          <p eId="para_54"> I have five or six questions. On page 2 of the summary note the Taoiseach gave for the Department of the Taoiseach, the outturn for 2024 was down between €4 million and €4.5 million. It was projected to be €37 million in 2024 and the outturn was actually €33 million. I wonder why that was down €4.5 million.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_30">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_55">That Vote relates to the commissions of inquiry. There is a variety of them on the go, so to speak. When you draw down the expenses or bills for those, they come at different times.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_31">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_56">It is primarily a timing issue then.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_32">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_57">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_33">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_58">Okay. The second question is on the budget itself and the figures. On page 32, Vote 2, I wish to comment generally. This is a theme common to a lot of this document. We do not have 2024 data. Say, on page 32, the data on stuff like public service-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_34">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_59">For which, did you say?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_35">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_60">Page 32, on the budget. I am also working with that full budget document, the 250-page document where the Votes are broken down. It is a general point I am making.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_36">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_61">The Deputy has the REV.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_37">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_62">The whole budget book.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_38">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_63">The Revised Estimates Volume.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_39">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_64">I do not have that here with me but the Deputy can go ahead.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_40">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_65">I have a general comment on it. It only has 2023 figures for a lot of the statistics on public policy impact, outcomes, growth, employment, income and poverty levels. It does not have 2024. As a general point, I have raised this issue on other Votes, where statistics are not up to date. We are seeing, 18 months later, the statistics for 2023. We should really be seeing 2024. It is not specific to the Department of the Taoiseach but generally, the statistics on the reports-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_41">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_66">The REV would have been published towards the end of last year. That is the 2024 REV the Deputy is looking at it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_42">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_67">So we do not have up-to-date figures.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_43">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_68">You would not have 2024 data in 2024.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_44">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_69">Okay, if it was the end of 2024. I am not sure what date that was published.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_45">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_70">I think it was the third week of December last year.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_46">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_71">Okay. That answers that question. This comes up a good bit - Vote 4, page 36 on the REV - salary increase. I have seen that across Votes 5, 6 and 4, which I will bring to the Taoiseach's attention first. There is a 13% increase in salaries under Vote 4. Is there any particular reason for that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_47">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_72">A public service pay award. That is the Vote for the Central Statistics Office, so that would include the conduct of the census.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_48">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_73">Vote 4 - CSO.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_49">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_74">Yes, that would be the census.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_50">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_75">I have the same question on Vote 5, where there is an increase of 16%. That is the office of the DPP.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_51">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_76">It sought additional staffing and over the last number of years would have advocated for significantly increased resources. When I was formerly Taoiseach, I would have received correspondence in respect of this. With regard to the conduct of justice and our criminal justice system, in my view it is important we would respond to that. It is increased staffing and there are pay agreements.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_52">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_77">The same then for the Chief State Solicitor's office. That went up by a similar percentage, between 14% and 16%. Was it for the same reason?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_53">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_78">There were similar reasons. I will make a general point that historically we might have been penny-wise, pound-foolish in our approach to these agencies. I am of the view that the more efficient these bodies are, particularly in regard to the DPP and the Chief State Solicitor's office, the greater return to the State. With respect to the enormity of allocation in other Departments, we have to build really sustainable capacity in these organisations across the board.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_54">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_79">The Taoiseach would expect to see increased outputs as a result. It is not just extra salaries.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_55">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_80">You would, that is fair. You would, and we are.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_56">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_81">That makes sense.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_57">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_82">Gabhaim buíochas leis an Teachta.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_58">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_83">I have one last question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_59">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_84">Very briefly.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_60">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_85">Do all of those Departments review their spending every month?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_61">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_86">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_62">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_87">They do. Okay.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_63">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_88">That was lovely and succinct. Gabhaim buíochas libh. Bogaimid ar aghaidh le Teachta Burke.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ColmBurke" eId="spk_64">
          <from>Deputy Colm Burke<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_89">I thank the Taoiseach for making time available to be with us this evening. With regard to the DPP budget, I see there is a 177% increase in the number of court dates in the Central Criminal Court. There is the fact that in 2019, there were 127 court dates in the Central Criminal Court and by 2024, those outside the Central Criminal Court were up by 572%; in other words, it was outside of the Dublin base. The biggest problem with the creation of efficiencies in the courts is how our Prison Service adapts to that. In fairness to the DPP, all of the State solicitors and the gardaí, it is a really efficient organisation but the end result is our prison system not being able to adapt accordingly. I wonder if that is a concern, if we continue to increase the efficiency. The briefing we have got here shows the increase in the number of staff in the DPP. The problem is the logjam that results with regard to the Prison Service. I wonder if there is co-ordination in dealing with that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_65">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_90">In the first instance, the Deputy has acknowledged, to be fair, the enormous increases with respect to court cases, prosecutions and so on and yes, that does have an impact on the prison population. That is why the Minister for justice has sought and received Government approval for a significantly increased allocation in the short term to increase prison capacity because there is overcrowding in our prisons. There will have to be a medium-term programme with regard to prison expansion and a longer-term one as well. It reflects a significant growth in population over the last two decades. It has been very dramatic, certainly in the last 20 years. For the first time ever, the increase in population has meant that the island of Ireland is now above pre-Famine levels in population terms. That is impacting on all services. It may also be impacting in this area. The Deputy is predominantly right; there is a greater throughput so that will impact on the Prison Service. Not all of it necessarily has to, as the Deputy knows. There can be alternatives as well.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ColmBurke" eId="spk_66">
          <from>Deputy Colm Burke<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_91">Going back on the court dates, my apologies. There were 127 court dates of the Central Criminal Court outside of Dublin in 2019. By 2024, the number of court dates outside of Dublin was 854.</p>
          <p eId="para_92">That moves me on to the issue of opening a DPP office in Cork. I assume it has to do with having more Central Criminal Court hearings outside Dublin. There is a provision in the budget for the opening of that office in Cork. When will that office be fully operational? Does that mean that, when it moves to Cork, State solicitors' roles within the county will be removed? In other words, it will all be focused in the DPP office in Cork.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_67">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_93">The movement of the DPP to Cork is reflective of the city's status as a growing regional city.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_68">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_94">Be careful what you say.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_69">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_95">Bí cúramach anois.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ColmBurke" eId="spk_70">
          <from>Deputy Colm Burke<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_96">In fairness, we do have-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_71">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_97">No, but every now and again, people want all sorts.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EdwardTimmins" eId="spk_72">
          <from>Deputy Edward Timmins<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_98">We are doing our best for you, Taoiseach.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_73">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_99">You are doing your best. Fair play to you.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ColmBurke" eId="spk_74">
          <from>Deputy Colm Burke<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_100">We do have a very efficient Courts Service in Cork and the new courthouse-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_75">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_101">I know. I remember that, when the new courts were built in the Model School, there were a lot of people objecting. They preferred the older, medieval buildings, but that comes from the legal profession from time to time.</p>
          <p eId="para_102"> To be serious, I will revert to the Minister for justice in respect of what his plans are for the State Solicitor's offices. I do not have a timeline, but I will endeavour to get that for the Deputy.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ColmBurke" eId="spk_76">
          <from>Deputy Colm Burke<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_103">There will be a permanent office for the DPP in Cork and it will be fully staffed with a view to handling cases, I presume, for the Munster region. Is that the plan for dealing with that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_77">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_104">I will have to come back to the Deputy with the exact nature of the programmes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ColmBurke" eId="spk_78">
          <from>Deputy Colm Burke<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_105">Okay. Just going back to-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_79">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_106">Just very briefly, a Theachta.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ColmBurke" eId="spk_80">
          <from>Deputy Colm Burke<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_107">-----the appointment of additional judges, it means we are going to be increasing the throughput in the courts. We have increased the number of judges by, I think, 24.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_81">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_108">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ColmBurke" eId="spk_82">
          <from>Deputy Colm Burke<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_109">There is a proposal to increase it by a further 20. That means there is going to be an increase in volume and in the number of criminal cases that will be dealt with. It comes back to my original question about the capacity within the service to deal with the convictions and sentences after that. I am just wondering if the next three to four years of that have been thought out.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_83">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_110">The increase in judges is not just about criminal cases. It is right across the board, from commercial courts-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ColmBurke" eId="spk_84">
          <from>Deputy Colm Burke<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_111">I accept that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_85">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_112">-----to environmental courts, and justice delayed is justice denied.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ColmBurke" eId="spk_86">
          <from>Deputy Colm Burke<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_113">Absolutely.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_87">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_114">We were too low. As the Deputy said, the last Government took significant steps to increase the numbers, relatively speaking. Normally, there would two or three judges at a time, or just one, but we took a big decision-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ColmBurke" eId="spk_88">
          <from>Deputy Colm Burke<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_115">At one stage, there were 6,000-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_89">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_116">Go raibh maith agat.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ColmBurke" eId="spk_90">
          <from>Deputy Colm Burke<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_117">-----cases waiting for a hearing in the High Court in Cork.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_91">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_118">We are out of time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_92">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_119">What I am saying is it is about efficiency and, in particular, the economic aspect. A lot of these decisions have big economic weight and impact, so more judges are justified on that basis to get greater throughput of cases.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_93">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_120">Go raibh maith agat. Bogaimid ar aghaigh go dtí an Teachta Doherty agus ansin an Teachta McGreehan.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_94">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_121">Go raibh maith agat. Cuirim fáilte roimh an Taoiseach. On Vote 2 for his Department, there is a small increase in travel and subsistence. Some of the Taoiseach's travel made it into the media recently. He has returned from a trip to Japan and he rebooked that trip home through Toronto. It is suggested that was on the basis of security advice. If that is the case, will he explain why he did not share the security advice with any of the media corps who were travelling? Were there no issues with their security?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_95">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_122">It is a nonsense story.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_96">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_123">Okay, but will the Taoiseach answer the question?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_97">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_124">I am, but it is important the context is made very clear. The story is suggesting there was a rescheduling to do with the match. There was not. The alternative would have had me in at midday and the way I went, I came in at 8 a.m. I had nothing to do with it. I do not book the travel, so it was a nonsense story.</p>
          <p eId="para_125"> In terms of security, remember that these were booked a week in advance. There are issues in the Middle East, as we all know, in terms of cancellation of flights and challenges. That was the precautionary approach those who were booking the flights took. That is it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_98">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_126">So, it was on the basis of security advice.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_99">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_127">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_100">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_128">Does the Taoiseach know how many of the media travelled to Japan? Was it about ten or so?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_101">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_129">No, I do not think so. Was it?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_102">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_130">Okay. Did the Taoiseach's Department share-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_103">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_131">I am not sure-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_104">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_132">Hold on. Let me at least put the question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_105">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_133">Can we just have one voice at a time?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_106">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_134">Sorry, yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_107">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_135">What the Taoiseach has just told us is his Department had security advice not to fly into Dubai on the way home, so the flights were booked through Toronto at a cost to the taxpayer. There were media travelling with the Taoiseach and it appears his office never shared the security advice with members of the Irish media. Can he explain why? If there was security advice that there was a risk in him flying through Dubai, why would he not share that with other Irish citizens who were accompanying him on the trip?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_108">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_136">Two things. First of all, there was not an additional cost as a result of that, to my knowledge-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_109">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_137">The flights through Toronto were free, were they?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_110">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_138">Do not be getting facetious.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_111">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_139">No. If there was no additional cost-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_112">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_140">The flights on the other route would have been the same, roughly, so-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_113">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_141">Did the Taoiseach not have two flights at that stage?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_114">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_142">One speaker at a time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_115">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_143">Did the Taoiseach get a full refund on the original flights booked?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_116">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_144">I do not get involved in this.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_117">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_145">Okay.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_118">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_146">I do not get into the minutiae of the routes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_119">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_147">The Taoiseach suggested there was no cost. It appears from the story that he booked flights back through Dubai-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_120">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_148">I am not responsible for this.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_121">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_149">-----and then there were other flights booked. Therefore, there would have been an additional cost.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_122">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_150">No, there were not other flights booked. I am not responsible for the story. The Deputy can appreciate that. The story was all about the match and-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_123">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_151">I am asking about the security advice. Will the Taoiseach go back to the core question of why his Department did not share the concerns it had about his travel through Dubai with members of the Irish press corps who did travel through Dubai?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_124">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_152">Any journalist who is sent out by his or her media organisation takes his or her own advices. Journalists organise their own travel and so forth. The people who were organising it on my behalf took a view that the Middle East was problematic in terms of cancellations and activity there, potentially, and therefore took this route. That is what I have been told.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_125">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_153">It is a bit bizarre because the Taoiseach's Department gave out information on travel like what trains to book and so on, but not on a security risk over the flight back. As the Taoiseach mentioned, it was more about cancellation as opposed to anything personally happening to him. The story suggests that, out of an abundance of caution, the Taoiseach flew through Toronto because there was a risk of cancellation and, therefore, he would miss the match. That is what the story says.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_126">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_154">Hold on now.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_127">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_155">That is what the story says. The Taoiseach makes the point that there was no additional cost. Can he confirm that with the Department? Has it provided the figure for the additional cost? Obviously, there had to be an additional cost. Is it not the case there were flights already booked home through Dubai and then the Department booked other flights through Toronto? Can the Taoiseach outline the costs associated with his party of seven?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_128">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_156">The Deputy has made an assertion again that is wrong.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_129">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_157">I said the story was about the flight. That is what the story is.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_130">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_158">No, you said it was about the match.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_131">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_159">No, I said the story-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_132">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_160">You did. You did say it in your last comment. I unequivocally and categorically say that the truth does matter in these matters. This had nothing to do with the match. The match was on at 5 p.m. that day, so either route would have had me in at 8 a.m. or midday, so-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_133">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_161">You made the point there was a risk of cancellation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_134">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_162">-----I did not get-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_135">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_163">You made the point there was a risk of cancellation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_136">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_164">We are low on time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_137">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_165">No, you are conflating-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_138">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_166">One speaker at a time and we are low on time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_139">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_167">The Deputy is conflating and this has nothing to do with budgets or anything. It is just political you-know-what, stirring it up. That is what the Deputy is at and it is regrettable.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_140">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_168">We are wrapping this up.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_141">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_169">I want to say this much-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_142">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_170">Can the Taoiseach answer the question?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_143">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_171">I will. It was to mitigate any risk of flight cancellations generally. It had nothing to do-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_144">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_172">If the flight was cancelled, the Taoiseach would have missed the match.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_145">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_173">Go raibh maith agaibh.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_146">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_174">Rubbish. Rubbish.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_147">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_175">Go raibh maith agaibh.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_148">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_176">That is a fact.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_149">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_177">It is not.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_150">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_178">A Theachta Doherty, your time is up.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_151">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_179">If the flight was cancelled, Taoiseach,-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_152">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_180">You are stirring it as usual.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_153">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_181">-----you would have missed the match.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_154">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_182">One moment.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_155">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_183">That is a simple fact.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_156">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_184">No,-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_157">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_185">There is only one speaker at a time-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_158">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_186">-----because the security situation-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_159">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_187">-----and your times are up.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_160">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_188">-----had already resulted in extensive Middle East airspace being closed in the days prior to this being booked, so-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_161">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_189">How much did it cost?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_162">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_190">We are out of time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_163">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_191">You are the official, now-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_164">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_192">I have asked the question numerous times. How much-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_165">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_193">But you will not listen because you are not asking questions. You are asserting falsehoods.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_166">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_194">You are not willing to answer the question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_167">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_195">You are asserting falsehoods, Deputy,-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_168">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_196">A Theachta and a Thaoisigh-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_169">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_197">-----you will not allow a reasonable, rational explanation to be given and you are making assertions that are-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_170">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_198">We heard your explanation. This is the Estimates-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_171">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_199">I am sorry, now. You are both out of time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_172">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_200">With respect, Chair-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_173">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_201">You are both out of time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_174">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_202">The Deputy is not giving me a chance to answer the thing.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_175">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_203">Can the Taoiseach please outline to the committee-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_176">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_204">You are both out of time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_177">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_205">-----the additional cost involved in bookings for Toronto?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_178">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_206">I do not have the costs.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_179">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_207">Will the Taoiseach provide them to the committee?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_180">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_208">We can do that, no problem. The final costs-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_181">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_209">Perfect.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_182">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_210">Without delay, please.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_183">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_211">The final costs have not been reconciled.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_184">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_212">Bogaimid ar aghaigh go dtí an Teachta McGreehan.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_185">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_213">I am sorry, but could I just say that the final costs will be included in the Department's foreign travel report published on <i>gov.ie</i>, as we always do.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_186">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_214">Go raibh maith agat, a Thaoisigh.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_187">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_215">I am asking the Taoiseach to provide them to the committee without delay.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_188">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_216">I know, but I ask the Deputy to withdraw the assertion that there was any implication we changed-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_189">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_217">I am not withdrawing the assertion.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_190">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_218">Well, you should.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_191">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_219">The assertion was the story in the media was that you travelled through Toronto-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_192">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_220">It is a false-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_193">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_221">-----because there was a risk your original flight would be cancelled,-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_194">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_222">A Theachta agus a Thaoisigh-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_195">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_223">-----and if your original flight was cancelled----- </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_196">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_224">A Theachta, your time is up.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_197">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_225">No.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_198">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_226">-----you would have missed the match.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_199">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_227">That is a false-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_200">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_228">Your time is up.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_201">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_229">What I want to know is how much did the taxpayer pay for that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_202">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_230">That is a false assertion.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_203">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_231">Your time is up.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_204">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_232">That is not my story; it is the media's.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_205">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_233">Yes, but your time is up.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_206">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_234">You are articulating a false story deliberately.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_207">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_235">The time is up.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_208">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_236">I am stating a fact.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_209">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_237">Both your times are up.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_210">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_238">No you are not. It is outrageous.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_211">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_239">The fact is that the story was written.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_212">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_240">A chairde, both your times are up and we are now moving on to an Teachta McGreehan.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_213">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_241">Bad stuff. Just very poor politics.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_214">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_242">We are moving on to an Teachta McGreehan. If you do not stop, I will not have time-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PearseDoherty" eId="spk_215">
          <from>Deputy Pearse Doherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_243">It is bad that you do not have the answer as to how much it cost.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_216">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_244">One week on?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_217">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_245">I am going to have to turn off your mics. I call on an Teachta McGreehan.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ErinMcGreehan" eId="spk_218">
          <from>Deputy Erin McGreehan<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_246">We are finished with Deputy Doherty's clickbait. Good man. We will move on. My question is about the NESC. This is obviously budgeted from last year, but I am looking towards the future as to what is planned for next year for the NESC and its works. I am looking at its subgroups and what Deputy Ged Nash spoke about earlier, including child poverty and disability. I know there has been a huge emphasis on disability in the programme for Government. What will the NESC advise those subcommittees in the year coming?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_219">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_247">It is covering six main areas, including Ireland's future power system and economic resilience. That is investigating the impact of renewable targets in four areas: economic and enterprise opportunities, reliability of supply, energy costs and the export potential. It is working on deepening compact growth in Ireland, connecting people to the energy transition, international trade dependencies, the energy transition, and carrying and delivery capacity. That is done in collaboration with the National Competitiveness and Productivity Council. That will look at ways Ireland could improve its long-term planning provision and delivery capacity, particularly in housing, infrastructure, healthcare and other services. On artificial intelligence, this work will include a focus on AI adoption and its impact on Irish public services and the labour market. It will focus on issues such as transparency, ethics and equity and will help build public trust and confidence around the challenges and opportunities of AI and hybrid and remote working. This project will explore the evolution and impact on remote and hybrid working in Ireland since 2020. It will commence in quarter 3 of this year. It is expected to conclude in 2026. The small increase in the subhead is mainly to provide for pay increases due in 2025 under the current public sector pay agreement and for pensions and payments for NESDO employees retiring in 2025.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ErinMcGreehan" eId="spk_220">
          <from>Deputy Erin McGreehan<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_248">Going on the very important subcommittees of the Department of the Taoiseach, and looking at the extra staff or personnel or expertise the Taoiseach is bringing in, in particular on the disability committee, the costs that are involved in those experts obviously come out of the Department. Is the Department hiring in those experts?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_221">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_249">On disability?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ErinMcGreehan" eId="spk_222">
          <from>Deputy Erin McGreehan<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_250">I refer specifically to the disability group because, as I said, it is a hugely important part of our programme for Government. We want to make huge changes right across all of government as to how we deal with disabilities and support people. How are the experts being supported in coming in to give the Taoiseach advice on that subcommittee?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelMartin" eId="spk_223">
          <from> The Taoiseach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_251">The disability unit within the Department of the Taoiseach will be made up of public servants, will be led by a principal officer and is resourced within the social policy and public service reform division at present. Expressions of interest have been sought for additional staff, who will be assigned shortly to deliver on the commitment in the programme for Government. The unit will be made up of staff within the public service more generally. Obviously it will then co-ordinate with other Government Departments and with non-governmental organisations and stakeholders involved in the disability field with a view to getting their perspectives on a whole range of issues to do with disability.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_224">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_252">Go raibh maith agat, a Thaoisigh. We have to finish at 4.44 p.m. I will let an Teachta McGreehan in first the next time. I thank the Taoiseach and his officials for assisting the committee with our consideration of the Revised Estimates. Go raibh míle maith agaibh go léir. That concludes the select committee's business in public session for today. The select committee stands adjourned. Later today, the joint committee will meet in public session at 4.50 p.m. in committee room 3 to engage with An Taoiseach.</p>
        </speech>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_9">
        <heading>Message to Dáil<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#MaireadFarrell" eId="spk_225">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_253">In accordance with Standing Order 102, the following message will be sent to the Clerk of the Dáil:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_254">The Select Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure, Public Service Reform and Digitalisation, and Taoiseach has completed its consideration of the following Revised Estimates for public services for the service year ending 31 December 2025: Vote 1 - President's Establishment; Vote 2 - Department of the Taoiseach; Vote 3 - Office of the Attorney General; Vote 4 - Central Statistics Office; Vote 5 - Office of the Director of Public Prosecutions; and Vote 6 - Office of the Chief State Solicitor.</p>
          <p eId="para_255"> Under Standing Order 102(1), this message is deemed to be the report of the committee.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_5"> The select committee adjourned at 4.44 p.m. <i>sine die</i>.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
