<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#debates">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_food_and_the_marine/2024-11-06/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_food_and_the_marine/2024-11-06/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2024-11-06" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#author" href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/33/joint_committee_on_agriculture_food_and_the_marine"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_food_and_the_marine/2024-11-06/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_food_and_the_marine/2024-11-06/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2024-11-06" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_food_and_the_marine/2024-11-06/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_food_and_the_marine/2024-11-06/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2024-11-15" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#debates">
        <TLCPerson eId="JoeFlaherty" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Joe-Flaherty.D.2020-02-08" showAs="Joe Flaherty"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JohnnyMythen" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Johnny-Mythen.D.2020-02-08" showAs="Johnny Mythen"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MartinKenny" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Martin-Kenny.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Martin Kenny"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MichaelFitzmaurice" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Michael-Fitzmaurice.D.2014-10-10" showAs="Michael Fitzmaurice"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaulDaly" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paul-Daly.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Paul Daly"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="TimLombard" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Tim-Lombard.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Tim Lombard"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="VictorBoyhan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Victor-Boyhan.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Victor Boyhan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="VioletAnneWynne" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Violet-Anne-Wynne.D.2020-02-08" showAs="Violet-Anne Wynne"/>
        <TLCRole eId="An_Cathaoirleach_Gníomhach" href="/ie/oireachtas/role/office/an_cathaoirleach_gníomhach" showAs="An Cathaoirleach Gníomhach"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/chair" showAs="Chair" eId="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/vice_chairman" showAs="Vice Chairman" eId="Vice_Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/author" showAs="author" eId="author"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/editor" showAs="editor" eId="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>AN COMHCHOISTE UM THALMHAÍOCHT, BIA AGUS MUIR</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2024-11-06">Dé Céadaoin, 06 Samhain 2024</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2024-11-06">Wednesday, 06 November 2024</docDate>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_en">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_ga">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">Tháinig an Comhchoiste le chéile ag 05:30 p.m.</summary>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">The Joint Committee met at 05:30 p.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_3">Comhaltaí a bhí i láthair / Members present:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_1">Teachtaí Dála / Deputies</p>
              </th>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_2">Seanadóirí / Senators</p>
              </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#MichaelFitzmaurice">Michael Fitzmaurice</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#VictorBoyhan">Victor Boyhan</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#JoeFlaherty">Joe Flaherty</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#PaulDaly">Paul Daly.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#MartinKenny">Martin Kenny</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#JohnnyMythen">Johnny Mythen.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_4">I láthair / In attendance: Deputy Violet-Anne Wynne.</summary>
          <summary eId="sum_5">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#TimLombard">Seanadóir / Senator Tim Lombard sa Chathaoir / in the Chair.</person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Governance Issues: Irish Horseracing Regulatory Board (Resumed)<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T17:30:00+00:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_1">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_9">Apologies have been received from Deputies Cahill and Kehoe. I will take the Chair for this meeting. Before we begin, I remind members and witnesses to turn off their mobile phones. Members are requested to ensure their mobile phones are turned off completely or switched to a flight safety mode, whichever is appropriate to the device, for the duration of the meeting. It is very important that they are turned off because they may interfere with the broadcasting system.</p>
          <p eId="para_10"> I welcome the witnesses. I will now read the notice on privilege. Witnesses giving evidence from within the parliamentary precincts are protected by absolute privilege in respect of the evidence they give to the committee. This means that witnesses have a full defence in any defamation action taken based on anything they say in the committee meeting. However, witnesses are expected not to abuse this privilege and may be directed to cease giving evidence on an issue at the Chair's discretion. Witnesses should follow the direction of the Chair in this regard. They are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that, where reasonable and unless there is no alternative, no commentary should be made identifying a third person or entity. Witnesses giving evidence from outside the location of the parliamentary precincts are asked to note that they may not benefit from the same legal immunity as witnesses giving evidence from inside the parliamentary precincts and may consider taking legal advice on this matter. Privilege against defamatory action does not apply to publication by the witnesses outside the precincts or the committee on any matter raised by these proceedings.</p>
          <p eId="para_11"> Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside these Houses or an official by name or in such a way as to identify him or her. Parliamentary privilege is considered to apply to the utterances of members who participate online in a committee meeting but they must be within the parliamentary precincts. Participating in a public meeting online from outside the parliamentary precincts may result in that member having online access removed.</p>
          <p eId="para_12"> The first item on the agenda is an examination of governance issues with the Irish Horseracing Regulatory Board. I welcome the members of the board. I will ask Mr. Darragh O’Loughlin to introduce himself and to deliver his opening statement.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_6">
          <i>Senator Paul Daly took the Chair.</i>
        </summary>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_2">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_13">On behalf of the IHRB, I thank the Chairman and members of the committee for the opportunity to appear before the committee this evening to discuss governance in the board. I am the chief executive officer of the IHRB and I am joined by our new chief financial officer, Mr. John Murphy, and our chief veterinary officer, Dr. Lynn Hillyer.</p>
          <p eId="para_14"> The Irish Horseracing Regulatory Board is all-island body that exists to assure public trust in horse racing in Ireland and safeguard its global reputation. The Irish horse racing industry supports more than 30,000 jobs and contributes €2.46 billion to the economy. In 2023, between flat, national hunt and point-to-point racing, IHRB professional officials and volunteer race day stewards oversaw a combined 483 race fixtures across the 32 counties, with 38,601 runners in total. </p>
          <p eId="para_15"> It is the ambition of the board and management that the IHRB be recognised as a world-class regulator for horse racing with an ongoing focus on excellence in the delivery of our core functions of integrity, rider safety and equine welfare. The IHRB is currently engaged in an ambitious programme of modernisation and change, guided by the board's strategy for the period 2024-2027, which we published late last year. This strategy commits us to consistently applying a robust governance framework and rigorous probity regime.</p>
          <p eId="para_16">The IHRB’s horse racing integrity services funding comes via Horse Racing Ireland, HRI, and we meet at least quarterly with HRI to ensure transparency and oversight of spending under the agreed budget. In mid-2023, a significantly revised and strengthened service level agreement governing the provision and use of funding for horse racing integrity services was agreed between IHRB and HRI and we continue to operate within the agreed funding parameters.</p>
          <p eId="para_17"> As the committee will recall, the board became aware in June 2023 of an issue relating to financial governance which had occurred in early 2022. This was immediately brought to the attention of the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Horse Racing Ireland and the Comptroller and Auditor General, and was disclosed to the Oireachtas public accounts committee the following day. The issue concerned an unauthorised transfer in January 2022 of €350,000 from the Jockeys Emergency Fund, a charity bank account administered by the IHRB, to the IHRB’s bank account. This was subsequently reversed in April 2022.</p>
          <p eId="para_18"> The professional services firm Forvis Mazars was engaged to carry out an independent review of this and other financial governance matters, which involved detailed scrutiny of six years’ worth of IHRB financial and other records as well as interviews with relevant individuals. Its report was received late last week and has been shared with the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine and the Office of the Comptroller and Auditor General. It was published yesterday.</p>
          <p eId="para_19"> The IHRB recognises the importance of a robust governance structure and believes the incident that gave rise to the Forvis Mazars review should not have happened. Reassuringly, the review identified no transactions in breach of financial governance requirements other than that which prompted the initial concern, and there was no evidence of misappropriation for personal gain. Nonetheless, since commissioning the review, significant changes to enhance financial governance have been implemented by the IHRB or are in progress, guided by draft reports provided during the review process.</p>
          <p eId="para_20"> These measures, designed to address the recommendations, include strengthened financial controls, particularly regarding the authorisation and approval of online banking payments, with strict transaction approval limits and segregation of accounts access; developing and enforcing comprehensive documentation and formal approval procedures for all material financial transactions; strengthening and expanding the existing service level agreement between IHRB and HRI to capture governance and other requirements and enhanced transparency and reporting mechanisms in relation to the integrity services budget; putting in place formal written agreements and detailed procedures with all charities and non-profit entities receiving administrative support from the IHRB, setting out roles and responsibilities; strengthened governance procedures on the approval, funding and reporting of redundancy and retirement payments; supporting the trustees of the charities in their implementation of appropriate and effective charity governance policies and procedures; recording and tracking our organisational compliance with the code of practice for the governance of State bodies; closer collaboration with HRI and the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine on financial and governance matters; and increased operational collaboration with HRI on efficient delivery of shared objectives, which is already bringing gains in capacity, effectiveness and resilience.</p>
          <p eId="para_21"> The IHRB is resolute in our commitment to fully addressing the issues highlighted in the review, making the necessary changes to uphold the highest standards of financial governance and assuring public trust in the IHRB as the regulator of Irish horse racing. We are satisfied the measures identified will address the recommendations made by Forvis Mazars and we are on target to have them fully implemented by year end.</p>
          <p eId="para_22"> Reducing the risk of injury to racehorses on track, especially fatal injury, is a significant challenge to racing jurisdictions worldwide and is a core pillar of the IHRB strategy. To this end, the board initiated the equine injury in Irish racing risk-reduction project to determine, analyse and mitigate risk factors for racing-related equine injuries in Ireland and to identify opportunities to improve safety for our horses and riders. The project’s findings have led to an enhancement of the IHRB’s race-day equine veterinary inspection programme, new standards for racecourse trot-up areas, and implementation of an evidence-based risk assessment for race-day injury. Alongside enhanced inspections on track before any previously injured horse returns to racing, the IHRB veterinary team works with trainers and their own vets to ensure the horse’s suitability to race. We also run periodic expert seminars for trainers and vets to provide information on reducing race-related equine injury.</p>
          <p eId="para_23"> The equine anti-doping programme remains a top priority and our approach continues to evolve in line with international best practice, with ongoing phased implementation of the recommendations of the independent Suann review. IHRB teams took 5,866 samples from horses in 2023, which were analysed at LGC in Newmarket, one of only six IFHA recognised reference laboratories worldwide. These resulted in the detection of six adverse findings and the trainers involved have been dealt with through our disciplinary processes in accordance with the rules of racing.</p>
          <p eId="para_24"> This year we also launched a joint anti-doping initiative with the British Horseracing Authority which saw approximately 250 samples, both blood and hair, taken from more than 120 horses across 14 training establishments in advance of the Cheltenham festival. To enhance transparency, we have begun monthly publication of anti-doping and other integrity activity data on our website, including details of horses which have been the subject of an adverse finding.</p>
          <p eId="para_25"> I thank you, a Chathaoirligh, for the invitation to appear and for members' attention this evening. My colleagues and I are happy to expand on any element of this statement or to answer any other questions members may have.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#VictorBoyhan" eId="spk_3">
          <from>Senator Victor Boyhan<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_26">I have audit business relating to the Oireachtas to do and I will have to go. I am very conscious of audit and have a huge interest in the corporate governance of organisations. I have served on a number of State boards. I welcome Mr. O’Loughlin, Mr. Murphy and Dr. Hillyer and thank them for coming here.</p>
          <p eId="para_27"> This is probably the last meeting of the agriculture committee before the general election. I take this opportunity to acknowledge the significant work of our Chair, Deputy Jackie Cahill, who has indicated he will not be standing in the next general election. He is not here and I would have liked to have said it directly to him. He has been an exceptional Chair. I would not like to let this opportunity go without acknowledging his excellent and amazing knowledge of agriculture and his very fair approach to chairing the business of this Oireachtas committee. He understood the brief exceptionally well. He worked exceptionally well with the members and the Department. He was never afraid to confront or challenge the <i>status quo</i> and worked effectively with organisations. He included them and encouraged them to come in here in an open and frank way and participate and engage. He was always courteous to us and facilitated us here. I take this opportunity to wish Jackie well in the future. As I say, he was an excellent Chair and guided us through our work. At this point I also acknowledge the work of our clerk and the secretarial support and all the other support around it. I just wanted to get that out of the way. Jackie is an exceptional man with huge knowledge of agriculture and we will certainly miss him and his guidance of this committee.</p>
          <p eId="para_28"> Coming to the business in hand, I start on a positive note. I was speaking in the Seanad the day before yesterday, and we were celebrating and I was talking about the Irish jockey Robbie Dolan, who rode Knight's Choice and claimed the Lexus Melbourne Cup. What a day and what an achievement. It is a really positive story for racing internationally. I am sorry I did not have a penny on him because, at 80-1, the odds were fantastic and happy days for anyone who had €500 on that. That is a really positive note to start here.</p>
          <p eId="para_29"> We have an amazing equestrian industry and an amazing reputation all over the world. We do not want that to be blemished or undermined. We want to work constructively with all stakeholders in this sector because the Irish sports horse and all that goes with it are vital. We have discussed the issue at length. We acknowledge that there are shortcomings in governance. There have been challenges with testing for doping in sports in the past but I think things are genuinely improving.</p>
          <p eId="para_30"> I do not intend to ask too many questions but I want to make a few observations. I considered in detail the various reports that were submitted to us. All members have seen them and studied them. We teased out the details among ourselves. I examined the IHRB annual reports before I came here today.</p>
          <p eId="para_31">The IHRB statement of strategy for 2024 to 2027 is fantastic. It is great to set goals and achievements. We cannot forget what has gone before but that is really positive and important. The statement is well laid out and explained. It is easy to measure and I salute the witnesses for that.</p>
          <p eId="para_32"> I looked at the report of the equine injury in Irish racing reduction project, which is important. It was interesting to learn about that. I read the IHRB equine anti-doping reports, which were interesting. There are challenges in that regard, as the witnesses acknowledge. There have also been vast improvements in that regard. I also read the independent review of the IHRB equine anti-doping programme, which is important. I see pathways and evidence of a concentrated and positive way of going forward. That is what I want to dwell on tonight.</p>
          <p eId="para_33"> I have also studied the detailed financial governance review from Forvis Mazars and certain transactions with the IHRB. That sets out a comprehensive background to some of the issues that the witnesses have addressed today. I do not intend to dwell on those matters. It is good that we have an auditing system. Mazars is an exceptional company and it has set out a number of issues, so that is transparent and important. Transparency is key to governance.</p>
          <p eId="para_34"> I will touch on a few issues. I looked at the strategic plan, the vision and governance, and the various pillars that have been set out. The IHRB, as we all know, has a legal responsibility to protect the reputation and integrity of the Irish horse racing sector. That is important. We talked about the Melbourne Cup. Anything to do with our reputation is critical to the success of the industry, its further growth and the realisation of its potential. That is something that Irish people in general are very proud of and it is important.</p>
          <p eId="para_35"> I also think of the context of this report. There is an absolute responsibility in terms of administration and management. Substantial Government grants are significant to the industry. Every year, we approve funding and consider issues around sports horses generally. It is not always easy. There is a lot of conflict around some of those issues in the days leading up to the approval of funding with consideration of whether it should be varied and whether more money should be designated or ring-fenced for welfare as opposed to something else. That is important. I have no vested interest here and I do not know anyone on the board or any of the governors or trustees. I see evidence of a clear strategy for good corporate governance, which is important.</p>
          <p eId="para_36"> There is the ongoing issue and challenge around ensuring compliance with good practice and the code of practice for the governance of State bodies. The witnesses will be familiar with that. I see evidence of all of that. It is there. The witnesses are clearly aware of their corporate governance responsibilities in that area, which is also important.</p>
          <p eId="para_37"> I am not fully apprised of and do not have an in-depth knowledge of the organisation in respect of how it is resourced for compliance and risk functions. I note that is in there but it is an important challenge. There is a risk assessment audit system within the Oireachtas. Every organisation has such a system. It is important that sufficient resources and skill sets are available and applied to ensure high compliance. What gives confidence to people in respect of compliance is transparency. The witnesses are here today on a programme that is broadcast on Oireachtas TV. They are on the record of the Oireachtas. That sort of transparency instils confidence and that is important.</p>
          <p eId="para_38"> I encourage the witnesses to have greater collaboration with HRI. Mr. O'Loughlin identified that issue. He said that he plans to have greater engagement with HRI and the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine, as it is now. It may become a different Department in a few months' time.</p>
          <p eId="para_39"> It is nice and dandy to say there will be constructive stakeholder engagement through strong communication processes, consultation or collaboration, but there needs to be greater evidence, going forward. I ask the witnesses to focus more on that issue because it is important.</p>
          <p eId="para_40"> It is rare that I come to this committee, which I have been a member of for the past five years, without a question to ask. Having studied in detail the documents submitted to the committee, I am of the view that the board is putting in place, and has put in place, mechanisms. It would be interesting if the witnesses were to come back to the committee in 12 months' time and tell us how it is going. I do not have any questions. I thank the witnesses for coming and for being upfront and honest about the problems they have encountered. They have acknowledged that some system threw up this anomaly or concern and that has now been addressed. I thank the witnesses for coming before the committee.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" as="#An_Cathaoirleach_Gníomhach" eId="spk_4">
          <from>An Cathaoirleach Gníomhach (Senator Paul Daly)<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_41">The Senator said he did not have any questions but the witnesses may like to comment on his comments.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_5">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_42">I am grateful for his comments. I echo his words about Deputy Jackie Cahill, the Cathaoirleach of this committee, who has always been a great supporter of the horse racing industry. I have had conversations with him at racecourses across the country. He is not just a supporter but a constructive critic when that is needed. That is always useful. We send him our regards through the committee.</p>
          <p eId="para_43"> I am grateful for Senator Boyhan's observations. I am grateful that he took so much time to read our documentation. As he said, we are trying to be as transparent and open as we can to set out a plan for the future. We are guided on a daily, weekly, monthly and annual basis by that strategy. My staff are probably sick of hearing me tell them why we do what we do under that strategy and linking that work back to that strategy. It is important to have a vision for an organisation. That vision for us includes governance, probity, transparency and accountability. That is important.</p>
          <p eId="para_44"> The Senator spoke of, and emphasised the need for, consultation and collaboration. I agree with him. Over the course of this year, which is the first year of the strategy, we have made particular efforts to expand our consultation and collaboration with stakeholders. We have, for example, engaged frequently, professionally and constructively with the Irish Jockeys Association, even in relation to penalties for riding offences under the rules of racing. There has been a need to increase penalties in some areas and to ease them in others to modify behaviour and ensure safe riding. We have found through that engagement that the jockeys have been very helpful. The resulting changes have landed much better. They have been accepted by the members of the association and that audience, which makes for a smoother and better regulatory atmosphere. We are not asking them what penalties they want but we are explaining why we are doing what we are doing and the jockeys are helping by telling us how they think we should do what we were going to do anyway. I agree with the Senator on that point and, as I said, I am grateful to him for taking the time to understand our organisation and industry to such an extent.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_7">
          <i>Senator Tim Lombard resumed the Chair at 5.57 p.m.</i>
        </summary>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_6">
          <from>Deputy Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_45">I thank Mr. O'Loughlin and his colleagues for coming before the committee. I have a couple of queries. Who brought in Forvis Mazars? Was it the Department or the board?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_7">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_46">We commissioned Forvis Mazars partly because we did not have an existing relationship with the organisation. It provides internal audit services to HRI and in the interests of transparency and speed, we jointly commissioned the report with HRI. HRI, which has governance oversight of the IHRB, selected Forvis Mazars to conduct the report. The terms of reference were signed between us, HRI and Forvis Mazars in order to carry it out. The report was issued to us and to HRI simultaneously.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_8">
          <from>Deputy Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_47">Who paid for the report? Was it HRI or the IHRB?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_9">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_48">HRI is paying for the report.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_10">
          <from>Deputy Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_49">Is Forvis Mazars still providing a service or has it finished with the IHRB?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_11">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_50">This was a single piece of work. Since issuing the final report, Forvis Mazars' relationship with us is over.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_12">
          <from>Deputy Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_51">That is grand. How much did the report cost?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_13">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_52">We have not seen the invoice. All I can tell the Deputy is that Ms Suzanne Eade, the CEO of HRI, put on the record of the Committee of Public Accounts the value of the project. Somebody can check the transcript but, from memory, I think the cost was €80,000.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_14">
          <from>Deputy Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_53">Mr. O'Loughlin said it was good that no impropriety was detected. How did the transfer of €360,000 happen? Did someone press the wrong button? What is the explanation?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_15">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_54">We detected no other inappropriate transaction. That transaction of €350,000, which was transferred from the Jockeys Emergency Fund to the IHRB bank account, was an improper, inappropriate and unauthorised transaction.</p>
          <p eId="para_55">We were reassured that we had asked for Mazars to scrutinise all of our financial transactions and financial records going back to the establishment of the IHRB at the beginning of 2018, and they found no other similar transactions. I just wanted to clarify that.</p>
          <p eId="para_56"> With regard to how this happened, unfortunately I do not believe it was an inappropriate or accidental pushing of a wrong button. This is a step that was proactively taken in a particular set of circumstances and, as I said in the opening statement, it should not have happened.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_16">
          <from>Deputy Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_57">Was it for personal gain or was it to cover issues that were happening within the finances of the organisation?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_17">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_58">As set out in the Mazars report, they looked at the particular circumstances around it. They looked at the transaction itself, how it had happened, and the particular set of circumstances that led up to it. It was not a question of misappropriation or personal gain. According to the Mazars review there was a particular cash flow crisis, as it were, in January 2022 because a number of payments had been made that had not yet been funded. Redundancy payments were being made and there was a shortage of money in the IHRB bank account such that that month's payroll potentially could not have been met. It was in those particular circumstances that the then chief financial officer actioned this transfer.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_18">
          <from>Deputy Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_59">I see that a number of steps have been taken to guard against that. What is the procedure now for someone to transfer money within the organisation?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_19">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_60">Before any transfer, we have different procedures. We have tightened procedures for all transfers. Depending on the value of the transfer, the procedure can be even tighter. For a transfer of that scale, it would require me as chief executive officer to sign off on it and to see the reasoning or the rationale for that transaction. Any transaction over €100,000 requires me as CEO to authorise it personally, in addition to one other member of senior management such as the chief financial officer beside me.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_20">
          <from>Deputy Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_61">That is very good. I assume the €360,000 was returned.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_21">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_62">Yes, it was returned in April of 2022, which was 94 days after it had been transferred.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_22">
          <from>Deputy Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_63">Did that cause any issues then for the Jockeys Emergency Fund given the 90 or so days?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_23">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_64">No. The Jockeys Emergency Fund did not suffer nor did any beneficiary of the Jockeys Emergency Fund suffer the loss of the money for the period. In saying that, I am not suggesting for a moment that it was appropriate or okay that it happened. It is a reassurance that the charity did not miss the money to extent of any beneficiary suffering any ill effects. The charity carried on as normal.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_24">
          <from>Deputy Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_65">I thank Mr. O'Loughlin. I have a question for Dr. Hillyer on anti-doping measures. There were 5,866 samples in 2023. What is the target for this year?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_25">
          <from> Dr. Lynn Hillyer<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_66">We are hoping to achieve around the same number. At the moment it does slightly depend on the challenges that come in. We have some flexibility within the budget to allow us to do that. As we have said before, it is not purely the numbers it is the type of sample as well. It is very important that we take the right sample at the right time so we can balance the two.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_26">
          <from>Deputy Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_67">Last year there were just fewer than 39,000 runners. I was never good at maths but that is probably less than 20% sampled.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_27">
          <from> Dr. Lynn Hillyer<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_68">Overall, but several horses get sampled more than once. It is basically done on a risk basis as well. Again, we try not to just pick it on the numbers. We try to assess the risk in each individual horse's circumstance. The really important point is to make sure we take sufficient samples off the racetrack. Keeping that percentage of out-of-competition samples up is one of my priorities.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_28">
          <from>Deputy Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_69">What is the international standard or the norm?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_29">
          <from> Dr. Lynn Hillyer<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_70">It does vary depending on the jurisdiction. There are some racing jurisdictions where the first four horses in a race could be sampled and other jurisdictions where there is no out-of-competition testing. The common theme in all jurisdictions is to achieve best practice internationally. That is set out in an international agreement to which we are a signatory. The quality of the product depends on the circumstances on the ground. We take that very much into account here.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_30">
          <from>Deputy Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_71">With that international best practice, in terms of a percentage, we are probably at one in five horses competing. What is the international standard?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_31">
          <from> Dr. Lynn Hillyer<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_72">There is actually no average as such because the jurisdictions are so different but we can certainly stand over the depth and breadth of our testing internationally. That was evidenced in Dr. Craig Suann's review of our testing. That is exactly what he concluded.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_32">
          <from>Deputy Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_73">Is Dr. Hillyer comfortable that we are not scaling it up? Does he think that we should scale it up, notwithstanding resources? Given the vast amount the State invests in horse racing and the annual contribution to horse racing, which I fully support, and which is routinely derided by many of the public, does he believe there is an onus on IHRB to ensure the absolute integrity of this sport?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_33">
          <from> Dr. Lynn Hillyer<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_74">We absolutely do and our focus is relentless on that, on both the anti-doping and the equine welfare side. They are both very much interlinked. It is really critical that we do not stand still. We have to keep moving forward. Developing my team, developing how we take our samples, where we take them, what we take and what we do with those results, is a constant focus. It is always evolving. I keep going back to this; it is not just about the numbers. We need to make sure the numbers are as high as they can be within reason but it is the quality as well as the quantity that is so important.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_34">
          <from>Deputy Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_75">Horse racing has a good many friends within this House at the minute but this might not always be the case. IHRB certainly must ramp up what it is doing in anti-doping. It is increasingly an issue among the general public. Most of us who grew up in rural Ireland fully support horse racing and country pursuits, and we enthusiastically support them and follow them, but there is an onus on IHRB to ramp up what it is doing on doping. I understand that this will present issues for IHRB in respect of staffing and resources. I am aware it is not straightforward to take a sample off a horse and that it is multifaceted but there is an onus to ramp it up.</p>
          <p eId="para_76"> On the initiative IHRB undertook with the British Horseracing Authority, BHA, was this initiated by that authority or was it a collective meeting of minds to do that around the Cheltenham Festival?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_35">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_77">It arose out of discussions I was having with the director of integrity or regulation in the BHA. We have regular interactions with them in professional forums such as the European Horserace Scientific Liaison Committee, of which Dr. Hillyer is a member, and various other similar fora. On the fringes of that we had discussions because, as the Deputy will know, many Irish horses go over to the UK and many British horses come here. We try to encourage that flow back and forth. We thought it could be useful as a way of demonstrating confidence in each other's testing regimes if we were to go testing together. Their director asked that Dr. Hillyer would get in touch with the chief veterinary officer in the BHA and set something up. Dr. Hillyer might explain how it came about it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_36">
          <from> Dr. Lynn Hillyer<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_78">It is exactly as Mr. O'Loughlin has said. We have been collaborating informally for years. I came from that jurisdiction some years ago so there was a quite a knowledge, an understanding and an informed exchange of information on anti-doping and equine welfare, which are the two pillars I work in. It became very clear, as Mr. O' Loughlin said, that we needed to make sure we have a consistency between the two jurisdictions. The shared testing was an obvious part of that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_37">
          <from>Deputy Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_79">Are there plans to build on that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_38">
          <from> Dr. Lynn Hillyer<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_80">Yes, absolutely.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_39">
          <from>Deputy Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_81">We have the big festivals happening again in 2025. Has the IHRB met with any the representatives of the Irish festivals with which it will do that joint initiative?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_40">
          <from> Dr. Lynn Hillyer<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_82">We have a lot of plans in place and we will develop them. It will not just be the testing. There will be collaboration between the teams and sharing of expertise and knowledge.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_41">
          <from>Deputy Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_83">Will that cross-agency approach include some of the Irish festivals in 2025?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_42">
          <from> Dr. Lynn Hillyer<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_84">Yes, it will.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_43">
          <from>Deputy Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_85">Will it be one or two?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_44">
          <from> Dr. Lynn Hillyer<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_86">I am hoping at least two.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_45">
          <from>Deputy Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_87">Two. That is very good.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_46">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_88">As other Deputies and Senators have done, I wish to pay tribute to Deputy Jackie Cahill. The one thing about this committee is that politics went out that door with everyone, in fairness to everyone here who worked together with him. The Chairman was very helpful. I have been in the Dáil for a few different agriculture committees and I found him to be one of the most helpful Chairs that we ever had. I wish him well. The Dáil is finishing and I thank Christy and Rebecca and the rest of the secretariat team for putting up with us for the past few years.</p>
          <p eId="para_89"> I thank the witnesses for coming in. When the figure of €242,990 was being given who came up with that? Was Mr. Murphy the chief financial officer at the time?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_47">
          <from> Mr. John Murphy<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_90">I have been chief financial officer only since July of this year.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_48">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_91">Were there more redundancies in that line of the business?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_49">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_92">There was a voluntary redundancy and early retirement scheme in place in HRI and it was extended to IHRB, as the Mazars report outlines, in 2021. In the scheme rules, there were criteria for calculating how much a person's redundancy or retirement payment would be by reference to their salary and number of years of service. It was those criteria that were used to calculate individual entitlements.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_50">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_93">It must be an unusual type of criteria because I see what is written in the newspapers about even politicians and what they get or are entitled to when they retire. The figures I see there are fairly substantial. How were they arrived at?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_51">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_94">The scheme predates Mr. Murphy's involvement in the IHRB and my involvement in it, so our knowledge is derived from the Mazars report. Mazars established that by applying the criteria that were in place at the time, the entitlement was that sum of money to-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_52">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_95">Am I correct in saying that in the report there was no formal written justification, or IHRB got no go-ahead from HRI, to sanction this?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_53">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_96">As it states in the report, the payment was made in September 2021. At that time, there was no specific approval given by HRI for that payment to be made.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_54">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_97">They went ahead without approval.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_55">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_98">As it states in the report, the payment was made without the funding being in place and without-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_56">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_99">I presume there is a board and different people in positions. How many of the people who were involved in making that decision are still there?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_57">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_100">The IHRB has a board of eight individuals but the-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_58">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_101">I do not care if there are 28. I am asking how many people are still there who decided to give a package without the go-ahead from HRI. Are any of them still on the board? Were there any sanctions?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_59">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_102">There were no sanctions for any director on the board and-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_60">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_103">Who gave the go-ahead?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_61">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_104">Four members of the board that was in place at that time are still on the board. There are four current directors who were not on the board in 2021.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_62">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_105">I refer to the jockeys fund. I cannot understand this and I ask Mr. O'Loughlin to explain it to me. The IHRB gets a budget to do its different things for the year. I refer to the amount of moneys that were unforeseen, we will say. I understand the jockeys one, where it was put over because there were cash flow problems, even though it was not the proper process. Then when the money came in from wherever the IHRB was getting the money, it reverted. Explain to me the following. If you get €10,000 to run a house for a year, you have €10,000, so you have to make the best of it. I refer to unforeseen expenses. Where did that large amount for paying the CEO come from? Is it money the IHRB can do without every year?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_63">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_106">No, and I would say the report demonstrates that, at the time, the IHRB could not do without it then either because it was around the time the retirement and redundancy payments were paid out that the cash flow issue arose.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_64">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_107">I know that but I am talking about the separate payment to the CEO.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_65">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_108">The Deputy is referring to the CEO payment that was made in September 2021.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_66">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_109">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_67">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_110">The way our budget works is we agree the annual budget with Horse Racing Ireland and it is paid over to us monthly. At the beginning of a month, we get 90% of that month's budget.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_68">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_111">I presume that when the yearly amount was agreed, this figure was not foreseen, to put it simply.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_69">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_112">No, I do not believe it was.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_70">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_113">What was done by the end of the year? Was this money picked up by someone? Obviously, the taxpayer picked it up in the end.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_71">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_114">All the money that comes to us from HRI is ultimately taxpayers' money.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_72">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_115">I am trying to find out the following. Of the budget agreed at the beginning of the year, whatever figure it was, was this money given to the IHRB to cover it, did it have to do without it or was something cut?</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_8">
          <i>Deputy Martin Kenny took the Chair.</i>
        </summary>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_73">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_116">I am going back to September 2021 because the report says that is when the payment was made. At the beginning of September, the IHRB received the money for the September budget. The Deputy is correct that this sum would not have been included in the budget because it was not foreseen at the beginning of the year when the budget was done. The payment was made. There would always be a balance in the bank account. The bank account of the IHRB is not zero.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_74">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_117">Would it be that big of a balance?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_75">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_118">Obviously, at that time, it was. I was not there and Mr. Murphy was not there, so we are speculating that if this payment was made, clearly there must have been some other budgeted expense that was not incurred or was not paid. That is simple mathematics.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_76">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_119">Was Mr. O'Loughlin there by the end of the year? When was he there?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_77">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_120">Mr. Murphy only joined us in the past couple months and I have been there since the end of June 2022.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_78">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_121">So Mr. O'Loughlin was there.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_79">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_122">No, this all happened in 2021.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_80">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_123">We are sort of working in the dark, are we?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_81">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_124">Well, we have this report.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_82">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_125">I know that. I am sick looking at reports.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_83">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_126">Mazars reviewed all of the transactions related to these things.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_84">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_127">I understand that but I am only asking a simple question. When Mr. O'Loughlin came in, was there a shortfall of that figure in his books for the end of 2021?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_85">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_128">There was not a shortfall in that we did not run a deficit because presumably-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_86">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_129">Did extra money come in?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_87">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_130">No.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_88">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_131">Which services that the IHRB had budgeted for was money not given to?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_89">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_132">I cannot answer that question, not because I do not want to but because I do not know. I asked previously, but I do not know what was budgeted to happen in November and December 2021 that could not happen because the money was not there.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_90">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_133">Surely, there is a schedule for the year of what the IHRB needs money for. I presume Mr. O'Loughlin would try to find out if it went there or not when he came in as CEO.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_91">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_134">All the activities were properly paid for. As a result, the organisation appears to have run out of money in January 2022.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_92">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_135">Was that for other salaries and redundancies?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_93">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_136">That is what the next big payment was, and that was the payment they did not have enough money to make. It is in the report.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_94">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_137">I understand Mr. O'Loughlin joined in June and he was not there before that. There was a shortfall in January, so moneys were transferred across. Was a bigger budget then given by HRI to cover the deficits for 2022?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_95">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_138">In November 2022, HRI made an additional payment to the IHRB to fund-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_96">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_139">How much?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_97">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_140">It was that exact amount - €283,900. Although HRI had never-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_98">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_141">HRI gave money to IHRB that it never sanctioned, but it gave it to the IHRB the following year.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_99">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_142">That is exactly what it says in the report.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_100">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_143">That is taxpayers' money.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_101">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_144">It is.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_102">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_145">Dr. Hillyer appeared previously before the committee and we spoke about a few things in the line of doping and all of that. When she was here, we bought up a difficulty that was happening when the IHRB was going out to where horses were kept or trained because, at times, horses could be gone somewhere else, and there was not traceability. Has that been resolved?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_103">
          <from> Dr. Lynn Hillyer<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_146">It is certainly improving.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_104">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_147">I asked a question. Has it been resolved?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_105">
          <from> Dr. Lynn Hillyer<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_148">We do not have a full traceability system in place at the moment. That project is being led by the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine with assistance from us and Horse Racing Ireland. That traceability project is not yet completed but it has made good progress this year.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_106">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_149">What does Dr. Hillyer mean by "good progress"?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_107">
          <from> Dr. Lynn Hillyer<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_150">We have monthly board meetings - we had one this morning, actually - to monitor progress. Weatherbys Ireland is a key stakeholder in this regard. There is a great deal of work under way. My team has been involved in end user testing of prototypes. We are now at the stage of there being something to test, so I am encouraged by the progress.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_108">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_151">Testing what?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_109">
          <from> Dr. Lynn Hillyer<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_152">The database that will allow us to have better visibility of traceability from-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_110">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_153">Will it be like the AIM system for cattle?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_111">
          <from> Dr. Lynn Hillyer<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_154">In time. We are starting by picking up the known movements of thoroughbreds. When foals are notified to Weatherbys as being in existence, as it were, when they are registered, when they pass through public sales and each time we identify them through their microchips, all of those points along the animals’ lifespans will be documented and recorded. We will then fill in the gaps.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_112">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_155">That will not solve the problem. From memory, the IHRB told us at a previous meeting that there was a difficulty, in that it could visit somewhere and be told that a horse had gone somewhere else. From what Dr. Hillyer is saying now, it is like we are Nanci Griffith and looking at it “From a Distance”, in that we are looking at different parts of where a foal is, but before the IHRB goes out on a visit, it cannot press a button and know exactly-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_113">
          <from> Dr. Lynn Hillyer<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_156">We are coming at it from two different directions. The big traceability project is what I have just described. Concurrently, we are putting into the rules of racing, where we have jurisdiction, the requirement that licensed trainers return the whereabouts of all the horses on their licensed premises.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_114">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_157">Return them how quickly?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_115">
          <from> Dr. Lynn Hillyer<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_158">That change is expected by the end of the year.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_116">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_159">No. I mean, how quickly will they be required to return that information? Will it be within a day, a week, a month or a year?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_117">
          <from> Dr. Lynn Hillyer<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_160">On the day the animal is on the premises.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_118">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_161">The IHRB will know exactly where every horse that is in training is.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_119">
          <from> Dr. Lynn Hillyer<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_162">Every horse that is on a licensed premises, regardless of whether it is involved in training, will need to be notified to us via HRI. This is a significant move forward. As Mr. O’Loughlin mentioned, we have been working in close consultation with the Irish Racehorse Trainers Association and others on moving this forward. It is not the IHRB-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_120">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_163">Are the witnesses aware that there is a problem and there is still not proper movement? This is not a matter for the IHRB directly, but are the witnesses aware of the problem with books for horses and so on?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_121">
          <from> Dr. Lynn Hillyer<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_164">The requirement for passports to be with the horses at all times is something that we enforce rigorously in every inspection. We take that extremely seriously.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_122">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_165">The IHRB might take it seriously, but the witnesses are probably aware that there is a problem when a foal is born and gets its books and so forth.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_123">
          <from> Dr. Lynn Hillyer<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_166">The gap between notification that a foal has been born and the foal’s registration is being addressed by others. The Deputy is right, in that it is not something in which we are directly involved.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_124">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_167">Is the IHRB frustrated by that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_125">
          <from> Dr. Lynn Hillyer<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_168">There is movement and a great deal of effort is being made in that regard. We play our part. When we inspect a licensed yard, we require the passports of the animals there. It is filling in the gaps along the animal’s lifespan that is important to us.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_126">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_169">When the IHRB last appeared before us, we discussed a matter that some members have raised at this meeting, namely, how the IHRB was considering a system whereby, between a horse just running and before the finish, it could be checked from where it took off. Was that ever done?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_127">
          <from> Dr. Lynn Hillyer<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_170">Sorry?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_128">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_171">At the time, there were allegations that there were certain ways of boosting a horse and we inquired into them at the meeting. A shot could be given to the horse that would only last for a certain time and would not show up if it was tested afterwards. The IHRB was considering a way of testing horses at the starting point of a race. Was that ever done?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_129">
          <from> Dr. Lynn Hillyer<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_172">If memory serves, I believe we were referring to pre-race testing, that is, taking blood samples before horses raced, to check for the presence of certain indications.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_130">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_173">It was a while ago, so off the top of my head, I think that there were some allegations, which may or may not have been true and I am not saying they were true. The IHRB stated that it would consider testing horses at where they would be taking off from. Was anything ever done in that regard?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_131">
          <from> Dr. Lynn Hillyer<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_174">We actively include pre-race testing in our anti-doping strategy.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_132">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_175">What is pre-race testing? Explain it to me as someone who does not know.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_133">
          <from> Dr. Lynn Hillyer<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_176">It involves taking a blood sample from a horse before it races.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_134">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_177">Where?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_135">
          <from> Dr. Lynn Hillyer<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_178">On the racetrack. In addition, if we have concerns or intelligence, we will test the animal at home before it gets to the racetrack. That is out-of-competition testing.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_136">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_179">When Dr. Hillyer refers to the racetrack, does she mean down near where the horse takes off or where?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_137">
          <from> Dr. Lynn Hillyer<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_180">In the stable yard, but it can happen up to saddling if we need to. In fairness to the trainers, it is a difficult time to be sticking a needle into a horse,-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_138">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_181">Granted.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_139">
          <from> Dr. Lynn Hillyer<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_182">-----so we would be respectful about when to take samples. It is generally about one hour before race time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_140">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_183">Can hair samples not be taken?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_141">
          <from> Dr. Lynn Hillyer<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_184">We take hair samples as well. The key is to take the right samples at the right times. Hair samples, blood samples and urine samples all have good qualities and show us different things. The key is to use them in a mixture. We do that every day. Every time we go racing, we look carefully at which sample we need to take from each horse. That is the same whether it is done on the track or off it. That is what gives us our strategy and is very important.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_142">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_185">My final question is for Mr. O’Loughlin. The IHRB has a new governance system. Who pays the €80,000 for someone to do this report?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_143">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_186">The report was done on the HRI account, so-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_144">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_187">I know that, but I presume it was the IHRB that required the report because it wanted HRI to account for everything and be transparent.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_145">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_188">HRI has said that it will pay for the report.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_146">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_189">I presume that is more taxpayers’ money.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_147">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_190">It is part of HRI’s internal audit budget. Senator Boyhan spoke about the costs associated with governance and compliance. There is a cost, and it needs to be resourced. Forvis Mazars already provides internal audit services to HRI. It is as part of that contract that it conducted this particular audit of the IHRB.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_148">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_191">Regarding the system for adjudicating what a person is worth, is it the IHRB that writes that up?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_149">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_192">I am sorry, but which system?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_150">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_193">If someone is getting a redundancy payment, who puts that calculation together? Is it done internally by the IHRB?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_151">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_194">According to the Forvis Mazars report, the criteria and calculations were set by HRI. It says that in the report.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_152">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_195">Essentially, HRI lays out how it is done.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_153">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_196">It sets out the criteria. The calculations were done in the IHRB and checked by HRI. The calculations of the amounts were checked by Forvis Mazars as part of this report. It has reported that, in the case of the voluntary and compulsory redundancies, all of the calculations were correct.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_154">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_197">What is the IHRB’s situation now?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_155">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_198">We have not had-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_156">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_199">I mean financially.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_157">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_200">Any regulator would say that it would like to have a bigger budget, but we are managing. We have agreed an annual budget with HRI and are operating within the agreed funding parameters. We meet HRI at least every three months to review our management accounts for that period and to preview spending for the upcoming period. We operate on the basis that there should be no surprises. We like HRI to know where we are financially. If we are anticipating any particular expense, for example, a large legal expense or a capital expense, we always flag that with HRI well in advance.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_158">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_201">Does HRI have another pot of money from which it can throw more to the IHRB? Is it a fixed budget for the year? How does it work?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_159">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_202">HRI’s budget is fixed by reference to the Vote, with the Dáil voting it a particular budget.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_160">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_203">Mr. O’Loughlin stated that, if something cropped up, the IHRB would flag it. Does HRI have another piggy bank from which it can pull another bit? I am trying to fathom how this works.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_161">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_204">Unfortunately, it does not have any piggy banks. Where an additional cost arises in the IHRB and where we have HRI support, one can only assume that HRI has had to take that money from some other budget.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_162">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_205">I thank Mr. O’Loughlin.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" as="#An_Cathaoirleach_Gníomhach" eId="spk_163">
          <from>An Cathaoirleach Gníomhach (Deputy Martin Kenny)<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_206">I thank the witnesses for their presentation. I apologise, as I was late arriving and missed their opening remarks.</p>
          <p eId="para_207"> I will make a few brief comments.</p>
          <p eId="para_208">We all recognise the importance of the equine industry in Ireland and the huge contribution it makes to the economy and our reputation internationally. Part of that is about having a proper regulatory structure in place to ensure authenticity in what happens in this regard. When questions arise, naturally people will immediately look to the regulatory authority. They will ask why, if there are rules in place, they are not being followed and why there are breaches and issues. In that context, it is important that the regulatory authority have everything in order, more so than anybody else, because it is the body that is supposed to be policing everybody else. In this context, it is quite alarming that there were issues. In fairness, the delegates have dealt with them and they have been spelled out here. Nonetheless, we need to have accountability in all of this. Sometimes there are blame games in various places. Blame is one thing but it is really a matter of responsibility and taking responsibility. I acknowledge that the delegates have taken responsibility for the issues that have arisen but there are still difficulties for many people and many issues. Various people from the equine industry in general have raised difficulties and problems with us, and this too needs to be acknowledged and dealt with.</p>
          <p eId="para_209"> On the issues in regard to the financial transactions and the way money was moved, are the delegates certain that none of these issues can arise now?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_164">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_210">We have controls in place. We have very much tightened the controls around all these financial transactions. A transaction of the scale in question cannot happen unless I have personally authorised it. I have to physically sign off on a transaction of that scale before it can happen.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" as="#An_Cathaoirleach_Gníomhach" eId="spk_165">
          <from>An Cathaoirleach Gníomhach (Deputy Martin Kenny)<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_211">Up to what scale does Mr. O’Loughlin not need not to sign off?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_166">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_212">We have thresholds in place, and anything between €25,000 and €100,000 requires me or the chief financial officer to sign off on it, in addition to at least one other member of senior management. If the sum is above €100,000, it has to be me and the CFO or another member of senior management. What the Deputy is alluding to would require all of us acting in concert, and I would like to think that would not happen.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" as="#An_Cathaoirleach_Gníomhach" eId="spk_167">
          <from>An Cathaoirleach Gníomhach (Deputy Martin Kenny)<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_213">We would like to think it would not have happened before, but it did, and that is why we are in this position.</p>
          <p eId="para_214"> We also need to recognise that there have been issues with documentation. The issue of passports has arisen here before. I am aware that our guests are not directly responsible in this regard but the governance needs to be tightened up with haste because it is a problem for people.</p>
          <p eId="para_215"> On the anti-doping regime, it is equally important that we have high standards and that those standards are seen to be met and worked on. Colleagues have mentioned that the State puts a very large amount of money into the horse racing industry. There is no other “sport” in Ireland that gets funding at anything like the same level. Government coffers are always tight and there are always issues. We have people on waiting lists to get appointments in hospitals and to get housing, and one of the things that keeps coming up is the absence of resources. The public sees a large amount of money going to an industry that, to most looking from the outside, is doing pretty well. If the Government and the Oireachtas as a body are to stand over that, they have to be certain of authenticity and that the bodies that provide funding and the regulatory bodies that govern all of this do so with absolute integrity. That is why it is so important that we get all this stuff right.</p>
          <p eId="para_216"> I acknowledge that it is not just the blood sports and horse racing that do very well out of this. There is the wider industry. The gambling industry also does very well, and that is why it is so important that we get all of this stuff right and be seen to hold the IHRB and other agencies involved in this industry to account for everything that has happened and is going on.</p>
          <p eId="para_217"> Of course, there are great success stories. The Irish horse industry is renowned throughout the world. We have had successful jockeys, including Robbie Dolan, the young man in Australia who won the Melbourne Cup the other day. We have great success stories that we need to acknowledge. However – I want to finish on this point as I am not here to ask questions and was late to the meeting – it is important that the board that governs the IHRB, and not just the guests present, and the boards that govern all the organisations that benefit from Government funding for the horse racing industry recognise that they have a huge responsibility to the public to ensure everything is done with complete integrity in the industry. There have been serious question marks in this regard. This is a message that the guests need to take with them. I will leave it at that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_168" as="#An_Cathaoirleach_Gníomhach">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_218">I also want to be associated with the remarks regarding our outgoing Chair, Deputy Jackie Cahill. It is no secret that Jackie, along with being a colleague, is a very good friend of mine. While we might knock sparks off each other as quickly as anybody else on an issue, we have had a very good working relationship. It was always a pleasure to be here at his request to step into the Chair if he had somewhere else to go. Perhaps the clerk could convey to him the expressions of high regard made here this evening. As Deputy Fitzmaurice said, this committee is here for the good of dealing with the topics in front of its members. Politics was left outside the door. That came down to how Jackie chaired the committee and approached everything. He will be a loss to these Houses and we wish him well and thank him for services rendered.</p>
          <p eId="para_219"> I always have to put on the record that I am a racing man. I am a director of Kilbeggan Racecourse, as is known. Also for the record, I am a horse owner. I would have been the proud owner of a runner in the 4.45 p.m. race in Dundalk only she turned up in season this morning.</p>
          <p eId="para_220"> I apologise for having to leave for a vote. It was the famous vote on the Finance Bill, which is now passed. As they say in racing, the white flag is officially raised. I could not miss the vote and I apologise if I repeat anything said while I was away. The guests can tell me they have dealt with any matter I raise if that is the case and I will be able to find the response in the transcript.</p>
          <p eId="para_221"> I will probably concentrate mainly on the Mazars report, which we got yesterday evening and which I read. I welcome it and all the actions coming from it, but I want to go back to why it had to be commissioned in the first place. Saying we will leave it now and walk on is like saying that, although there were problems, they will never happen again. We cannot turn our backs on what did happen. I have a few questions based on that. There are two paragraphs in the material on the report with which we were supplied that I find very damning. I will take it from there. They are about the payment of the former CEO. They state:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_222"> On this basis we do not consider that this payment fell within the rules and criteria of the Scheme. We consider that the use of public funds provided by HRI to IHRB for the purpose of a retirement payment to the Former CEO, was not specifically sanctioned in writing by HRI. We believe such a formal/written sanction should have been required under the governance arrangement for retirement and redundancy payments established by HRI.</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_223"> From a review of the Financial Statements of IHRB for the year here from a review of the financial statements for the year ended 31 December 2021, we noted that the retirement amount paid to the Former CEO was reported as being part of the Voluntary Redundancy and Early Retirement Scheme. Based on our review and analysis, as noted above, this payment was not made or formally approved within the criteria of the Scheme, and this disclosure is therefore incorrect.</p>
          <p eId="para_224">That is in IHRB’s accounts. It is public funding. As said on a couple of occasions while I was here this evening, we are getting more and more grief every year when it comes to us – perceived to be racing people – sanctioning the horse and greyhound fund. Then one reads what I have just quoted. It is in the public domain. I just quoted it for the purpose of my question. The questions raised are still not answered. It is okay to say that what happened happened and that there are recommendations from a company – they cost €80,000 – to ensure it will never happen again, but it did happen and we need answers. The retirement amount is recorded in the accounts as being part of the voluntary redundancy and early retirement scheme.</p>
          <p eId="para_225">The only word missing is "or". It should read "and or early retirement". Did the man take voluntary redundancy or early retirement? Why did he receive €141,000 more than was in the package? Did any heads roll over this? The argument that this is never going to happen again and that we should move on does not wash with me to be honest.</p>
          <p eId="para_226"> This all came to light at a meeting of the Committee of Public Accounts. Mr. John Murphy's predecessor was on paid leave for over a year. I read last night about what was going on. There were voluntary redundancies. How many people applied for them and how many were unsuccessful in their application? Compulsory redundancy was also mentioned and I would like to know more about that too. The money was not there to pay them or to pay the over-and-above payment for the CEO's retirement. In fairness to Mr. Murphy’s predecessor, from my reading of it, he found himself in a situation in which the wage checks were going to bounce. He got €350,000 to make sure that did not happen by moving money from one account to another in order to get over the hump because €141,000 was spent that had not been budgeted for. He got over the hump and then the money went back. Did he leave of his own free will after one year of garden leave? Is he the only person who fell on his sword? I believe he was doing the best he could to ensure wage checks did not bounce. There are a lot of questions to be answered before we accept that the systems in place now are the solution to the problem because this problem happened.</p>
          <p eId="para_227"> I have a big grievance. As I said at the outset, I am racing man. I attend a lot of racing and talk to a lot of racing people. A lot of people are annoyed and will be even more annoyed when they read this report because it damages the good reputation of racing. The reading of this report could not be more damaging to the good reputation of racing. As people said to me on the racetracks, a trainer called John Joseph Hanlon, better known as “The Shark”, inadvertently - and it was careless - did not secure a tarpaulin properly over a dead horse on a Friday evening when he needed to move it or he would have been in bother for not moving before the following Monday morning. He received a ten-month suspension as a result. Horse welfare is involved when horses have to be moved. The suspension has been halved on appeal. Those horses have to be moved. There are jobs at loss. That man is suffering for a little bit of recklessness in a rush on a Friday evening. I am being told by racing people that this man is being used as an example. No one will suffer in this case, however. Who is getting the ten-month suspension over what happened here? Who is going to lose their job? Who is going to have to sell off their horses? Who is going to have to let staff go for the now reduced time of six months? I am only relaying what has been said to me on the racetracks. He is being used by the IHRB as an example to show that it is running such a tight ship and that this is how it deals with someone who brings racing into disrepute. Who, however, is suffering and falling for this?</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_9"><i>Senator Tim Lombard resumed the Chair</i>.</summary>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_169">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_228">I thank Senator Daly. We, of course, are familiar with his love of racing, which we all share. The two cases cannot be equated. It would not be fair to Mr. Hanlon for me to expand on his particular case. The charges were brought under the rules of racing to which all trainers and licensees sign up. The man appeared before a referrals committee, which is our disciplinary process, and was fully represented by a solicitor and senior counsel. As the Senator said, he had an appeal, which is a part of our process.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_170" as="#An_Cathaoirleach_Gníomhach">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_229">Maybe I spoke for too long because I feel passionately about it. The comparison between the two cases in that the one common denominator, in my opinion, is the damaging of the good reputation of racing. Both cases are similar in that regard. That is the common denominator.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_171">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_230">Could I ask-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_172" as="#An_Cathaoirleach_Gníomhach">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_231">Who is suffering for damaging the reputation of racing in what happened here?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_173">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_232">I instruct members and witnesses to talk to the topic on the agenda. I do not want to go into other issues. We must stick to the topic on which the Irish Horseracing Regulatory Board was asked to attend this committee meeting.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_174">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_233">As Senator Daly pointed out, the then-chief financial officer of IHRB is no longer in place. It is a matter of public record that he was on leave. He was placed on leave at the end of June 2023 when we became aware of what had happened more than one year earlier at the beginning of 2022. He resigned earlier this year. That again is a matter of public record. The man resigned from the IHRB at the beginning of July. I will not say any more about him other than that the Senator is correct; he was on a period of leave. The Senator is also correct that he resigned.</p>
          <p eId="para_234"> Since this happened in the IHRB, we have a new CEO, chief financial officer and new independent directors on our board of directors. We have a different chairman and a new strategy which has been published and is providing the direction in which we are travelling. We are professionalising what we do. We are aiming for a measure of consistency in how we enforce the rules of racing and sanction people who are in breach of the rules or racing. We are using the time and the expertise of judges and retired judges from the High Court to make the important decisions in our referrals and appeals. We are an utterly transformed organisation and are still not finished. We collaborate much more closely with Horse Racing Ireland, HRI, than was the case previously. As I detailed already, we have quarterly meetings which are quite formal in nature in which we go through and expose all of our finances, management accounts and our spending. We also have ongoing informal communications. As I said in the opening statement, we work with HRI on shared objectives such as a shared IT strategy and a shared services approach to human resource management and procurement. It provides us with resources and assistance and, in turn, we provide it with full transparency in all of these areas of governance which are so important. HRI has governance oversight of the IHRB and there is nothing we are not being transparent about with it at the moment.</p>
          <p eId="para_235"> Rather than looking backward and deciding who should suffer and what they should suffer in terms of sanctions, we are very much looking forward. We have put controls in place, which I outlined earlier, to ensure that nothing of this nature can happen again. We have not for a moment said that what happened and what is described so accurately and in such detail in this Forvis Mazars report was acceptable or that any of it should have happened. We have held our hands up as an organisation and have outlined all of the steps we are taking under new management, with new independent directors on our board, to address this and to make sure that from this point forward, we do things as they should be done.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_175" as="#An_Cathaoirleach_Gníomhach">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_236">I welcomed the report and everything Mr. O'Loughlin has just outlined going forward. I do not accept, however, that we should not be looking back and only be looking forward. Some €141,000 of State, taxpayer and public money was paid, which was not sanctioned by HRI. It was accounted for, “as being part of the Voluntary Redundancy and Early Retirement Scheme payments”. Was there any effort to get that money back? It was not part of the package. Who decided to pay it? When a payment like this is discovered, on the back of a report which is basically saying that it was mis-accounted, you cannot move on. We are responsible for the public purse. I cannot walk out of here this evening and say this will never happen again, that there was €141,000 and I am happy in the knowledge that it is never going to happen again. I cannot do that. I take my job seriously. I am responsible to ask the questions on behalf of the taxpayer who paid that €141,000 at the end of the day.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_176">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_237">That is a valid question. Senator Daly will no doubt be pleased to know that the sum of €141,000 was not paid by the taxpayer. It was ultimately paid by the members of the Turf Club and the Irish National Hunt Steeplechase committee.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_177" as="#An_Cathaoirleach_Gníomhach">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_238">They are funded by HRI which, as has been stated, receives massive sums of money from the public purse ever year. While it may receive a certain amount of money from the State and a certain amount of money from elsewhere through entry fees or whatever, putting the two parts together, there is no way of knowing what part was used. When a body is in receipt of public funding and money is spent or misappropriated, it is public money. It has matching funding and other sources of income, but it is a beneficiary of public funding.</p>
          <p eId="para_239">Why else is it even duty-bound to come in here? Why else is it answerable to us? Why does it answer to the Oireachtas? Why does it and HRI have to attend the PAC? It is public money.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_178">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_240">It might be helpful for me, for the committee, to distinguish between the Irish Horseracing Regulatory Board, IHRB, which is the racing regulatory body under the Horse Racing Ireland Act 2016, and the Turf Club and the INHSC, which before 2018 carried out that function. The INHSC and the Turf Club are not currently the racing regulatory bodies; they are private members' clubs. They are very important stakeholders in the IHRB and they each nominate directors to our board. Those two organisations, as private members' clubs, do not receive State funds. The Turf Club is not State-funded; it is a private members' organisation. The IHRB is a separate entity. My contract of employment is with the IHRB, not with the Turf Club and not with the INHSC. I do not work for those clubs, my CFO does not work for them and my chief veterinary officer does not work for them. We work for the IHRB, and the IHRB is funded by the taxpayer through an integrity services budget which comes from HRI. As the Senator has outlined, HRI is funded by the taxpayer. The-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_179">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_241">But-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_180">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_242">This is important.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_181">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_243">The figure is €242,990.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_182" as="#An_Cathaoirleach_Gníomhach">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_244">That was the package. There was €141,000 on top of that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_183">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_245">That is HRI's contribution-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_184">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_246">Correct.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_185" as="#An_Cathaoirleach_Gníomhach">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_247">That was the package, just for clarification.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_186">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_248">That is taxpayers' money.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_187" as="#An_Cathaoirleach_Gníomhach">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_249">That was the correct package.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_188">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_250">That is taxpayers' money, Paul. It is the €242,000.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_189" as="#An_Cathaoirleach_Gníomhach">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_251">The €141,000 was paid over and above that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_190">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_252">The €141,000 is the Turf Club's money then.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_191">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_253">You are correct, Chairman.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_192">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_254">That is where the split came. The HRI money was €242,000 and the Turf Club money was €141,000.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_193" as="#An_Cathaoirleach_Gníomhach">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_255">But where was the €141,000 in the package, in the severance, in the terms and conditions?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_194">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_256">In our financial statements for 2021, which I did not bring with me, it was disclosed by the Comptroller and Auditor General that the total payment was €384,870. I am reading from paragraph 2.1.4 of the Mazars report. The total payment was €384,870, of which €141,880 was funded by the INHSC and the Turf Club. The remaining €242,990, which is the amount he was eligible for under the scheme, was funded by HRI.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_195" as="#An_Cathaoirleach_Gníomhach">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_257">Why then would it be here, in what I read out at the start? Why would it have to be camouflaged in accounts as being recorded as being part of a voluntary redundancy and early retirement scheme? It was not a voluntary redundancy; it was an early retirement scheme. Why was there a need for that false accounting, for want of a better term?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_196">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_258">At the time, there was a single scheme which was called a voluntary redundancy and early retirement scheme. People will go out on either voluntary redundancy or early retirement. What Mazars has found, however, is that because the package agreed with the CEO at the time was greater than the scheme rules allowed for, and, as Mazars has written in its report, because it was not sanctioned in writing by HRI, it did not comply with the terms of that scheme and, according to Mazars, should not have been reported as part of the scheme. Our financial statements for 2021, however, were audited, and in the audit report it was disclosed exactly how much had been paid to the retiring CEO. Then, as regards the three redundancies, there was one figure given for the scheme, and Mazars has said now, in 2024, that the way in which it was disclosed in the financial statements for 2021 was not correct, in its opinion. At the time, however, the auditors audited and they disclosed the payment that was made to the then former CEO.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_197">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_259">Paul, you are over time by three minutes. I will come back to you.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_198" as="#An_Cathaoirleach_Gníomhach">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_260">Sorry.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_199">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_261">Could I just get clarity on this? The package was €380,000-plus.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_200">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_262">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_201">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_263">So €242,000 basically came from the Department. You could argue the point that this is State money. The sum of €141,880 was the top-up, for lack of a better word to describe it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_202">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_264">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_203">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_265">Why was that topped up?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_204">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_266">That money was paid by those two private members' clubs in recognition of the CEO's I think 25, possibly 26, years of service to horse racing. It formed the balance, according to the Mazars report, and the total package was negotiated with-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_205">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_267">By a third party, was it not?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_206">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_268">As Mazars described it, a third party professional services firm.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_207">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_269">By whom was that third party professional services firm hired?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_208">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_270">The IHRB. The IHRB got legal advice on the package for the retiring CEO, and that advice came from what is described in the report as an international professional services firm with a presence in Ireland.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_209">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_271">The IHRB got an outside consultant to evaluate the potential package, and the top-up then came from the Turf Club to fill the hole regarding the potential package.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_210">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_272">That is pretty much what the Forvis Mazars report in front of us all says.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_211">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_273">Would you not consider that totally irregular?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_212">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_274">Mazars has noted that, as a result of that, it falls outside the terms of the scheme.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_213">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_275">Has the Turf Club ever corresponded with you, as an organisation, about the €141,000? Will this be the next CEO's proposal, that he will have another top-up from the Turf Club?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_214">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_276">Well, I am the next CEO-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_215">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_277">I am well aware of that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_216">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_278">-----and I have not been offered any top-ups in the Turf Club and do not fancy my chances, to be quite honest. I am not looking for top-ups.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_217">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_279">It is quite a bizarre situation, though. I know of no other organisation where an outside entity would channel money into it for a top-up for a retirement fund. It is potentially unheard of.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_218">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_280">It has been stated that it was the view - indeed, it is in this report - taken by the directors of the time that it was in the best interests of racing for the retirement to be facilitated.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_219">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_281">Four of those directors who were there in 2021 are still in place. Am I right?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_220">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_282">Yes. The directors on the board rotate often-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_221">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_283">But there are still four who were in place, so there are four individuals on that board who believe this was appropriate. Am I right in making that statement?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_222">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_284">I cannot speak for what they believe now, but it is in the report that at the time they made the decision it was in the best interests of racing.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_223">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_285">Have they ever commented publicly or privately about the possibility that it might not have been in the best interests of horse racing?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_224">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_286">The board of the IHRB today has received this report and has fully accepted it and all the findings in it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_225">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_287">Have the four members who were on the board at the time ever made a comment publicly about that issue?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_226">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_288">I am not aware of any public comments being made.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_227">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_289">Confidence is required in the system. The confidence comes from leadership, and if you have four members on that board who had confidence in it at that time, I just question how we can have confidence in the set-up at that stage.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_228">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_290">I will say if, I may, Chairman, that in my two and a bit years in this role, I have found the board to be supportive of the governance, probity, transparency and accountability measures we are putting in place. They have been supportive of the process by which we have arrived at this report and they have been very supportive in terms of the list of measures we outlined earlier that we are implementing to ensure that the issue I described here as an issue of grave concern in June of last year cannot reoccur. I have been challenged on my use of the words "grave concern" and I stand by them because at that time all I was aware of - all we were aware of - was that moneys from a charity had been moved-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_229">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T18:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_291">That is a slightly different issue.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_230">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_292">From that point, the board of the IHRB-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_231">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_293">We need to wrap up shortly. I will come to the charity issue in a moment. Regarding the top-up, what guarantees does the committee have that the potential CEO, whoever it might be, does not get another top-up from the Turf Club in respect of this issue?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_232">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_294">An expression that my mother used to use was, "Once bitten, twice shy." I imagine that expression could probably come into play. There is no reason why that particular set of circumstances would ever arise again. The circumstances were different in that the individual concerned had worked for 20 years, maybe more, for the Turf Club before becoming CEO of the IHRB, so there was a pre-existing relationship.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_233">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_295">It was bizarre, to say the least - and I am being polite - to think that the Turf Club would potentially have given money to the IHRB as part of a package of €380,000 for the individual in question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_234">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_296">I do not speak for the Turf Club, so I am at a disadvantage.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_235">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_297">Money was moved out of a charity account for 94 days. This is a significant issue. What safeguards have been put in place regarding the charity aspect? As CEO of his organisation, does Mr. O'Loughlin believe that its work with the charities needs to be looked at? Is it part of his remit to manage the charity fund? Should other entities be involved in managing the fund? When one looks at IHRB's role as a regulator and how it is involved in the charity aspect, I am perturbed in the context of how they all fit together. Will Mr. O'Loughlin explain how they fit together and whether they way in which his organisation and the charities work together is appropriate and international best practice? How does it work?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_236">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_298">It is an anomalous situation. The charities were established over time with the best of intentions-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_237">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_299">I appreciate that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_238">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_300">-----with much input and support from the Turf Club over the years. When the IHRB took on the role of racing regulatory body, it inherited the administration of these charities almost as custom and practice, as the Leas-Chathaoirleach pointed out, rather than as part of the regulatory remit. The measures that we have put in place meet the recommendations of this Mazars report in the immediate term. Ultimately, as the Leas-Chathaoirleach said, we need to take a higher level view and ask ourselves if it is appropriate for us, as a regulatory body, to be administering charities, albeit in a related area.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_239">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_301">Even the legalities of it are an issue. The IHRB is acting as a charity regulator and dealing with other issues that do not relate to it as the regulator of horse racing. It is slightly bizarre, to say the least, that the IHRB is tied into it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_240">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_302">It is probably important to note that we just provide the administration service to the charities. In other words, we provide the staff who do the administration. We do not provide decision-making for the charities. They all have their own boards of trustees and committees of management that do the decision-making, but IHRB implement those decisions to manage the accounts and finances.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_241">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_303">When it comes to paying out, if they have to, which I hope they do not, it is effectively IHRB's staff who make those payments.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_242">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_304">Yes. Our staff makes the payments once they have been approved by the trustees or the committee of management, but the question is still valid.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_243">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_305">But that did not happen in this-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_244">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_306">That did not happen in this case. The report is clear and we are all clear that what happened should not have happened. The Leas-Chathaoirleach's question remains valid, and we are asking it ourselves. Given that, as we discussed, our resources are not overly plentiful and should be applied to regulating horse racing, which we exist to do, we have to ask if it is appropriate that we are using our time and people to provide administration services for charities and ending up in a situation such as this. I am satisfied that we would not end up in this situation again but it happened and we have to ask if that is the right model. It would not be right for us to simply cut those charities adrift. That cannot happen. They do not have employees. We are doing the work for them.</p>
          <p eId="para_307"> I have already undertaken discussions with the Department to the effect that in the new year we have to go back and look at the effectiveness of what we are doing and how we are doing it. We need to come up with a model that is sustainable and that provides the right level of accountability, transparency and safeguards. I imagine we will be invited back here this time next year and I will report at that stage on what we have done in the intervening period to strengthen governance and make sure we have the right level of segregation between entities and accounts, which I think the Leas-Chathaoirleach is hoping to see.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_245">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_308">My final point is about the cash flow issue that the IHRB experienced. I do not think there was any malice or personal gain to what happened, but it was a cash flow issue that brought the IHRB into that scenario. As an organisation, what management changes has IHRB put in place to make sure it does not have another cash flow issue, taking into consideration changes in staff and redundancy? I am not sure. Issues might emerge within the organisation. Has the IHRB looked at other cash flow elements? How did it run into this cash flow issue? I think making redundancy payments was the issue. What strategic planning is happening to make sure that the IHRB does not have these cash flow issues?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_246">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_309">In this particular case, exactly as the Leas-Chathaoirleach said, redundancy payments were being paid out to individuals before the corresponding funding had come in from HRI. We have a service-level agreement with HRI which captures all of this. We strengthened it, revised it and worked on it in the past year. We are working on it again, with another review before the end of this year. Under the agreement that we now have with HRI, if we were proposing any redundancies, we would have to do a business case. We would give the business case to HRI, it would approve the redundancies, assuming the business case stands up, then having approved the business case, it would then approve the funding. We will not even offer terms to our employees or the union on any potential redundancy until we have that approval from HRI on the terms of the redundancy. No payment will be made to any individual who is being made redundant until the corresponding funding has come across from HRI. We prevent the cash flow issue by getting the cash in before the cash goes out. We will get the approvals in place in writing before any steps are taken.</p>
          <p eId="para_310"> Regarding cash flow issues generally, we continually scan the horizon. We are quite strict about looking at what lumpy expenditure is coming up on big-ticket items. We make sure we have the money upfront in our account, from our funders, before the expenditure is incurred.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_247" as="#An_Cathaoirleach_Gníomhach">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_311">Mr. O'Loughlin has nearly covered anything. I will not hog the meeting because we have been here for nearly two years. I asked about redundancies and Mr. O'Loughlin answered at the end. I know he said it was done with HRI. Were the voluntary redundancies a cost-cutting measure or was the IHRB overstaffed? Why was there a voluntary redundancy scheme to start with? Compulsory redundancy is mentioned in the Mazars report. I am intrigued by that. Maybe there are circumstances where Mr. O'Loughlin cannot comment on it. It jumps out when one sees compulsory redundancy in an organisation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_248">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_312">Yes. An individual was involved. I will not discuss any individual here, notwithstanding the privilege. Regarding why there was a round of redundancies, it was not just a cost-cutting exercise, but is about efficiency. It is not just about whether we have the right number of people but whether we have the right people in the right jobs for where we are today and where we want to go in the future. As an organisation, we continually have to evaluate what our resources are, who we have, what the skills base we have is, whether we have enough skills in the areas where we are very active, and if we are overpopulated in areas where we are not so active. I was not there at the time, but I understand this was not about cost-cutting as much as efficiency.</p>
          <p eId="para_313">It was not to reduce the overall headcount. It was to make sure we were recruiting and retaining people with the skills that were needed at the time in the organisation and giving people whose skills might have been superfluous the opportunity to leave on good terms.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_249" as="#An_Cathaoirleach_Gníomhach">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_314">I think it was reported it was two people during this period. There were two voluntary redundancies.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_250">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_315">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_251" as="#An_Cathaoirleach_Gníomhach">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_316">Were there unsuccessful applicants, for want of a better word, or was it just two people who took the package on?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_252">
          <from> Mr. Darragh O'Loughlin<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_317">In my experience, across industries there are always disappointed applicants when you have a voluntary redundancy scheme. Any manager would tell you that dealing with the disappointment of the people who are not selected for the voluntary redundancy is often the trickiest part of managing it and in this case, the IHRB is no different.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_253" as="#An_Cathaoirleach_Gníomhach">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_318">That is all.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_254">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_319">On behalf of the committee, I thank the witnesses for their appearance here. It is very important that we have had this discussion. Hopefully we can build confidence in the industry going forward. I sincerely thank the three witnesses for coming in.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_10">
          <i>Sitting suspended at 7.11 p.m and resumed at 7.15 p.m.</i>
        </summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>Eradication of Bovine TB: Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:10:00+00:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_255">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_320">Following the agenda, the second session of today's meeting is on the examination of the TB eradication programme.</p>
          <p eId="para_321"> The witnesses are welcome. I will now read the notice on privilege. Witnesses giving evidence from within the parliamentary precincts are protected by absolute privilege in respect of the evidence they give to the committee. This means that witnesses have a full defence in any defamation action taken based on anything they say in the committee meeting. However, witnesses are expected not to abuse this privilege and may be directed to cease giving evidence by a direction of the Chair. Witnesses should follow the direction of the Chair in this regard. They are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that, where reasonable and unless there is no alternative, no commentary should be made identifying a third person or entity. Witnesses giving evidence from outside the parliamentary precincts are asked to note that they may not benefit from the same legal immunity as witnesses giving evidence from inside the parliamentary precincts and may consider taking legal advice on this matter. Privilege against any defamatory action does not apply to publication outside the precincts of the committee on any matters arising from these proceedings. </p>
          <p eId="para_322"> I now call Mr. Conor O'Mahony to read his opening statement and we will take questions then afterwards. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_256">
          <from> Mr. Conor O'Mahony<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_323">I begin by thanking the Cathaoirleach, Deputies and Senators for inviting the Department to appear before them today. I am principal officer in the Department and am joined by Dr. Damien Barrett, senior superintending veterinary inspector. We are responsible for the development of policy in relation to and the implementation of the bovine TB eradication programme. We welcome the opportunity to appear before the committee to discuss the bovine TB eradication strategy.</p>
          <p eId="para_324"> The Department is acutely aware of the financial and emotional stress associated with a TB breakdown. It causes significant hardship for farmers and farming families. This Department is committed to the objectives of the bovine TB eradication strategy and programme, which aims to reduce and ultimately eradicate this disease in Ireland. Unfortunately, since we were before the committee last year, the prevailing disease situation has not improved despite the efforts of stakeholders. The importance of Ireland’s TB eradication programme in underpinning farm family income should not be underestimated. As a country that exports 90% of our livestock produce, access to international trade markets is fundamental. It is a requirement of EU trade law to have an eradication programme. This enables Irish farmers to access the EU Single Market for our cattle, including calves, and their meat and milk. This is also a requirement for access to third country markets. Our export markets to third countries have grown substantially in value and volume in the last ten years, and it is notable that in several cases, TB is a significant consideration in the context of trade and certification requirements. A cost benefit analysis report of the TB programme carried out by Grant Thornton in 2021 estimated that in economic terms, 78% of the benefits of the bovine TB eradication programme relate to private goods while 22% accrues to public goods.</p>
          <p eId="para_325"> TB is a challenging disease to control and eradicate due to several factors. The relative contribution of each of these factors varies from farm to farm. They include movement of cattle with undetected infection; residual infection in cattle previously exposed to TB; the inherent limitations of the tests; a reservoir of disease in a protected species, namely, the badger; and inadequate biosecurity practices on farms. As such, it is important that farmers are empowered to make the best choices for their own circumstances to protect their cattle from TB. It is critical that they are given practical advice based on scientific research about how they can reduce their TB risk, as well as relevant and useful information about their own herds, their own cattle and their own farming practices in order that they can make any management changes which may be necessary if they wish to avoid the costs and stress of a TB breakdown. This includes making informed decisions about the purchase of cattle and maintaining good overall herd health. The advice on how to reduce TB risk in a herd has remained generally consistent over many years and we continue to encourage farmers to act on it utilising a broader range of communication tools. Stakeholder endorsement of this advice, through the TB Forum, is hugely important in encouraging farmers to take active steps to reduce their TB risk. </p>
          <p eId="para_326"> Vaccinating badgers reduces the transmission of TB within the badger population and thereby reduces transmission to cattle. </p>
          <p eId="para_327">This protects cattle and reduces losses to farmers while safeguarding a native protected Irish wild species. Scientific research carried out in Ireland over many years has demonstrated the effectiveness of badger vaccination. We are providing information and advice on the practical steps farmers can take to reduce the risk from badgers by a range of means, including text messages, videos, leaflets and farmer meetings. By combining these practical farmer-led risk reduction actions with the policy of vaccination to prevent breakdowns and targeted licensed badger removal where necessary in response to spillover from badgers to cattle, we can greatly mitigate the risk of TB at the wildlife and cattle interface.</p>
          <p eId="para_328"> The bovine TB stakeholder forum, established in May 2018, in line with international best practice on the governance of animal health programmes has a mandate to develop evidence-informed policies that can control and ultimately eradicate TB. The Bovine TB Eradication Strategy 2021-2030 was published in January 2021 and identified the key actions necessary to eradicate TB. The key actions in the strategy are preventing spread from herds with a high risk of recurrence; enhanced actions to clear infection from extended breakdown herds; addressing the risk from inconclusive animals; action plans for areas with increased localised TB levels; aligning with changes in the EU animal health law TB regulations; reducing the risk posed by badgers and deer; tailored and simplified communications between the Department and herdowners; clearer messaging of the risks of TB transmission and how to address them; and biosecurity advice delivered to farmers, with a focus on practical, clear and effective actions to reduce risk and incentivise risk-lowering behaviour.</p>
          <p eId="para_329"> From time to time, a narrative develops that our objective should be to control TB due to the failure thus far to eradicate it. Aside from our EU obligation to have an eradication programme and the importance of this programme to our export partners throughout the world, I wish to be clear that the actions we need to focus on and implement are the same, whether the goal is to control or eradicate this disease.</p>
          <p eId="para_330"> As of 27 October, 5,906 herds had suffered a TB breakdown in the previous 12 months in comparison with 4,914 in the same period last year. Data analysis suggests the reasons underpinning current levels of TB incidence are the expansion of the dairy herd and the resulting increased levels of intensive cattle farming and increased movement of cattle. These conditions are associated with heightened susceptibility to disease, whether that is TB or any other infectious disease. We have also seen a substantial increase in the number of reactors, with 39,339 being disclosed in the past 12 months in comparison with just over 26,500 in the previous 12 months, an increase of 12,758, or 48%. In addition, almost 9.89 million tests were carried out in the 12 months up to 27 October compared with around 9.66 million tests in the same period in 2023.</p>
          <p eId="para_331"> In driving strategic change in the bovine TB programme in Ireland, the Minister, Deputy McConalogue, has consistently highlighted the important role of stakeholder collaboration. Reflecting this, implementation of the TB strategy is being facilitated by a governance structure designed to ensure all perspectives are considered. The TB stakeholder forum is supported by three working groups, scientific, finance and implementation, each of which has an independent chair to deliver on its specific terms of reference. The working groups report back to the TB forum as required throughout the year.</p>
          <p eId="para_332"> In 2023, more than 9.8 million individual animal TB tests were completed in more than 100,000 herds. Delivering the TB programme in any given year represents a massive logistical operation achieved through the co-operation of farmers, private vets and Department officials right across the country. The overall cost to the Exchequer of the TB programme, excluding staff costs, has increased from full-year costs of €57 million in 2023 to €74 million as of the end of October, and it is on track to increase further in 2025. In this time, the primary driver of increased costs has been compensation. For many years, Ireland’s TB programme has been financially supported by the EU. However, EU support for the TB programme has ceased because of funding pressures for other emerging diseases throughout the EU. This funding gap will have to be addressed by the remaining stakeholders and is a potent reminder of the need for collaboration and urgency of action to decrease the disease levels.</p>
          <p eId="para_333"> The TB strategy sets out how the Department and stakeholders will continue to engage on the issues impacting on TB levels in Ireland, which will involve some difficult choices. By building our policies on a foundation of science and by providing practical science-based advice which farmers can act on to reduce their risks, we can together focus our efforts to protect cattle from infection and farmers from the stress, uncertainty and costs of a breakdown. Most actions set out under the current TB strategy have either been implemented or are advancing well towards implementation. However, we are at a point now where we have to consider whether we are, as a collective, prepared to make the difficult choices that may be required to make a step change. Some of these have been discussed at the TB forum. They include voluntary or mandatory informed purchasing; voluntary or mandatory risk-based trading; incentivising risk-lowering behaviours and disincentivising risk elevating behaviours; reducing spread between areas using contract rearing risk mitigation and restrictions on movements from high to low TB areas; dynamic risk estimation at herd and animal level; supporting quality TB testing using gamma interferon blood testing and spatial tools to identify each group of cattle; and reducing spread from high-risk herds by restricting older breeding cattle and confining TB exposed cattle to controlled finishing units. None of these options are easy for anyone but with stakeholder support, they have the potential to make a real difference.</p>
          <p eId="para_334"> From the Department’s point of view, we acknowledge the legitimate concerns of those whose businesses and lives are affected by this disease. Equally, we have an obligation to use the best scientific evidence to reduce the risk of infection for herds that are currently free of the disease and to help those with chronic or repeating problems to manage their way out of them. We can only make real progress together and the Department is committed to constructive and collaborative engagement on all of these matters.</p>
          <p eId="para_335"> We now have the building blocks in place to implement additional measures to the existing TB programme that can lower disease incidence and result in fewer farm families having to endure the challenges associated with a TB restriction. We are committed to constructive engagement with all stakeholders in helping the farming community. I hope that the next time we address the committee on bovine TB, we will be able to outline a positive picture of reducing TB incidence. I welcome any questions from members of the committee.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_257">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_336">I thank Mr. O'Mahony and Dr. Barrett for coming before the committee this evening. This is something we have dealt with on a regular basis at the committee and on the field of play as farmers, which most of us here are. With the greatest respect to everybody involved, and there is no blame game here, as the opening statement relates, the situation is getting worse instead of better. I do not know where we go from here. Everything has been tried. The last time the witnesses came before the committee I spoke about vaccination. I heard a bit on Claire Byrne's radio programme the other morning and I know the Department is working in collaboration with the UK and monitoring its development of a vaccination. The issue is being able to tell the difference between a reactor and vaccinated animal.</p>
          <p eId="para_337"> It is probably an easy cliché, and this would not get the same determination, but we came up with the Covid vaccination for human beings in a matter of months. I know I am comparing apples with oranges and it is not a proper analogy to make. Given the amount of money we are spending and the lack of progress we are making, is there an argument to be made that we throw the proverbial kitchen sink at this with a pharmaceutical company, a scientific unit in a university or an expert in the field of science? Should we throw ten years' worth of TB money at this to come up with a vaccination? This will not be solved until we are vaccinating. I would like the opinions of the witnesses on that.</p>
          <p eId="para_338"> We are vaccinating badgers and it is very hit and miss. I get text messages about badger movement in my area but they are hit and miss. Some people will not respond to the text messages because they fear drawing the Department on top of them. This is human nature and it is a fact. Many of these things are ignored because someone thinks if they respond to say they saw a badger, they will have the whole Department down the following day. These measures are difficult to make work for many such reasons. What do the witnesses think about vaccination? Is there the potential to expedite it? This problem will not be solved until we are vaccinating.</p>
          <p eId="para_339"> Mr. O'Mahony spoke about the issues discussed at the TB forum which would be bitter pills to swallow but may have to be the next step. Whose decision would it be to move to this next level and introduce some of the measures he mentioned?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_258">
          <from> Mr. Conor O'Mahony<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_340">Dr. Barrett will answer the question on vaccination.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_259">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_341">Senator Daly has made a very valid point on vaccination. Our modelling suggests if we had a vaccine available, it would be the single most effective intervention we could make. We do not have a vaccine on the market. As the Senator is aware, work is being done by the Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs, DEFRA, in the UK and we are liaising with it. The biggest research funder in TB in the world is the Gates foundation. It is also looking at vaccination. It is looking at it as a public health measure in the developing world.</p>
          <p eId="para_342">There is a significant body of research on TB vaccination. TB, by its nature, is one of those diseases where it is proven that developing a vaccine for a microbacterium, which is the type of bacteria that TB is, is significantly more complex than developing one for a virus like Covid. All things are possible, however. The crunch point here, as Senator Daly rightly pointed out, is differentiating between vaccinated cattle and infected cattle. That is being worked on.</p>
          <p eId="para_343"> On the other side of this, there are very significant legislative and trade implications to vaccinating animals. As a nation which exports a volume of bovine-derived product, be that beef, dairy or whatever, that would have massive implications for the export of that product. That is another front which needs to be addressed. </p>
          <p eId="para_344"> In simple terms, a vaccine would make this far more straightforward from a disease control point of view. The logistics of achieving that are complicated and the trade implications are probably more complicated.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_260">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_345">Going back to where Dr. Barrett started there about DEFRA and the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation, are they collaborating or are they two separate projects? If they are separate, which of them is the more advanced?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_261">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_346">The focus of the Gates foundation work is probably more in the public health sphere - people - but where there is research on TB, whether it is in people or in animals, there is probably a crossover and the technology may be shared. From the point of view of a product that would be ready to go, my understanding is that the DEFRA research is probably more advanced for something in the cattle sphere but it is not imminent.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_262">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_347">As I mentioned at the outset, if the vaccination is working with badgers, why will it not work with bovines?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_263">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_348">It is not so much the vaccination. The studies suggest reasonable efficacy in cattle but it comes down to the differentiation between animals. We are obliged to continue to have an eradication programme under the animal health law. With the current test technology we have, we cannot differentiate between which animals have been vaccinated. An animal that has been vaccinated will give an immune reaction that is similar to that of an infected animal. That is the crux of it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_264">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_349">Right.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_265">
          <from> Mr. Conor O'Mahony<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_350">On the issues being discussed in the forum and who will make that decision, ultimately, the best policy is an agreed one. A couple of years ago, we saw significant farmer opposition to certain policies that the Department tried to implement. The forum is trying to bring everybody together by working collaboratively. We know where the issues are with regard to the risk of TB and further outbreaks of the disease. In the past couple of months the Department and the farmer organisations have been discussing how to address these key issues which we need to wrestle with. All farm organisations are aware that we just cannot stay with what we have been doing for the past number of years because it is clearly not working. Those conversations, as the Senator can imagine, are difficult and I do not want to breach the confidential nature of any of those conversations-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_266">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_351">I appreciate that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_267">
          <from> Mr. Conor O'Mahony<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_352">-----but to go to the Senator's point, we want to move together to make hard decisions everybody understands and appreciates and which we can implement collaboratively because that is our best hope of ultimately being effective.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_268">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_353">I thank our witnesses and the Chair.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_269">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_354">I call Deputy Fitzmaurice. He will need to be brief.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_270">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_355">I thank the witnesses for coming in. I have a couple of quick questions. I raised an eyebrow at the suggestion that the Gates foundation would be more into disease in humans. My understanding is that the foundation is buying up a great deal of land in America and leaving it idle. It is not a fan of cattle, in my understanding.</p>
          <p eId="para_356"> On the research, and I have looked into this a bit, it is a long way off. One vaccine was produced but it was not possible to distinguish between a positive and a negative. They are trying to perfect that. People are not living in a sort of Funderland - realistically, it is a while off. Would that be fair to say?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_271">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_357">That is very fair to say. In the interim, we have to look at the other interventions we can make.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_272">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_358">Of the herds, I believe there are 5,000, approximately, and there used to be 4,000. What is the breakdown between beef, suckler and dairy in those herds?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_273">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_359">About 70% of the reactors are derived from dairy herds and the remainder is a combination of beef and suckler. We have seen a surge. As the demographics of the cattle herd have moved more towards dairy, we see that mirrored in the numbers of reactors among dairy-bred cattle.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_274">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_360">My next question come from a guy would did a fair bit of looking at TB; he was a Department person and he looked at different scenarios. Is it true to say that, no more than there could be a gene for cancer in a person and something will trigger it, all cattle have a gene for TB that could be triggered? Is that fair to say?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_275">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_361">I would not say it is in all cattle. There are differences insofar as whether that come across it are more genetically susceptible or resistant to it. Coming up to breeding season this year, farmers received text messages advising them, when choosing bulls for the breeding season, to choose bulls with greater resistance. The Deputy has correctly pointed out that there will not be a vaccine on the horizon in the short term. In the absence of a vaccine, what is available in the short-term is breeding for resistance. This is essentially genetic resistance, rather than vaccine resistance.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_276">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_362">Is that factual, I wonder? Some would say-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_277">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_363">It is factual. We would see that-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_278">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_364">Are these bulls of all different breeds?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_279">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_365">Yes. They are across all different breeds. Animals with the lowest resistance to TB have 26% more reactors among their progeny.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_280">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_366">I hope Dr. Barrett will be able to explain one thing to me which I can never understand. Many farmers have phoned me up to tell me a few animals had gone down. On the accuracy of the two stabs in the neck, when the animals go to the factory and the results come back, it is discovered that animals do not have the disease. That is causing a great deal of vexation among farmers.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_281">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_367">It is not true to say that they do not have the disease. It is that the disease has not reached an advanced stage at which the animal would develop lesions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_282">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_368">Dr. Barrett is saying the animals still have it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_283">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_369">It takes at least four months for lesions to develop. At an early stage, this might not be news that people want to hear but it is actually good news for them that the disease has been detected earlier rather than allowing the disease to spread within their herd.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_284">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_370">Is the blood test a better test?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_285">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_371">It depends. It has better sensitivity and detects more but the specificity is not as good. That means there are more false positives. We use the blood test in circumstances where we are confident that there is cattle-to-cattle transmission going on. We generally do not use it in single reactors or where we do not believe on epidemiological grounds that cattle-to-cattle transmission is taking place because there is a risk that we would be taking out false positives.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_286">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_372">Is it taken from one animal to another?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_287">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_373">Does the Deputy mean spreading?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_288">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_374">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_289">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_375">Very much so.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_290">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_376">There is a vaccine programme in respect of badgers. When the Department carried out its analysis in the various areas, did it discover if it has worked? We hear the opposite; in other words, that it has not worked. Is that right?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_291">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_377">We have the evidence and trial work, which has shown it is on a par with culling. One needs to bear in mind we need to get penetration of the badger population and have sufficient numbers of the badger population vaccinated. That is why we sent out those texts to which the Senator referred. We need to know where the badgers are to vaccinate them. That is the challenge. It is not a small body of work, going through the byroads of the country.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_292">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_378">I know. This is probably a question for Mr. O’Mahony because, in fairness, Dr. Barrett is on the veterinary side. There seems to be a horrid shortage of people for culling badgers, testing and trapping them or whatever. You hear about farmers ringing up and about their awful frustration. Is it that there is not enough of a budget for that? What is wrong?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_293">
          <from> Mr. Conor O'Mahony<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_379">Our expenditure on the wildlife programme, which includes capturing for vaccination and culling, has almost doubled in the past four or five years. There is no lack of resources. Going back to the early 2000s when we started culling badgers, we have more or less consistently culled the same number over that entire period. Our culling level has not dropped. It might go up a couple of hundred-odd a year.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_294">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_380">Would the badger population not have increased?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_295">
          <from> Mr. Conor O'Mahony<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_381">We are taking out about 6,000 a year. Since 2019, we have started capturing significant number of badgers for vaccination. Any increase in the population of badgers is associated with increased vaccination within that population. The ideal goal is to have a healthy wildlife population as well. It is not a question that there are not enough resources put into the wildlife programme. Our resources have almost doubled in the past couple of years.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_296">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_382">I have heard theories. Someone said that zero grazing has a higher risk. Is that right or wrong?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_297">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_383">That is correct. We recommend that badger setts be fenced off.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_298">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_384">A fence around a sett.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_299">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_385">They come out and toilet immediately in the vicinity of the sett. There could be quite a bit of contamination of grass. When the zero grazer comes along, if it comes close to that, it can lift it. Likewise, it could lift it if it was harvested for-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_300">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_386">Faeces.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_301">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_387">Yes. Likewise, it could do so if it was harvested for silage but in the ensiling process, the pH level going down kills off the bacteria. It is a risk. We are highly concerned about it. We have tried to highlight it. Zero grazing has become more popular in the past few years, particularly last spring when fodder there was a shortage of fodder.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_302">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_388">Dr. Barrett made the comparison between deer and badgers. In the context what the Department has sampled, what is the percentage? Is one as bad as the other?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_303">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_389">No. We have evidence from County Wicklow through whole-genome sequencing that the same strains of TB were present in deer, badgers and cattle. We do not have that evidence established in other parts of the country. Absence of evidence is not evidence of absence but we have good data there. Generally speaking, the level of TB in deer samples that have been submitted to regional veterinary labs for analysis is approximately 2%. In one particular study in County Wicklow, we found that to be about 16%. In low-incidence areas, the level of TB among badgers is about 15% and in high-incidence areas it could be between 30% or 40%.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_304">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_390">That is high.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_305">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_391">Badgers are worse.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_306">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_392">Yes. There are other reasons for the management of deer, as well as TB, in the lines of biodiversity, forestry or road safety. There are other reasons to manage deer.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_307">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_393">They are taking over the country. Mr. O’Mahony said when Senator Daly spoke that there would be harder measures and the Department will propose or talk to farming organisations. What is in the pipeline?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_308">
          <from> Mr. Conor O'Mahony<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_394">To reiterate, there is an acceptance among all stakeholders that something different needs to happen across a number of areas. The risk of transmission from high-risk animals to other herds needs to be addressed and wrestled with. A number of years ago, proposals put forward by the Department were not accepted by other stakeholders. We have been discussing with them over the past few months potential measures that could be implemented to address that particular risk that can be acceptable to them, while at the same time reducing the transmission of TB from what we consider higher-risk animals and higher-risk herds. As I said to Senator Daly, those conversations with farm organisations are ongoing. I do not want to betray the nature of those conversations. Given the high levels of disease now relative to a couple of years ago, there is a chance of ultimately getting agreement on these new measures.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_309">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_395">I see one is on reducing the spread. What does restricting older breeding cattle mean? Is that older cows? What age?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_310">
          <from> Mr. Conor O'Mahony<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_396">Older breeding animals, for example, cows that have had a significant number of lactations in dairy herds or even in suckler herds would be considered higher-risk animal.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_311">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_397">What is older? Is it a 17-year-old cow or a 12-year-old?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_312">
          <from> Mr. Conor O'Mahony<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_398">An average dairy cow has three and a half lactations. In the dairy context, it is anything above the average. In a suckler cow, they tend to be older cows.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_313">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_399">In sucklers, for example, what age?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_314">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_400">We are looking at higher-risk animals in higher-risk herds. This would not be a blanket approach. It would be specific and probably would be animals present at a high-risk breakdown where cattle-to-cattle transmission was evident.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_315">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_401">Correct me if I am wrong, but if there are younger animals, some of the feed lots have the right to buy and put them in. They could have animals that are clean. Dr. Barrett just said they could spread the disease. How does that operate? If I am a feed lot owner, my understanding – correct me if I am wrong – is that some cattle that have TB can be bought by feed lots.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_316">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_402">Farm-restricted herds. No, they are not reactors. They are animals that have passed the tuberculin test. Any reactors go for slaughter.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_317">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_403">It is good to know that because there seems to be a feeling out there-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_318">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_404">To clarify, I think the Deputy referred to what we call controlled finishing units. They are subject to a specific set of rules.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_319">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_405">Dr. Barrett is 100% right. Will Mr. O’Mahony indicate if I am correct in saying that it was once the case that farmers whose animals went down in wintertime could not get the hardship grant? Can they get that grant now?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_320">
          <from> Mr. Conor O'Mahony<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_406">They can. This was agreed with farming organisations in the context of the financial working group. The hardship grant conditions were amended to remove the off-farm income limit but it would only be paid in the event that the farmer had more animals this winter than last year as a result of the restriction.</p>
          <p eId="para_407">Take the classic example of a suckler farmer who sells their weanlings in October or November. They often test a month or two beforehand. If they got locked up they will be left with the weanlings they would otherwise have sold over the winter. In agreement with the farm organisations the conditions were that farmers had to have more animals this winter than last winter as a result of their restriction, because the purpose of the hardship grant is to help people who must incur the additional cost of holding onto these animals over the winter.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_321">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_408">I will ask just one more question because the Vice Chair is jumping. A few farmers have been on to me in the last few weeks. There is the assessment done on a dairy cow where the amount of milk she had is looked at to do the valuation and all that, but on the EBI something has changed over the last few weeks so there is between €50 and €80 less being got for the same cow than would have been got six months ago. Am I right in saying that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_322">
          <from> Mr. Conor O'Mahony<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_409">There was an EBI top-up introduced ten to 15 years ago, or more, at the time of the introduction of the EBI. At that time EBI was new and when farmers were buying animals it was not really built into the market value of an animal. The Deputy might remember it was back in 2000 or 2001 that the EBI was originally introduced. In the intervening 20 years I think there has been an acceptance of EBI among dairy farmers. It is built into farmers' breeding decisions and also their purchasing decisions, so when you are selling an animal on the open market the EBI is taken into account when somebody decides what to bid on that animal. On the live market valuation, the last time there was an EBI revision was over ten years ago. It was €1.05 per unit EBI. That was for the last ten years. In the intervening time EBI is becoming more and more incorporated into the purchase price of dairy stock by farmers, therefore the necessity of an EBI, or more accurately the extent of the EBI top-up, was not really reflecting marketplace activity because it is almost built into people's everyday decisions when buying dairy cattle. That is why it was reduced. The financial working group has started to meet again lately on doing a review of the changes introduced two years ago and one of the changes is looking at how we can use EBI better in the context of incentivising people to-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_323">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_410">Am I correct in saying the price is less? I am hearing from farmers that between €50 and €80 less is being got for the same animal.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_324">
          <from> Mr. Conor O'Mahony<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_411">It has gone down. The reduction was 30 cent per unit EBI, but it is important to stress the original purpose of the EBI was to encourage uptake of EBI and to get people taking EBI into account when they purchase animals, because we are talking about calculating the market value of the animal. For the last 15 to 20 years the marketplace for dairy animals has incorporated EBI, so the previous rate-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_325">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_412">Why has it changed in the last few weeks or months? This is all I am asking because this is-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_326">
          <from> Mr. Conor O'Mahony<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_413">I know. Obviously, this was not just done overnight. There was work done on trying to accurately identify what is more appropriate.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_327">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_414">And is the Department going back and looking at that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_328">
          <from> Mr. Conor O'Mahony<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_415">We are indeed. It is on the work programme for-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_329">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_416">Does Mr. O'Mahony expect the €50 or €70 will be brought back up?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_330">
          <from> Mr. Conor O'Mahony<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_417">We are looking at how it can be better used in the context of better breeding decisions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_331">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_418">I thank the witnesses for their opening statement and the discussion in respect of the situation with TB eradication. It is something farmers across the country have had a somewhat jaundiced view of, in some cases. A lot of money has been spent on it and it is not really delivering. We can all say that pretty truthfully. We had the Minister in here yesterday and I raised this with him in the context of the budget that goes to TB eradication every year. I said that if a portion of that budget could have been put towards research into a vaccination programme ten, 15 or 20 years ago, we would be in a better place now. I want to tease that out a little with the witnesses.</p>
          <p eId="para_419"> I appreciate the discussion we have had up to now. I am aware of some of the work that has been done by various companies and laboratories on this. I would like to ask about a situation where a vaccination was developed and was given to calves when they are born. This is one of the things I want to find out. If a cow has TB and a calf is born, does the TB carry through to the calf? If we had a vaccination programme and we started with the calves, how quickly do the witnesses think we would be in a situation where we would have the herd vaccinated across the State? Is it possible to put some kind of marker in? I get the point that the test for an infected animal and a vaccinated animal will produce the same result as things stand. Could a marker be put in to distinguish between vaccinated and infected animals?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_332">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_420">That is where the research is probably working on at the moment. There are tests called DIVA tests which can identify infected antibodies from natural infection antibodies. That is where that is at. As I said earlier, the technical side of it is challenging, but ultimately it will be addressed and gotten over. The trade implications of this are even more challenging. It is going to depend on agreement at EU Commission level and World Organisation for Animal Health level and that is not a straightforward task.</p>
          <p eId="para_421"> The Deputy asked whether the disease can be transferred from dam to calf. It can be transferred via milk and on occasion we see that happening.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_333">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_422">Dr. Barrett is saying the calf is not born with TB.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_334">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_423">Yes. He has probably acquired it through ingestion.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_335">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_424">Through ingestion afterwards, okay.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_336">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_425">On the research into vaccination, there has been a lot of commentary in the last while about a vaccine. I am sorry, the question was how long would it take us to get it to the population. We would get it done in a year because we get the national population tuberculin tested once a year and it would be a similar type of procedure.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_337">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_426">It would be pretty quick, therefore, if we had it in place.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_338">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_427">If we had it, there is no reason it would not be mobilised fairly quickly. We have not really thought about it because it is not on the horizon, but I cannot see it being much different.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_339">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_428">I asked the question because we are all aware of the experience with Covid and how quickly a number of vaccines were developed when backs were to the wall. If the same level or even a percentage of that level of dedication was put into finding a solution here, we could be in a different place.</p>
          <p eId="para_429"> There is another point I want to tease out with Dr. Barrett a little. He mentioned how it is about getting not just the vaccination but also all the approvals that have to be secured because we export so much of what we produce and we export some of our cattle live as well. As a natural result, we would have to have international agreements around whatever is going to be happening here. Even if we had the vaccine and everything in place and we were confident it would work, we would have to have all that international approval. I assume that would probably take longer than rolling the vaccine out across the herd.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_340">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_430">It is interesting that the UK is probably the leader in this as it is a country that is not self-sufficient in livestock produce. It could consume all its livestock produce, whereas we could not. I would not underestimate the challenge of getting international agreement to this because our competitors would be only too glad to put a stick in the spokes of our bicycle.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_341">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T19:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_431">There was a list provided of things that have been discussed and what they are. Included is voluntary or mandatory informed purchasing and voluntary or mandatory risk-based trading. Much of that is about movement of animals. In a reply to Deputy Fitzmaurice, Dr. Barrett mentioned these restricted farms, fattening units or whatever. The animals that go in there do not move or leave. There is no movement and from that perspective they get a different set of standards or a different regime from other animals being traded on the open market. Is restricting movement of animals part of the solution here? Is that the direction of travel Dr. Barrett is going in?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_342">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_432">The restriction of movement would be specific to high-risk animals from high-risk herds. In our discussions, we understand any additional controls need to be focused on higher risk. We know there are higher-risk animals in higher-risk herds and they are the ones we are most concerned about.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyMythen" eId="spk_343">
          <from>Deputy Johnny Mythen<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_433">I want to get my head around some stuff here. We have probably one of the best pharmaceutical industries in the world here in Ireland. We have top class scientists. We have top class laboratory technicians. The TB programme started around 1954. It is a bacteria. One can be a little bit cynical about the pharmaceutical companies. How much does a human test cost?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_344">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_434">I do not know that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyMythen" eId="spk_345">
          <from>Deputy Johnny Mythen<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_435">There are 9.89 million of them per year; that is a lot. I am not a conspiracy theorist or anything but it seems to me that from 1954 to now, we could not solve it. We did all that stuff with other bacteria like chickenpox and everything else but we cannot seem to get a vaccine in that length of time.</p>
          <p eId="para_436"> Dr. Barrett spoke about the badgers. How is that detail gathered? Is there a specific programme from gathering the detail of the badgers such as where they are exactly, how many have been done and so forth?</p>
          <p eId="para_437"> The cost of the bovine TB eradication programme was €57 million in 2023 and it is €74 million at the end of October and the projection is that it will go even higher. It is worrying that the funding has been ceased by the European Union. Is there a plan in place to fill that gap or who fills the gap?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_346">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_438">As for the research on this, in the context of northern Europe the countries that are affected most by bovine TB are Ireland, Wales and the south-west of England. The market for this, relatively speaking, compared to the market for Covid vaccines is very small. There is probably not the same level of research and development going into this although there is research on it. The other thing about a bacteria is that we should not underestimate it. We are all afraid of viruses like Covid and foot and mouth disease and they are considered to be relatively fast moving pathogens. TB is slow moving but it is tough and it has a couple of different complications that makes it very difficult to deal with it. It persists in the environment for several weeks and months compared to a virus that exists for two weeks.</p>
          <p eId="para_439"> Some animals that are infected by it may go undetected as the disease advances. The tests we have available for it may not be able to detect it. It is not an insignificant body of work to develop this vaccine. The BCG vaccine that a lot of us may have received as children is 100 years old. Most of the modern vaccines we deal with are either that or a variation of that. TB is a particularly difficult nut to crack. I understand why people may be cynical but we also need to understand that while it costs this sum, it supports the export industry. We would not have those exports if we did not have a programme.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyMythen" eId="spk_347">
          <from>Deputy Johnny Mythen<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_440">There is no argument there. On EU funding, what is the position on that and what is planned?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_348">
          <from> Mr. Conor O'Mahony<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_441">The EU funding has ceased. In essence, the shortfall and the increased cost is met by the Exchequer through direct funds. Farmers pay disease levies as well. The quickest way we can reduce the cost of that is to reduce the disease levels in the herd by reducing the number of herds that are restricted and reduce the number of reactors.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyMythen" eId="spk_349">
          <from>Deputy Johnny Mythen<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_442">With all due respect, how is the Department doing that because the rate is 48% higher?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_350">
          <from> Mr. Conor O'Mahony<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_443">That goes to the point we made earlier on the discussions we have with the farming organisations to look at ways of making more difficult decisions with them to address that increase.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_351">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_444">The countries we can learn most from are probably Australia and particularly New Zealand. Our pasture based system is not unlike the system in New Zealand. They have embarked on these controls around animal movements which we are talking about here. That is a key element. In New Zealand, they have a wildlife reservoir like ourselves but their wildlife reservoir is a possum, which is not a protected species. They also make more aggressive use of the gamma interferon blood testing. The experience there is the curtailment of the movement of high-risk animals from high-risk herds is probably the single most effective thing which we are not applying to the same extent.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyMythen" eId="spk_352">
          <from>Deputy Johnny Mythen<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_445">I ask Dr. Barrett to explain a point to me as I do not really understand it. The report states 78% of the economic benefits of the bovine TB eradication programme relate to private goods while 22% accrues to public goods. Could Dr. Barrett explain what that means?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_353">
          <from> Mr. Conor O'Mahony<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_446">The findings of that report were the main benefit to the TB programme is market access to third countries. Essentially, that means private companies and co-ops, beef exporters and milk processors exporting product across the world on foot of the TB eradication programme.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyMythen" eId="spk_354">
          <from>Deputy Johnny Mythen<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_447">On the last one, the Department is aligning changes to the EU animal law health law with our TB regulations. How is it aligning that? What is the progress on it?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_355">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_448">The big thing on that, which the Deputy's constituents may have heard about, related to adult cows and bulls over 36 months. After that age, they need to be within a six month window of getting tested. That has been the main alignment with the animal health law. Our legislation was fairly closely aligned apart from that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_356">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_449">I question the conclusion about the building blocks being put in place and the prediction that there will be a lower disease level. I look at my own part of the world, that is, south Cork and south-west Cork. I argue that we are on the verge of an epidemic of TB in the next few months there. Cattle will be housed within the next few days. There are exceptionally high levels of TB at that moment in that part of the world. When they are housed, the potential for the disease to spread through the herds is quite obvious. I know from my own experience on our farm that when cattle go in with a high level of TB and when we do our TB tests, we have chaos. What could happen here next January, February and March is something we will never again see. I genuinely think we are at epidemic levels in our part of the world.</p>
          <p eId="para_450"> I compliment the staff we have in Clonakilty. Ed Myers and his team are doing an amazing job there and they are dealing with huge outbreaks and vast numbers.</p>
          <p eId="para_451">The days of going into a farmyard and having one or two reactors is gone. There are now multiples. It could be 24, 25 or 52. The number we are dealing with are unheard of. The level of infection in the community is at the highest level I have ever seen in my part of the world. The majority if not all of these herds are closed herds. That is an issue where the movement of animals is going to have an effect. I do not know if it will. These are dairy herds in particular. Some 70% of the national herd comprises dairy herds with animals that have been found to have TB. I have a great worry about what will happen.</p>
          <p eId="para_452"> I want to raise a number of issues with the officials. What is the logic in having doubtfuls in the system? Why do we have TB tests for doubtfuls every six months after they are doubtful? That is the logic we have in the system. Were one to get rid of the doubtful, one would have to dispose but one cannot go through mart. There is then a knock-on implication that there is a value loss as a consequence. I do not understand why we have doubtfuls. This is coming from a farmer who has had doubtfuls. I have been involved in a TB test scenario where every six months we were TB testing the animal. When I realised that an animal was doubtful, I moved it on very quickly. Have we a pattern or policy for what we will do with the doubtfuls in our herds? It should be pass or fail. The farmer needs to have a financial reward if there is a fail. Otherwise, he will be caught in the middle and he is going nowhere. That issue has to be looked at.</p>
          <p eId="para_453"> On the wildlife issue, Dr. Barrett said the budget has doubled. We have heard that there are not enough wildlife officers on the ground and that we are looking at a scenario where farm-relief services are involved and Department staff are not available. We have heard that there may be eight wildlife officers missing nationally. How many gaps are in the service and where are those gaps? We need to know where the gaps in the service are.</p>
          <p eId="para_454"> On the potential for farmers' animals to go down next January, February and March, they will be stuck in a scenario where they have calves they cannot move. The percentage of those calves which will go down at 42 days is very limited. One might argue how can they get the infection unless they are getting the milk. If they are getting the milk, maybe there is a way around this. The welfare issue for the farmer and for the animals in a herd that is potentially locked up in springtime is enormous. It is frightening. I was there three years ago, and we still talk about it. We did not sell a calf until 2 July. It was chaotic. We got through that period, but it cost us a fortune. We need a solution for it. We have nobody who will take a Friesian bull calf. Therefore there are two options: one rears that animal or one does the disastrous job which is to slaughter the animal, which none of us wants to do as farmers. We have to find a solution for the 42-day-old calf. We have to see a proposal because the only avenues are to rear it or it will be slaughtered. We do not slaughter them. The stress caused by that is frightening.</p>
          <p eId="para_455"> Take the high-incidence herd that the Department is saying could be the issue we need to look at. If a herd is then categorised as being high incidence, there is a financial impact immediately in respect of that herd. How will we then deal with that herd? Look at my part of the world. If you go to Ballinhassig, Barryroe, Caheragh or Drimoleague vast herds are all locked up. Parishes are locked up. We are potentially saying that trading from parishes could be stopped if that was to happen. How can that happen and what could the solution be?</p>
          <p eId="para_456"> On the badger population, one veterinary surgeon told me last week that we have a housing issue in respect of badgers because there are so many there at the moment. Instead of having two to a sett, there are seven or eight. That is one of the key issues. We have such large numbers in some areas. Has the vaccination programme increased the number of badgers and, in turn, also increased the volume of TB because there are not enough setts and there is not enough habitat? What have we considered around those issues?</p>
          <p eId="para_457"> The main issue here is the stress on the family farm and the farmer. I would also mention the stress on the vet coming into the yard and putting down 30, 40 or 50 animals. He goes back the next week and he has to look at that farmer. He has to deal with those issues. It is a tough game. We all know the suicide rate among vets. There are issues there as well. However, this entire thing is at epidemic levels in my part of the world. I am fearful of what will happen next January, February and March when animals are housed for six, eight or ten weeks when they are going in with levels of infection. The officials might correct me, but I am of the view that the levels of infection in south and west Cork are at an all-time high.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_357">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_458">The Leas-Chathaoirleach raised a number of issues. There is no doubt that in his part of the world we are looking at very high levels of TB. Herd incidences have reached very high levels. The fact the disease has been identified and the numbers he has spoken about indicate high levels of cattle-to-cattle transmission. We cannot say for certain how it was introduced to those herds but when one sees numbers like that there have been large levels of calf to cattle transmission. We would hope the efforts to remove the reactors has removed the focus of infection from those herds. However, it is worth bearing in mind that since 2019, from our analysis of what we call the healthy slaughters, that is slaughters from unrestricted herds, the levels of TB in that population rose 13% year on year between 2019 and 2023. That also increased the transmission to the badgers. There has been a rise. The detection of that rise really kicked in from mid-2023. It seems to have been surging ahead from mid-2023.</p>
          <p eId="para_459"> To return to the point about whether housing will be the risk, I do not have a crystal ball. I cannot be sure. I would be confident that the level of removal of reactors should reduce that risk substantially. As I say, I do not have a crystal ball but I am very hopeful. I hope those herds have seen their worst. </p>
          <p eId="para_460"> On the doubtfuls, this has been the interpretation of the test and the standards. Doubtfuls carry a risk. When we mention herd incidence, the herd was not restricted as a doubtful but those animals were at higher risk. What we have been trying to do is encourage people to take those animals out voluntarily.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_358">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_461">The problem with that is there is no compensation for it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_359">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_462">If the animal is taken out the benefit is that when the animal is gone the herd is not restricted.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_360">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_463">I agree on the non-restricted part but still. One must send it to a certain abattoir and one knows what one is going to get. It will not be market value, and the farmer loses.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_361">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_464">It might not be but it is a trade-off.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_362">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_465">And I have been that soldier.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_363">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_466">I understand that.</p>
          <p eId="para_467">We must get to a situation where we treat this as a disease eradication programme rather than asking the State to fund it without rooting out disease. These are one or two animals in large operations. There is a risk–reward aspect here in respect of the reward to be gained by taking these animals out versus the consequences of leaving them behind, which will lead to bigger breakdowns. People need to make these business decisions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_364">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_468">It is a business decision, but from a risk point of view in respect of the Department, having doubtful animals in the system is a risk. Have we looked at the policy element of having such doubtfuls? We are not talking about the financial element, because we can talk about that and argue the point in that regard. There is, though, a risk element to having doubtfuls in a system. In some cases, when we have doubtfuls in a system and then a reactor, the doubtfuls are automatically taken out after.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_365">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_469">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_366">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_470">This calls into question the doubtfuls and whether, realistically, they should be looked at differently now when we consider where we are now with the figures regarding TB. We are looking at having a supplementary budget. If I am right, that is going to be increased by 71%, with another €40 million going into it. It is a huge amount of money.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_367">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_471">It is. The doubtfuls are not driving this surge.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_368">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_472">I agree, but it is a part of a circle.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_369">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_473">It could well be, but there are bigger fish to fry here in terms of cattle movement than doubtfuls.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_370">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_474">I would argue that many of the 70% of dairy herds are closed herds.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_371">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_475">We actually have data on what are closed herds. Of the 105,000 herds, I think about 10,000 have been closed for the past three years.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_372">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_476">That probably could be a stock bull in that-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_373">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_477">It could.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_374">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_478">It would be logical in the majority of our operations.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_375">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_479">Yes, but we have scenarios here where we have flying herds being encouraged. What must be borne in mind here is that an individual farmer could have his herd 100% closed. If he has a flying herd beside him, however, that may introduce disease to badgers. That farmer, then, through no fault of his own, may see his herd infected. If there is a flying herd beside him, that may be a source of infection for the badgers. That may, in turn, be a source of infection for that farmer's herd. I feel very sorry for those people with closed herds where, through no fault of their own, the disease may be introduced.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_376">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_480">Regarding the calves, we are looking at the system of 42 days being put in place now. We can argue whether that should be extended, but this is not the point. The point is that there is no outlet for calves if you are locked up tomorrow morning.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_377">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_481">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_378">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_482">Potentially, I could be told calves could be sent to a unit, but no unit is available.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_379">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_483">No, there is not. This is something we understand is causing considerable hardship and welfare implications for man and animals. Some of our team are currently discussing this issue. While the calves may be lower risk, they are not a zero risk.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_380">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_484">Are they the same kind of risk as the doubtfuls?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_381">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_485">It depends on the outbreak. We have had some outbreaks in the recent past where we have had big numbers of calves. When we come across an outbreak, we cannot determine what way it is going to go. We need to adopt a precautionary principle there. They are not a zero risk at all. I do, however, fully accept that they create considerable difficulties for dairy farmers at a time in the year when labour is short and accommodation is lacking. We are considering a way of addressing this issue in such a manner as to mitigate the risk. On the badger management, as Mr. O'Mahony said already, the levels of culling have been relatively consistent over the past 20 years.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_382">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_486">Are we short of personnel?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_383">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_487">We need to refocus on how we break down the transmission pathway or block the transmission pathway between cattle and badgers. It is unrealistic to think that vaccination is going to deliver that outcome on its own. We captured around 9,000 badgers last year for vaccination. That figure has doubled since 2019. We conducted some modelling research and it suggests that vaccination on its own and our current controls are insufficient to eradicate TB. This also suggests we need to break the link. We need to prevent the opportunities for badger-to-cattle interactions. This involves fencing off badger setts, raising water troughs and fencing off yards. Beet and maize in yards are two foodstuffs badgers are very fond of. They will need to be fenced off so the badgers cannot access those resources. The Department oversees the vaccinations but there is also an onus on farmers to break this transmission link themselves.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_384">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_488">Turning to the high-risk herd proposal, will Dr. Barrett comment on its financial implications?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_385">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_489">To be clear on this, we are talking about high-risk herds plus high-risk animals within high-risk herds. Without breaking confidences, this revolves around animals that are cohorts of reactors. These are the high-risk animals. In effect, they are cows. If the cows are the high-risk animals, the calves would not be considered as high risk. We could see a scenario where there are controls on the movement of cows out of herds but not controls on the movement of calves.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_386">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_490">Before I stop, I compliment the Department's staff. I said this previously. It has great men down there, and women too, actually. Those staff do a fantastic job in trying circumstances. I just wanted to put that point on the record. I call Deputy Violet-Anne Wynne.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_11">
          <i>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice took the Chair.</i>
        </summary>
        <speech by="#VioletAnneWynne" eId="spk_387">
          <from>Deputy Violet-Anne Wynne<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_491">I am thankful for the opportunity to contribute. I have a few questions. Reference was made to the limitations of the test. I would like the witnesses to provide some background to that for my benefit. I represent County Clare and I wonder if the witnesses have any indication of the level of infection in the county. That would be great. I engaged with a few farmers in County Clare and they told me about a few of their concerns. Even reading the opening statement, it is quite bleak in respect of the increases reported as well as the funding gap that is now going to be present from the EU.</p>
          <p eId="para_492"> With the levels of increases we have seen and the possibility of more projected increases, the question arises of animal welfare. If we are going to continue to see increases, when it comes to the removal of reactors, first of all, from a farmyard, how can we ensure regulations are going to be adhered to there? My other question concerns contamination. Mention was made of the risk posed by badgers and deer. This may be a stupid question, but should we have any other contamination concerns in this regard? I refer especially to removal methods. Is there any risk of contamination to members of the public, for example? I would like some clarity on this issue. My last question concerns what would happen if something goes wrong. Why would there ever be a situation where a batch of reactors may be left in a dairy complex? It is something that can occur, so why would it occur?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_388">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_493">I will start by discussing the limitations. At best, the skin test has a sensitivity of 80%. We use the test because it has a specificity of over 99%. The test has very few false positives and that is important in a national screening programme. We increase the sensitivity of our programme by using the blood test where we know there is cattle-to-cattle transmission, which raises sensitivity to between 90% and 95%. The inherent problem relates to the skin test and that imperfection.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_12">
          <i>Senator Tim Lombard resumed the Chair.</i>
        </summary>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_389">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_494">On contamination and risk to the public, the big thing that protects the public is the pasteurisation of milk. That is one of the main reasons tuberculosis in people is not the issue that it was prior to pasteurisation. By the same token, we recommend that people, and farmers in particular, do not consume their own milk, but instead use pasteurised milk to avoid that risk. There may be some unpasteurised products and we have additional controls and testing on herds that supply milk for those products. Abattoir workers are at greater risk but they are given PPE to wear when reactor animals are being slaughtered.</p>
          <p eId="para_495"> On the question about animals being left, generally speaking, animals are removed from farms within two days of valuations being accepted. There may be the odd exceptional case but, generally speaking, our average removal time is less than two days.</p>
          <p eId="para_496"> The current herd incidence in County Clare is approximately 4%. Last year it was approximately 3.5% and the year before that it was around 2.5%.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_390">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_497">So the incidence rate has increased in County Clare.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_391">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_498">I wish to mention a few more scenarios to our guests. I have seen the following happen in the west. Let us say a contract rearer takes in calves that will be kept as weanlings for the first year and later returned if they are dairy stock. The contract rearer is caught in the middle of an awful situation. How can that be resolved? Let us say I take in calves, rear them, bring them on and next they are impregnated using AI or a bull. Contract rearers are caught between the devil and the deep blue sea. A person could have cattle but not have facilities to cubicle train them or calf them down. How does that work out?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_392">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_499">We try to adopt a pragmatic approach in those scenarios because there is no point in having heifers calf down where there is no facilities to calve or milk them. In that scenario we would restrict both herds, which would have to get two clear tests to become de-restricted. We want to avoid animal welfare situations like that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_393">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_500">I am trying to fathom the following. If the animals are tested for TB coming in and the farmer's animals had tested clear down through the years, what would be the cause of TB the following year? There are people who never had TB on their lands but, all of a sudden, even if animals were tested coming in as sucklers, next thing there is a TB outbreak. Perhaps I picked up wrong what Dr. Barrett said in response to the Leas-Chathaoirleach. Did Dr. Barrett mention a fly or something like that going across?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_394">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_501">No. This is a flying herd.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_395">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_502">Please tell me what that is.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_396">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_503">A flying herd is one that is assembled to milk cows. Essentially, it could be a herd of animals were sold as culled cows and milked down. Those are higher-risk animals. That is the worst case scenario. Some people may be forced to purchase animals to keep their numbers up, especially if they lose reactors. We have seen several scenarios where those animals have come from high-risk herds.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_397">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_504">Unfortunately, some farmers have had a test but then more of their animals went down with TB so they had to get rid of the whole herd. Why must farmers in that situation wait four months before they-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_398">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_505">That comes back to the point I made earlier on the persistence of this bacteria. We reckon it can persist in the environment for up to six months. Therefore, we insist on a cleaning and disinfection programme. This is a braces and belt cleaning and disinfection. Places are left fallow for that length of time to reduce the chance of a new herd being infected.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_399">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_506">Does the Department reckon that a lot of the bacteria will be gone by that stage?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_400">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_507">That is the idea, between the cleaning, the disinfection and leaving the place fallow.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_401">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_508">My next question is for Mr. O'Mahony. Farmers feel like they have to go through a lot of hoops to get their money. A lot of these farmers are in a tough financial situation. How efficient is the Department's system at ensuring farmers are paid?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_402">
          <from> Mr. Conor O'Mahony<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_509">In terms of the on-farm market valuation, we can only pay that once we get all of the paperwork returned on time from farmers. The farmer accepts the valuation and may have to help the valuer formulate a market valuation and may have to provide him with paperwork such as milk records or anything else. I do not have the exact figure off the top of my head. We have well over 90% compliance in terms of paying compensation, which is in line with our commitments as per the farmers' charter. Some delays may be caused by missing paperwork or something like that. Generally speaking, we endeavour to pay farmers as quickly as possible because we are very conscious of the financial impact on farmers.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_403">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_510">The international element was discussed earlier. Let us say Wales has an issue.</p>
          <p eId="para_511">What is the wildlife implication in that part of the world?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_404">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_512">They have no wildlife control programme. There is no culling or vaccinations. Any post mortems on badgers are carried out on animals killed in road traffic accidents. They do not have a wildlife programme as such.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_405">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_513">Is TB prevalent in badgers or deer there?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_406">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_514">I could not comment on that. It is certainly prevalent in cattle.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_407">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_515">Regarding the New Zealand study and New Zealand’s potential as a place to look at in terms of how it put in place a programme that worked, can Dr. Barrett elaborate on what they did with regard to the wildlife in that part of the world? He stated there was no-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_408">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_516">Possums are considered vermin in New Zealand. As they are quite prolific breeders, getting a handle on numbers or reducing the population is challenging. The country has a multifaceted approach to controlling TB in wildlife and controlling it through a more aggressive testing regime. It has a more aggressive approach to the movement of high-risk animals from high-risk herds.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_409">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_517">Are the majority of those animals from closed herds?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_410">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_518">I could not say.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_411">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_519">If we were to look at a model is that the one that would be most closely aligned to us? Ireland is damp and humid. If there is going to be TB, Ireland is the most likely location in the world to have it. It can spread because the prevailing temperature is not cold or too hot and we have a moist climate. It ticks every box when it comes to the spread of TB.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_412">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_520">It does. That is coupled with the way we manage our cattle because of the weather.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_413">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_521">That makes it very hard.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_414">
          <from> Dr. Damien Barrett<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_522">Yes, it makes it very difficult.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_415">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_523">I have one more question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_416">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_524">We cannot stop the Deputy.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_417">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_525">If a farmer has to clear their herd and get rid of it and they then do nothing for the four or six months, is there any money there for them for those six months? They cannot live on fresh air.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_418">
          <from> Mr. Conor O'Mahony<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_526">There is-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_419">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_527">Is this just the thing for a person who is working or not working?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_420">
          <from> Mr. Conor O'Mahony<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_528">In the event of a full depopulation a farmer gets all of the on-farm market evaluation on all of the animals, plus a depopulation grant which is the equivalent of four months of income supplement.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_421">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_529">That is provided if the whole herd goes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_422">
          <from> Mr. Conor O'Mahony<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_530">Correct. In the case of partial depopulation, in terms of the cohort of the animals being partially depopulated-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_423">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_531">Okay. I thank Mr. O'Mahony for that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TimLombard" eId="spk_424">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2024-11-06T20:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_532">As there are no other contributions and this is potentially the last meeting of the committee - if the witnesses have been listening to the news, they will know a general election will be called on Friday - I wish to acknowledge the Chairman, who is not here at the moment, Jackie Cahill. He has been a fantastic Chairman of this group for the past four or more years. He was very diligent and capable and did a fantastic job and was dedicated to making sure that everybody got time to speak. He was also very fair when it came to witnesses. I wish to acknowledge Jackie. I know he is not running for re-election. His ability to chair a meeting and his commitment to the agricultural industry need to be acknowledged here this evening.</p>
          <p eId="para_533"> I thank Christy Haughton and his team, who have been great ambassadors for the Civil Service and done a fantastic job in making sure this committee has worked efficiently and capably. They deal with correspondence coming in and out, witnesses, the publication of reports and thorny issues from nitrates to TB to ash dieback. They are a very competent team. I wish to acknowledge all of the work they have done and I wish them the very best for when this committee is re-established. This is the last meeting of this committee. I thank Christy and his team and I wish every member of the committee the best of luck in their endeavours, whatever they intend to do in the next few weeks. Whenever this committee meets again, I hope it will be successful in its work.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_13"> The joint committee adjourned at 8.45 p.m. <i>sine die.</i></summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
