<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#debates">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_infrastructure_and_national_development_plan_delivery/2025-07-09/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_infrastructure_and_national_development_plan_delivery/2025-07-09/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-07-09" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#author" href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/34/joint_committee_on_infrastructure_and_national_development_plan_delivery"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_infrastructure_and_national_development_plan_delivery/2025-07-09/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_infrastructure_and_national_development_plan_delivery/2025-07-09/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-07-09" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_infrastructure_and_national_development_plan_delivery/2025-07-09/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_infrastructure_and_national_development_plan_delivery/2025-07-09/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-07-16" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#debates">
        <TLCPerson eId="CathalByrne" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Cathal-Byrne.S.2025-01-29" showAs="Cathal Byrne"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ConorSheehan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Conor-Sheehan.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Conor Sheehan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="EileenFlynn" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Eileen-Flynn.S.2020-06-29" showAs="Eileen Flynn"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JoeNeville" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Joe-Neville.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Joe Neville"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JohnClendennen" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/John-Clendennen.D.2024-11-29" showAs="John Clendennen"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="LouisOHara" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Louis-O'Hara.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Louis O'Hara"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PatriciaStephenson" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Patricia-Stephenson.S.2025-01-29" showAs="Patricia Stephenson"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PeadarToibin" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Peadar-Tóibín.D.2011-03-09" showAs="Peadar Tóibín"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ReadaCronin" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Réada-Cronin.D.2020-02-08" showAs="Réada Cronin"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="SeanFleming" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Seán-Fleming.D.1997-06-26" showAs="Seán Fleming"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="TonyMcCormack" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Tony-McCormack.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Tony McCormack"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/chair" showAs="Chair" eId="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/vice_chairman" showAs="Vice Chairman" eId="Vice_Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/author" showAs="author" eId="author"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/editor" showAs="editor" eId="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>AN COMHCHOISTE UM BONNEAGAR AGUS SEACHADADH AR AN BPLEAN FORBARTHA NÁISIÚNTA</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>Joint Committee on Infrastructure and National Development Plan Delivery</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2025-07-09">Dé Céadaoin, 09 Iúil 2025</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2025-07-09">Wednesday, 09 July 2025</docDate>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_en">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_ga">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">Tháinig an Comhchoiste le chéile ag 03:30 p.m.</summary>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">The Joint Committee met at 03:30 p.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_3">Comhaltaí a bhí i láthair / Members present:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_1">Teachtaí Dála / Deputies</p>
              </th>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_2">Seanadóirí / Senators</p>
              </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#JohnClendennen">John Clendennen</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#CathalByrne">Cathal Byrne</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#ReadaCronin">Réada Cronin</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#EileenFlynn">Eileen Flynn</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#TonyMcCormack">Tony McCormack</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#PatriciaStephenson">Patricia Stephenson.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_9">
                  <person refersTo="#JoeNeville">Joe Neville</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_10">
                  <person refersTo="#LouisOHara">Louis O'Hara</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_11">
                  <person refersTo="#ConorSheehan">Conor Sheehan</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_12">
                  <person refersTo="#PeadarToibin">Peadar Tóibín.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_4">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#SeanFleming">Teachta / Deputy Seán Fleming sa Chathaoir / in the Chair.</person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Business of Joint Committee<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T15:30:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_1">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_13">As we have a quorum of four Members, including one Deputy and one Senator, I call the meeting to order and advise Members we are in public session.</p>
          <p eId="para_14"> At the outset, I advise members of the constitutional requirement that they must be physically present within the confines of the Leinster House complex in order to participate in public meetings. This does not apply to meetings held in private.</p>
          <p eId="para_15"> Members are also reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice that they should not criticise or make charges against any person or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable or otherwise engage in speech that may be regarded as damaging to the good name of that person or entity. Therefore, if Members' statements are potentially defamatory in relation to an identifiable person or entity, they will be directed to discontinue their remarks. It is imperative that Members comply with any such direction.</p>
          <p eId="para_16"> The first item on the agenda is the minutes. Are the minutes of the last meeting, which have been circulated, agreed to? Agreed. There are three items of correspondence. The first is an invitation for members of the committee to visit the Seven Mills housing development in Clonburris, Dublin 22 which came in, as the committee will see, from those involved with the housing development. Are Members interested? It will not happen this side of the summer but we will keep the correspondence on hand. Somewhere along the line it might be in our interest to visit a housing development in an area that is reasonably accessible. We may or may not choose to do so in the autumn. We acknowledge the correspondence and hold it on file for future consideration. Is that agreed? Agreed.</p>
          <p eId="para_17"> The next item of correspondence is from a private citizen suggesting that the committee meet with the Gluas group to discuss the proposal for light rail in Galway city. The NTA recently published a study relating to the proposal and reported on the potential economic and social benefits of the project. There is a request for another meeting. I propose that we note the correspondence and thank them for it. We will keep the matter under consideration. </p>
          <p eId="para_18"> The next item is from An Coimisiún Pleanála relating to a presentation to the housing spokespersons as part of its stakeholder engagement. This correspondence was requested by our members at the last meeting with An Coimisiún Pleanála. It is a presentation from An Coimisiún Pleanála which was given to the housing spokespersons of all the parties as part of its increased stakeholder engagement. We asked for a copy of that and it has been received. We note it and will publish it. It is a very good document if people want to go through it.</p>
          <p eId="para_19"> The next item is the committee report. We have been working on preparing a report for the committee. I remind Members that a draft report will be circulated tomorrow morning for their comments and input. Members are asked to send any amendments to the secretariat by email by next Monday at 3 p.m. The report reflects on our meetings with the Department of Public Expenditure, Infrastructure, Public Service Reform and Digitalisation, Uisce Éireann, the Department of Transport, Transport Infrastructure Ireland, the National Transport Authority and IBEC. In order to agree a final report, we are required to meet outside of our usual slot. We cannot publish a report without us agreeing to it. I propose that we meet in private session next Tuesday at 11 a.m. It is the only time available in committee room 1. Members will be able to join remotely if they wish. The link will issue as usual. Because it is a private meeting, people do not have to physically be here but we want to ensure we have a quorum to sign off on the report. If Members have amendments, they might send them in before Monday afternoon so we can incorporate them or if there is an issue with them, we can discuss them with the report.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalByrne" eId="spk_2">
          <from>Senator Cathal Byrne<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_20">It is at 11 a.m. on Tuesday. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_3">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_21">The meeting is on Tuesday at 11 a.m. The deadline for observations is 3 p.m. on Monday. We will have the private meeting outside of our usual slot on Tuesday at 11 a.m. and the launch is scheduled for 1 p.m. in the audiovisual room next Wednesday, 16 July. Representatives of the bodies included in the report will be invited to attend alongside the press corps. The launch will be recorded on Oireachtas TV. We will not have a regular meeting next week at 3 p.m. The launch will be our event next week. We will be the first committee to issue a report in this new Dáil so it is good we are in a position to do so.</p>
          <p eId="para_22"> As this will effectively be our last public meeting before the recess, we will want to line up some people for the autumn schedule. I suggest we try to get the Minister, Deputy Chambers, in for the first meeting, if possible. The review of the national development plan will be published at the end of this month so it will not happen in this Dáil term. I suggest we should meet the Minister at our first meeting after the summer, if at all possible, before he is totally tied up with the budget.</p>
          <p eId="para_23"> The other people I suggest we meet - if anyone has other names to add, please do - are on the list we discussed weeks ago. They include the Commission for Regulation of Utilities, the Environmental Protection Agency, EirGrid and Bord Gáis. We have to check with EirGrid if it is commercial or semi-State. I am not sure of its exact status.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeadarToibin" eId="spk_4">
          <from>Deputy Peadar Tóibín<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_24">Yes, they are. They own the grid.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_5">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_25">We will check their status. The OPW has many contracts for Garda stations and millions of other things it does directly.</p>
          <p eId="para_26"> These are all the public bodies. I then suggest - we will work on this after those bodies - we bring in some of the engineering bodies in the country, such as the Engineers Ireland association and maybe some architects. They are involved in the design of all the projects. I would then invite the County and City Management Association, because of much is done through local authorities. Finally, later on in the next session, I wish to have two meetings with the main contractors who do the work on behalf of the State. I ask the secretariat, through the Oireachtas research unit, to find out who are the main contractors that may have recently completed a big project or are in the middle of one and have experience with big infrastructural projects. This is to get their perspective on how long the process takes and what the issues are. It is all well and good meeting every public body in the country but the men and women who do the work are crucial to the whole process. I suggest, after we have gathered some information, we bring them in.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatriciaStephenson" eId="spk_6">
          <from>Senator Patricia Stephenson<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_27">Could it be BAM?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_7">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_28">It will depend on its turnover. It will not deal with one project - we are not going to cross over PAC specifically - but it could be BAM or anyone.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatriciaStephenson" eId="spk_8">
          <from>Senator Patricia Stephenson<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_29">It is doing a bit in Cork on the pipeline as well which could be good.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_9">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_30">I suspect it will be at the top of the list. We will get the list of the top five or six. I suspect it will be there and if it is, well and good but if it is not, there will be other companies doing work for Iarnród Éireann or Uisce Éireann or our roadway projects and different projects around the country. It is important to hear from the people doing the work and getting that specification. They are the people at the end of the line who have to deliver the project. If the committee were to do this work without seeing and talking to the people who actually deliver these projects, it would be a major gap in our work. It is not a question of talking to every public servant in the country. That is important but we will want to move on after that. We do not have those names so we will ask the secretariat with the Oireachtas research facility to try to obtain some information. This meeting will take place later in the next session. We will get the other bodies in first so we will have time and will agree the names of the contractors ourselves. We will see if they are willing to come in at that stage. That will be when we get this in the next term.</p>
          <p eId="para_31"> That is as much as we have on that. Are there any other suggestions to add to the mix? This will take up most of the next term.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeadarToibin" eId="spk_10">
          <from>Deputy Peadar Tóibín<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_32">Construction Federation Ireland, as I mentioned, would be one.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_11">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_33">Yes, we will put it in there because we need some of the people who do the actual work. This is what we have to get to in the second half after we have spoken to all the public bodies. If anyone has any extra name, they should let the secretariat know. Members will get the feel of what we are trying to do.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeadarToibin" eId="spk_12">
          <from>Deputy Peadar Tóibín<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T15:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_34">We had Uisce Éireann in but electricity is one of the connection issues regarding infrastructural projects and housing especially. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_13">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_35">Yes, with the ESB.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeadarToibin" eId="spk_14">
          <from>Deputy Peadar Tóibín<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_36">We mentioned EirGrid.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeNeville" eId="spk_15">
          <from>Deputy Joe Neville<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_37">That would cover that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeadarToibin" eId="spk_16">
          <from>Deputy Peadar Tóibín<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_38">EirGrid looks after the grid itself, but for connections I imagine Electric Ireland is the right organisation. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_17">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_39">We can check that. We can invite the two to the one meeting if it is the same topic. Previously, we had both An Coimisiún Pleanála and the regulator. We can handle that. We know the space we are in for the autumn and we will invite in those types of groups.</p>
          <p eId="para_40"> That covers most of the issues between now and then. As I said, the draft report will go out tomorrow and amendments will be submitted by 3 p.m. on Monday. We have a meeting at 11 a.m. on Tuesday to sign off on the report. The committee has to do that. We will then launch at 1 p.m. on Wednesday in the audiovisual room. That will be the committee’s activity next Wednesday, rather than a meeting. Effectively, this will be our last meeting, and we will be reporting on the first four or five meetings we had. There will not be a final conclusion because we are only starting, but there will be key observations and points we have noted to date. We will try to incorporate as much as possible what has been said at the various meetings to date.</p>
          <p eId="para_41"> We will suspend while the guests arrive.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_5">
          <i> Sitting suspended at 3.51 p.m. and resumed at 3.54 p.m.</i>
        </summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>Judicial Review and Appeals Process: Engagement with Courts Service<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T15:50:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_18">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_42">The purpose of the meeting today is to discuss the role of the Courts Service and an overview of the steps in the judicial review process and appeals process, to include information on trends in the number of applications received and the timeline for processing. We are of course talking about planning and construction matters, rather than every type of case that the courts deal with. If anybody has any query about any other case not connected with this, they can take it up outside.</p>
          <p eId="para_43"> I am pleased to welcome representatives of the Court Service Ms Angela Denning, CEO, Ms Kim Duffy, principal registrar of the High Court, and Ms Lisa Scott, principal officer at the office of the chief executive. For people watching, this is a meeting on the operations of the Courts Service and we are not examining any cases that have gone before judges. In case the public thinks we have judges here who will comment on previous cases, that is not the case. We will look at the management, the caseload, the workload and its prioritisation, and the process. It will not involve anything to do with the details of any particular case. I say that in case people were wondering about the role of the people here today.</p>
          <p eId="para_44"> Witnesses are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice that they should not criticise nor make charges against any person or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or identifiable, or otherwise engage in speech that might be regarded as damaging to the good name of the person or entity. Therefore, if their statements are potentially defamatory in relation to an identifiable person or entity, they will be directed to discontinue their remarks. It is imperative that they comply with any such direction.</p>
          <p eId="para_45"> I remind members they will be afford a six-minute speaking slot for questions and answers, with a second opportunity to contribute at the end of the meeting or the first round of speakers, if they so wish.</p>
          <p eId="para_46"> I now invite Ms Denning to make her opening statement.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_19">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T15:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_47">I thank the Cathaoirleach and the members of the committee for the invitation to appear today. I am accompanied by Kim Duffy, principal registrar of the High Court, and Lisa Scott, principal officer in my own office. I look forward to discussing the role and remit of the Courts Service and the steps in the judicial review process.</p>
          <p eId="para_48"> The Courts Service has been responsible for the management and administration of the courts since 1999. As members are aware, the administration of justice is a matter for the Judiciary and, in accordance with the constitutional independence of the Judiciary and the provisions of the Courts Service Act, is outside the scope of the functions of the Courts Service. Separately, the Judicial Council is an independent body that was established in December 2019 and oversees the education and training of the Judiciary. Therefore, I am precluded from commenting on any matters relating to the exercise by a judge of his or her judicial functions or matters relating to the training of judges. This includes discussion of individual court cases.</p>
          <p eId="para_49"> The Courts Service is an independent State body established by the Courts Service Act in 1998 to support the third branch of government, namely, the courts and the Judiciary. We have 1,326 staff today in 47 offices nationwide, supporting 193 judges. We have 100 active court venues nationwide. Our primary functions are to manage the courts, provide support services to the judges, provide information on the courts system and provide court buildings and facilities for court users. The executive is accountable to a board chaired by Ms Justice Dunne, a nominee of the Chief Justice, and comprising 17 others. The board determines policy and oversees its implementation by the executive.</p>
          <p eId="para_50"> The committee has asked me to provide an overview of the steps in the judicial review process. Judicial review is a very important component of our legal system. It is a process whereby the High Court supervises lower courts, tribunals and public bodies to ensure their decisions are lawful and fair. It is not an appeal. The court focuses on the legality and fairness of the decision-making process, not the merits or substance of the decision itself. There are, broadly speaking, two types of judicial review, conventional and statutory. Procedures for conventional judicial review are governed by Order 84 of the rules of the superior courts. They are a bit like the Houses’ Standing Orders. Planning is one type of statutory judicial review, which the Oireachtas has made special provision for in legislation. To apply for judicial review, an applicant must show they are affected in some way by the decision they are challenging. Applicants must also show their case has grounds to be brought.</p>
          <p eId="para_51"> The High Court can make a range of different orders. The court can quash a decision, compel the making of a decision or stop a decision being made. Other reliefs are to make a declaration or issue an injunction. Since the middle of June, SI 246 of 2025 has provided us with new rules of the superior courts, Order 103, in relation to the planning and environmental list. This dedicated list was established in December 2023 in response to the increasing complexity and volume of planning and environmental litigation. This initiative, introduced as part of the Housing for All strategy, aims to streamline the handling of planning and environmental cases before the High Court and reduce delays in the resolution of disputes with cases heard by specialist judges. The new list now encompasses proceedings related to EU environmental legislation and areas of national legislation, which include planning, transport, water, climate, natural heritage, built heritage, waste, mineral exploration, the marine, agriculture and pollution. Rule 5 of Order 103 sets out the purpose and objective as being to facilitate specialised, just and expeditious processing of litigation in the planning and environmental field and the promotion of specific strategies to give effect to the right to a hearing within a reasonable time, and the heightened obligation in that regard, in particular proceedings such as the EU law obligation of expedition in relation to renewable energy projects. </p>
          <p eId="para_52"> The year 2024 saw the first full year of operation of the list. Three judges are assigned full time with assistance from two others. This allows the assigned judges time out of court to write their decisions, speeding up the delivery of decisions to litigants. The court aims to deliver every judgment within two months of the hearing. There were 143 active cases in this list when it commenced and 241 new cases came in during 2024. By year end 2024, there were 252 active cases. There are 107 new cases so far in 2025, with 268 live cases as of today. This is a 28.8% increase in cases year on year. The list today includes cases relating to housing, wind farm development, emissions licences, agricultural infrastructure, communications masts, quarries and bus corridors, reflecting the broad remit of the court and the increase in activity in An Coimisiún Pleanála. A dedicated user group of the list held its first meeting in December 2024. The purpose of the user group is to serve as a forum for dialogue between the court and stakeholders on practice and procedural issues relevant to the efficient functioning of the list. The membership includes representatives from legal practitioners and public bodies regularly participating in the list.</p>
          <p eId="para_53"> A separate statutory procedure applies to applications for judicial review of decisions made by the planning authorities or An Coimisiún Pleanála. Sections 50 and 50A of the Planning and Development Act 2000, as amended, set out this procedure. The time limit for instituting a judicial review in respect of a decision under the Planning and Development Act is eight weeks from the date of the decision or the doing of an act by a planning authority or An Coimisiún Pleanála.</p>
          <p eId="para_54"> Since the idea of a planning and environment list was first mooted, the court and Courts Service have worked together to take steps to assist parties and the public with their work. On the practical side, there is: the use of a core book of pleadings; documents are shared electronically; authorities are provided by way of a list; a default directions schedule has been provided by the court; and cases are automatically listed in the list to fix dates following completion of pleadings. More recently, the court has designated the applicant as the default document management party, introduced provisions to manage claims for costs protection in an orderly way, and provided for a standard procedure for hearings of two to three days or an expedited procedure of three and a half hours. For the public, a facility was established to allow members of the public and interested parties view proceedings remotely. A redesigned webpage on <i>courts.ie</i> provides information on the court, including a frequently asked questions page to assist users.</p>
          <p eId="para_55"> The committee may be interested in the throughput of the court. As an example, on Monday, 30 June, hearing dates were allocated to all but 14 of 54 cases seeking dates. Of the cases seeking dates, 78% were seeking an order in respect of a decision of An Coimisiún Pleanála, reflecting its increased output in recent times. The other cases were against the EPA, the Minister for housing, the Minister for the environment, the Commissioner for Environmental Information, two county councils and some private entities, such as quarries. Forty-three sets of proceedings are now scheduled to be heard during the period from 15 September to 19 December 2025.</p>
          <p eId="para_56"> Importantly, the new court rules provide an expedited procedure, which is a fast track with accelerated timelines that applies automatically to strategic infrastructure cases; proceedings alleged to be strategic lawsuits against public participation; challenges to projects within the renewable energy directive; and cases on access to information on the environment. Proceedings issued in January and February this year were heard in June and, at time of writing, await judgment using this procedure.</p>
          <p eId="para_57"> The Courts Service remains dedicated to supporting the administration of justice in planning and environmental matters. We look forward to continued collaboration with stakeholders to ensure that our court system meets the evolving needs of society and supports sustainable development. I am happy to take any questions members have.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_20">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_58">Thank you for that very helpful presentation, specifically regarding the issues this committee is dealing with, and you were very focused on that. I have a few quick questions before we hand it over to other members. Bearing in mind people in the legal system understand what goes on, a judicial review goes to the High Court, where it can be dealt with or otherwise, but if there is then an appeal it also goes to the High Court, will you explain the difference between them? One you are looking at whether it was dealt with appropriately, while the other you are probably looks at the merits of the case. Explain that. They are both in the High Court. The judicial review and then the-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_21">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_59">It depends on the legislation. For example, some appeals in some environmental and planning matters go to the Circuit Court. Some appeals will go to the High Court, but judicial review is only dealt with in the High Court. Again, the difference is that an appeal is a complete rehearing and look at the facts. You start afresh, but with judicial review the judge is only looking at the process to make sure that the process set out in legislation or in statute is complied with. For example, in planning matters, if An Bord Pleanála is supposed to take certain matters into account when making its decision, judicial review is to ensure that it took those matters into account and does not look behind the decision itself.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_22">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_60">How many cases that went for judicial review are then appealed?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_23">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_61">Are then appealed on to the Court of Appeal?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_24">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_62">You mentioned the Court of Appeal. I am being the devil's advocate here. We are talking about the High Court but now you are talking about the Court of Appeal. I am talking about cases dealt with by the High Court, in substance, before they go to the Court of Appeal.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_25">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_63">In substance-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_26">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_64">I am saying this because most people get lost when they hear Court of Appeal, judicial review or High Court. I want to help ordinary people watching this. I am sorry if people think it is a bit basic-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_27">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_65">No, you are okay.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_28">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_66">-----but ordinary people need to know precisely-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeNeville" eId="spk_29">
          <from>Deputy Joe Neville<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_67">There is no such thing as a silly question. There genuinely is not.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_30">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_68">The judicial review total is divided up because we have a list for immigration matters and then the planning and environment list. In total, it looks like we-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_31">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_69">We are only interested in the planning side, not the immigration or other-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_32">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_70">Of the cases on the planning list, we got 241 cases in last year.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_33">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_71">For judicial review.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_34">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_72">They included judicial reviews and other types of cases. For example, some of the environmental cases, if there was an application under some of the wastewater matters, were done by way of notice of motion and affidavit. You do not do a judicial review of those if you are not happy with the decision.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_35">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_73">You have lost the public there.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_36">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_74">You can understand already how it is such a technical list. Once the High Court makes its decision, if it is a planning judicial review case, that can only be appealed to the Court of Appeal if the High Court judge certifies there is an important point of law. There is no automatic appeal up. You can only go to the Supreme Court if it looks at your application and decides that a constitutional point of law is involved. We had very few appeals on from planning cases because of that provision in the Planning and Development Act.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_37">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_75">You said, "To apply for judicial review, an applicant must show they are affected in some way by the decision they are challenging." Does that mean a person from Cork cannot appeal against a wind turbine application in Meath?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_38">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_76">Generally, the way the court looks at that-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_39">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_77">That is the way I read that statement.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_40">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_78">-----is whether the applicant participated in the planning process earlier.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_41">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_79">If you had an objection or-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_42">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_80">If you had objected earlier, for example, or if your house was next door. Again, in certain types of cases, such as environmental cases, you do not have to show that you have any connection at all. As a matter of European law, you are entitled to bring a judicial review in certain types of environmental cases.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_43">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_81">In other words, "To apply for judicial review, an applicant must show they were affected in some way by the decision they are challenging", or it is one of those limited number of environmental cases.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_44">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_82">It is one of those limited number of cases where you do not have to show it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_45">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_83">Okay. I am with you so far. Then you said there is a 28% increase in planning cases this year. What do you attribute that to?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_46">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_84">An Coimisiún Pleanála was here last week and it told about how it got rid of its backlog. When it gets rid of a backlog, that automatically generates a bit of extra work on our side. There has been a general increase across the board in certain types of cases. We have a number of cases at the moment relating to bus corridors in Dublin. We have an increase in cases this year relating to quarries and communications masts. That is where the increases this year have come from. It is very varied. The courts always reflect what is going on out in the wider world. The work that comes in depends on what is happening outside.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_47">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_85">Does the issue of common good as it relates to strategic infrastructure come into play? I am not asking you to give a view on-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_48">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_86">That is a legal question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_49">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_87">That is why I am asking it. Does the Courts Service have a definition of the common good?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_50">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_88">We would know what the common good is. I am an Accounting Officer so, for example, when I am looking for value for money for the taxpayer, I understand what the common good is, but I am not hearing or deciding cases.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_51">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_89">At this stage, Deputies and Senators-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EileenFlynn" eId="spk_52">
          <from>Senator Eileen Flynn<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_90">I am interested in knowing the definition of the common good you have in you mind. It is the same question, Chair. It is just that it would be a shame to let it go without talking about what the common good is.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_53">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_91">Okay. I will help you on this. These are administrators who run the Courts Service. There is no judge here. It is a matter for a judge to decide what the common good is in an individual case. The witnesses cannot comment about an individual case. We are here to find out how many cases there are, what the delays are, what the process is, and how long it takes. We are looking at the delivery of national infrastructure and the Courts Service and judicial reviews are part of it. How a judge makes up his mind is not for him or her to explain to the Oireachtas. They are independent of the Oireachtas. The issue of the common good is something that we, as a committee, can come back to in our report. We cannot comment on the common good in a legal case. That is a matter for a judge. We have to respect their independence whether we like it or not. I am sure we will deal with the issue of the common good in our work as a committee going forward.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeadarToibin" eId="spk_54">
          <from>Deputy Peadar Tóibín<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_92">Gabhaim buíochas leis na finnéithe as a gcur i láthair inniu agus cuirim fáilte rompu. The purpose of our committee is to try to unpick the delays and costs that are affecting so many infrastructural and housing projects. It seems to be the case that, even before construction ever starts for anything, the journey is so long. There are so many different hoops that have to be jumped through from scoping to planning to tendering. Judicial reviews often become a <i>bête noire</i> in here. People often use it to say it is not their fault, the judicial reviews are going haywire and they cannot do anything about it, etc. I am just trying to find out how long it takes judicial reviews to happen, why there has been such an increase in judicial reviews, and what kind of staffing is in place to make sure that these judicial reviews progress in a timely fashion? This is the space we are in. I think there was a 67% increase in judicial reviews in one year. Ms Denning referred to An Coimisiún Pleanála's backlog. When we questioned its representatives about it, we asked if they were getting the necessary staff to deal with the backlog. Since that backlog has now come to the Courts Service, where is its staffing at in terms of delivering on that backlog?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_55">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_93">There are two elements to the work that we have. One is the judicial side of it, so you have to have enough judges to hear the cases and then I have to have enough staff to support those judges.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeadarToibin" eId="spk_56">
          <from>Deputy Peadar Tóibín<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_94">Has there been any increase?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_57">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_95">The number of judges has increased on the list. When the list started off, it was a subset of the commercial list. A judge was added in prior to the establishment of the planning and environment court. Just before the list was established, a third judge was added. We had our annual report launch on Monday and I understand that, after that, more judges will be added into the system this year. I expect that, in the event that more judges are added to the High Court, more judges will be appointed to this list.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeadarToibin" eId="spk_58">
          <from>Deputy Peadar Tóibín<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_96">Ms Denning said that 252 cases are currently in the system for this year. There are three full-time judges and two part-time. Let us say there are four judges in this scenario. That means each judge has 63 cases. If it takes two months for a judge to give a judgement on each of those cases, then we are talking about 126 months for those cases that are in place, which is ten years for this year's cases. I may be wrong and there could be judgements being made concurrently. A judge may have five or six cases going on, etc. How long does it take on average from when an application comes in for judicial review to start to when a person receives a judgement and the tangled knot is cut and the process can start again?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_59">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_97">That is a difficult question to answer because every case is different. The reality is we have some cases that have been on the list for four or five years. They would be the worst case scenario. They may be cases where they were waiting on decisions from Europe. They may be cases where they were waiting for certainty as to costs. The Heather Hill decision, for example, meant-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_60">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_98">Explain the Heather Hill case, please.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_61">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_99">This was a case about protective costs orders. It brought certainty to the eligibility for protective costs orders. What we have seen on the list since is that we are having fewer costs hearings in the middle of cases, which means that the time to move cases through the list has sped up. The judge in charge of the list has put a number of regimes in place to try to speed up that hearing time. For example, two strategic infrastructure cases where An Coimisiún Pleanála made the decision just before Christmas have now been dealt with.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_62">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_100">Could you explain protective costs orders to the public?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_63">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_101">Under the Aarhus Convention, there is a protective costs order in relation to environmental matters. Now that the Supreme Court has found under the Heather Hill decision, anyone bringing proceedings relating to environmental matters is entitled to not have to pay costs that are prohibitively expensive. In some cases, this means the court will make an assessment of your ability to pay. In most cases what we are finding now is that, if it is an environmental case and the applicant is of good standing, the respondent is tending to just consent to the making of a protective costs order at the outset of the proceedings.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_64">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_102">Does that mean they pay the costs?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_65">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_103">Again, depending on what happens, there are pages in Order 103 of the rules setting out now, depending on the circumstances and what happens both for interim applications and the full hearing of the case, who pays what where there is a protective costs order in place. While that may seem very complicated, it has actually brought clarity to the cases. It means we have fewer of those hearings before a case starts or just at the start of a case to try to determine what is going to happen with costs. Generally, the parties bear their own so that the person who has the protective costs order, if they lose the case, the winning side cannot seek a large costs award against them. It also means that if they lose the case, a respondent bears their own costs in most cases, unless there has been, and the rules do-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_66">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_104">Has the applicant to pay their own costs?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_67">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_105">They may have to pay a small amount or an amount that-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_68">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_106">Who pays the balance?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_69">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_107">Usually people pay their own.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_70">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_108">But you just said they might have to pay a small proportion.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_71">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_109">Generally-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_72">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_110">Can a person of straw, to use the old phrase, take an environmental case?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_73">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_111">They can and the new-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_74">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_112">Is this encouraging more cases?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_75">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_113">The reality is, if you do not have grounds to bring a case, you will not get over that first threshold.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_76">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_114">If you do have grounds, you are scot free.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_77">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_115">If you do have grounds and you have a point to bring-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_78">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_116">Who pays the barristers?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_79">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_117">There is a new regime provided for in the 2024 Act which is a form of legal aid for this. It has not commenced just yet but it will provide for that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_80">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_118">Thank you for explaining that. Sorry, Deputy Tóibín.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeadarToibin" eId="spk_81">
          <from>Deputy Peadar Tóibín<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_119">No bother. Ms Denning has given us examples of two speedy cases and slow cases of four and six years. Can we as a committee get an average? I do think that is important. It may not be today, but at a further time. We are regularly told by Ministers that the judicial review process is slowing down the delivery of construction infrastructure. We need to know what the average time is.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_82">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_120">There were 67 residential cases in the list that got dates the week before last, which I assume is what the committee is interested in. Of those, 13 were older than 2024 or 2025. Only 13 of the 67 were more than a year and a half old and they all got dates for before Christmas.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeadarToibin" eId="spk_83">
          <from>Deputy Peadar Tóibín<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_121">Is that the start time of the process?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_84">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_122">That is the start time of the case. They were in planning before that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeadarToibin" eId="spk_85">
          <from>Deputy Peadar Tóibín<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_123">Is it not the case that a person puts in an application first and then a date is given?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_86">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_124">Those cases have made their application and are looking for hearing dates.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeadarToibin" eId="spk_87">
          <from>Deputy Peadar Tóibín<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_125">I understand that, but is there a difference in time before I make an application for a judicial review and then a date is given? I want to know if we are starting from the very start of the process? Getting a date might not be the start of the process.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_88">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_126">No, it might not be, but the year of issue would give us an indication of when the case started. Of those 67 cases, 54 were issued in the past 18 months.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeadarToibin" eId="spk_89">
          <from>Deputy Peadar Tóibín<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_127">Can we get an average to the committee?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_90">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_128">I can get that in writing.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeadarToibin" eId="spk_91">
          <from>Deputy Peadar Tóibín<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_129">That is important. Finally, there has been a massive increase, but it is not just because of An Coimisiún Pleanála either. It is also in part because of the SHD process. That is now being replaced by the large-scale residential development, LRD, process, I understand. It looks like the SHD process has turbo-boosted the number of judicial reviews coming into place.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_92">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_130">In general, right across the courts, whenever there is a new process or a new piece of legislation, it will be tested. I remember when the Intoxilyzer came in for drink-driving, there were multiple cases related to it. Whenever there is new legislation or a new process, people will test it to see what the words mean and so on. That is the reality we see every day. Every time there is a change, a few cases come out of it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeadarToibin" eId="spk_93">
          <from>Deputy Peadar Tóibín<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_131">The judicial review focuses on legality or fairness in a court process. If more judicial reviews are happening, does that mean more mistakes are happening in the court process?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_94">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_132">It could be, but the population has increased, we have more going on and the scope of government has expanded. The State is doing more for the public than it used to. That then means more decisions are being made.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeadarToibin" eId="spk_95">
          <from>Deputy Peadar Tóibín<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_133">I am finished now, but maybe at a later date we could get the staffing over the past five years for us to compare and contrast.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_96">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_134">I have that and can send it in.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeadarToibin" eId="spk_97">
          <from>Deputy Peadar Tóibín<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_135">That would be great.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TonyMcCormack" eId="spk_98">
          <from>Deputy Tony McCormack<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_136">I thank Ms Denning, Ms Duffy and Ms Scott for coming in, and Ms Denning for her opening statement. We are here today in the infrastructure committee. My questions will be on the statutory judicial reviews with regard to planning, energy and transport. I listened to Deputy Tóibín and am trying to follow on from that.</p>
          <p eId="para_137"> There are probably too many judicial reviews happening. It is probably too easy for people to be able to make a judicial review. Without affecting people’s statutory rights, what can we do to reduce the number of judicial reviews? As a country, we are in a state of crisis with regard to housing, and as part of that housing, infrastructure has to be built to be able to put it in place. We need to do something in order for the processes to become quicker and faster. What can we do as a Government that will help the Courts Service? Is it getting more staff, more judges or more staff working with those judges? Is it changing the process? What is the best way of moving forward to have less of this?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_99">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_138">First, I cannot comment on policy. From a courts perspective, at the end of 2023, more judges were added into the system, and that sped up the throughput of cases right across the system, in respect of not just planning but all kinds of cases. The more judges we have, the shorter the waiting times will be. For something like judicial review, there is an inherent time built in. The parties have to exchange the papers and so on. That will always take four months at a minimum. If we had more judges and the appropriate supports for them, that would speed the process up. As to the scope and so on, that is a policy question and a matter for the Oireachtas and the policy departments to decide.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TonyMcCormack" eId="spk_100">
          <from>Deputy Tony McCormack<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_139">What percentage of judicial reviews in recent years have had, say, a positive outcome for the person or group that has brought them? I am trying to figure out whether it is the case that An Board Pleanála is getting it wrong or that people are bringing these judicial reviews in the hope they will stop something or slow it down. Is it just a way of putting a stick into the spokes of a wheel?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_101">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_140">The Deputy will probably be astonished to hear this, but the Courts Service does not really care who wins or loses. What we care about is that the case gets finished and that an order is made. We keep records of how many different types of orders are made – <i>mandamus</i>, <i>certiorari</i> and so on - but we do not keep a record of whether an applicant won or lost.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TonyMcCormack" eId="spk_102">
          <from>Deputy Tony McCormack<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_141">Is that something Ms Denning could provide us with at a later date?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_103">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_142">I do not think so. I think the people who are best placed with regard to that are the likes of An Coimisiún Pleanála, where it will be looking at its own decisions to see what proportion of them it is winning or losing, because that then determines its training for its own staff in the same way that county councils will have a record of how many they won or lost. From our perspective, we look at getting cases through the list and making sure that cases can get on daily – that we have a judge, a courtroom, a registrar and an interpreter if one is needed, that the papers are ready for the case to be heard and that the judges have what they need to make their decision. We are not concerned with the winners and losers. We are a bit like the facility staff in Croke Park. We provide the pitch and everything else but we actually do not care who wins the game. I know that sounds a bit-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#TonyMcCormack" eId="spk_104">
          <from>Deputy Tony McCormack<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_143">The Courts Service is impartial. It is making the judgment on legislation and what is there. To sum up, what Ms Denning is saying is that if we can provide more judges and staff to go along with that, we can expedite the whole process and make it easier and faster.</p>
          <p eId="para_144"> I again thank the witnesses for coming in. I appreciate it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ReadaCronin" eId="spk_105">
          <from>Deputy Réada Cronin<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_145">I thank Ms Denning for her opening statement. There is a certain kind of negative, false narration around judicial reviews that they are blocking necessary infrastructure and that. Where would I find a breakdown of the people or groups that take judicial reviews? I believe it is members of the public, developers, landowners, local authorities and public authorities. Where would I find a breakdown of that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_106">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_146">We have some figures on that. Of 278 cases that went through the list in recent times, 12 parties were self-represented and all the others had legal representation. That is the only concern we have because self-represented litigants need a bit more assistance from us on the procedural side. As to whether they were community groups or a developer objecting to the refusal of grant of permission, conditions on a grant or anything like that, we do not keep those statistics.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ReadaCronin" eId="spk_107">
          <from>Deputy Réada Cronin<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_147">My understanding is that the information the Courts Service has is high level but that only around 40% of judicial reviews are taken by members of the public as such. The majority are landowners, developers and public authorities. It would be nice to get a broad picture if we could have that information.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_108">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_148">On any given day, we have the court list on the Courts Service website, <i>www.courts.ie</i>. It can be seen from the list-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ReadaCronin" eId="spk_109">
          <from>Deputy Réada Cronin<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_149">There are names mentioned but it is not very easy to see from the names of the applicants whether it is a group or just an individual.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_110">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_150">You can generally tell. The groups tend to be called something like “Such-and-Such Neighbourhood Limited” or a community group or something like that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ReadaCronin" eId="spk_111">
          <from>Deputy Réada Cronin<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_151">You have to go into it a bit more. You have to dig a bit deeper to get it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_112">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_152">The developers would be companies and so on, or there are quarry cases, where it might be called “Such-and-Such Quarries Limited”.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ReadaCronin" eId="spk_113">
          <from>Deputy Réada Cronin<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_153">Last week, we had An Coimisiún Pleanála officials in regarding the staffing levels, and the representatives seemed to be quite satisfied with what it has. How does the Courts Service feel? Has it considered the impact on staff and resources following the implementation of the planning Act 2024? There is legislation being rushed through the Dáil tonight on that. My experience of the legal profession is that they love the grey. Black and white is easy to read. There is a worry that how the Planning and Development Act was rushed through the Dáil could result in a tsunami of litigation coming through. How is the Courts Service with staff and resources?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_114">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_154">I need enough staff to support each judge, so it is very much linked to the number of judges we have, as well as the infrastructure, such as whether we have enough courtrooms. If the cases will be heard remotely, and cases in this list can be heard remotely, we do not need a courtroom for them. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ReadaCronin" eId="spk_115">
          <from>Deputy Réada Cronin<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_155">Does Ms Denning think the Courts Service is adequately resourced?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_116">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_156">We operate on the basis of around 6.3 staff per judge, so as long as I get the 6.3 staff when a new judge comes along, we will be able to manage and get the cases on.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ReadaCronin" eId="spk_117">
          <from>Deputy Réada Cronin<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_157">Part 9 of the 2024 Act changed the rules on judicial reviews..</p>
          <p eId="para_158">It removed the requirement to apply for leave before you would make an application. The requirement for leave screened out a lot of nonsensical kinds of things. Is that a worry for the Courts Service with its resources?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_118">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_159">It is a legal question but the leave applications, where you had leave on notice, could itself create a delay in the list. A lot of time could be spent dealing with the leave application and then you have to start all over again to hear the actual case. It is fine as long as the legal threshold for bringing a case into the list is clear. Over the years we have done experiments with leave on notice and leave <i>ex parte</i> where it is not on notice; and the leave on notice tended to add a little more delay into the system. We will have to wait until it is tested.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ReadaCronin" eId="spk_119">
          <from>Deputy Réada Cronin<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_160">Ms Denning's feeling at the moment is that it might be positive.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_120">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_161">It might be a positive for the list.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ReadaCronin" eId="spk_121">
          <from>Deputy Réada Cronin<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_162">We touched on the Heather Hill case earlier. There was a quote from Supreme Court Justice Brian Murray. He warned the Government about changing litigation. It took a decade to catch up with litigation to sort things out after the previous planning Act. The changes to multiple other factors will be a multiple of that. We hear from the Government that there are lessons learned, but are we really learning lessons when every time we change the law, we open the door? Ms Denning said earlier that every time the law is changed, people like to test it. Every time we change the law, we open the door to more litigation. I hear there could be a tsunami of litigation coming down the track. Does Ms Denning feel lessons are learned? Mr. Justice Murray's quote on the Heather Hill judgment is long to read out, but he stated:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_163">In a period of a little over a decade, the provisions intended to give effect to the ‘<i>not prohibitively expensive</i>’ requirements of the Aarhus Convention (which I refer to throughout this judgment... ) have generated at least thirty-five reserved judgments of the High Court, four decisions of the Court of Appeal, three references to the Court of Justice of the European Union, one judgment of that Court (so far) and, now, this decision of this Court.</p>
          <p eId="para_164"> Considering the multiplier effect that this can have, what advice does the body have? I am not asking for Ms Denning's opinion.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_122">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_165">Since the Heather Hill decision, we have had fewer cases involving issues as to cost protection. The clarity the Supreme Court gave seems to have had a settling effect on the applications for a protective costs order. The new court rules, which came into being in the middle of June 2025, have taken account of that and have also had an eye to the new legislation so we do not think we will have to make changes to the court rules when the new legislation is enacted. The rules committee seems to have had an eye to the 2024 legislation and the commencements of certain parts of it, with a view to not having to make rules changes again after the legislation has commenced.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ReadaCronin" eId="spk_123">
          <from>Deputy Réada Cronin<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_166">That would be positive if that is the case.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LouisOHara" eId="spk_124">
          <from>Deputy Louis O'Hara<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_167">I thank the witnesses for their time. I will pick up on staffing and resourcing. The 2025 EU justice scorecard has ranked Ireland at the bottom of EU member states in terms of judges. On this list, I think it was mentioned that another judge and six supporting staff would be a help or would put the Courts Service in a position to deal with cases in a timely manner. Is that the case? What kind of difference would that make? I am sure the increase in cases is causing significant challenges. They mentioned they are expecting more judges this year. I am unfamiliar with the process of how that works, so how certain are they that additional judges will be in place? I also have an overall question about whether enough judges are being trained. I am again unfamiliar, but does the Courts Service have a role in this, and what is being done to increase the numbers?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_125">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_168">It is a Government decision to appoint extra judges. The previous Government made a decision before it finished up. We are expecting 20 new judges later this year or early next year. I understand six of those will be for the High Court. What has helped with the time it takes to hear cases in the planning and environment list is that the judges specialise and do nothing else. That has been a key factor. You do not have a judge who is hearing personal injury cases today, or other types of work, and then taking up a planning case. These judges just do planning cases, apart from the two who come in to assist from time to time to deal with short matters. You have three dedicated judges, and if that were to increase you would increase the throughput of the list and we would look forward to that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LouisOHara" eId="spk_126">
          <from>Deputy Louis O'Hara<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_169">Do they have time as it stands to properly assess the cases that come in to try to get judgments in a short timeframe? There are obviously a lot, from European directives to national legislation and so on. Is there a risk to the quality of decisions that are being made at present?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_127">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_170">That is a matter for the Judiciary. If your judgment is not of a quality, you will be overturned. The reality as of today is that there are approximately 20 outstanding judgments for the whole list. When you consider the throughput of work they have, I think that is fairly good. The judicial planning working group dealt with this in its report. The ideal is that when a judge finishes hearing a case, they would get out of court to write the judgment straight away while all of the facts are fresh in their minds, and that they would get the time to do that. It is not possible to do that all of the time at the moment because of the demand on the list. We would love to get to that. You could schedule cases. The president would have enough resources available to him. The president of the High Court allocates judges to the different lists. He would have enough resources available to let a judge out of court when they finish a complex case to write the judgment straight away while everything is fresh in their mind.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LouisOHara" eId="spk_128">
          <from>Deputy Louis O'Hara<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_171">The opening statement mentioned an expedited procedure for the strategic infrastructure cases. Will the witnesses outline how that works and how much quicker these cases are heard?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_129">
          <from> Ms Kim Duffy<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_172">The key element of the expedited procedure is that it was introduced in June 2024, and it has proven highly effective for priority cases. It involves a shorter hearing time, so it is a one-day case maximum and there are tighter timeframes for the filing of documents. The biggest advantage of those two factors is that the parties can get a hearing date sooner. The expedited procedure will apply as a default to challenges within the renewable energy directive, but it is also frequently applied for in proceedings alleged to be SLAPPs, in SID cases and in cases involving access to information on the environment. It will not apply in any case where cross-examination has been ordered. The intention is that the expedited procedure will only be applied in a minority of cases at any given time. An application for an expedited procedure can be made at any time in the process. That includes prior to the granting of leave. That is made on notice to the list registrar and the other parties, and crucially the consent of the other parties is not required. To apply, a party completes a checklist that is available on the webpage. They email that to the registrar. The matter is listed in the next convenient Monday. The expedited procedure will be afforded to any given case, including the default cases, at the discretion of the court and having regard to judicial capacity and workload at any time.</p>
          <p eId="para_173"> The majority of renewable energy cases seeking a date availed of it, which is more than 90%, as well as some other infrastructure cases. While there is no wait time to get a date, the estimated average time for major infrastructure cases from application to a day for hearing is between approximately four and six months. Bearing in mind it takes approximately four months to compile and complete the paperwork as it is, that has been ground down to the bare minimum. That process, including the paperwork, is all case managed and timetabled. Again, the procedure is available to any party applying and the court, having an available slot, will do its best.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LouisOHara" eId="spk_130">
          <from>Deputy Louis O'Hara<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_174">I thank Ms Duffy very much.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_131">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_175">The next speaker was meant to be Senator Cathal Byrne who is in the Seanad Chamber. Senator Stephenson may come in now and then we will go back to Senator Byrne when he comes back in from the Seanad.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatriciaStephenson" eId="spk_132">
          <from>Senator Patricia Stephenson<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_176">I thank the witnesses so much. I am really sorry if I end up asking them something I missed while I was out for votes.</p>
          <p eId="para_177"> I note that the Courts Service does not currently publish disaggregated data when it comes to judicial cases in terms of the sector involved, the type of applicant or the case outcome. Is there a plan to do that? There is a bit of a narrative around nimbyism and in the context of 2024, we saw an increase of developer- and landowner-driven judicial reviews. Do the witnesses have any data on that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_133">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_178">No. As I said, we do not care who brings the case or whether they win or lose. It is very much about the case load and the throughput in the list, trying to maintain waiting times as low as we possibly can. The parties to the cases would have more information, so the likes of the coimisiún would know exactly how many of its cases have been overturned, what the percentages are and so on.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatriciaStephenson" eId="spk_134">
          <from>Senator Patricia Stephenson<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_179">Okay. I feel that there is probably a public interest in understanding where the judicial reviews are driven from, again, because of the narrative we see a lot around nimbyism and trying to understand. That data would really help in terms of policymaking. I know that is not necessarily Ms Denning's space, but given that the Courts Service manages and collates the cases, the-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_135">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_180">We do not manage the cases. The judges manage the cases.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatriciaStephenson" eId="spk_136">
          <from>Senator Patricia Stephenson<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_181">I am sorry; I mean the Courts Service. The cases come to the Courts Service and, therefore, the data already exists at the Courts Service level in terms of the different criteria by which it might disaggregate data.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_137">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_182">This is part of the challenge, and that difference between us and the courts themselves. I always say our job is to get the judge onto the bench and then we leave the theatre, so to speak. After that, the judge takes over. The content of the case is not really a matter for us-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatriciaStephenson" eId="spk_138">
          <from>Senator Patricia Stephenson<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_183">Sure, okay.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_139">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_184">-----but I do think that the policy departments are definitely more interested in what is going on in courts. We are publishing more open data all the time. Our annual report data will go up as open data. That then helps people to look in the right places in order to find the answers.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatriciaStephenson" eId="spk_140">
          <from>Senator Patricia Stephenson<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_185">I will note that I do think there would be a lot of public interest in having that disaggregated data around cases, but recognising what Ms Denning said in response to that.</p>
          <p eId="para_186"> In terms of the current capacity, has Ms Denning requested or put in requests for additional supports around processing judicial reviews? Under the Part 9 changes to the 2024 Act, we may see more judicial reviews as a consequence. Has Ms Denning requested more resources in anticipation of that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_141">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_187">We are in the middle of the Estimates process at the moment in terms of making our submission and so on. We have included an application for more staff for the courts right across the board. Planning and judicial review is not the only area that is going to increase in the next year or two. We expect to see an increase in immigration cases as the Department of justice processes more. We have new family courts legislation. We have increased numbers of speed cameras, so we are going to have extra pressure on the district courts. We are seeing increases in childcare domestic violence right across the board. That is all encompassed in our Estimates submission, which has gone to our parent Department. I will say no more.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatriciaStephenson" eId="spk_142">
          <from>Senator Patricia Stephenson<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_188">Okay. When it comes to the planning and environment list, does Ms Denning have cases that have been admitted under those? Does she have that data?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_143">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_189">Cases that have been-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatriciaStephenson" eId="spk_144">
          <from>Senator Patricia Stephenson<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_190">Admitted to the planning and environment list.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_145">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_191">Into the list, yes. We had 241 cases last year, and I think it is 108 so far this year. Some 65% of those cases are against An Coimisiún Pleanála. We have 67 cases against residential developments, 11 against wind farms, nine with regard to emissions, seven with regard to agricultural infrastructure, 19 communications mast cases, 15 quarries cases and 17 transport cases at the moment. That is the rough breakdown of the list. In 2024, we had 241 cases in, with 253 disposed of. They were cases from the previous year or whatever, and 58 written judgments were delivered. So far in 2025, the judges have delivered 42 written judgments.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatriciaStephenson" eId="spk_146">
          <from>Senator Patricia Stephenson<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_192">I have a follow-up question. I think the answer is probably "No". Does Ms Denning have data on who is submitting those judicial reviews?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_147">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_193">No, but they are publicly in the legal diary for anybody to see. If someone goes in to look at the hearing dates that are fixed, he or she can see the names of the parties and it is very clear when someone looks at them who is making the applications.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatriciaStephenson" eId="spk_148">
          <from>Senator Patricia Stephenson<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_194">The collation of that data into something that is easier to access rather than going through every single individual list is a policy decision that would sit outside the scope of the Courts Service's remit.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_149">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_195">Absolutely, yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatriciaStephenson" eId="spk_150">
          <from>Senator Patricia Stephenson<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_196">Where would that policy decision sit?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_151">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_197">If they are housing cases, the Department of housing will have an interest in how many cases were related to the coimisiún, for example. The Department of communications will be interested in the communications masts. The Department of Transport will be interested in the cases about the bus corridor.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatriciaStephenson" eId="spk_152">
          <from>Senator Patricia Stephenson<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_198">When it comes the whole thing around judicial review, is anyone responsible for presenting that data in a way that is actually accessible to the public?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_153">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_199">Judicial review applies to any public body decision----- </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatriciaStephenson" eId="spk_154">
          <from>Senator Patricia Stephenson<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_200">In the context of planning, I mean.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_155">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_201">I do not think there is any one. Housing for All has kind of pulled together a lot of the Departments, and we go there as well and provide whatever data is requested from time to time. Certainly, we will always assist with that. That is the only kind of central body I know of that is looking at housing planning. It is not necessarily looking at some of the other infrastructural areas. Then, it is for individual Departments to look at those.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatriciaStephenson" eId="spk_156">
          <from>Senator Patricia Stephenson<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_202">Yes, maybe that is an issue we can discuss as a committee. I feel like there is a real gap there in terms of the public interest around judicial review and understanding what is driving that, and without that data, we cannot do that. I recognise that it is all available if one goes and looks, but that is not easily accessible. There is a level of public interest linked to that. We should have data that is more consumable, really, for individuals.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_157">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_203">One thing the judge in charge of the list has done is that we have a public observation channel now. The public can dial in and watch judicial review cases in Judge Humphreys's list to see both what is going on in the list and the cases for hearing so that for people with an interest in the area, there is transparency there and they can see what is happening.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatriciaStephenson" eId="spk_158">
          <from>Senator Patricia Stephenson<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_204">I thank Ms Denning very much.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_159">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_205">Following on briefly from that, I commented on the excellent report the Courts Service published earlier this week. I have seen the report and looked at some of it. It has a big section of about 80 pages on the year in numbers. There is phenomenal information in it for people who are interested. Is it possible next time to maybe have the information the Senator is referring to in terms of appeals and put some numbers or do a section on the issues that have been raised? Is it in the annual report and if not, could it be considered for the future? Many people have a big interest in the judicial review issue.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_160">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_206">One of the challenges we have is that we do not ask individual applicants what they are bringing their case for. We do not engage with the applicants really; we just process the paperwork. We do not ask them about their motive either. We are-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_161">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_207">Can the Courts Service categorise them without asking? Can it categorise judicial reviews? I am looking at the report and it goes down to the details where one party is suing another under family law. It has outstanding information. It mentions commercial issues and commercial courts, examinerships, childcare orders, supervision of care orders and domestic abuse. It has phenomenal information in there. The Courts Service has categorised the cases that have come to it to provide that. Is it possible to categorise what the Senator is talking about?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_162">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_208">If we take childcare as an example, while we know how many numbers of cases we had in and out, we do not look to see who the applicant was and whether it was it Tusla or the HSE, who made the application, whether it was it a grandparent, so-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatriciaStephenson" eId="spk_163">
          <from>Senator Patricia Stephenson<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_209">It exists, surely. That type of disaggregated data does exist somewhere in the submissions, surely.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_164">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_210">Yes, in the submissions. I do not want to go back to funding here, but if I was to pay staff to go through the submissions to-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_165">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_211">To identify that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_166">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_212">There are lots of data we could get if we were to go through all the papers belonging to every case, but we simply are not resourced for that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_167">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_213">Right. You get the point. I am still complimenting you on the detail you have in there.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_168">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_214">There is a research element that goes along with this, and our ambit does not cover research.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_169">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_215">There is a PhD there for somebody. I thank the Senator. The next speaker is Senator Cathal Byrne because he was out of the room, and we said we would bring both Senators in.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalByrne" eId="spk_170">
          <from>Senator Cathal Byrne<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_216">I appreciate that. I thank the Chair very much. I thank our visitors who are in with us today. I have a couple of questions around the idea that it is so easy to take judicial review proceedings. It is a personal opinion of mine that somebody who is not directly impacted by a planning decision should not be allowed to contest and challenge it either at the local authority stage or subsequently in a judicial review.</p>
          <p eId="para_217">I appreciate that the officials from the Courts Service are here to answer specific questions about how the process is managed as opposed to how the legislation is interpreted, but it is important to put that point forward.</p>
          <p eId="para_218"> Regarding this stages of an individual taking a judicial review case, am I correct that in the first instance the application is made to the High Court for leave to bring the judicial review? Does the Courts Service have any data about how many of those cases fall at that stage?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_171">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_219">I will get data. However, from my past experience as registrar dealing with these cases for a long number of years, I know that very few fall at that stage. That is down to the legal thresholds. It is a legal question as to whether people have been involved, the level of involvement and whether they can pass that threshold. I believe that is covered in parts of the 2024 Act.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalByrne" eId="spk_172">
          <from>Senator Cathal Byrne<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_220">When somebody gets past that initial stage and then gets permission to bring forward the case, what is the average time it takes from step 1 to step 2?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_173">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_221">It very much depends on the case. Where the parties go for the expedited procedure and they have legal teams who know everything about planning, that can move relatively quickly. If everybody stuck to the time limits in the rules, everything would be done in four or five months. Unfortunately, that does not always happen for various reasons. People may look for extra time to prepare their papers. There is a big difference between a case where a developer has been refused permission by the coimisiún and a case where an individual does not want their next-door neighbour building an extension that may block their light or whatever it may be. The smaller the case, the longer it is likely to take.</p>
          <p eId="para_222"> In cases that are strategically issued to try to stop developments going ahead, one party there is not interested in getting the case moving quickly. The good thing is that consent is not required to use the expedited procedure. That is something judges are very clear about. In the new rules, the judge can decide that he or she will use the expedited procedure and that will speed things up. Some of the simple tweaks to the list have actually speeded things up. For example, the applicant is responsible for uploading the papers onto a share file. All those kinds of things have brought clarity as to whose job it is to do different parts of the procedure. Because of that clarity, fewer people are coming into court asking for directions on it or back and forth between the parties in correspondence, and then they come into court looking for another adjournment because they need to sort something out.</p>
          <p eId="para_223"> Our legal system is adversarial and much of it is left to the parties to sort out between themselves. However, directions are now given fairly early in the procedure so that everybody knows where they stand and knows the workload ahead of them. The view of the court is that the judges want to spend less time dealing with procedural matters and more time hearing actual cases. Therefore, they will make orders on the papers, and try to sort out directions and things like that between the parties by correspondence rather than wasting court time dealing with it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalByrne" eId="spk_174">
          <from>Senator Cathal Byrne<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_224">This committee is interested in trying to fast-track the delivery of infrastructure, be that houses, hospitals or whatever other key State infrastructure. If there were to be changes, what changes would Ms Denning like to see that could speed up the process for the case getting from when the initial application for permission is granted to the case being substantively heard?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_175">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_225">In the process we have those new rules; they are only a month old. They codified what the judges in the list were doing anyway but they need to be given a bit of time to bed in. From our perspective, the big one is resources to hear the case and then to get to that stage where the President of the High Court could allow judges out of court immediately after they hear a case to write their judgment and give the decision. That would really speed up that end of it. If the time limit is reduced, fewer people would strategically bring cases to delay developments.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CathalByrne" eId="spk_176">
          <from>Senator Cathal Byrne<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_226">Individual cases can go on for any length of time. It is important for us to get to grips with what can be controlled, for instance, how long it takes to get to the court even though we cannot decide how long the case will be in court. I am trying to get a better understanding of that. I ask Ms Denning to come back to the committee with the information as to how many of those applications for judicial review are refused at the first stage.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_177">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_227">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_178">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_228">Will Ms Denning be able to provide information on the percentage of cases that go through the expedited procedure? If she does not have that to hand, perhaps she might send it on to us.</p>
          <p eId="para_229"> Further to what she said, I have often heard people say when they are not happy with a development, "Sure, we'll go for a judicial review and it'll take as long as it takes." They feel the other side might give up and not proceed with the development. Ms Denning was mirroring that in what she was saying. Some people are not that interested in progressing the case. They just want their case there possibly to delay or maybe even sometimes to kill off a development. Is that something the Courts Service is conscious of?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_179">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_230">We are.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_180">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_231">Does the judge ever offer the parties six months and if they are not back with their stuff, he will dismiss the case, make a ruling or whatever? Can that happen? Does that happen?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_181">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_232">The courts are very conscious of that. As it is an adversarial system, people will try to play either the delay or the cost. Those are the two levers people have in these cases. That is why it is important that we try to keep them moving along and that we have the resources to keep the cases moving.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_182">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_233">Some people might regard taking a judicial review as an abuse of process. While I am not saying it is a fact, anecdotally we hear people who are involved in these saying that. In a roundabout way we are more or less saying the same thing. The judge will spot if somebody is not really co-operating with getting the case moved by sitting there.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_183">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_234">We need to remember that judicial review does not just apply to planning matters; judicial review applies to any decision. It is an oversight provided by the Constitution to ensure that power does not go to any of our heads. The important part is that supervisory power. As long as decision makers stick within the guardrails of what they are supposed to do, judicial review will not work. The other side of it is if public bodies are under pressure to make decisions quickly, they say that mistakes are more inclined to be made, they do not have time to train staff and so on. It all feeds into the system. We need to remember that judicial review is a very important component of our democratic set-up.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_184">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_235">It is indeed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ConorSheehan" eId="spk_185">
          <from>Deputy Conor Sheehan<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_236">I thank the witnesses. I want to go back to the 2023 OECD report, which recommended a 26.2% increase in full-time judges. What percentage increase has the Courts Service received since that report was published?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_186">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_237">We have had 24 additional judges enter the system. We had eight in the District Court; eight in the Circuit Court; six in the High Court; and two in the Court of Appeal. The proposal is to appoint another 20 this year, which would bring us up to a 25% increase over the two- to three-year period.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ConorSheehan" eId="spk_187">
          <from>Deputy Conor Sheehan<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_238">The OECD report identified a need for 108 additional judges. Those increases will bring us up to about half of that number so. If we were to follow the recommendations of the OECD report, would that comprehensively deal with the backlogs in the Courts Service? Is it a question of resourcing? I will get on to the question of modernisation in a minute.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_188">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T16:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_239">Regarding additional judges, we could have one judge for every case. In an ideal world we would have judges waiting for cases to come in, as happens in some countries. That is not the system we have here.</p>
          <p eId="para_240">One of the recommendations of the judicial planning working group is that the number of judges is reviewed every number of years and that a system is put in place to do that. Traditionally, if a backlog of work grew in an area, the president of that court would write through the Attorney General and say we need additional judges. That is not an ideal situation. You are always reactive. Ideally, we would have enough judges in place to ensure the backlogs do not develop.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ConorSheehan" eId="spk_189">
          <from>Deputy Conor Sheehan<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_241">Has the passage of the Judicial Appointments Commission Act delayed the appointment of judges?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_190">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_242">I do not think so. I am not very <i>au fait</i> with it but I know interviews took place recently. A number of vacancies had to be dealt with first.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ConorSheehan" eId="spk_191">
          <from>Deputy Conor Sheehan<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_243">On inefficiencies in the court system, could Ms Denning give the committee an idea of the work the court has done on automated court management? What are the funding requirements for the digital strategy? How much funding has the service received? How much funding does the Courts Service need? What work is being done to make the current IT system fit for purpose? That is really important as well</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_192">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_244">On the first part of the question, the Courts Service has gone on a bit of a journey, to use that phrase, in terms of IT over the previous five years.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ConorSheehan" eId="spk_193">
          <from>Deputy Conor Sheehan<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_245">We all have.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_194">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_246">We have come from a very low base and we have improved dramatically. We now have 165 tech-enabled courts nationwide. We have Wi-Fi in every courthouse in the country, apart from the CCJ. That will be sorted out this summer. There were problems with the Wi-Fi there.</p>
          <p eId="para_247"> There is work ongoing on a new, single case management system where all of our cases across all jurisdictions and all case types will be dealt with in the one system with staff having one view, the judges having a different view and the ability for practitioners to lodge their cases online. The first part of that, which is the staff part, has gone live for the High Court civil work, for the probate office, and for family law in the Circuit Court. The portal part, which is the judicial view and the practitioner view, has gone live for Circuit Court family law in Dublin as a pilot in recent weeks.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ConorSheehan" eId="spk_195">
          <from>Deputy Conor Sheehan<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_248">Is there an implementation plan that Ms Denning could share with the committee-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_196">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_249">Absolutely.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ConorSheehan" eId="spk_197">
          <from>Deputy Conor Sheehan<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_250">-----or what has been implemented by the judicial planning working group and the funding requirements to implement the rest of it?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_198">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_251">The judicial planning working group implementation is overseen by the Department of Justice. There is a steering group there and they report to Government once a year on that. In terms of our modernisation programme, the executive reports to the Courts Service board. Our most recent three-year strategy was published last October. That set out our plans for the next three years for digitisation. A big part of that is to get all of our cases onto that unified case management system over the next year so people can engage with us digitally properly as opposed to just emailing in cases.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ConorSheehan" eId="spk_199">
          <from>Deputy Conor Sheehan<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_252">I have one final question. The Court Service was initially allocated €191 million in budget 2024 and €196 million in budget 2025.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_200">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_253">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ConorSheehan" eId="spk_201">
          <from>Deputy Conor Sheehan<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_254">Could Ms Denning give us an idea of what is needed in budget 2026?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_202">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_255">I cannot answer that here. We are in the middle of the Estimates process and it will have to go through the process. What I can say is that from the 2024 budget, we spent €75 million on pay. We spent €47.8 million on non-pay. IT spend was just more than €20 million. Our capital court houses were €5.7 million. Our public-private partnership, PPP, unitary payments for the Criminal Courts of Justice were €23.8 million-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ConorSheehan" eId="spk_203">
          <from>Deputy Conor Sheehan<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_256">Is funding an issue for the Courts Service?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_204">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_257">It is always an issue for us. We are an expanding population. There are expanding expectations of us. I will always take more money if it is given to me.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnClendennen" eId="spk_205">
          <from>Deputy John Clendennen<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_258">I thank the witnesses for attending. Considering the Courts Service remit is so broad and ours is so narrow, does Ms Denning get the sense there is an emergency around infrastructural development and planning for the cases that are coming forward? Does she get the sense of urgency that there is an emergency?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_206">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_259">Absolutely. The judge in charge of the list has established a user group that comprises people from county councils, somebody from An Coimisiún Pleanála, the Chief State Solicitor's Office, both small practitioners and bigger firms, members of the environmental law association and so on. I remember when I was the registrar on the list, a barrister came in and said to me we will have a lot of cases about solar farms. You get wind of that and then the discussions happen between the judges on the list, the Courts Service and the president of the court to see what can be done. With the breadth of our remit, the challenge we have is we have emergency bombs going off all over the place at times. It is a bit like whack-a-mole; you solve one problem and another one pops up. That is the reality of it. There are limited resources that have to be divided up and it is about how best to divide them to make sure there are no catastrophic problems anywhere.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnClendennen" eId="spk_207">
          <from>Deputy John Clendennen<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_260">There have been a good few references towards resources on judges, Ms Denning's own staff and so on. She referenced a match and providing the stadium. Have we too many stadiums? Have we too many courts? Have we enough? Are they being sweated as assets? Are we using them to the extent we should be?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_208">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_261">In terms of the service?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnClendennen" eId="spk_209">
          <from>Deputy John Clendennen<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_262">Are there enough days during the week for courts to sit?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_210">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_263">We have had an increase of 24 judges since the end of 2023. Our court sittings have gone up to 26,500 sittings a year. We have had a 27% increase-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_211">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_264">That is an increase to 26,500 days.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_212">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_265">Sitting days, yes. We have had an increase of 29% in the District Court, 23% in the High Court and an average of 27% increase with a 2% increase in staff.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnClendennen" eId="spk_213">
          <from>Deputy John Clendennen<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_266">Can they be related directly to planning and environment?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_214">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_267">No. For planning and environment, we now have three dedicated judges so that is progress in itself.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnClendennen" eId="spk_215">
          <from>Deputy John Clendennen<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_268">In terms of sitting days, however. Are there cancellations or are there deferrals? Do witnesses not turn up? What waste or leakage is there in the system?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_216">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_269">I have figures here on the sitting days. We have had 191 sittings so far in 2025 in the planning and environment court.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnClendennen" eId="spk_217">
          <from>Deputy John Clendennen<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_270">What was that figure for 2024?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_218">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_271">I do not have that figure for 2024. I just got the figures-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnClendennen" eId="spk_219">
          <from>Deputy John Clendennen<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_272">Just as a comparison, because there were three judges dedicated to it in 2024.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_220">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_273">There were three dedicated judges assigned in 2024. There is also help from others where there is capacity on Mondays and so on.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnClendennen" eId="spk_221">
          <from>Deputy John Clendennen<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_274">There are three dedicated judges and 190 days.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_222">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_275">This year so far.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnClendennen" eId="spk_223">
          <from>Deputy John Clendennen<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_276">That is this year. We will probably have 120 days per judge, which is probably two days a week, give or take.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_224">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_277">Nobody goes to court to get their case heard. They go to court to get the decision. The hard part of planning cases is not the hearing of the case. It is the writing of the judgment afterwards.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnClendennen" eId="spk_225">
          <from>Deputy John Clendennen<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_278">That is true but once it is in hearing, how long does it take? Is it in and out in the same day?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_226">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_279">It depends. The judge in charge of the list has instigated new procedures on that as well. He has divided cases up into different groups and categories. The expedited cases, such as the strategic infrastructure cases and so on, are to be dealt within three and a half hours - within one day.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_227">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_280">Is that the entire case?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_228">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_281">The entire case is to be dealt with in three and a half hours. Submissions are limited to 5,000 words. When Ms Duffy said the parties had to do more, it is a much tightened procedure. People really have to focus.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnClendennen" eId="spk_229">
          <from>Deputy John Clendennen<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_282">Should this become a broader practice in general, although, obviously, not in every court?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_230">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_283">It is needed for this list. Bear in mind, if this was to be done for every type of case right across the system, the parties would need much more resources. For example, if there is a dispute between neighbours where two people do not like whatever it might be, it would put the neighbours on the line for the cost of that. For these type of cases and the cases that are in that expedited procedure, it works. The judge has cases that can be dealt with on the papers so nobody comes into court at all. He just reads the papers and gives the decision. There are cases where the judge sees an issue and says he wants to hear the parties on the issues. Those issues are dealt with on a Monday afternoon and take between 60 and 90 minutes. Injunction applications are dealt with in between 60 and 90 minutes.</p>
          <p eId="para_284">The standard hearing is two to three days. It is three days maximum.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_231">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_285">Will Ms Denning send a note on all of that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_232">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_286">I will.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnClendennen" eId="spk_233">
          <from>Deputy John Clendennen<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_287">On that point, there is an enabling effect. That is an issue that has been introduced to make a positive impact and try to expedite the process. What are the outstanding disrupting or disruptive pieces that we need to address?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_234">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_288">I suppose it is humans, unfortunately. As I said, there are two parties in the case. We have an adversarial system. Some people will not play ball.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnClendennen" eId="spk_235">
          <from>Deputy John Clendennen<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_289">Have we pushed it as far as we can in the enabling piece?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_236">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_290">These new rules are less than a month old and they need to be given time to bed in to see the impact on the process of the moving of cases through the list. They codified a lot of what was there previously but the Heather Hill judgment is not that old realistically. In court time it is not that old so this is only bedding down now as well. We will have the changes that come with the commencement of the new Act but I believe this is one of the areas where the rules need to be given a bit of a chance to work.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnClendennen" eId="spk_237">
          <from>Deputy John Clendennen<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_291">Ireland is not the only country in the world experiencing housing shortages and issues with supply and construction. Has any international benchmarking been done where there would have been similar pinch points in their court services for delivery? If the Courts Service has any comparisons done in that area, the witnesses might share them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_238">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_292">I work with my colleagues at the same level in Scotland, England, Wales and Northern Ireland in relation to all court administration matters because wherever we see pinch points it is very rare that one would see something and be the first. We have an advisory group for our modernisation programme - a senior judge from England is there, and his predecessor was a judge from Australia - to get advice on where things have gone wrong in other countries so we do not replicate those mistakes and to learn from the good things that people have done in other countries.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnClendennen" eId="spk_239">
          <from>Deputy John Clendennen<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_293">Has that proven beneficial?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_240">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_294">So far.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeNeville" eId="spk_241">
          <from>Deputy Joe Neville<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_295">I will start with the obligatory thanks to the witnesses for coming in, which it seems we all have to say. I am getting used to the committees here. Obviously we have different topics coming in. Infrastructure is a strange one because we can jump all around the map. It is funny. When I was talking earlier with one of our colleagues, Senator Stephenson, we said that one of the issues we have as a committee is that one week it is Irish Water, the next week it is somebody else, and the next week it is somebody else again. This week it is the Courts Service because, in fairness, it has become topical. From listening to the other speakers, it strikes me that it is good to listen to other people before speaking because everybody can come in on different topics in different ways. Deputy Sheehan was more focused on the courts systems, and someone else could focus on planning. I want to touch on both but primarily we were invited in to discuss planning so I might start off with that as the key issue.</p>
          <p eId="para_296"> One thing I heard for many years when I was a councillor was that judicial reviews had become more common. The witnesses have provided the statistics but would it be correct to say that they have become more common? Is it correct to say that? Why am I hearing more about it?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_242">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_297">We get peaks and troughs. I was the registrar in the judicial review list for years and I remember one year we had 270 cases related to handgun licences.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeNeville" eId="spk_243">
          <from>Deputy Joe Neville<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_298">Just in relation to planning.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_244">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_299">In relation to planning these have increased slightly but I believe this is down to the throughput of An Coimisiún Pleanála. The committee will remember that the board at one stage did not have enough staff-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeNeville" eId="spk_245">
          <from>Deputy Joe Neville<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_300">This is just what comes out at the other end.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_246">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_301">We are the far end of that process. The coimisiún, I understand, has gotten rid of its backlog now, or has got through the peak of it, so we should start to see the cases against the coimisiún fall off.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeNeville" eId="spk_247">
          <from>Deputy Joe Neville<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_302">Ms Denning said earlier that she does not really care, or is agnostic, as to who is in it and who wins, but at the same time has she noticed any trends? What type of person is bringing the cases? The risk, obviously, with a judicial review is that somebody is trying to play the system and to delay the decision. It might suit them to delay the decision. That is my experience as I have seen it. It is someone almost meddling and using the system. This is what I have seen. Has Ms Denning seen that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_248">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_303">Again, I am only talking from my personal experience as a registrar.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeNeville" eId="spk_249">
          <from>Deputy Joe Neville<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_304">Yes. It is someone being obstructively against a decision.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_250">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_305">The only common factor is that somebody who is unhappy with the decision is bringing the application. The judge in charge of the list recently gave an interview where he said he had noticed an increase in developer applicants-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeNeville" eId="spk_251">
          <from>Deputy Joe Neville<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_306">That is what I am talking about, yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_252">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_307">He had seen an increase over recent times in developer applicants who were not happy, maybe with a local development plan or were not happy with a grant or a refusal of permission.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeNeville" eId="spk_253">
          <from>Deputy Joe Neville<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_308">Yes. Maybe it is a decision on EirGrid lines, for example, or something like that, which may have gone your way and yet they bring a judicial review.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_254">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_309">The variety in the list very much reflects how planning touches so many areas of life and it is not always about residential development.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeNeville" eId="spk_255">
          <from>Deputy Joe Neville<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_310">Yes. I would not want it to be used as a weapon and I wonder if it is becoming more common. Ms Denning is saying that anecdotally she is hearing it might be, but at the same time-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_256">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_311">Again, it is quite difficult because up until a couple of years ago planning cases were not divided out from the normal judicial review non-jury list. Then they were divided out into the strategic infrastructure list, as part of the commercial list, but they had to have commerciality - they had to be worth over €1 million - in order to go onto that list. So there were still some cases in the non-jury judicial review list and some cases in the commercial list, and then we would have injunction applications coming in, perhaps over the summer, and a judge would keep them. We never had a complete picture really until last year of all of the planning and environmental matters as they stood.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeNeville" eId="spk_257">
          <from>Deputy Joe Neville<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_312">What is the cost of bringing a judicial review? I know this is an open-ended question but what is the initial cost?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_258">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_313">I would not know. Again-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeNeville" eId="spk_259">
          <from>Deputy Joe Neville<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_314">Obviously there should be a negative because, for example, if I was trying to cause a problem or meddle in a decision there should be some sort of initial-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_260">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_315">Unless there is a protective costs order, the costs would be awarded against you if you lose.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeNeville" eId="spk_261">
          <from>Deputy Joe Neville<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_316">But I could start the process and would not have to follow through.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_262">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_317">Costs would still incur. If you start a case that you are not going to continue, costs would be awarded against you.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeNeville" eId="spk_263">
          <from>Deputy Joe Neville<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_318">A person might have deep pockets. This is what I am wondering. What would be the typical cost? This is why I am asking.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_264">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_319">The expedited procedures the judge has put in place deal with SLAPP orders. What this means is somebody with deep pockets would bring proceedings in order to perhaps thwart another developer. We see that too.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeNeville" eId="spk_265">
          <from>Deputy Joe Neville<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_320">That is what I am talking about. What is the typical cost in that situation?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_266">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_321">I would not know what the costs are. We do not deal with the costs. They are measured by the legal costs adjudicators.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeNeville" eId="spk_267">
          <from>Deputy Joe Neville<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_322">I am just curious because there should be-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_268">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_323">With costs, a very straightforward case could run very quickly. The papers might all be dealt with on time. There might only be one or two affidavits in it. In a complex case, the costs get higher. That is a matter between you, your solicitor and your legal team. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeNeville" eId="spk_269">
          <from>Deputy Joe Neville<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_324">That is the thing. Someone might have deep pockets and might have solicitors on the go to bring a judicial review just because they know it is upsetting someone else.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_270">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_325">That is why they are one of the types of cases that would mandatorily be in that expedited procedure, to try to speed those through the list and decide them quickly.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeNeville" eId="spk_271">
          <from>Deputy Joe Neville<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_326">Can a judicial review be pulled halfway through a process so they do not have to go through it, and it is, therefore, just meddling?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_272">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_327">They can. However, section 36(b)(2) of the new rules provide:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_328">Where a consent order involves the striking out, dismissal or withdrawal (whether unilaterally prior to service, or on consent following service) of the proceedings, the order must be dealt with in open court and shall be accompanied by a written declaration by each applicant ... that the termination of the proceedings is not for the sole or improper purpose of securing the payment of any consideration to, or the doing of any other thing for the benefit of, any person.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeNeville" eId="spk_273">
          <from>Deputy Joe Neville<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_329">Okay. That is interesting in itself. I will change tack and perhaps go back to being slightly parochial. Will Ms Denning clarify if it is 193 judges across the country?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_274">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_330">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeNeville" eId="spk_275">
          <from>Deputy Joe Neville<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_331">At 100 venues. So that is 100 courthouses.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_276">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_332">Yes, 100 courthouses.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeNeville" eId="spk_277">
          <from>Deputy Joe Neville<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_333">I am in north Kildare. A lot of people might use the courts in Dublin, but a courthouse like Naas Courthouse is in an area of growing population and growing demand, as referred to earlier. How do we go about getting extra judges to deal with backlogs of cases, and extra buildings if there is a lack of facilities in a place like Naas? I am using Naas only as an example. How can we expand Naas Courthouse and get through more cases?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_278">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_334">In Naas for example, the Courts Service purchased a site at the rear of the courthouse in 2023 in order to expand the courthouse because we were looking at demographics and so on. The population has grown. Naas deals with District Court and Circuit Court cases. It is a matter for the president of each court to assign judges for the workloads that are there. Kildare also has Athy Courthouse. There are no significant issues there.</p>
          <p eId="para_335">We are putting in a network there to get videoconferencing into Athy. I understand that is imminent and it will be in place for a Circuit Court case later this year. On the allocation of funding, the expansion of Naas is actually in the national development plan but it just has not been funded to date.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeNeville" eId="spk_279">
          <from>Deputy Joe Neville<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_336">Okay. I will get on to the relevant Minister. He is in PAC tomorrow and I might have a chat with him. We need extra funding there and extra judges. Will it be the Courts Service who will be assigning, not extra judges <i>per se</i> but-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_280">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_337">I am responsible for the accommodation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeNeville" eId="spk_281">
          <from>Deputy Joe Neville<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_338">The service lets people know that we need them as they can see there are extra services required.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_282">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_339">The presidents of the courts look for the extra judges where they have a shortage or a deficit. Administratively, my staff provide data to the court president as well-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeNeville" eId="spk_283">
          <from>Deputy Joe Neville<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_340">That is what I am saying. The Courts Service notes it and-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_284">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_341">-----and we would say there is a backlog in a particular area or a particular type of work.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeNeville" eId="spk_285">
          <from>Deputy Joe Neville<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_342">That is what I mean.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_286">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_343">We discuss that with the president of the court, who may or may not, depending on the resources, allocate additional resources. There might be special sittings. There might be an additional judge assigned to an area for a couple of weeks to clear a backlog and so on.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeNeville" eId="spk_287">
          <from>Deputy Joe Neville<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_344">I thank Ms Denning.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_288">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_345">We will suspend for ten minutes for a vote in the Dáil.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_6">
          <i> Sitting suspended at 5.22 p.m. and resumed at 5.38 p.m.</i>
        </summary>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_289">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_346">We are resuming our discussion with the Courts Service on planning and infrastructure matters specifically.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatriciaStephenson" eId="spk_290">
          <from>Senator Patricia Stephenson<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_347">Deputy Neville spoke a little bit about judicial reviews being used in an obstructive way. He touched on the point I was making around the data and trying to figure out if that is indeed the case. In response to him, I think Ms Denning said there has been an increase in developers taking out judicial reviews.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_291">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_348">The judge in the list gave an interview recently and, in that interview, he indicated there was. He knows the facts of each of the cases.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatriciaStephenson" eId="spk_292">
          <from>Senator Patricia Stephenson<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_349">Ms Denning touched on this already but I want to put on record that people have a right to challenge decisions. I know she knows that but there can be quite a negative narrative as well around judicial reviews. Obviously, people have a right to challenge planning decisions and we do have planning decisions which are sometimes bad for communities. It is really important to highlight that constitutional right. I am glad Ms Denning touched on that as well in her reply to somebody else. Particularly with the Aarhus Convention and for the environmental justice piece, it is really fundamental. Ms Denning said this herself but for other members, I warn against the use of expediting cases as a standard process.</p>
          <p eId="para_350">In some instances, that limits fair access to justice by restricting hearings. It is fine in a special case, but if it were to be rolled out across the board as a sort of solution to the backlog, I think that would be limiting. I do not know if Ms Denning wishes to comment on this, but I think it would limit access to justice.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_293">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_351">The view of the judge in charge of the list is that the expedited procedure is there. Certainly, in the context of some of the environmental cases, European legislation states they shall be dealt with in a certain period of time. There are other cases where it makes no sense to allow parties to drag things out. There is also strategic infrastructure, if we look at things that are of national importance.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatriciaStephenson" eId="spk_294">
          <from>Senator Patricia Stephenson<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_352">Absolutely, yes. I suppose a degree of flexibility is provided.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_295">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_353">The Senator is right in that not every case can be expedited because we simply do not have the resources.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatriciaStephenson" eId="spk_296">
          <from>Senator Patricia Stephenson<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_354">Yes, but I would probably argue it should not be in some instances if it would limit people's access to justice.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_297">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_355">Some cases will need the two to three days to be heard.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatriciaStephenson" eId="spk_298">
          <from>Senator Patricia Stephenson<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_356">Yes, absolutely. Regarding prioritisation and the specialised lists, and while I recognise what she is saying around EU law, does Ms Denning think there is any concern with those processes around access to justice in light of the Aarhus Convention?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_299">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_357">Concern that the court is more specialised?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatriciaStephenson" eId="spk_300">
          <from>Senator Patricia Stephenson<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_358">Just the reducing of the time for the hearing.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_301">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_359">That was a decision made by the court to try to meet the balanced expectations of the court. European law in relation to the environment provides - it is there in the purpose of the legislation - that cases shall be dealt with in a manner in keeping with the heightened obligation concerning, in particular, proceedings such as the EU law obligation of expedition in relation to renewable energy projects. Some parts of legislation, therefore, expect that a hearing will be provided in a reasonable time. I suppose the question then is what a reasonable time is. You cannot say to somebody they can have a hearing in six months but that hearing can also take six months. We must think about everybody else on the list as well. The judges are trying to make the best of the resources that are there to try to get as many cases on as possible as quickly as possible, and calls have to be made.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatriciaStephenson" eId="spk_302">
          <from>Senator Patricia Stephenson<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_360">Absolutely. Ms Denning talked about many of the changes being very new and that time will be needed to evaluate their effectiveness. Going back again to the Aarhus Convention and Ireland's obligations, based on what Ms Denning has seen so far with the new changes, does she think they will ensure compliance with those obligations, from her perspective?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_303">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_361">There is certainly compliance in relation to the costs provisions that are there and the judges-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatriciaStephenson" eId="spk_304">
          <from>Senator Patricia Stephenson<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_362">In terms of the timely and effective access to justice.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_305">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_363">That is the intention of these different procedures for different types of cases. The judge in charge of the list can look at the particular case and the particular parties and say this type of a hearing will get this case on the quickest for the type of case it is. I think that is very important.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatriciaStephenson" eId="spk_306">
          <from>Senator Patricia Stephenson<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_364">Yes. It will improve access to justice is Ms Denning's view.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_307">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_365">It should do, yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatriciaStephenson" eId="spk_308">
          <from>Senator Patricia Stephenson<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_366">I thank Ms Denning.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_309">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_367">Would anybody else like to contribute? Deputy Cronin.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ReadaCronin" eId="spk_310">
          <from>Deputy Réada Cronin<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_368">I thank the Cathaoirleach. I had to leave for a short while but I caught up on MS Teams. Going back to Part 9 of the 2024 Act, the changed rules on judicial reviews and the removal of the need to apply for leave, it is true that Ireland ranks very low in terms of our spending on the judicial system by the State. I do not mean what they earn. Ms Denning said we need to see the new laws and the new court procedures bed in, but is it not the case that this is going to be very much up in the air and we cannot really say yet whether we think there will be many more cases arising out of the changes in Part 9?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_311">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_369">No, because we do not know. Everybody hopes things will work out the way they were intended, but as we have seen in the past, there are always some unintended consequences.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ReadaCronin" eId="spk_312">
          <from>Deputy Réada Cronin<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_370">It is a grey area.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_313">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_371">We just have to wait and see. From our perspective, we keep an eye on it. We are part of the Housing for All group. The user group will also feed information back to us so we can assist the President of the High Court by giving him data that will then allow him to decide how many judges he allocates to the list.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ReadaCronin" eId="spk_314">
          <from>Deputy Réada Cronin<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_372">The extent of changes to the rules on judicial reviews in Part 9 of the Planning and Development Act 2024 saw it go from taking up five pages in the 2000 Act to 25 pages in the 2024 Act. That is a fivefold increase so it is bound to result in more cases.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_315">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_373">It depends. From my reading of it at a high level, the new Act will restrict who can apply in certain circumstances and will change some of the thresholds. Whether that will make more or less work for us, we do not know yet. It may be that communities right around the country decide that, just in case somebody decides to build a development beside them, every housing estate will set up a partnership.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ReadaCronin" eId="spk_316">
          <from>Deputy Réada Cronin<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_374">How long could it take, if more staff and more resources will be needed, to meet an increased need, if that happens?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_317">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_375">We run competitions at the level concerned here, including court registrars. We run competitions for the High Court twice a year. We can get office staff through the Public Appointments Service system. We can run local competitions in the event that the Public Appointments Service does not have panels in place and we can also use staff mobility across the Civil Service. We can get staff in quite quickly. It takes a little bit of time to train staff, but I would be confident that if I knew judges were coming and were going to be assigned to the list, I would get the staff in.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ReadaCronin" eId="spk_318">
          <from>Deputy Réada Cronin<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_376">Ms Denning said that the Courts Service was founded about 27 years ago. What was in place before it?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_319">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_377">There was a courts division in the Department of justice and it dealt with the administration of the courts. Then there were the senior registrars, the registrars of the Supreme Court and the High Court. There were also C and D operations. For certain District Courts, they reported in to the Department of justice.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ReadaCronin" eId="spk_320">
          <from>Deputy Réada Cronin<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_378">I am not very familiar with the courts system, so that was just a background question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeNeville" eId="spk_321">
          <from>Deputy Joe Neville<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_379">It is just as well.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ReadaCronin" eId="spk_322">
          <from>Deputy Réada Cronin<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_380">I thank Ms Denning very much.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_323">
          <from> Ms Angela Denning<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_381">Not at all.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeanFleming" eId="spk_324">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-09T17:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_382">Okay. We have covered the ground. At this stage, I thank Ms Denning for assisting the committee today in this important matter. I ask that any information we requested but that was not available today be provided to the committee within two weeks from today. Mention was made of the Housing for All committee and the other committee. Ms Denning might send us some information from her perspective on that aspect. It was mentioned that the president was chairing some group as well in relation to deciding which areas were to be given priority at different times or something like that. She might send us a note on that. If there are any issues supplying the information, I ask that the clerk be informed as soon as possible.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_7"> The joint committee adjourned at 5.48 p.m. <i>sine die</i>.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
