<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#debates">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_housing_local_government_and_heritage/2025-12-04/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_housing_local_government_and_heritage/2025-12-04/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-04" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#author" href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/34/joint_committee_on_housing_local_government_and_heritage"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_housing_local_government_and_heritage/2025-12-04/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_housing_local_government_and_heritage/2025-12-04/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-04" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_housing_local_government_and_heritage/2025-12-04/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_housing_local_government_and_heritage/2025-12-04/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-12-16" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#debates">
        <TLCPerson eId="AubreyMcCarthy" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Aubrey-McCarthy.S.2025-01-29" showAs="Aubrey McCarthy"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="EoinOBroin" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Eoin-Ó-Broin.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Eoin Ó Broin"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MichealCarrigy" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Micheál-Carrigy.S.2020-03-30" showAs="Micheál Carrigy"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaulaButterly" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paula-Butterly.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Paula Butterly"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaulMcAuliffe" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paul-McAuliffe.D.2020-02-08" showAs="Paul McAuliffe"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="RoryHearne" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Rory-Hearne.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Rory Hearne"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="SeamusMcGrath" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Séamus-McGrath.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Séamus McGrath"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/chair" showAs="Chair" eId="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/vice_chairman" showAs="Vice Chairman" eId="Vice_Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/author" showAs="author" eId="author"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/editor" showAs="editor" eId="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>AN COMHCHOISTE UM THITHÍOCHT, RIALTAS ÁITIÚIL AGUS OIDHREACHT</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>Joint Committee on Housing, Local Government and Heritage</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2025-12-04">Déardaoin, 04 Nollaig 2025</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2025-12-04">Thursday, 04 December 2025</docDate>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_en">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_ga">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">Tháinig an Comhchoiste le chéile ag 03:30 p.m.</summary>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">The Joint Committee met at 03:30 p.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_3">Comhaltaí a bhí i láthair / Members present:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_1">Teachtaí Dála / Deputies</p>
              </th>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_2">Seanadóirí / Senators</p>
              </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#PaulaButterly">Paula Butterly</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#AubreyMcCarthy">Aubrey McCarthy</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#RoryHearne">Rory Hearne</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#PJMurphy">P. J. Murphy.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#PaulMcAuliffe">Paul McAuliffe</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#SeamusMcGrath">Séamus McGrath</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_9">
                  <person refersTo="#EoinOBroin">Eoin Ó Broin.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_4">I láthair / In attendance: Deputy Conor Sheehan.</summary>
          <summary eId="sum_5">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#MichealCarrigy">Teachta / Deputy Micheál Carrigy sa Chathaoir / in the Chair.</person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>General Scheme of the Apartment and Duplex Defects Remediation Bill 2024: Discussion (Resumed)<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:30:00+00:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_1">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_10">I advise members of the constitutional requirement that they must be physically present within the confines of the Leinster House complex in order to participate in public meetings.</p>
          <p eId="para_11"> The general scheme of the department and duplex defects remediation scheme Bill proposes to make provision for the payment of grants for the remediation of fire safety, structure safety and water ingress defects in purpose-built apartment buildings, including duplexes, constructed between 1991 and 2013, and related matters. An interim remediation scheme for the funding of emergency fire safety defects works in apartments and duplexes is currently administered by the Housing Agency.</p>
          <p eId="para_12"> I am pleased that today we will have the opportunity to consider these and other related matters with representatives from the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage, the Housing Agency and Dublin Fire Brigade. From the Department, I welcome: Ms Caroline Timmons, assistant secretary; Mr. Derek Rafferty, principal officer; Mr. John Wickham, senior adviser; and Mr. Eoin O'Dowd, architectural engineer and inspector. From the Housing Agency, I welcome: Mr. Martin Whelan, CEO; Mr. Ronan O'Halloran; and Mr. Martin J. Hernon. From Dublin Fire Brigade, I welcome: Mr. Greg O'Dwyer, chief fire officer; and Ms Mary O'Brien, assistant chief fire officer.</p>
          <p eId="para_13"> Before we start, I wish to explain some limitations to parliamentary privilege and the practice of the Houses with regard to references witnesses may make to others in their evidence. The evidence of witnesses physically present or who give evidence from within the parliamentary precincts is protected pursuant to both the Constitution and statute by absolute privilege. Witnesses are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice that they should not criticise or make charges against any person or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable or otherwise engage in speech that might be regarded as damaging to the good name of the person or entity. Therefore, if their statements are potentially defamatory in respect of an identifiable person or entity, they will be directed to discontinue their remarks. It is imperative that they comply with any such direction.</p>
          <p eId="para_14"> The opening statements have been circulated to members. With the short time available, we will take them as read. Is it agreed that they be published on the Oireachtas website? Agreed. We have a speaking rota. Members will have read the opening statements and will be very familiar with the scheme. I will start with Deputy McAuliffe.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMcAuliffe" eId="spk_2">
          <from>Deputy Paul McAuliffe<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_15">Will ask Ms Timmons to take us through some of supports with regard to owners' management companies, OMCs? Perhaps that is the place to start. Concerns were expressed previously in relation to procurement, the availability of frameworks and so on. Perhaps Ms Timmons would talk to us about how the legislation will allow for that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_3">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_16">We have worked with the Housing Agency over the past while to build the legislation, based on the findings identified by means of the interim scheme. Some of the things that came through strongly included that there is complexity in the scheme. There are requirements for engagement with the local authority fire service and public procurement. It is quite an extensive process. What emerged during that interim scheme was that some of the OMCs have very good capacity. However, even those with good capacity have found it complex. Some OMCs have little to no capacity to engage with the scheme, even though the Housing Agency has provided an excellent advisory service. One of the particular findings that the Housing Agency has been putting to us, along with some of the stakeholders we meet, is that some project management assistance would be welcome in that regard. The Department is happy to consider that as part of the proposals as we move forward.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMcAuliffe" eId="spk_4">
          <from>Deputy Paul McAuliffe<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_17">What format will that take? Will it be an online Zoom presentation to show how to do it or will it be more in the form of hands-on support?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_5">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_18">We do not have a formal proposal yet, but the expectation, from talking to representatives of the Housing Agency and the stakeholders, is that we will appoint a specific person to each project to manage it properly, interact with the OMC and take the project from start to finish. This is hands-on.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMcAuliffe" eId="spk_6">
          <from>Deputy Paul McAuliffe<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_19">That person will not take ultimate responsibility for the project; they will be there as a guiding assistant.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_7">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_20">That seems necessary to ensure that this works. We will look at the proposal when it comes in, but that is the expectation of the content.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMcAuliffe" eId="spk_8">
          <from>Deputy Paul McAuliffe<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_21">My follow-on question relates to a matter I previously raised with Ms Timmons. It is about the broader issue of OMCs and the regulation thereof. That is still a function of the Department of justice. I have spoken to both Ministers about the issue. Is there any further update in that regard?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_9">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_22">The Deputy is aware of the legal issue that persists. The Department of justice has to make a change to the primary legislation before it can be transferred. I understand that is under way.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMcAuliffe" eId="spk_10">
          <from>Deputy Paul McAuliffe<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_23">The expertise in that area lies in the Department of justice so it is better that it makes that-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_11">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_24">It has to. We are not allowed to make that primary change for the Department of justice. It must make it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMcAuliffe" eId="spk_12">
          <from>Deputy Paul McAuliffe<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_25">Is that happening? At what level is that conversation happening between the two Departments?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_13">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_26">There have certainly been meetings at assistant secretary level. Our corporate side has talked to its corporate side. We have already had the transfer of the Property Services Regulatory Authority, which only occurred in August. Had everything been okay on the legal side, the transfer would have been intended to happen at the same time. Subject to the Mulcreevy issue with the Act being sorted out, it should not be too much longer. It is on the legislative agenda for the Department of justice.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMcAuliffe" eId="spk_14">
          <from>Deputy Paul McAuliffe<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_27">I will come back in later rounds about pathfinders and things like that. The witnesses have the opportunity to see different levels of compliance.</p>
          <p eId="para_28">In some apartments, it will be something routine or easy to be resolved, while in others it would be significant. Will the witnesses paint a picture of the scale of the different types of works that might be required in OMCs and the potential threat as a result?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_15">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_29">Who is the question for?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMcAuliffe" eId="spk_16">
          <from>Deputy Paul McAuliffe<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_30">It is for Dublin Fire Brigade.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_17">
          <from> Ms Mary O'Brien<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_31">There are a wide variety of deficiencies apparent in apartment buildings. They can range from minor to quite complex. The pathfinder experience has shown us that there can be quite complex deficiencies in these buildings.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMcAuliffe" eId="spk_18">
          <from>Deputy Paul McAuliffe<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_32">Will Ms O'Brien provide us with some examples?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_19">
          <from> Ms Mary O'Brien<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_33">For example, fire stopping is an issue, as is the installation of fire doors. In some instances, hopefully rare, the build of the external walls may be an issue. That will be assessed on a case-by-case basis.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMcAuliffe" eId="spk_20">
          <from>Deputy Paul McAuliffe<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_34">Would that be at the extreme end?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_21">
          <from> Ms Mary O'Brien<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_35">That would very much be at the extreme end.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMcAuliffe" eId="spk_22">
          <from>Deputy Paul McAuliffe<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_36">At this stage, without having a full audit, Ms O'Brien has no idea of the prevalence of that kind of serious-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_23">
          <from> Ms Mary O'Brien<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_37">That is exactly it. It is only as the risk assessments are carried out, the details are uncovered and the opening up works are done that the extent of the effects will be uncovered.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMcAuliffe" eId="spk_24">
          <from>Deputy Paul McAuliffe<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_38">As we go forward, how will the expertise of Dublin Fire Brigade be folded into the OMC project process? At what stage is the Dublin Fire Brigade involved as we go through the project?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_25">
          <from> Ms Mary O'Brien<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_39">I am aware from the Housing Agency that there are a number of phases to the scheme. Dublin Fire Brigade is part of phase 3 or 4, although I stand to be corrected on that. At that stage, we engage with the competent professional who is appointed on behalf of the OMC. We ask that professional to send us a package of information, which includes as-built drawings, a fire safety assessment, a risk assessment, a full remediation plan and an interim remediation plan. Our level of engagement generally will be with the competent professional. I am heartened to hear that a project manager is being considered because that individual will certainly bring support to the competent professional and all the other individuals who may be tasked with helping with the production of the information. It is important that the competent professional work closely with the project management. That linkage will be important going forward.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_26">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_40">I thank the witnesses for their presentations. The briefing document is exceptionally helpful. If that was not covered by the agreement we made at the start, it should also be published. It is a document of some public interest.</p>
          <p eId="para_41"> The first point that would be good for our committee to understand is that it is just under two years since the interim scheme opened. There have been 229 applications, which is equivalent to about 20,000 apartments. Four pathfinders were extracted from that early last year, but only one grant has been awarded, with three are still pending. Will the Housing Agency talk us through those two years? If we take the one pathfinder that has been approved, what were the steps and stages? For something that was meant to be an interim fire safety scheme that was meant to deal with urgent fire safety works, how can we understand why it has taken so long to get one grant award from that set of 229 applications? This is for us to understand that process.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_27">
          <from> Mr. Martin Whelan<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_42">Before my colleague comes in, I will give a quick update. The Deputy is right. When we took on the scheme, there was no set of set instructions or toolkit in place. We have had significant learnings. We also now have considerable hindsight, which can help inform the statutory scheme and, more important in the here and now, will help us deliver on the interim scheme.</p>
          <p eId="para_43"> On the numbers, we have validated 229 applications relating to some 20,000 apartments. That is the immediate pipeline for projects that will go into construction next year and beyond. Of those, 44 are in a position to enter our dynamic purchasing system, DPS. That is a procurement framework for the appointment of the competent professionals my colleague referred to. That pipeline is ready to go. It is advanced. </p>
          <p eId="para_44"> On the four pathfinders, the first, largest and most complicated is Crescent Park in Park West. It has grant agreement and construction has begun, which is a positive. Two further projects - Seabrook Manor in Portmarnock and Wellington Court on Mountjoy Street - are at phase 4. That means they have submitted the relevant documentation to enable my colleagues to carry out the various assessments. We expect to be able to move to grant agreement within the coming weeks, hopefully before Christmas. On the fourth project, Chambers Park in Kilcock, County Kildare, the OMC confirmed that it did not and could not furnish proof of ownership of the common areas. For this reason, under the scheme as currently constituted, it could not progress. We have just received welcome confirmation from our colleagues in the Department that the legal requirement is no longer a provision of the scheme. We have engaged with the OMC today. It is at an advanced stage. I think it has tendered for building works, so that pathfinder will move quickly. I totally accept that there has been a two-year period, but we are now beginning to see the fruits and benefits of the work and learnings that have gone into that.</p>
          <p eId="para_45"> There are two key requirements for us. The first is dedicated, professional project management to work hand in glove with OMCs to guide them through every stage of the process. That is critically important. Alongside that, we need accessible, robust and transparent frameworks for the procurement of both the consultants - the competent professionals - and builders. We have the first in place. We are going through the final stages of back-and-forth with the applicants. That will come on stream shortly. We are now looking at the best possible mechanism to stand up the framework for the procurement of builders to complete the work.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_28">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_46">Before Mr. Whelan brings in his colleague, on those 44 applications that are in a position to move towards the competent professionals, is the expectation that they will start to progress their way through the scheme in parallel with the passage of the primary legislation to deal with the wider defects scheme? Before that scheme is open to applications, does the Housing Agency expect a significant number of those 44 applications to be at a more advanced stage?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_29">
          <from> Mr. Martin Whelan<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_47">Absolutely. We feel that 20 are ready to go. The documentation is in place. There is a phased nature to this as well to accommodate our colleagues in the local authority, fire services and capacity. There are 24 schemes immediately behind those 20 which will be in place to follow. As far as we concerned, the interim scheme proceeds as planned in the here and now, including the DPS and the other measures we have talked about. That is the lesson. It is to support OMCs through those mechanisms to get to the position we all want to get to, that is, where we are now, thankfully, with Park West in terms of the commencement of the remediation that is envisaged by the Oireachtas.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_30">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_48">I am out of time. I will come back to Mr. O'Halloran in the second round.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_31">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_49">The big concern of mine, which was raised at the previous committee meeting, is the risk to life and health and the risk of harm to the people in buildings. That is what I have been particularly concerned about and that the buildings are remediated on an emergency basis as soon as possible. What is the fire service's assessment of the current risk to life and to the safety of buildings? I ask the other witnesses how that is being addressed now and how it will be addressed in the coming months.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_32">
          <from> Ms Mary O'Brien<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_50">We all want people to be safe in their homes and every building. How is that categorised and how is safety measured? That is not an easy thing to do. There is no such thing as zero risk.</p>
          <p eId="para_51">We can have risk mitigation measures. In the context of fire safety in buildings, we have layers of risk mitigation measures. That is how we would approach fire safety in buildings to try to reduce risk and increase safety. We know there may be defects in these buildings. That would be uncovered because the risk assessments are done, as I mentioned earlier. There are things people can do to keep themselves safe. The legislation is framed such that the persons in control of a building have responsibility for fire safety.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_33">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_52">I understand that. When we visited the apartment block in question recently, we saw that there is mitigation. Some people are hiring security and all sorts. From the Fire Brigade's perspective, are there buildings that are currently classed as high risk?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_34">
          <from> Ms Mary O'Brien<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_53">For any building that we are aware of that is of high risk, we have significant enforcement powers under the Fire Services Act, and we act on those powers as judiciously as possible while being aware that these are people's homes we are talking about. In every case, we engage with the OMC or the persons in control of the building to try to mitigate the risk to a sufficient level that they may stay in their homes until deficiencies that are uncovered can be-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_35">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_54">Is the Fire Brigade concerned?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_36">
          <from> Ms Mary O'Brien<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_55">All the buildings we are talking about in the scope of the scheme have fire safety certificates. That means they have a general level of safety in compliance with the minimum standard of the building regulations. Invariably these buildings are built of non-combustible materials. All of these buildings have protected escape routes. While they may not be 100% because of deficiencies in the building the overall picture is that they are robust buildings. There are things that can be done for mitigation and the Deputy saw that in the building he visited.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_37">
          <from> Mr. Greg O'Dwyer<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_56">In addition, for any of the premises we know are at risk we have carried out significant pre-incident plans for those buildings. We have tagged our mobilisation system. If we get an incident in one of those buildings, there is a tag that informs the responding officers that they are going to a building that may not act in the way they think it should. They also have the pre-incident plan to refer to.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_38">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_57">Are there not buildings the Fire Brigade has not had access to and has not assessed?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_39">
          <from> Mr. Greg O'Dwyer<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_58">There are buildings we do not know of yet.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_40">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_59">Yes, apartment blocks and apartment complexes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_41">
          <from> Mr. Greg O'Dwyer<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_60">Yes. Some of those buildings would probably pre-incident plans on them even though they may not have been identified as defective premises yet.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_42">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_61">We cannot really say that all the apartment blocks affected by defective issues are not at a high risk.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_43">
          <from> Ms Mary O'Brien<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_62">We do not know yet.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_44">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_63">No, we do not know.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_45">
          <from> Ms Mary O'Brien<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_64">The scheme is demand led so we will not know until people-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_46">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_65">I understand that in terms of the scheme. I do not know how to describe this. There are ones applying for the scheme. However, in general does Dublin Fire Brigade carry out assessments of apartment blocks that are potentially dangerous, or does it only operate on the basis of someone contacting it?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_47">
          <from> Ms Mary O'Brien<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_66">In an ideal world, we would love to be able to do that, but in terms of capacity we deal with what comes towards us and advise as such.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_48">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_67">I asked this on the previous occasion. Is the Department concerned that there are potentially buildings we do not know about that are at high risk, particularly from defects around fire?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_49">
          <from> Mr. Eoin O'Dowd<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_68">As Ms O'Brien has pointed out it is an unknown quantum in the context of the built environment. There are many buildings. We expect there are robust laws in place in terms of building control and building regulations. The Fire Services Acts are engineered and geared towards ensuring those levels of safety. Where they are an unknown quantum it is a demand-led system. Where applications come through to the process there are robust procedures in place to determine the level of non-conformity and utilise the procedures. However, the built environment is an unknown quantum.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_50">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_69">Is the Department worried about that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_51">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_70">Our regulations are quite strong. I do not think we are having an indication that there is a concern we need to address immediately. If one was brought to our attention, the Deputy can be assured that we would absolutely act on it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_52">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_71">It is concerning that we are not pre-emptively assessing. We are probably aware that there are apartment blocks affected by defects that are probably high risk that we do not know about because people are not partaking in the scheme or do not have the owner management system set up. Is there something we can do to address that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_53">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_72">It has certainly been put that the owner management company system needs to be strengthened. It is something the Department will reviewing next year. As the Deputy is aware, one of the actions in the new housing plan is that we undertake a review of the Act once it comes over to us. OMCs need to be strengthened in that regard, particularly where they are responsible for fire safety in their buildings. That is a fair point.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_54">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_73">I thank the witnesses for being here. I will start with the interim remediation scheme. They have outlined 229 applications in approximately two years. Do we anticipate further applications at this stage?</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_6">(Interruptions).</summary>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_55">
          <from> Mr. Martin Whelan<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_74">-----all the while there are references to OMCs and multi-unit developments. We have a unit in the Department that engages with OMCs around the country in a different context. We engage on that and bring information about this scheme to the attention of those groupings.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_56">
          <from> Mr. Ronan O'Halloran<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_75">At the Housing Agency we have an outreach campaign that speaks to the previous question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_57">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_76">Deputy Hearne's question, yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_58">
          <from> Mr. Ronan O'Halloran<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_77">We have external facing communications. We have the website. We have <i>gov.ie. </i>We have our multi-unit developments, MUDs, road show that travels around the country. We have added slides into that, which refer to the interim scheme, how to apply to it and the premise of the scheme. As the interim scheme begins to show progress going forward it will draw other OMCs to apply to it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_59">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_78">I am trying to get an understanding of the scale. Overall, we are saying there are 100,000 apartments that will need remediation work, but we are only at 20,000 with the remediation scheme. It goes to Deputy Hearne's point. There are potentially residents out there in apartment blocks where there are not organised OMCs where they are effectively brushing this under the carpet because nobody is stepping up to lead an OMC.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_60">
          <from> Mr. Ronan O'Halloran<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_79">I go back to the figure of 100,000 homes that was spoken about. That is derived from the 2022 working group report, which I am sure everyone is familiar with. Within that 100,000 there is a breakdown that to our knowledge there are approximately 44,000 homes that have not been remediated. The remainder either have been remediated or are currently undergoing remediation works outside of the scheme we are speaking about.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_61">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_80">Sorry, so 44,000 have not.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_62">
          <from> Mr. Ronan O'Halloran<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_81">There are 44,000 completely outstanding. We have applications in for in excess of 20,000.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_63">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_82">That is just under half of those.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_64">
          <from> Mr. Ronan O'Halloran<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_83">We hope, as our delivery pipeline increases moving into 2026 that we will get closer to that 44,000 figure. That would be the intention.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_65">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_84">The interim scheme effectively will capture the majority of outstanding-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_66">
          <from> Mr. Ronan O'Halloran<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_85">Of interim houses. That is correct. We will not capture the water ingress or structural defects.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_67">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_86">I understand that. The interim scheme is obviously for the immediate safety concerns. There will be a significant number of applications to come yet. That is their anticipation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_68">
          <from> Mr. Ronan O'Halloran<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_87">We think so, yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_69">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_88">I will focus on the Housing Agency for now. It referred to learnings from the process as it has evolved and so on. The common area issue is resolved now as I understand it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_70">
          <from> Mr. Martin Whelan<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_89">That is a significant development. We and our colleagues in the Department were aware of the fact that precluded a significant proportion of potential applicants, and we had a number of potential projects stalled. The advisory from the Department on that is very significant.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_71">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_90">That should speed up.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_72">
          <from> Mr. Martin Whelan<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_91">That would not only speed up, but that would also bring into play a number of developments where substantial preparatory work-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_73">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_92">But they were stalled.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_74">
          <from> Mr. Martin Whelan<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_93">-----has been done so we are not starting from standing still. That is a significant development.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_75">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_94">The other key item in the opening statement related to project management. Have we agreement on that now?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_76">
          <from> Mr. Martin Whelan<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_95">We are preparing a detailed proposal, which we will submit to our colleagues in the Department. The Department has been supportive of our position on this and understanding of where we are coming from. The onus is on us, and we are advanced on the work in this area in making that proposal to our colleagues.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_77">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_96">I will turn to the Department on that point about project management. Is there a willingness and acceptance to take that point and accept those recommendations, albeit it has not seen the report at this point? Is there an openness to that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_78">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_97">We will have to confirm. It is subject to the detailed proposal but the Minister has indicated that we should be open to the project management.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_79">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_98">That is good. That was one of the points that was strongly made.</p>
          <p eId="para_99"> I will turn to the fire service, Dublin Fire Brigade and the issue of those areas most at risk. It was stated that a lot of planning work and pre-incident plans have been done. Obviously, not all these departments are in Dublin, so can we say the same of other fire services across the country? Does anyone want to take that question?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_80">
          <from> Mr. Greg O'Dwyer<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_100">All fire services around the country have a national guidance document from the national directorate for fire and emergency management on pre-incident planning. They all apply the same methodology when looking at high-risk premises. It is a prioritisation system. Each local authority's fire service views the risks in its area and carries out an area risk categorisation. Any buildings, particularly high-rise apartment blocks, come in under that. A pre-incident plan would be carried out.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_81">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_101">What I getting at concerns the 229 applications that are in. Are we sure there is proper co-ordination between all the fire services relating to those applications at a local level? Is there the same level of preparation and awareness as there is in Dublin Fire Brigade?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_82">
          <from> Mr. Martin Whelan<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_102">One of our work programmes over the last two years, to that very point, has been engagement with our local authority fire services colleagues. We have systematic engagement in place around that. As our colleagues pointed out, we have a number of stages in our application process. Some of those relate specifically to our engagement with our fire services colleagues. That is very joined-up.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_83">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_103">Okay. That is good.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_84">
          <from> Mr. Martin Whelan<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_104">We are confident that engagement is positive and will yield the sort of structured phased delivery we require.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_85">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_105">That is active. That is good to hear.</p>
          <p eId="para_106"> The committee carried out a site visit to Clarion Quay. One of the key points raised with us that day was the high costs for residents, particularly for insurance, because there are issues around safety and so on, which we are well aware of. In that case, if I am allowed to say this, there were annual charges of up to €8,000 per resident, which is a staggering amount of money. A significant part of that was the insurance cost. Is there any proposal to assist residents in the short term in covering those annual charges that are incurred directly as a result of these defects? It is something that badly needs to be looked at. It is not sustainable that residents have to pay that level of annual costs simply to live where they bought apartments. Specifically on the issue of insurance, and this is directed at the Department, is that something that could be considered, or has been considered or looked at?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_86">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_107">The general issue has come up. As I understand it, the former Minister, Deputy Darragh O'Brien, met Insurance Ireland at the time, engaged with it on this and received assurances from the sector, at that point, in relation to its approach to the insurance of these particular developments. I am not sure we have detail to say that we absolutely need to do something about this or that we have any more detailed proposal; we have not. That is as far as it went in terms of the contact with Insurance Ireland. We have relied on those assurances.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_87">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_108">I appreciate that. My time is up, but this point deserves further discussion. Whatever level of assurance was given to the former Minister at the time, that did not bear out in the discussions we had with the residents on their insurance costs. Perhaps it can be picked up.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AubreyMcCarthy" eId="spk_88">
          <from>Senator Aubrey McCarthy<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_109">I thank the witnesses for being here. In the last few weeks, when we discussed the various defects and the new Bill, etc., we brought up the example of Clarion Quay, where the fire spread in under 30 minutes. We also mentioned a housing development close to where I live in Newbridge, Millfield Manor, where six houses burnt down in under an hour. I know one of the residents there. The residents are taxpayers, yet it was their taxes that paid for the rebuilding of the houses and the fixes for defects. From the Department's statement, it seems the system is still being built and, after two years, people are wondering who built, designed and certified these buildings, and who inspected and insured them. Again, the people who did all of that are let off the hook and the people living in the houses, who are paying their taxes, are the ones who are paying for everything. It is the taxpayer once again. Do the witnesses feel, going forward, this will be something we will be able to deal with through this Bill?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_89">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_110">It is not dealt with in this Bill. It is not part of what we have been asked to do. We have been asked to build a statutory scheme to provide grant assistance to people in these apartment buildings. That is not one of the issues countenanced in it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AubreyMcCarthy" eId="spk_90">
          <from>Senator Aubrey McCarthy<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_111">A sum of €2.5 billion will be spent fixing a problem. Going forward, will we have another housing committee in two or years' time dealing with the same, and having to remediate issues that have happened in the last couple of years?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_91">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_112">No. There has been significant change in respect of the regulations we have brought in over the intervening period, particularly from 2014 onwards. I will ask the expert colleagues I have brought with me to comment on some of the changes we have made that should provide some reassurance to the committee. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_92">
          <from> Mr. John Wickham<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_113">To go back to the original point about the cause and nature of the defects, I will bring it back to the report of the working group to examine defects in housing. It identified that there was no single cause of the failure. It was a multiplicity, including design, product and workmanship, as well as oversight, which formed part of it. There was no one single issue that caused a lot of these defects. The learning is we are living in the shadow of the legacy of defects in buildings. A lot of reforms have been initiated since 2014, primarily starting with the building control amendment regulations, which empowered professionalism and have brought a mandatory level of statutory certification of buildings and mandatory inspection. It first starts with getting the design of these buildings right, getting a certified design, getting it lodged with an inspection plan that is implemented throughout the course of the works on-site, and ending with a statutory certificate co-signed by a builder and competent professional.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AubreyMcCarthy" eId="spk_93">
          <from>Senator Aubrey McCarthy<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_114">We had all that before. We had the certification, the insurance and HomeBond, or whatever it was, but when we came calling for the money, it was not there. What changes have been put in place so that will not happen again?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_94">
          <from> Mr. John Wickham<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_115">Prior to 2014, what existed was an opinion of compliance by professionals that did not have a process of lodgement, of drawings in particular, with the building control. People who were registered professionals did their design. Builders built in accordance. They should have built in accordance with those designs-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AubreyMcCarthy" eId="spk_95">
          <from>Senator Aubrey McCarthy<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_116">Will this new Bill fix all this, so we cannot repeat what has been done? I want to ask the fire brigade a question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_96">
          <from> Mr. John Wickham<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_117">This new system has restored an accountability across the-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AubreyMcCarthy" eId="spk_97">
          <from>Senator Aubrey McCarthy<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_118">Is that legally tight?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_98">
          <from> Mr. John Wickham<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_119">-----construction industry. That is legally tight. At the end of the day, it has borne fruit in terms of the quality of build that has happened since 2014. Colleagues in the local authorities may be able to clarify that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AubreyMcCarthy" eId="spk_99">
          <from>Senator Aubrey McCarthy<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_120">Thanks for that. I will ask the fire brigade a question. Maybe two weeks ago, we had witnesses in here. They mentioned they have people who work - they had a word for them - basically as security personnel who look after fire safety. They mentioned the Beacon area. Their job is to be on-site 24 hours a day, seven days a week, to keep an eye out to see if fires break out, which seems very piecemeal. From the fire brigade point of view, lives can be protected with alarms, detection and clear escape routes.</p>
          <p eId="para_121">Is there something questionable about that approach? Is it fixing a patch by applying a sticking plaster?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_100">
          <from> Ms Mary O'Brien<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_122">In some instances where defects are uncovered, interim measures are put in place to allow time and space for the defects to be fixed. In those instances, if there are defects in the fire detection alarm system itself or there is no fire detection alarm system, fire wardens, which were alluded to by the Senator, may be put in place for a temporary and short period because they are a very expensive solution to that problem. Obviously, we want to see the fire detection alarm system to be up and running in a building, especially in an apartment building, because it is a person's first line of defence, and that is what we would advise. We have accepted and advised the use of fire marshals in the past, as have other local authorities, but for a very short period. That is generally how they are used.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_101">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_123">I call Deputy Ó Broin.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_102">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_124">I am happy to cede to Fine Gael and I will come back in after.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_103">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_125">Next is Deputy Paula Butterly.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulaButterly" eId="spk_104">
          <from>Deputy Paula Butterly<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_126">My first question is on the proposal for project managers made by the Housing Agency. How soon will the agency be able to get that to the Department?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_105">
          <from> Mr. Martin Whelan<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_127">In days, Deputy. We are very advanced in our design of that. I would imagine that it will be days.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_106">
          <from> Mr. Ronan O'Halloran<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_128">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulaButterly" eId="spk_107">
          <from>Deputy Paula Butterly<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_129">So, before Christmas.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_108">
          <from> Mr. Martin Whelan<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_130">Absolutely.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulaButterly" eId="spk_109">
          <from>Deputy Paula Butterly<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_131">How soon can the departmental officials assess the proposal and make a decision?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_110">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_132">I cannot put a timeline on it but it will be quick. We are as anxious as anybody else to move this along. There is no particular reason to delay but it will depend on being able to move it to the Minister by Christmas, which we will have done ourselves. We will certainly have moved it that far.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulaButterly" eId="spk_111">
          <from>Deputy Paula Butterly<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_133">Nobody has a crystal ball but I would imagine Ms Timmons has a good understanding as to the flavour of what will be contained in the proposal. Do we have a guarantee that it will receive priority?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_112">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_134">It will receive priority, yes. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulaButterly" eId="spk_113">
          <from>Deputy Paula Butterly<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_135">I thank Ms Timmons.</p>
          <p eId="para_136"> I thank the members of the Dublin Fire Brigade for coming in today. I noted Ms O'Brien said the scheme would be demand led, which will pose problems and challenges in regards to resources. How does the DFB suggest we could overcome the resources issue? It was also noted that the greater Dublin area would be particularly challenging. Perhaps the witnesses have already answered my questions, so I apologise for getting them to repeat their answers, but I would like to hear their views. Is the issue skill shortages or a lack of bodies? Pardon me, as that is a terrible way of putting it, but the witnesses know what I mean. "Boots on the ground" may be better terminology.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_114">
          <from> Ms Mary O'Brien<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_137">The scheme will be demand led. We know in advance that the vast majority of the homes will be in the Dublin region. For that reason, the local authority made an approach to the Department very early in the process seeking extra resources, and as part of that, we were granted a number of resources in the Dublin region. We have tried to recruit these resources for the last year but, unfortunately, have ran into significant difficulties. There literally is an insufficient number of boots on the ground, as the Deputy put it. It is not just our issue. Right across the local authorities and the wider public sector, it is a challenge to attract people. It is a huge challenge to attract the skills and experience needed for the scheme. We do not seem to be in a position to compete with the market. That is just a fact of life. We have been unable to recruit the number of staff for which we received sanction.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulaButterly" eId="spk_115">
          <from>Deputy Paula Butterly<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_138">Is that from an economic perspective due to the salary offered? Is it due to the lifestyle, shift work or hours of work? What are the key barriers?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_116">
          <from> Ms Mary O'Brien<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_139">The main barrier is economic. We offer a very attractive workspace. We have normal office hours that is no shift work. We also have a balanced, family-friendly workspace. The main barriers are economic factors ,which is where we just cannot compete.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulaButterly" eId="spk_117">
          <from>Deputy Paula Butterly<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_140">I have a few questions for the departmental officials. Considering these challenges and the key component that is required by the fire services in order for this scheme to work, will the Department review the pay conditions and salaries to attract more people into the fire services? This has been a challenge for the fire services over the last couple of years. I would not like to think this could be a stumbling block. Please pardon my use of bad terminology today, but it would be a major stumbling block if we cannot attract a key component into the scheme like the fire services.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_118">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_141">To confirm what we said earlier, we have provided sanction for significant resources to the fire service. That was forthcoming very early on.</p>
          <p eId="para_142"> While I under the problems with recruitment, I am afraid that is not an area of my responsibility in the Department so I will take it back to the Department and acknowledge to my colleagues in that area that this issue has been raised at this committee meeting.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulaButterly" eId="spk_119">
          <from>Deputy Paula Butterly<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_143">I guess that, at the beginning, the Department imagined that it would attract X amount of people at an Y salary base. That is not the case, so this issue is definitely something that requires urgent review.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_120">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_144">I will take that back to the Department.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulaButterly" eId="spk_121">
          <from>Deputy Paula Butterly<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_145">I thank Ms Timmons. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_122">
          <from> Mr. Martin Whelan<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_146">On the practical side, we have an agreement in place with the local authority fire services around the phasing and sequencing of proposals on a rolling four-to-six-week basis to take into consideration any capacity issues that may exist. That is well thought out and linked to known risk factors. I am not speaking to the resource issue but there is co-ordination as part of this project, which acknowledges the capacity issues that exist.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulaButterly" eId="spk_123">
          <from>Deputy Paula Butterly<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_147">At a national level.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_124">
          <from> Mr. Martin Whelan<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_148">Absolutely. Across the country.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_125">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_149">I thank the delegations for all of their answers because they are very helpful for informing the committee. I have some final questions.</p>
          <p eId="para_150"> It would be good for the committee if Mr. O'Halloran took us through the steps and explain, for the next group that comes through, how those steps will be shorter steps than is currently the case.</p>
          <p eId="para_151"> We are talking about the interim scheme but it will ultimately be rolled through the transitional mechanisms into the new scheme. I ask Ms Timmons to give us more information about how that is envisaged and the timeline because Mr. Whelan spoke about 44 additional schemes in a position to move into the dynamic purchasing system. Maybe there are 20 of those ready to go, but there is still an awful lot behind those. At what point will the interim scheme blend into the overall scheme? What is the thinking on that?</p>
          <p eId="para_152"> I have a final question for Ms Timmons and Mr. Whelan. Two of the other resourcing asks that arose in our conversations with others are as follows. One is the need for a tenant liaison to assist the OMCs and the approved housing body, AHB, sector to engage with tenants, particularly with large multi-unit developments, on all aspects of the organisation and mobilisation of the scheme. This is something very different from project management. Is this on the Department and Housing Agency's radars? Are they thinking about it? Do they think it has merit?</p>
          <p eId="para_153"> We met one of the large OMCs on site that has been through a partial remediation of its own block as a result of a fire but also has defects, probably to the value of €200,000 per apartment, and is currently paying management fees of €8,000 a year because a fire warden and very high-interest costs are included. The OMC's members also talked about the need for a client representative because their thinking was that project managers were just project management and an OMC board may not include people who understand contract law, for example, or other areas of responsibility. I am referring to somebody who is able to advise the OMC on those. That could be a set of services that the Housing Agency advises on or a stand-alone individual. I would like to hear a response to the two suggestions of a tenant liaison and client representative. I suggest Mr. O'Halloran will first outline the process and explain how it can be sped up with the learnings that he has outlined.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_126">
          <from> Mr. Ronan O'Halloran<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_154">I thank the Deputy for that key question. It is an eight-phase process. I will not labour through the eight phases but they essentially are as follows. In phase 1, the application is received and validated by ourselves. The real work starts in phase 2, which is when an OMC has engaged a competent professional. The key pieces of work and the key documents that competent professional produces are the fire safety assessment, the fire safety risk assessment and, out of that, the remedial works plan. At that point, the OMC's competent professional then engages with our colleagues in the local authority fire services.</p>
          <p eId="para_155">That is a key interaction in the overall process.</p>
          <p eId="para_156"> Regarding the pathfinders, we have spoken about the two years that has lapsed. I would like to speak to the work that has gone on in those two years and how we have fed those lessons learned back into our process going forward. In the example of when the remedial works plan is being drawn up, with the pathfinders, there are significant opening-up works to be done within the apartment block, as was mentioned earlier, to see what is in the walls, in the ceilings, what are the issues and the defects and to identify them. In the pathfinders, we found at times the works were not extensive enough and did not go far enough to determine and get enough information from the local authority fire services to provide sufficient comment to justify the progression of that OMC. On that basis, we have fed that back into our processes and now, at phase 3, the competent professional will be procured through a dynamic purchasing system. Again, it is a procurement mechanism, but it ensures a higher level of quality and a more detailed scope of works that the competent professional has to undertake when engaged by the OMC with our assistance. That means when the competent professional brings the remedial works plan to the local authority fire services the opening-up works will be more extensive and more categorical in determining where the defects are and what the level of defects are in the building and the nature of them. As a result, the remedial works plan will identify the measures absolutely required to remediate that. We are hoping it will help expedite the process while also bringing quality, supporting the OMCs further and bringing further comfort to the residents in those homes. As the phases progress and we pass into phase 4, we draft the grant agreement. Again, we have lessons learned from that to turn that around as quickly as possible. When the information hits the desk of the Housing Agency we work on that straight away. We will be able to get grant agreements back in a short number of weeks with the assistance of our colleagues in the Department.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_127">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_157">I would like to go back to phase 3. My understanding is that in part one of the things that caused some of the delay with the pathfinders was not just the issues around the extent of the opening up and the assessment, but also reaching an agreement in principle between the competent professional and the OMC on one side and the fire service on the other because, ultimately the fire services have to be agreeable to the works that are going to be proposed for the scheduling in phase 4. Has there been sufficient learning from that so we will get a clear understanding of the that will be bar required by fire services for them to be able to sign off on the works programme? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_128">
          <from> Mr. Ronan O'Halloran<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_158">There has, yes. We need to determine what the eligible works are under the scheme, what are defects-related and, for example, what are related to a lack of maintenance and issues like that. The pathfinders have been absolutely instrumental and the work that has gone into them in the past 18 months to two years. The findings related to quality in and quality out. That is across the board with the pathfinders and the engagement with the local authority fire services. There are a number of working groups which we participate in and this has all been discussed and reviewed and fed back through feedback loops. We are seeing the benefits of it now. Moving forward into next year, as the next OMCs progress through the system, we hope the process will become more efficient. We will be constantly reviewing the process and refining it and improving it all the time. It will also speak to the resource issues in the local authority fire services that the documents that will be hitting their desks will be more detailed and will have more pertinent information in them. There may not be as much requirement for back and forth to request further information. The intention is that the quality will be there from day one. The pathfinders and the work to date are absolutely instrumental in getting to that point.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_129">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_159">The intention is to try to be as seamless as possible with the transitional arrangements under the scheme. Obviously, we are still building it but at the moment if an application has been made to the Housing Agency before the Act came in and the agency has not has not made a decision, it will be deemed to be brought in under the section of the Act and will be grandfathered straight in. If it has already made a decision on the application, that will be deemed to stand under the previous scheme. I do not think anyone will feel a particular change. Most people will move into the statutory-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_130">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_160">In those cases of those schemes, for people to avail of remediation of structural defects rather than fire safety, will they have to apply separately to the new scheme or will there be some other mechanism for them to be incorporated but for those wider structural defects to be assessed? Let us say they have water ingress and they are already at grant-awarding stage and contracting stage for their fire safety works, how do we get them into the structural for water ingress under the new scheme?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_131">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_161">That would probably a matter for pragmatic management by the Housing Agency of the ones they are already aware of. If the details are already available to agency, there is no reason it cannot be dealt with from a practical perspective. However, they will need to make the application under the Act for those particular defects. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_132">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_162">To the new scheme. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_133">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_163">Yes, to the new scheme, because they are not in the old one. They will all have to be assessed because there will be documentation that will not be available in relation to those. It will have to be managed in a pragmatic sense. I do not see anybody trying to hold up applications unnecessarily. One of the issues that stakeholders have raised with us is that it is important the transition into the statutory scheme does not prevent us from taking care of the interim works that need to be done. We are very conscious that the scheme needs to operate in a way that even if an application is under the statutory scheme it does not mean they do not do interim works. They should still be able to do that. There should not be any difficulty there.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_134">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_164">Quickly, on the tenant liaison and client representative-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_135">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_165">The Deputy has gone way over time. I call Deputy McGrath.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_136">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_166">We are repeating similar points. Regarding what has evolved with the interim scheme, if an application is made today what is the approximate turnaround time the witnesses anticipate? In terms of the learnings and how the scheme has evolved, how do they see that going regarding a timeline?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_137">
          <from> Mr. Ronan O'Halloran<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_167">We have data from the pathfinders. There is no doubt that has been a long process. It has been laborious and intensive for all the stakeholders involved. We have worked with the OMCs throughout the process. The timelines there could range from 12 to 18 months to get to a grant agreement to get to site. I hope with the lessons learned and the experiences to date we are feeding back into the system; which includes the project management work, the dynamic purchasing system and potential future frameworks for contractors, that we can expedite that process. We have to remember these are still significant projects in the realm of millions of euros. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_138">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_168">Can we halve that timeframe?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_139">
          <from> Mr. Martin Whelan<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_169">Our focus is taking time out of the application process. Sometimes the delay and time are conflated. It will take a certain period in terms of construction and what we have worked on; the dynamic purchasing system, the procurement framework for builders; the project management. It is about taking as much time out of that as possible. I will build key performance indicators around that, so we have very transparent timelines. I believe we can take significant time out or the process, the applications-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_140">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_170">Yes, but obviously work still takes time. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_141">
          <from> Mr. Martin Whelan<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_171">That is the reality of it. These are significant. One of the projects we are just about to sign off on is a very complex, large-scale project that reflects the earlier comments on scale. That leads back to Deputy Ó Broin's comment. The project management and the term is my fault. I am talking about a very detailed construction professional support that will help fulfil the client relationship piece as well, as I will propose to the Department. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_142">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_172">What is the budget for interim scheme for 2026?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_143">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_173">The budgets have not been published yet. They will be published in the Revised Estimates. We do have a significant allocation in 2026 and will be more than enough to cover the scheme. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_144">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_174">What will it be approximately? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_145">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_175">It will be €100 million or so. I cannot confirm the exact amount. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_146">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_176">It will be in that region. As the main scheme comes on track, the interim scheme will remain a live option. Will that remain the case for some time?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_147">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_177">The interim scheme will be folded immediately into the statutory scheme, but the types of works that were available under the interim scheme will now be available under the statutory scheme. That is the intention. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_148">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_178">Can the works that are necessary from a safety point of view be done upfront and then other works-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_149">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_179">That is the intention. The flexibility needs to be there to allow the scheme to move quickly. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_150">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_180">The interim scheme, therefore, changes name but in effect it is the same approach.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_151">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_181">That is the idea. It is just a difference in language of how we approach it, but it is the same idea. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_152">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_182">I will just turn to the framework. Where exactly are we with professionals and builders at present?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_153">
          <from> Mr. Martin Whelan<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_183">The dynamic purchasing system has gone to the market and we are now dealing with queries from potential service providers who have applied to be part of that framework. </p>
          <p eId="para_184">That is the normal procurement - answering queries, questions and so on. An important feature of that is it will remain live so parties can come into the process. As the pipeline of projects increases, we have the capacity to bring competent professionals on board. That is for professionals. We are looking at the option of a framework for builders, perhaps existing frameworks or we can do DPS, whichever is the most expedient. Both will be stood up.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_154">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_185">There is no form of vetting taking place, necessarily.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_155">
          <from> Mr. Martin Whelan<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_186">We have certain provisions built in in terms of quality and standards. If someone has been involved in a scheme previously as a consultant, builder or contractor, they are excluded from working on that scheme. Quality control is built in. A lot of the checks we are now carrying out in relation to tenders are about standing up that-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_156">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_187">There can be a degree of confidence in the quality of-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_157">
          <from> Mr. Martin Whelan<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_188">Absolutely.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_158">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_189">There is some due diligence.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_159">
          <from> Mr. Martin Whelan<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_190">For competent professionals, we have wrapped criteria around that role. We experienced that it was variable in terms of competent professionals and their knowledge of the procurement process, etc. We have sought to shore that up by building it into the criteria.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_160">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_191">When is it hoped that framework will be available in both cases?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_161">
          <from> Mr. Martin Whelan<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_192">Before Christmas.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_162">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_193">Is that for the professionals and builders?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_163">
          <from> Mr. Martin Whelan<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_194">For the professionals, before Christmas. We are looking at it for builders now actively.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_164">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_195">Will that take months?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_165">
          <from> Mr. Ronan O'Halloran<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_196">We will have it stood up in time to meet the demand of projects that will result from the work of competent professionals.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_166">
          <from> Mr. Martin Whelan<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_197">There will be no delay. Once the competent professionals are engaged and the work my colleague outlined at phases 2 and 3 has been completed, our undertaking is to have the framework in place for builders. There will be no delay.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_167">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_198">My next question is for the Department. For works already done and the retrospective reimbursement, if I understand correctly, that will not happen until the main scheme is up and running. Is that correct?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_168">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_199">There is a report that needs to be brought to Government. The Housing Agency provided us with a report and we brought it to the Minister. We intend to finalise any thinking on retrospection, subject to anything in the report.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_169">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_200">Will Ms Timmons give us a sense of the scale of the reimbursement that may be required for works already done?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_170">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_201">I do not think I have any detail with me on the scale of that today. I can see what we have for the Deputy but there is a significant number of apartments which have already undergone works.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_171">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_202">We are talking tens of thousands of apartments so it is obviously a significant amount of money.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_172">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_203">Yes. There is a significant amount.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_173">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_204">Ms Timmons does not have a figure on that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_174">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_205">No. I do not have a figure today.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_175">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_206">Can we get that figure furnished to the committee once it is available?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_176">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_207">Once it is available, absolutely.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_177">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_208">Is it fair to say that when the main scheme is up and running, there will be a tsunami of applications for reimbursement based on works that are done? They will come in pretty quickly, I imagine.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_178">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_209">We expect that funding will need to go out pretty quickly as works commence. We have a vast number of projects ready to go.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_179">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_210">Is the Department preparing for that in the budgetary process to ensure the funding will be available to reimburse for works done?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_180">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_211">Yes, there is no difficulty in that respect. That has all been smoothed out over the process of building the scheme. I do not anticipate any issues.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_181">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_212">Of the overall bill of €2 billion or €2.5 billion, a significant part will be that reimbursement.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_182">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_213">The retrospection could be significant but that depends on the decisions made in due course.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_183">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_214">A large part of the overall bill will come quite quickly.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_184">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_215">There is potential for that but there will be a process.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_185">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_216">I have a couple of questions before I let Deputy Hearne in again. Following on from what Deputy McGrath said, Ms Timmons indicated that potentially €100 million would be available in 2026. If there is a tsunami of applicants, only €100 million is allocated.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_186">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_217">I assure the Chair that if we have to revisit that, it is the first thing we would do. It is a demand-led scheme. The Department is not unaware of the potential for that. We probably have made sufficient provision for next year. When we were thinking about this, we did some calculations but, that said, if things change, we will be quick to respond.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_187">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_218">The Department will be before the committee with further Estimates.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_188">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_219">I hope we will not have to do that but that sometimes happens.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_189">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_220">Following on from a meeting we had on the issue of the common areas, I think Mr. Whelan said there is a solution for a large number of those. Will anyone miss out?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_190">
          <from> Mr. Martin Whelan<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_221">We have estimated, based on the applications we received, that around 25% to 30% of OMCs are affected by this. It is an ongoing issue. The cost of remediation for OMCs is very onerous. We think the figure is higher because some of the OMCs that have not yet made applications are probably even more affected and are at an earlier stage. This decision brings all of those OMCs into place. It does not deal with the other issues we are trying to deal with and which we spoke about, but it means, all of a sudden, a large cohort of developments is now in play that could not apply under the scheme, as of today. This is a message we will send out from the Housing Agency to OMCs. As of today, all of those OMCs and developments are now eligible under the scheme we are operating. That is very welcome.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_191">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_222">All of them are eligible. It is not the case that some will fall through the cracks and will not be eligible under the proposal.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_192">
          <from> Mr. Martin Whelan<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_223">No.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_193">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_224">The Housing Agency is happy to say all of them will be eligible.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_194">
          <from> Mr. Martin Whelan<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_225">Yes, on that point. On the legal ownership point, the clarity we received from the Department is clear.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_195">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_226">Ms Timmons mentioned project management. We met an OMC which was lucky enough to have a sufficient number of professionals living in the apartment complexes who were able to do a significant amount of work on what was not their fault, ultimately. Not everyone is in that position. Putting something in place to help them was mentioned. Will financial supports for those organisations or OMCs be in place to get legal or engineering advice, or whatever advice or professional supports they may need, to go through that process to be compensated for those costs and not be out of pocket for having to get professional help to proceed with the scheme?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_196">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_227">I have not seen the proposal yet so I cannot comment on what would be covered. I do not know that all of the categories the Cathaoirleach mentioned will be covered, but the intention is there will be project managers of a calibre to give that advice to the OMC. Subject to seeing the proposal, I can inform the Cathaoirleach further as to what we agree in due course.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_197">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_228">It is very important that no owner management company is out of pocket. They already are - Deputy Séamus McGrath and Deputy Ó Broin mentioned a figure of €8,000 in charges, as matters stand. They should not then start footing legal or professional bills to remedy something in their apartments that is not their fault. There have to be guarantees.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_198">
          <from> Ms Caroline Timmons<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_229">I should clarify that nobody has made any proposal about legal advice or legal professional fees. What is in play is project management fees. That is what we have been talking about.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_199">
          <from> Mr. Martin Whelan<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_230">It is to guide OMCs through the process. We envisage the calibre of the project management will be such that they will be knowledgeable and be able to assist. As the process becomes more streamlined, there should not be a requirement for additional or ancillary advice. We are talking about hand-holding during the process, a readily accessible framework to engage a competent professionals who then take on a significant degree of work and then to take on a competent builder. The proposal we will make will be as comprehensive as possible. When the details are seen, I will be happy to discuss it further. It is comprehensive and will address the issue the Cathaoirleach raised.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_200">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_231">We were told that some of the OMCs had to get legal advice. Would that be monitored?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_201">
          <from> Mr. Martin Whelan<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_232">An issue we have seen relates to ownership and title. That does not now apply for the scheme as far as we are concerned, moving forward. We engaged with OMCs and it was a significant cost. Even with that cost, it is a difficult and long process without any guarantee of a successful outcome. I have no doubt legal costs tied to that process will now fall away.</p>
          <p eId="para_233">The OMC may for different reasons, but for the purposes of this scheme, it will not require it. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_202">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_234">Just on the scheme in question, we were not asking for support for legal advice. The specific issue was in the context of us having discussed the idea of a project manager previously. I think the idea was then taken up as being more like a foreman on site making sure things worked. It was highlighted to us in that instance that the insurer concerned was paying for the cost of remediation, but the relationship with the insurer was not unlike the relationship that will now exist with the State in respect of fire safety remediation. It was said that some of the challenges encountered included having to sign a contract with the building contractor. This obviously requires some level of knowledge or information, and I think it would suffice if the project manager has those skills.</p>
          <p eId="para_235"> With the indulgence of the Chair, there is a second piece here. It is the issue of the tenant liaison. It came up very prominently in the last hearing on this issue. Again, I think it would be worth hearing initial thoughts in this regard. It is a separate piece of work, particularly for those OMCs that do not necessarily have the skills within their board of directors or where there has been a history of conflict, division or tension, especially for very large schemes of perhaps 200 to 500 occupants. Something additional may be required there. I know a "Yes" can be given in response to it now, but I do think it is going to be something that will need to be considered in the course of the pre-legislative scrutiny of the wider scheme. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_203">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_236">I thank Deputy Ó Broin. No other members are indicating. I thank everyone very much for coming in here again. I know they have had and will have a very busy schedule, so I thank the witnesses for their time to allow us to consider this proposed legislation. I propose we suspend briefly now to allow the witnesses to take their seats for our next session. </p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_7">
          <i>Sitting suspended at 4.52 p.m. and resumed at 4.58 p.m.</i>
        </summary>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_204">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_237">I welcome the following representatives from the Construction Defects Alliance, Mr. Pat Montague, co-ordinator, and Ms Fiona Dunkin, policy manager with Clúid. From the Not Our Fault group, I welcome Mr. Sam Doran. Before we start, I wish to explain to the witnesses some limitations of parliamentary privilege and the practice of the Houses as regards reference they may make to another person in their evidence. The evidence of witnesses physically present or who give evidence from within parliamentary precincts is protected, pursuant to both the Constitution and statute, by absolute privilege. Witnesses are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice that they should not criticise or make charges against any person or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable or otherwise engage in speech that may be regarded as damaging to the good name of the person or entity. Therefore, if their statements are potentially defamatory in relation to an identifiable person or entity, they will be directed to discontinue their remarks. It is imperative that they comply with any such direction.</p>
          <p eId="para_238"> The opening statements have been circulated to members. I think we will take it that those opening statements have been read by members. Is it agreed that we will publish the statements? Agreed. </p>
          <p eId="para_239">We will start now with our speaking rota. Based on the number of members here, we will go with ten minutes each. We will start with Deputy Séamus McGrath.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_205">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_240">I thank the witnesses for coming in this afternoon. I want to start off with the opening statements in relation to the scale of the problem here. Mr. Montague's statement states, "In human terms, what that figure means in practice is that over 100,000 people are living in homes that do not have an acceptable level of fire safety with all of the worry and anxiety that this situation entails." That is a strong statement.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_206">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_241">It was referenced somewhat in the earlier discussion. A figure of 44,000 was used. In fact, it is 54,000. In the working group report, 12,000 were estimated to have been fully remediated and 34,000 partially remediated, which leaves a cohort of 54,000 that basically have less than an acceptable level of fire safety. If you do the maths on that, you are talking about more than 100,000 people living in those units. They are the people who would fall prey if there were any incidents, God forbid, in those developments. That is the reality. I will give the Deputy a little snapshot. In one of the projects which has applied to the interim remediation scheme and has an extraordinarily high risk profile, in the last two weeks there have been fires in the foyer of the building. These were fires that were set off where bin bags were left there, and unfortunately some of the tenants, young people, set fire to the bin bags. That is exactly the sort of thing we are talking about.</p>
          <p eId="para_242"> The fire at Clarion Quay was caused by an overheating phone charger. That is what caused that fire. It does not take much. Mr. Doran will tell you about cigarettes thrown where rubbish is held on timber balconies. People leave flammable materials on it. The balconies themselves can have flammable timber. In a lot of cases, when they are flammable as in the case of Clarion, there is timber cladding attached to the windows and it is all linked in together. That is how the fire in Clarion went up. There is a high level of risk and it does not take much for that risk to become manifest.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_207">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_243">Obviously within those 54,000 apartments, with over 100,000 residents, there are varying degrees of risk. Where would Mr. Montague quantify the high end in terms of a breakdown?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_208">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_244">The answer is nobody knows.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_209">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_245">We do not know.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_210">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_246">Part of the reason that nobody knows is that, to some extent, there is a bit of smoke and mirrors - no pun intended. I heard some inappropriate words being used earlier on such as stumbling blocks.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_211">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_247">As part of the interim scheme, was there to be a triaging of the most severe?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_212">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_248">There has not been. Here is where things get messy. If the Deputy listens back to what the Department said on 18 November, it plays back to Deputy Hearne's points, both today and on 18 November. Basically, the Department is very clear - we had a vigorous discussion about this yesterday at the stakeholder forum - that legal responsibility under the fire services legislation and under the Multi-Unit Developments Act rests with the owners' management company. That is why the Department keeps on saying it is a demand-led scheme. The reality is that many of those owners' management companies are deliberately not looking. Why? The whole deck of cards collapses when they discover fire safety defects because-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_213">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_249">I made that point. Some of them are not facing up to it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_214">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_250">A lot of them are adopting a "Hear no evil, see no evil, speak no evil" approach. Once they open up works, they have to notify their insurers, and other things arise from that. What happens then is that their insurance goes from €36,000 a year to €197,000. We heard the insurance costs in Clarion Quay when we were there.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_215">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_251">A lot of this is being buried, effectively.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_216">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_252">Massively. We must recognise that owners' management companies are led by volunteers. They do not have expertise. We discussed this with the committee on 14 October when we looked at issues regarding the Multi-Unit Developments Act. We know that, frankly, a lot of owners' management companies are not well managed at all. Legally, yes, it is true that is where responsibility lies, but there has to be some role for the State to either mandate or require - it could be an amendment further down the road to the Multi-Unit Developments Act - that there be ongoing safety audits within this sector. Something like that has to be required unless there is some prodding by the State. In other words, if the State just sits back and it is up to companies to apply to the State, we are going to miss an awful lot of these fire safety issues. That <i>laissez-faire</i> approach is laden with challenges and difficulties. I do not think it is going to solve the problems. As I said, we had a vigorous discussion about this yesterday at the meeting.</p>
          <p eId="para_253"> Our starting point on this is the safe as houses report, which Deputy Ó Broin was involved in and was produced by a forebear of this committee, and the working group report, which was clear that the reason this issue came about in the first place was that the State has responsibility for the emergence of defects. It has responsibility because it did not oversee the building regulations effectively during the period between 1990 and early 2014. That is why this issue has emerged. It is not just down to shoddy workmanship. The builders were allowed to get away with shoddy workmanship because the State did not ensure compliance with its own building regulations. It is not sufficient simply to say it has regulations, it has regulated or legislated and it has done its bit. The State has to take a more hands-on role in encouraging the discovery of defects than it seems ready to take at the moment.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_217">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_254">Instead of waiting for it to come to it. I accept that. I will ask about some of the specific points in relation to what we heard earlier. I think Mr. Doran and Ms Dunkin were here and Mr. Montague was listening. I raise the issue around common areas. Are they happy that this is satisfied now?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_218">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_255">We have not seen the detail.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_219">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_256">I know. Would Mr. Doran or Ms Dunkin like to speak?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_220">
          <from> Mr. Sam Doran<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_257">It is a major step forward because it is not that they were not aware of it. When you get into it, you have to submit that you own the common areas. In our case, our building was built in 2003. Our common area was not signed over until 2009. There is six years and a gap in between it there. A lot of them are not aware. They have not even gone to check it out. It could be up to maybe 40% that will not have common areas. That is a great day for them today.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_221">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_258">The Housing Agency effectively said that from now on they are able to proceed. That is important.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_222">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_259">It will definitely bring forward more applications into the scheme because people have heard that this was an issue and have held back. It will definitely be a plus.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_223">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_260">Before I move on, would Ms Dunkin like to comment?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_224">
          <from> Ms Fiona Dunkin<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_261">On that point, looking at our own scheme with Clúid, we did a quick calculation on our top 100 OMCs. Approximately 68% of them have not had their common areas transferred over. Obviously none of those OMCs have applied for the scheme. The number in reality is going to be a lot greater than 25% to 30% because if the Deputy looked at the application process yesterday - maybe it has been changed today - it was clear that they were not eligible for this scheme.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_225">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_262">People simply were not able to proceed. That has changed, according to today's testimony. On the issue of project management and what the witnesses heard earlier, it seems that there are steps in the right direction there. They are broadly welcome.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_226">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_263">They are broadly welcome. Again, the devil is in the detail. We will have discussions. As people will be aware, since Caroline Timmons came into her role in the Department, we are now involved in the stakeholder forum.</p>
          <p eId="para_264">There had been a stakeholder forum around defects remediation for some time but it involved just the Housing Agency and the Department. Now we are involved, which is a great step forward. We had a meeting yesterday. Let us see what emerges in the detail. There were some different emphases between the Department and the Housing Agency. The Department takes a more "suck it and see" approach and the Housing Agency is looking for a more belt and braces approach. We are absolutely clear and have said on two previous occasions that we need project managers. That needs to be there as a systemic part of the scheme.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_227">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_265">My time is up but some of the other members might pick up on procurement and the frameworks in terms of what we heard today, in respect of the professionals but also the builders. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_228">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_266">That is one of the questions I will follow up on. I want to focus on the detail. Over the last couple of weeks it is clear that the situation is actually quite fluid, which is positive because it means there is scope for improvements. I want to acknowledge that. We need to keep pressing for the detail we would like to see in those improvements. I have four questions which the witnesses can divide among themselves as they see fit. The first is about how we accelerate the process. The Housing Agency talked about how they think that, as a result of the learnings from the interim scheme, stage 2 with the competent professional and stage 3 with Dublin Fire Brigade could become much shorter. Mr. Doran had a full head of hair at the start of stage 2 and we can see the consequences of that. I would be interested to hear the witnesses' reactions to that and how we can ensure that those phases are as short as possible. That is the first one. The second one is to pick up on Deputy McGrath's point. It was interesting that the Housing Agency people were talking about a much more expanded definition of a project manager, not just a foreman but somebody who would have experience in some of those broader areas. I am inviting the witnesses to tell us what they need to see in that foreman's role. Likewise with the framework agreements, I invite them to fill in the detail they want to see. The third issue is the transitional mechanism. There has been quite a change. We seem to be inferred at an earlier stage that the bulk of the applications into the interim scheme would not be dealt with until the full scheme was up. The Housing Agency is now saying something substantively different. I want to invite the witnesses' response to that. Also, even where somebody in the interim scheme is getting the fire safety work, what is the best way to have them rolled into the new scheme? What would be seamless. Finally, we did not get to deal with the non-defects upgrades today but we will deal with it when the Department comes back. We are going to have to find a resolution to this. If there are fire safety issues that need addressed and the OMC does not have the money at that point to pay for that work, there will need to be some mechanism for the State to step in and pay it and then recoup it from the OMC at a later stage. I would like some detail on that, rather than the general principles. That will help us when we are with the Department and ultimately doing our prelegislative scrutiny report next year.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_229">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_267">Mr. Doran might answer on the procurement as he has dealt with it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_230">
          <from> Mr. Sam Doran<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_268">On the procurement thing, in our place we had done a tender process and gone all the way to drawing down the money. When we were drawing down the money, they came to the conclusion that they could not give us the money because it was more than 50% so it had to be on public procurement. That put us right back to the start all over again. It was a lengthy thing with procurement. It is complicated, it takes a lot of time and it is slow getting through it. When you get to picking and moving on, it takes a lot of time. On the project manager role, that really came from the competent professionals. They were architects, engineers or surveyors but they did not want to communicate with the OMC. They will go in and survey the building and that is as far as their job goes. We had gone through three competent professionals until we got to the company we have at the moment. They were fairly hands on, explained everything to us and encouraged us to be there every day when they were doing the opening of works to explain what the problems were. We got to learn a lot. That is where the project manager comes in. The competent professional does not way to talk to lay people so we need somebody to bridge the gap there and go back to them to make sure they get what they need, and then the process can move on. The lack of engagement by the competent professional was holding up the process. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_231">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_269">I will come back to that but I want to come to the procurement piece. I listened with interest when Mr. O'Halloran was talking about that earlier and mentioned a 12 to 18-month period. To be frank, nobody has got through in 12 months. It is 18 months or so at the moment. Having spoken to the Housing Agency, the view is that with a fair wind, leaving aside the new elements, under the current process it would take about 13 to 14 months. I think with the additional things we are still talking about a nine or ten-month process. One of the things we have to do is around the issue of fire alarms. I was really struck by Mr. Dennis Keeley's comments when he was in here on 18 November, that fire alarms are the key element of any fire safety strategy. We mentioned that in our opening statement. I think we need to look at decoupling the provision of fire alarms from the procurement morass. I remember engaging with a former CEO of the Housing Agency. Their view was that they would basically go in like a buzz saw through all those 54,000 or whatever, to put in fire alarms and do it over a period of two or three years. We need to look at a much more ambitious, fast-moving approach to fire alarm installation. That might involve it being done directly by the Housing Agency. For me, that is the biggest single thing that needs to be done in the first instance. </p>
          <p eId="para_270"> That comes back to the issue of the interim scheme. There is unfortunately a misunderstanding at times, and again we had a vigorous debate about this yesterday. The interim scheme is not interim in terms of time. It is about putting in place the interim fire safety measures as recommended in recommendation No. 5 of the working group report, and as set out in section 8 of the code of practice. It is not about being interim and then to be wrapped up into the full scheme. We made it very clear that there needs to be a separate thread for the interim scheme within the statutory scheme. The number one priority has to be to ensure that those 54,000 homes are all brought up to an acceptable level of safety as quickly as possible. The idea of doing all the rest of the stuff while we are there seems nuts to me. We have made that very clear. We have to focus on getting that done first, hence the idea of decoupling the installation of fire alarms from the procurement piece and looking at other ways of doing that. It is really crucial and would bring the level up much more quickly than we are able to do at the moment. The way it is currently being done in respect of provision of fire alarms is way too slow, given the level of risk that exists.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_232">
          <from> Ms Fiona Dunkin<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_271">I totally agree with Mr. Montague on that. It needs to be decoupled. Procurement is going to take time and we all accept that. If we can find ways to circumvent it, great, but we need to deal with the very urgent items which we mentioned at the last discussion. If we are taking that approach, which would be fantastic, we do not necessarily have a full view of the risk ratings within the actual applicants so far for the interim remediation scheme. The application process is very light-touch, which is positive and was done intentionally to allow people to move through applying to the scheme on an initial basis before moving on to the more complex areas around the scheme itself.</p>
          <p eId="para_272">There is a yes or no question whether a fire safety risk assessment has been undertaken. If you click "No", you will still be taken through to the application process. We do not necessarily have a view of the risk. There may be a view that height would be looked at first but it is just to make that point that we do not necessarily have an understanding of which we would go through or where would we put the smoke alarms in the fire detection first if we were to take that approach.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_233">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_273">To follow up on the piece about protecting the interim measures scheme, we have come to a view after the discussions we have had that it may be prudent to actually include a specific section in the legislation in relation to interim remediation scheme. Folding it in and that it all becomes the one thing would be a grave error. We have to focus on bringing everybody up to standard. Bringing those 54,000 units up and folding them in has to be the priority. The Department is now aware of our view on that. We had a full discussion about it yesterday. I am just saying it here. It probably is required to have a specific section in the legislation regarding the interim remediation scheme. Remembering what the then Minister, Deputy O'Brien, said when it was launched, it is about providing people with an acceptable level of safety while they are awaiting full remediation. That is the biggest need and the biggest challenge we have at the moment.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulaButterly" eId="spk_234">
          <from>Deputy Paula Butterly<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_274">I do not have any questions but I wanted to make a couple of observations. It has been a great listening exercise for me and I had the opportunity to listen to the previous contributions, even when I was not here. The witnesses have made very sensible and common-sense suggestions, first and foremost regarding the fire alarms. Prevention is always key. People have lived with enough stress and fear without taking this on board and adopting it very quickly. Is there something to be considered, even outside of a legislative approach, to guarantee that this could be a speedier process and maybe find a way that the Housing Agency can, in the interim adopt a measure so that it does not have to wait for the passage of legislation?</p>
          <p eId="para_275"> On the point as regards nudging people along in those management agencies to allow them to come forward. They are not agencies but I am lost for words today. I get a hint from what the witnesses were saying that they are nearly too afraid to scratch the surface in case it opens a Pandora's box of items that have perhaps nothing to do with the other issues on hand. Then, we come into the complications of insurance. Also there, I refer to some engagement while we wait for the passage of legislation to encourage them to move quicker on this. As they are quick to say, this is demand-led. It would be beneficial for everybody concerned because then we will get a quicker view of the whole picture.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_235">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_276">One of the things that had been discussed previously was that, when the interim remediation scheme was launched, two years ago next week, it was agreed that there would be a proactive information campaign run by the Department. We are not talking about letters but about a campaign in social, local and national media. A budget was allocated for it. I think that is necessary. To be fair, the reason it was held back at that time, and we heard it already, was because we hit the buffers in terms of local authority fire services resourcing, which was why we then pivoted towards just working with four pathfinders. Now that we are, in a sense, putting the proper systems in place, it strikes me that we are again coming back to the State acting not so much as a passive agent and saying the responsibility is on OMCs and it is demand-led. That is part of the proactive approach. I know Mr. O'Halloran mentioned that the Housing Agency had been doing MUDs seminars and all the rest of it. That is fine but the people who are going to that are people who are in the know. The reality is, the vast majority of owners' management companies have no connection with the Housing Agency and no connection with the State. We do not even have a database. There are thousands of them. There are loads of them out there living in blissful ignorance or, obviously less than blissful ignorance. The problem is that it is the people living in those complexes who would bear the brunt if something were to happen. We have made it clear that we have a responsibility as a society to go beyond simply saying we put the scheme and the regulations in place and it is up to the owners to come to us. The State has to be way more proactive, given its responsibility for the creation of this mess in the first place.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulaButterly" eId="spk_236">
          <from>Deputy Paula Butterly<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_277">On that, just thinking out loud, there could be a voucher system with the local authorities, where, once it is identified that theirs is a defective apartment, people simply go in, get their voucher and go to a local supplier, or the authority might have a list of trusted suppliers who would come and fit these alarms systems. These costs could then be recouped later on.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_237">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_278">One of the issues is that what we are looking to do is ensure the standard is there. It is not just fire alarms. We are looking at stuff like the decibel levels of bell heads. One of the big challenges at the moment is that the noise of the alarm system is loud enough so that if somebody is asleep in bed, it will wake them up. That was one of the problems that was highlighted when we were in Clarion Quay. They did not have that. It was just pure luck. What actually happened was the person in whose apartment the fire started went around, after the alarm went off, and knocked on people's doors to get them out because some people had slept right through the alarm. Why? The noise was not loud enough to wake them. This was happening in the wee hours of the morning. The fire started after midnight. I think what the Deputy is saying is we need to find a way, whatever way it is, of quickly bringing up the standard of the fire alarms. I am not sure everybody is sufficiently seized of the urgency of that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulaButterly" eId="spk_238">
          <from>Deputy Paula Butterly<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_279">I am not for one minute suggesting people get a voucher, go into the nearest shop, buy any old alarm and just install it yourself. It has to be of the right level, it has-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_239">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_280">Absolutely.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulaButterly" eId="spk_240">
          <from>Deputy Paula Butterly<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_281">-----to be functioning and be approved. However, having to wait to insert this into legislation is far too slow in my mind.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_241">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_282">It is.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulaButterly" eId="spk_242">
          <from>Deputy Paula Butterly<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_283">I would hate to think a fire would start and rampage through a building. I read something there about the golden hour. We do not have that luxury in these buildings. Surely there is a practical measure that we can put in place within a matter of weeks or months.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_243">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_284">One of the other challenges in that regard is the issue about owners' management companies being able to access people's apartments in order to do that. The owners' management company has responsibility for the common areas. There are often challenges in accessing apartments themselves to carry out works. That is something we would need to look at in providing owners' management companies with the wherewithal to do that. It is not just about the sanctity of people's apartments because of the nature of apartment living. What happened in Clarion Quay is that a fire started in one person's apartment and spread to everybody else's. It cannot be contained within one place. The notion that somehow I can say "you are not coming into my place to check on the alarms", owners' management companies need to be able to go in and ensure this. It is a safety issue not for one person in their apartment but for everybody living in that block and, at the moment, there are challenges around that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_244">
          <from> Mr. Sam Doran<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_285">In our own existence, we were one of the first to be identified with fire defects and we had the threats such as being put out of our homes. We had engaged with Dennis Keeley on that. What we had to do was put in a fire alarm ourselves, which cost €394,000.</p>
          <p eId="para_286">We had to hit all the members to pay for it. As we said, as regards decibels, it has to be brought up to 75 dB. Most of the apartments only have a sounder in the hall, however. When the bedroom doors are closed, they do not hear it. If they have drunk alcohol, especially after a football match – I had one such incident a couple of weeks ago - they fall asleep and do not hear it. That happened in another development. We put that in to provide early warning. We then put in 156 fire extinguishers, which cost another €16,000. We also had to service our automatic opening vents, AOVs, and the whole lot.</p>
          <p eId="para_287"> The OMC needs to be active. Putting in a fire alarm is grand but if a fire alarm activates, someone might decide they are not going out and may turn off the panel and remove the head on the ceiling instead. If they do not put it back up the next day and then they go on holidays for two weeks, there is no early warning in that apartment. That is where a fire really gets going. In our place, I walk our building and sign off on it every day. This is where the OMC has to take some responsibility that it is checking the fire panels. In our case, if someone removes a fire head, we will hit them with a €200 fine. If it is not paid within 28 days, we take their parking in the car park. We enforce it. We have had nine panels handed over to the builder in nine different blocks and not one of them had a yellow light on because of the enforcement we do. It is easy putting in the fire alarm. It is about the maintenance and policing of it and making sure people do not interfere with it. If that is done, it provides an early warning and is effective. People getting an early warning is the most important part of the building. They should have 60 minutes to get out but due to the defects, they do not have 60 minutes so every minute is important. That is the kind of money that you are talking about for fire alarms. We are a big building with 232 units, so it depends on the size. It is the most important thing.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_245">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_288">Sorry, I had to go to another meeting. I echo what was said earlier. I have a real concern that we are not identifying, and have not identified, buildings at risk. We do not know. As mentioned, it is a demand-led scheme and there are potentially thousands of people living in buildings that are unsafe that we do not know about. No one seems to be proactively going out to try to find that out.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_246">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_289">No, there is not. To be clear, it is correct to say that under the fire services legislation and the Multi-Unit Developments Act 2011, the legal responsibility rests with the directors of the owners' management companies. That is correct. I am not sure that will actually do the job, however.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_247">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_290">It is more than a legal responsibility. The State has a responsibility to its citizens in terms of their well-being and health.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_248">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_291">Absolutely.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_249">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_292">I just do not understand how the Department can say it does not know or have any sense of the number of potentially unsafe buildings.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_250">
          <from> Ms Fiona Dunkin<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_293">Mr. Montague mentioned earlier that an information campaign is vital. The welcome change and legal advice around the common area transfer are great. We need to have an information campaign now, from today, to let those people and OMCs know, which did not apply last week because they knew they were not eligible for it, that they are now eligible. As I said, that is 68% of our OMCs within Clúid. That increases the number massively.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_251">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_294">Could the fire services be required to carry out assessments of these buildings? Could they be given the resources and time to do that, given that we know this is a problem?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_252">
          <from> Mr. Sam Doran<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_295">If they go out and are aware of an issue, they will have to empty the building. They did that years ago and it proved very costly. I do not think they want to revisit that. That is the reason we are being told the onus is on the OMCs.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_253">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_296">The State has powers in this regard. The dangerous buildings and dangerous places legislation empowers-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_254">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_297">The State is adopting a we-do-not-want-to-know approach because of the consequences if it finds out. Of course, no one wants to put people out of their homes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_255">
          <from> Mr. Sam Doran<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_298">There are 1,000 people in our building. We got all those threats at the start that we were going to be put out if we did not pay up, but the people could not pay up. We lost our insurance for ten days but then we got it back, but for mad money. We were going to lose our mortgages. They were going to be called in because we did not have insurance. People were totally stressed out. Then it quietened down. We did something to bring it up to a level. We policed our building and did what we could to stay safe and it did not proceed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_256">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_299">This goes hand in glove with the issues around the Multi-Units Developments Act because the State does not have a list of all the OMCs in the country. Such a list does not exist. Therefore, it cannot communicate with all of them directly to inform them of a scheme, their responsibilities and all the rest of it. That is why we are talking more generally about a media campaign. It will still be hit or miss but it is better than what is there at the moment.</p>
          <p eId="para_300"> The Deputy is right; there is nothing being done proactively. Even when it comes to the assessment process, it is all desk-bound, as is the issuing of fire certificates, for instance. It was said earlier that these buildings have fire certificates but, frankly, the fire certificates are not worth a tuppenny damn. They are based on whether these buildings were built in accordance with the original plans and designs. The reason they are defective is that they were not. You cannot rely on those fire certificates. They are meaningless. The Deputy is right that there is a sort of passive approach. If we are going to address this, there needs to be a more proactive approach, one where the State is acting like the good, proactive citizen, as distinct from a passive approach and sitting back, which largely has been the approach.</p>
          <p eId="para_301"> To be clear, this is a big an improvement on what existed before because the approach before 2020 was basically to say, “Don't knock on our door, we don't want to talk to you. We're not interested. Go and fix it yourselves. It has nothing to do with us.” That at least has changed. To be fair, this committee is due huge credit because there is now cross-party consensus that this needs to be tackled, which is why we are discussing the legislation. Things have changed but this committee has an opportunity to advance that even further with the report it writes around this legislation. That piece about the State's role is an important one.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_257">
          <from> Ms Fiona Dunkin<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_302">We do it well when it comes to food safety. The Food Safety Authority issues warnings around salmonella and other products. We do not know who has bought those products, similar to OMCs. We do not know where the OMCs necessarily are or where the defects are. That is why a wide-ranging campaign is absolutely vital.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_258">
          <from> Mr. Sam Doran<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_303">In our experience, the best thing that can be done is to get fire alarms into all of these buildings as quickly as possible.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_259">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_304">That is crucial.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_260">
          <from> Mr. Sam Doran<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_305">One thing I found important in our development was that when fire defects are identified, everyone must be notified. When the people who lived in our building knew the defects, they knew what to watch out for and what not to do. For example, if someone were to have a barbeque in Park West at the moment, my phone would be hopping straight away with people informing me that they have seen someone entering the building with a gas cylinder or barbeque. Before the individual would ever get to light the barbeque, residents would be onto me to go and sort it out. The residents police the building strongly because they are aware there is danger. By not investigating or finding out, they are not protecting their own people. They need to know what the defects are. They need to know what the consequences of certain things are. Then they can police it themselves. We have so many buildings with defects and there is nowhere to move the people to.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#RoryHearne" eId="spk_261">
          <from>Deputy Rory Hearne<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_306">The State should know, at minimum.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_262">
          <from> Mr. Sam Doran<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_307">It should know. Even the people living there should know they are living with danger so they are aware of it.</p>
          <p eId="para_308">It is not going to be fixed overnight. It is going to take time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_263">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_309">However, the fire alarms piece can be done relatively quickly. It is relatively low cost too, particularly if you are doing it at scale. That is something that can be done that would make a massive difference to those 100,000-plus people living in those units.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_264">
          <from> Mr. Sam Doran<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_310">Fire alarms could be done in days if they are wireless. They do not have to be wired. It is only a matter of fitting modules. You are not trying to run cables. If the will was there to do it within a couple of months, you could have fire alarms into all these places. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMcAuliffe" eId="spk_265">
          <from>Deputy Paul McAuliffe<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_311">Mr. Montague was being very kind talking about the expertise in the committee. Let us be honest. Listening to what he was talking about in relation to Priory Hall and some of the other issues, we have come an incredibly long way. The main reason that has happened is because of the people who have lived in those complexes who have been fighting very hard to seek an alternative to the courts declaring somewhere has to be shut down and where the fire certificate was the responsibility of the local authority or Dublin Fire Brigade and then the local authority having to step in in some way. That is all down to the people who lived in the complexes and the expertise there. It is also a bit of an exception. Deputy Ó Broin talked about the position being fluid. The fact that we will have pre-legislative scrutiny and there is so much agreement between the Department and those immediately impacted points to the very active and ongoing conversation that is happening with the witnesses on one side and the Department on the other. Even the changes confirmed earlier, which are very welcome, about the common areas, the project management assistance, the movement of the framework, for example, the alternative for procurement, even in the past couple of months or maybe weeks, show the movement we have had. An awful lot has happened. We deal with pre-legislative scrutiny all the time. There are many Bills we would be not be as informed about and equally so the Department. It is because of the work that has been done. It is worth underscoring that.</p>
          <p eId="para_312"> The pre-legislative scrutiny report is an opportunity for us to shape legislation. There are things that would be appropriate for the legislation and things that will be appropriate for the scheme. It will be really important. I am looking at the opening statement and there is a mix. In tabular form or an index, it might be worth identifying in the report those which are specific to the legislation and that the witnesses feel are important for it and those that might be more for the operation of the scheme, supports and so on. The reason is that I do not want to have to suggest amendments. The amending Stage should be really simple. We should not have many amendments. It would be good to point out to the Department specific things that the witnesses want in the legislation early on rather than what they are happy to accept in operational terms.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_266">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_313">In our previous submission, we went through this head by head and set out changes that we were looking for in each head. The only addition to that is the requirement for a specific section in relation to the interim remediation scheme. That is because it is patently clear to us now that there is a fundamental misunderstanding or there has been one. I hope that after yesterday it may be changing. To be fair, the Department representatives did say they would take away what we had to say which is testament to the Deputy’s earlier point that we now have a process. To be fair, we are now part of the stakeholder forum. In the past I had observed it was a case of a stakeholder forum but where were the stakeholders? Why were we not at the table? To be fair to Caroline Timmins, she brought us in straight away so I give her huge credit for that. For me, that is the single biggest thing.</p>
          <p eId="para_314"> There has been a fundamental misunderstanding about the nature of the interim scheme. It is not interim, in that it is there to transition into the full scheme. It is interim because it addresses the immediate measures set out in the working group report and in the fire safety code of practice. Those interim measures are the number 1 priority that need to be addressed. Those interim measures are about providing people with an acceptable level of safety so they can continue living in their homes while they are awaiting full remediation. That has to be enshrined in the legislation so we do not end up with a dog’s dinner of a situation where they talked about the thing folding in. The problem is that if it folds in, we could end up where people with an urgent need end up competing with people who might have water ingress issues. Those are very difficult and intractable but we have to prioritise life safety first. That comes back to the fire alarm stuff. That needs to be done but those are outside matters to do with the scheme or whatever. However, from our point of view, in addition to what we put in the first one-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMcAuliffe" eId="spk_267">
          <from>Deputy Paul McAuliffe<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_315">The specific thing we should be referencing from a legislative perspective is the interim scheme.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_268">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_316">Absolutely. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SeamusMcGrath" eId="spk_269">
          <from>Deputy Séamus McGrath<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_317">Did it say it was going to be enacted in that way?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_270">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_318">What it said was more in terms of looking at how it was going to be integrated. The only provision at the moment that relates to the interim scheme is what are called transitional arrangements and that is basically about phasing it out. What we are saying is that the interim scheme does not close until everybody has an acceptable level of safety.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMcAuliffe" eId="spk_271">
          <from>Deputy Paul McAuliffe<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_319">Is it worth identifying timelines in the legislation or specific targets? Is that something Mr. Montague would like to see? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_272">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_320">What it identifies is the stuff that is in the code of practice which are the type of measures which might identify priority works for the scheme. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMcAuliffe" eId="spk_273">
          <from>Deputy Paul McAuliffe<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_321">I am sorry to rush Mr. Montague but we have such limited time. The second area is the Multi-Units Developments Act, and he knows my view on that from last time, and the regulator. The point was made earlier that if we had a regulator and a mandatory list of OMCs, it would be very easy to inform every OMC of its legal obligation because they would all be regulated and they would all have registered contacts and we would be able to have an evidence trail of having informed them of their legal obligations. The social media campaigns and all of that are really important but if you have a proper regulator and a proper register you do not need some of that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_274">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_322">Correct. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMcAuliffe" eId="spk_275">
          <from>Deputy Paul McAuliffe<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_323">Mr. Montague will have heard the comment I put to the Department. We have been nice to them in the first half so let us be more critical of them in the second half of the conversation. I am not happy with the response from the Department in regard to the transition from justice. I have not had any update from the Department of justice. I wonder have the witnesses.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_276">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_324">Deputy Roderic O’Gorman put down a parliamentary question on 27 November. The reply came back that there is basically a one-size-fits-all piece of legislation for criminal and civil issues - I cannot remember the name-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMcAuliffe" eId="spk_277">
          <from>Deputy Paul McAuliffe<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_325">Like an omnibus Bill.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_278">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_326">An omnibus Bill. It has gone through pre-legislative scrutiny. I think the report was issued by the justice committee on 13 November. There is a provision in that to address the Mulcreevy case issues. However, that has just gone through pre-legislative scrutiny and obviously it still has to go through the full process. The fact it is added in with a lot of other stuff in an omnibus piece of legislation means that being realistic, I do not see it getting passed until mid-year next year. That means we are towards the back end of next year before any regulatory work can begin. My understanding is, and it is a fair position, that the Department has not allocated any resources to the Housing Agency for 2026 to do any regulatory work because it does not have jurisdiction for it. I hope the Department will come back with a Supplementary Estimate for that because the amount of money involved is very small. It is about people. Unfortunately, however, the time of year means we will be talking about 2027 before any effective regulation begins.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMcAuliffe" eId="spk_279">
          <from>Deputy Paul McAuliffe<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_327">Even though it is not related to the legislation before us, we need to reference this in our pre-legislative scrutiny report. If you were the Comptroller and Auditor General and you were being really cautious, you would be saying the remediation scheme should not proceed without that regulation being in place. That is the difficulty. Are there any protections we could put into this legislation that would pre-empt the work that would be done in a full review?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_280">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_328">We need to look somewhere, whether it is this Bill or the MUD Bill, but it is probably this one. We certainly need to look at strengthening OMCs' ability to access people's apartments. There are provisions in relation to that but they need to be reviewed to make sure they are watertight, for instance, with things like fire alarm upgrades or smoke detectors or whatever. I was talking to somebody in an OMC today who was saying they were trying to put proper smoke detectors into an apartment and the owner would not let them in. They just could not get in. This is an issue not just for that person but for everybody living in that building, so there is an issue about empowering OMCs so they can do the works that are necessary to protect people's safety. That needs to be enshrined in this legislation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulMcAuliffe" eId="spk_281">
          <from>Deputy Paul McAuliffe<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_329">That is useful. I thank Mr. Montague.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_282">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_330">I have a couple of questions. There was a term used, which was an acceptable level of safety when it comes to fire alarms. There should not be an acceptable level of safety but a high level when it comes to that. Mr. Doran mentioned going from €36,000 for insurance to-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_283">
          <from> Mr. Sam Doran<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_331">€197,000.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_284">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_332">I assume that is common.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_285">
          <from> Mr. Sam Doran<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_333">It is. I was informed last week RSA has reviewed the insurance on two other developments because of the fire defects not moving on.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_286">
          <from> Ms Fiona Dunkin<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_334">We had a similar experience in Clúid with massive leaps in insurance costs.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_287">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_335">Are insurance companies using it as an opportunity?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_288">
          <from> Mr. Sam Doran<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_336">I would not think so. I think they are calculating the risks and they are saying there is a danger there. Our building is valued at €97 million, overall, so that is the risk. It is a huge risk taken on.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_289">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_337">In some cases what happens is the insurance companies, when it comes to renewal time, are saying - especially about the issue around delays - people were told there was a scheme or people had applied for a scheme, but the work still has not been done. They are giving people a year to get works done or they will withdraw cover. Mr. Doran mentioned that happened in his place. He lost cover for about ten days.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_290">
          <from> Mr. Sam Doran<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_338">We lost cover. The company had been warning it was going to withdraw cover but the management agent in place at the time had not informed us of it. It came up to the deadline of the end of February and the company pulled the cover. We had to search around for ten days. We ended up going with a broker here who went to a broker in England and that broker got insurance from Germany for us, so we are insured with a German company. It is the only way we can get insurance put on the building.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_291">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_339">I noted there was a question on insurance asked of Caroline Timmins earlier. She referenced the fact the former Minister, Deputy O'Brien, had discussions with the insurance company but our conversations with him went further than just that piece, which was also about the fact the increased costs to OMCs and then to owners as a result of insurance hikes are something owners should be able to get back because they are directly related to the defects. To be fair to the former Minister, he indicated he would consider that and look at it. It is something that needs to become part of the scheme in the form or retrospective payments and reimbursement as those costs are a direct result of the defects and are not in any way the fault of the owners but it is the owners who are having to foot the bill.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_292">
          <from> Mr. Sam Doran<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_340">He did say there would be insurance support. I went into his office when we were losing the insurance. He asked me for a copy of our policy and said he would see what he could do. When we were losing the insurance we had a corporate landlord and they threatened us with a solicitor's letter that they were taking us to the High Court for not having insurance. They said their investors felt nervous we did not have insurance so they were looking to take us to court to wind it up. When I got insurance they came back and said we had stolen their insurance. I asked how and they said they were working on it. I had to go back to the former Minister and say did I not speak to him ten days ago and say I was working on this insurance. I do not know where they were going with it but they served me with solicitors' letters for their investors. It was not about the people in the building; it was that their investors were nervous. Insurance was a headache. The former Minister said to me not to worry and there would be insurance support.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_293">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_341">That is important.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_294">
          <from> Mr. Sam Doran<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_342">That is what he told me. How do you go from €36,000 to €19,000? The Minister, Deputy Carroll MacNeill, was the Minister of State with responsibility for insurance at that time and she came out to us and tried to get insurance for us to assist us in any way she could. The two of them were working on it at the time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_295">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_343">All right. I thank Mr. Doran. We have five minutes and I will let members who indicate back in. I call Deputy Ó Broin.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_296">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_344">I will make a few quick observations and if people want to respond, that is fine. Even if the legislation to facilitate the transfer, like the MUD Bill, etc., were to happen tomorrow we need to be a bit realistic here. The Government will set up a working group, there will be a public consultation and it will be several years before there are any recommendations. In the best-case scenario nothing will be happening on actual reform of the Multi-Unit Developments Acts, the creation of an OMC regulator and all the things we agree are needed before this scheme opens. An issue Deputy McAuliffe rightly raised at a previous meeting is handing over tens of million of euro to unregulated bodies. There is a solution to that, which is not handing over tens of million of euro to unregulated bodies but having framework agreements through the Housing Agency so the agency enters into the contracts, as has happened through the Pyrite Resolution Board. Everything is done in consultation with, and with the agreement of, the OMC. There is therefore a mechanism that could be introduced or at least should be explored in this legislation either for all OMCs or for OMCs where there are significant governance challenges, given the scale of money involved. I offer that by way of observation.</p>
          <p eId="para_345"> There are two things that are changing. If we take the view as a committee when we do our deliberations on the pre-legislative scrutiny that the interim works must be done first and that becomes the position, that is very different from where we were when we were initially discussing the general scheme. This is because the general scheme has a transitional provision just to roll the interim scheme into the overall scheme, so it is almost like a scheme that has two parts. Right across the State all the interim works would have to be done first and then we would move on to the other works. We just need to think that through. I am not against the proposition because it makes eminent sense but it is a big shift from what is in the general scheme. It is also a big shift in terms of cost because the €100 million Caroline Timmins mentioned earlier is not €100 million for this scheme but €100 million for all defects, namely, Leinster pyrite, defective blocks, interim, retrospective and new schemes. It will be more money than we had in previous years but if we prioritise certain categories of work, they are the ones that have to get funded.</p>
          <p eId="para_346"> Likewise, we are introducing - and I am not opposed to it at all - not just retrospective cost in terms of remediation works but other costs that were incurred by OMCs as a consequence of defects. Obviously insurance is one but there is, for example, an ancillary grant provision in the defective concrete block scheme that covers the cost of storage and accommodation during works. When we were in the scheme in the docklands, families had to move out for two years-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_297">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_347">€4,500 a month.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_298">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_348">Their insurance policy paid for a portion of that but only a portion. All I want to do is highlight that if we are now moving towards making the case for those as a committee, which we will obviously discuss in private session, we need to be very clear that means we are talking not just about retrospective payment of remediation costs but also about ancillary grants, some of which would be retrospective, for costs incurred as a consequence of defects existing. None of those things are in this scheme and they need to be thought through.</p>
          <p eId="para_349"> On the issue of fire alarms, and Mr. Montague, Ms Dunkin or Mr. Doran should correct me if I am wrong, not all fire alarm systems are defective. That begs a question which we are going to have to grapple with in the pre-legislative scrutiny report. There will be fire alarm systems that were defectively installed which will therefore be covered by the interim scheme and-or the wider scheme. There will also be a lot which are not defective but will need upgrading or to be replaced but the OMC does not have the money. I am not arguing that the State should pay for those. If the witnesses want to make that case, that is fine, but I am arguing that those works are going to have to be done. On whether the State pays for them up front and places a 0% interest rate charge on the OMC to be repaid over time, without that the fire service is not going to sign off on that bit of stage three of the process. We have raised it with the Department but it has not responded. Ultimately, that is a political decision; it is not a Civil Service decision. We cannot have a situation where there are some fire safety defects, for example, like a fire escape, and there are maintenance issues around fire alarms, and the works cannot proceed because the OMC does not have the money to upgrade the fire systems.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_299">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_350">As a case in point, we had a meeting this morning and one of the people at it was talking about how in their complex, they had done the defects remediation work themselves. They want to bring their alarm system up to date but they have had to put that on hold because they used their sinking fund towards the remediation costs as well as imposing a levy of about €15,000 or €16,000 per owner. They have nothing left in the tank.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_300">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_351">That is less of a concern to me, so long as they are retrospectively reimbursed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_301">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_352">That is the point but they cannot proceed with the other stuff until they get the money back.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_302">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_353">My point is a different one. At least they had a sinking fund and they were able to dip into it to fix some urgent stuff.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_303">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_354">Correct.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_304">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_355">Where an OMC does not have a sinking fund and does not have the wherewithal to bring its fire alarm system up to standard, we are going to have a problem. On some of the pathfinder projects, there were some issues that were not originally seen as defects but then on further inspection, it was discovered that they were defective. On some of these things like the lighting systems and fire alarms, there are going to be a lot of poor maintenance cases.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_305">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_356">Absolutely.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_306">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_357">The committee would be on stronger ground not if we are asking for the State to pay for that but to pay for it, in the first instance, and to then have a mechanism to recoup it over time, so long as it is on a 0% interest basis, for example.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_307">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_358">I do not think that we would have a problem with that because the principle has been agreed that issues to do with the lack of maintenance by the owners' management company is not a defect. To be fair, in the cases the Deputy talked about, some of the pathfinders were quite generous in terms of their interpretations of what was a defect and what was not. The amount of money involved in each case was very small. The Deputy is right. Some of the OMCs would be challenged to have the money to do that. It would be a lost opportunity not to do it, when we are doing other stuff as it would ensure that people have that protection.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_308">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_359">It is important to understand that it is more fundamental than that. Dublin Fire Brigade is not going to sign off on its portion of stage three unless it is assured that all of those works are done, whether they are defects are not.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_309">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_360">Absolutely.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_310">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_361">We will therefore not be able to proceed to stage four without a fix for that. I am highlighting it because, from the sounds of it, the Department has removed the ownership of common areas from the criteria, which is great.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_311">
          <from> Mr. Pat Montague<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_362">It is brilliant. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#EoinOBroin" eId="spk_312">
          <from>Deputy Eoin Ó Broin<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_363">Equally, we have to find a fix for the maintenance upgrades, where the OMC does not have the wherewithal. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_313">
          <from> Mr. Sam Doran<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_364">I just want to quickly add something. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_314">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_365">We have gone over time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_315">
          <from> Mr. Sam Doran<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_366">The OMCs cannot get finance. The banks will not lend to them because they have no assets to secure a loan against. The Deputy referred to a 0% loan. That would be a way out of it for them because they cannot borrow money. The only thing they can do is go back and hit people with levies again. Levies do not work. Even Leo Varadkar paid a levy. He told me that a third paid, a third would not and a third could not, so the works could not be carried out on his building either. What do they do then? They put levies on people and then take legal action against them. We know of people around the country where levies were imposed on them regarding fire works. They have been before the courts and their credit rating is now gone and they are destroyed. Ruthless management agents then moved the levy onto the management fee, so that they could charge more interest at 20%. These people are now stuck in limbo because they cannot do anything. If there was a mechanism where management companies could apply to the State for a 0% loan, I think they would be only too delighted to do that and to pay it back. It is a good idea.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_316">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-12-04T18:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_367">I thank Mr. Doran, Ms Dunkin and Mr. Montague for coming in, not just today, but on numerous occasions. We thank them for their work and advocacy as they continue to highlight this issue that affects 54,000 apartments. It is important to acknowledge Caroline Timmins from the Department. We plan to have another discussion with representatives from the Department. We originally had it pencilled in for next Tuesday but we might have to move it to Thursday as it clashes with other committee and Seanad commitments. I think the defective block scheme is in the Seanad. I thank the witnesses. We will work on a report. I would like to see us agree on a report prior to Christmas.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_8"> The joint committee adjourned at 6:08 p.m. until 3 p.m. on Tuesday, 9 December 2025.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
