<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#debates">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_social_protection_rural_and_community_development/2025-07-16/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_social_protection_rural_and_community_development/2025-07-16/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-07-16" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#author" href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/34/joint_committee_on_social_protection_rural_and_community_development"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_social_protection_rural_and_community_development/2025-07-16/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_social_protection_rural_and_community_development/2025-07-16/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-07-16" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_social_protection_rural_and_community_development/2025-07-16/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_social_protection_rural_and_community_development/2025-07-16/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-07-23" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#debates">
        <TLCPerson eId="AnneRabbitte" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Anne-Rabbitte.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Anne Rabbitte"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="CatherineArdagh" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Catherine-Ardagh.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Catherine Ardagh"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ConorDMcGuinness" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Conor-D-McGuinness.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Conor D McGuinness"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JoeFlaherty" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Joe-Flaherty.D.2020-02-08" showAs="Joe Flaherty"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JohnnyGuirke" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Johnny-Guirke.D.2020-02-08" showAs="Johnny Guirke"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JohnPaulOShea" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/John-Paul-O'Shea.D.2024-11-29" showAs="John Paul O'Shea"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="LouiseOReilly" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Louise-O'Reilly.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Louise O'Reilly"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MichealCarrigy" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Micheál-Carrigy.S.2020-03-30" showAs="Micheál Carrigy"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="NoelODonovan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Noel-O'Donovan.S.2025-01-29" showAs="Noel O'Donovan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PatTheCopeGallagher" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Pat-the-Cope-Gallagher.D.1981-06-30" showAs="Pat the Cope Gallagher"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PeterRoche" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Peter-Roche.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Peter Roche"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="SarahOReilly" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Sarah-O'Reilly.S.2025-01-29" showAs="Sarah O'Reilly"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="WilliamAird" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/William-Aird.D.2024-11-29" showAs="William Aird"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/chair" showAs="Chair" eId="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/vice_chairman" showAs="Vice Chairman" eId="Vice_Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/author" showAs="author" eId="author"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/editor" showAs="editor" eId="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>AN COMHCHOISTE UM CHOIMIRCE SHÓISIALACH, FORBAIRT TUAITHE AGUS POBAIL</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>Joint Committee on Social Protection, Rural and Community Development</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2025-07-16">Dé Céadaoin, 16 Iúil 2025</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2025-07-16">Wednesday, 16 July 2025</docDate>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_en">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_ga">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">Tháinig an Comhchoiste le chéile ag 09:30 a.m.</summary>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">The Joint Committee met at 09:30 a.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_3">Comhaltaí a bhí i láthair / Members present:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_1">Teachtaí Dála / Deputies</p>
              </th>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_2">Seanadóirí / Senators</p>
              </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#WilliamAird">William Aird</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#ImeldaGoldsboro">Imelda Goldsboro</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#CatherineArdagh">Catherine Ardagh</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#NoelODonovan">Noel O'Donovan</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#PatTheCopeGallagher">Pat the Cope Gallagher</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#SarahOReilly">Sarah O'Reilly</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_9">
                  <person refersTo="#JohnnyGuirke">Johnny Guirke</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_10">
                  <person refersTo="#AnneRabbitte">Anne Rabbitte.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_11">
                  <person refersTo="#LouiseOReilly">Louise O'Reilly</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_12">
                  <person refersTo="#PeterRoche">Peter Roche.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_4">I láthair / In attendance: Deputies Micheál Carrigy and Conor D. McGuinness and Senator Joe Flaherty.</summary>
          <summary eId="sum_5">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#JohnPaulOShea">Teachta / Deputy John Paul O'Shea sa Chathaoir / in the Chair.</person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
        <summary eId="sum_6">
          <i> The joint committee met in private session until 9.44 a.m.</i>
        </summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Engagement on Matters Relating to the Auto-Enrolment Retirement Savings Scheme: Department of Social Protection<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T09:40:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_1">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T09:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_13">Before we begin, I will read a note on privilege and housekeeping matters. Witnesses and members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice that they should not criticise or make charges against any person or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable or otherwise engage in speech that would be regarded as damaging to the good name of the person or entity. Therefore, if their statements are potentially defamatory in relation to an identifiable person or entity, they will be directed to discontinue their remarks. It is imperative that they comply with any such direction I make.</p>
          <p eId="para_14"> Members attending remotely are reminded of the constitutional requirement that, to participate in public meetings, members must be physically present within the confines of the Leinster House complex. This is due to the constitutional requirement that, to participate in public meetings, members must be physically present within the confines of the place where Parliament has chosen to sit. In this regard, I ask any members participating on Microsoft Teams to confirm they are on the grounds of the Leinster House complex if they wish to make contributions. I remind all those in attendance to make sure their mobile phones are switched off or in silent mode.</p>
          <p eId="para_15"> Auto-enrolment is a new savings scheme that will be introduced on 1 January 2026. It is designed to help over 800,000 workers to begin saving for their retirement. The committee welcomes this engagement with officials and looks forward to receiving an update on the introduction of auto-enrolment and the body that will administer the scheme.</p>
          <p eId="para_16"> I welcome the officials from the Department of Social Protection: Mr. Tim Duggan, assistant secretary general; Ms Clare Dowling, principal officer; and Mr. Donal Spellman, principal officer. I invite Mr Duggan to make his opening remarks.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_2">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T09:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_17">The introduction of the auto-enrolment retirement savings system, called My Future Fund, is one of the programme for Government’s key reform commitments to support workers. The Minister has made it clear since his appointment earlier this year that it is a key priority for him.</p>
          <p eId="para_18"> Such a scheme is necessary to address the considerable pension coverage gap that exists in Ireland, where it is estimated that only 35% of private sector workers are in pension schemes despite the fact that successive Governments over many decades have provided very significant incentivisation through tax relief. If not addressed, this low level of coverage means that people in retirement will either be entirely dependent on whatever State pension they can qualify for or will have to rely on assets they have accumulated otherwise. This may result in many people suffering a significant drop in living standards in retirement compared to the period of their working lives. Even where people may already be in a scheme, it seems that many of them may not be saving enough to ensure an adequate income in retirement that is commensurate with their lifestyles.</p>
          <p eId="para_19"> It is important to note that, contrary to the views expressed by some commentators, the State pension will remain the bedrock of the Irish State pension system, providing retirees with a basic level of income and protecting them against pensioner poverty. In that context, My Future Fund will not replace but simply complement the State pension and provide additional or supplementary income to future retirees to secure their standard of living in retirement.</p>
          <p eId="para_20"> The legislation to underpin this new system, the Automatic Enrolment Retirement Savings System Act 2024, became law in July 2024. The system has been branded My Future Fund, as this reflects the purpose of the scheme, which is to save and invest for the future, while highlighting that these savings will be the personal property of the participants. That is a key point.</p>
          <p eId="para_21"> The Minister has announced that the system itself will commence collecting and investing contributions from 1 January 2026, just a short five and a half months away. While the previous Government had scheduled 30 September 2025 for this launch, the Minister felt it prudent to reschedule it by a few short months to provide some additional lead-in time for employers, particularly small and micro enterprises, to prepare and be compliant with the legislation from the start. It also allows the new system to be fully aligned with the standard tax year, and it provides additional time for payroll developers and providers to ready and test their systems for the launch.</p>
          <p eId="para_22"> There are three core principles underpinning the scheme. The first is that the scheme facilitates choice but never requires it. Default options are automatically employed wherever somebody does not exercise the choice that is available to him or her. That in itself makes it much easier for participants. The second principle is that the scheme facilitates a pot-follows-member approach, which means that where an employee moves from employment to employment over his or her career, that employee can maintain the exact same My Future Fund account without having to start a new one and park the other one. Third, the system is automated through payroll to minimise the administrative burden for employers, especially those that do not have expertise in operating pension schemes. By that, I mean they do not have to set one up, set up trustees or administer a scheme, and they do not have to do anything at all in terms of paperwork.</p>
          <p eId="para_23"> Those earning in excess of €20,000 per annum across any number of employments, aged over 23 and under 60, and not already contributing to an occupational or private pension scheme through payroll, will be automatically enrolled. It is expected that approximately 750,000 workers will be enrolled in this way, most of them being brought into a retirement savings scheme for the very first time. Participants will be able to opt out after six months of participation, that is, in months seven and eight, at which time they will get their own contributions back, but the employer and State contributions will remain in their accounts.</p>
          <p eId="para_24">Participants may also opt out in months seven and eight after a rate increase, which I will cover shortly, and receive back the difference between the new and old contribution rates, but the employer and State contributions will again remain in their accounts. At any other time, participants will be able to suspend their participation for up to two years. If they suspend, they will not get a refund of contributions. In all cases where a person opts out or suspends, he or she will be automatically re-enrolled after two years, after which opt-out and suspension options will be available again. Anybody who is outside the age and income thresholds may voluntarily opt into the scheme. Where people do, their employers and the State will be compelled by the law to contribute as if they had been automatically enrolled. Contributions will be made equally by employees and employers, with the State providing a top-up of €1 for every €3 saved by an employee. In short, every €3 saved by an employee will automatically become €7. Contributions will start at 1.5% of gross pay, increasing to 3% after three years of operation, 4.5% after a further three years of operation, and finally 6% in year 10 and from then on. This will, in effect, add up to 14% of an employee’s gross earnings and is the very least that international evidence suggests is an adequate rate of saving. This incremental implementation of contribution rates is designed to allow employees and employers to adjust over time.</p>
          <p eId="para_25"> This money will then be invested. Participants will be able to choose from three investment options: low-risk, medium-risk and higher risk options. However, and in keeping with the principles I outlined, they will not need to choose. If they do not, they will be defaulted into a lifestyle strategy based on age, which will be de-risked as they approach the State pension age of 66. Up to the age of 51, a person’s pot will be invested in the higher risk option. Between the age of 51 and 61, a person’s pot will be moved and invested in the medium-risk option. Between the ages of 61 and 66, a person’s pot will be invested in the low-risk option. If people do not want the lifestyle approach, they can choose which risk option they prefer at any age.</p>
          <p eId="para_26"> People will be able to access their pots once they reach the State pension age of 66. In the first few years of the scheme, draw-down will be limited to a lump sum payment because pots will be relatively small. Taxation arrangements are being provided for separately in the Finance Bill and will broadly align with the tax treatment of PRSAs, including the application of the tax treatment of trivial pensions. Further draw-down options may be developed over the coming years alongside the annuity and ARF options that are already available from the pensions market. All of this will be managed and regulated by a new State body, called the national automatic enrolment retirement savings authority, NAERSA. The authority will determine who will be enrolled, electronically issue notifications of this information to payroll systems, collect the contributions and pool them for onward investment with investment managers. It will provide portals for employees, employers and their agents to access accounts and services. It will provide a customer support service both over the phone and electronically. It will ensure compliance with the scheme by following up where contributions are not collected and remitted, up to and including through the imposition of sanctions, penalties and prosecutions if need be.</p>
          <p eId="para_27"> We have made excellent progress in getting everything ready for the launch in January. Following an extensive procurement exercise, Tata Consultancy Services, TCS, based in Letterkenny, County Donegal, has been appointed as a managed service provider of the scheme’s administrative services and is busy building, configuring and testing its systems in line with the scheme’s requirements. This will result in the creation of quite a number of positions in Letterkenny, certainly north of 100. Three investment managers, namely, Irish Life Investment Managers, Amundi and BlackRock, have been selected, again following an extensive public procurement exercise, as the investment managers for the scheme. These are busy readying their funds and developing and testing integration with TCS.</p>
          <p eId="para_28"> We are working extensively with in excess of 60 payroll product developers across a range of payroll providers through the Payroll Software Developers Association, PSDA. We are assisting them with the changes they need to make to their software to facilitate the calculation and collection of My Future Fund contributions. I thank and compliment the members of the PSDA for their intense engagement with us, especially over the past nine months.</p>
          <p eId="para_29"> I acknowledge the considerable development and testing work we are doing with colleagues in the Revenue Commissioners, which will be providing NAERSA with the vital payslip data that will allow us to make enrolment determinations in the first place. We are making considerable progress in staffing and resourcing the new authority. The recruitment of its chief executive officer is at its final stage this week, as is the selection of board members. Competitions are under way for the senior management positions reporting to the CEO. Various competition types will be run over the remainder of the summer and into the autumn for all other staff positions. In addition, we are fitting out accommodation in our Letterkenny offices for the new authority.</p>
          <p eId="para_30"> We have already conducted significant communications exercises over the past year. We ran a general awareness campaign on a couple of occasions. However, we focused primarily over the past year on direct employer outreach through webinars and in-person conferences and we have reached many thousands of employers in that way. This will continue and intensify over the coming months. Members might have noticed a step change in our communications campaign over the past ten days as we launched our second-phase information campaign for the general public with television, radio, billboard, public transport and social media advertisements featuring the ice cream. In all cases, we refer people back to our auto-enrolment hub, which has vast quantities of information to explain the scheme to all types of stakeholders. This campaign will intensify considerably over the coming months.</p>
          <p eId="para_31"> I believe we are well prepared for go-live from 1 January 2026. I expect the scheme to be a truly transformative once it is up and going. I hope this very quick summary, coupled with the booklet I hope members got in advance, has given an understanding of the scheme and how it works.</p>
          <p eId="para_32"> Clare Dowling, who is sitting beside me, looks after the policy, legislation, communications and investment aspects of the project, and Donal Spellman looks after administrative and technical operations and integration aspects. Between the three of us, we will do our best to answer any questions members may have.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_3">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_33">I thank Mr. Duggan. I appreciate the remarks. I will now proceed to members for a discussion. First up is Deputy Louise O'Reilly.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LouiseOReilly" eId="spk_4">
          <from>Deputy Louise O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_34">I thank our witnesses. I have a couple of questions, some about the operation of the scheme and some, obviously, about the run-in to it. How many deadlines have been missed? September was the latest. How many other announcements were there? Were there two or three dates missed? It has been put back a few times.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_5">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_35">The only official date ever announced was 30 September of this year, and that was set in a commencement order.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LouiseOReilly" eId="spk_6">
          <from>Deputy Louise O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_36">There were a couple of others.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_7">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_37">There have been ministerial ambitions regarding dates.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LouiseOReilly" eId="spk_8">
          <from>Deputy Louise O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_38">And those have all slipped by along with the official one. Given that several deadlines have slipped past, is the Department confident it will be ready for the latest announced deadline?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_9">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_39">I am absolutely confident.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LouiseOReilly" eId="spk_10">
          <from>Deputy Louise O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_40">Would the Department have been in a position to proceed on the September date had the Government pressed ahead with that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_11">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_41">We believe we would have been.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LouiseOReilly" eId="spk_12">
          <from>Deputy Louise O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_42">Therefore, is Mr. Duggan saying it is the employers that are causing the delay or that business was not ready?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_13">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T09:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_43">I do not view it as a delay in that sense; I view it more as a rescheduling, and that is the view of the Minister. Payroll providers, employers and others said it would be helpful to them and make it easier if they could align the system with the tax year, zeroising their payrolls and the development work they do around budget time rather than trying to do it in advance.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LouiseOReilly" eId="spk_14">
          <from>Deputy Louise O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_44">Was the September date announced without any consultation with business? I wonder how that could have happened if they are so adamant now that they are not ready for it. The Department pressed ahead with a date in September and now that is being "delayed" again. I hope Mr. Duggan does not mind if I describe it in that way. Was there a miscommunication? I have got some details through freedom of information requests and I know the Department was lobbied fairly extensively by firms in this space. Were the companies telling the Department that while it was pushing for a September deadline, or were they not saying that and then when the Department put in a start date of September they said they would not be ready? How can we have confidence that this is going to go ahead on the specified date, given that a number of dates have slipped? At what point did the companies start telling the Department they were not ready? Was it after September was announced or was it in advance of it but the Department announced it anyway? Does Mr. Duggan see what I mean?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_15">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_45">Once the 30 September implementation date was announced sometime last year, people started to properly turn their attention to the implementation and over time it crystallised for them how it would be easier if it was pushed out by a couple of months to facilitate budget changes at the same time. That became clearer to them once they started working on it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LouiseOReilly" eId="spk_16">
          <from>Deputy Louise O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_46">Was this a specific request of industry? Mr. Duggan was lobbied by State Street Global Advisors Europe. The Minister was lobbied by the Irish Association of Pension Funds and the Payroll Software Developers Association and others. At what stage did they start telling Mr. Duggan that they were not ready?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_17">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_47">It is not so much that they were not ready, it is that they would prefer more time and it would make it easier for them if they were able to do this in conjunction with budget changes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LouiseOReilly" eId="spk_18">
          <from>Deputy Louise O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_48">So they were ready but they wanted a delay anyway.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_19">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_49">I do not know. We are talking about-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LouiseOReilly" eId="spk_20">
          <from>Deputy Louise O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_50">Mr. Duggan was the one in the meeting with them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_21">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_51">We are talking about 130,000-odd employers who have 60 different payroll software systems and hundreds of payroll providers. As to whether I can tell the Deputy all of them would have been ready by the 30 September deadline, no I cannot, but what I can tell her is that they are working and they have been working extensively on getting ready.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LouiseOReilly" eId="spk_22">
          <from>Deputy Louise O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_52">Mr. Duggan cannot tell me that 130,000 are ready but he can tell me that 130,000 are working on it. There have been a lot of false dawns with auto-enrolment. It strikes me that it has not been well handled. That is not any disrespect to Mr. Duggan and his colleagues, as a lot of it is down to Government decisions. I understand there has only been one official date but a number of announcements have slipped. Is Mr. Duggan in a position to tell me what is different about this announcement and if he believes it will happen unlike other potential announcements?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_23">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_53">The Government has decided it will be 1 January. The Minister has made it clear that it will be 1 January. We are putting in contracts. We have put in contracts that specify that the work must be done to facilitate that timeline. There are commercial, political and legal commitments to 1 January. I assume-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LouiseOReilly" eId="spk_24">
          <from>Deputy Louise O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_54">Were none of those commitments in place for 30 September?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_25">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_55">Deputy O'Reilly's time is up.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LouiseOReilly" eId="spk_26">
          <from>Deputy Louise O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_56">It is just one question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_27">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_57">The contract for investment managers is being put in place as we speak. That did not exist for 30 September.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_28">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_58">I call Deputy Ardagh.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineArdagh" eId="spk_29">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Ardagh<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_59">I thank the witnesses very much for coming in. We have been waiting for auto-enrolment for a long time. I remember being in the Seanad when the then Minister for Social Protection, Leo Varadkar, first discussed it. It is a step change when it comes to pensions in Ireland. So many people are looking forward to having their own separate pension. It is long overdue. As an employer I thought we would have to start earlier. We were ready to start. People are waiting for this. As other speakers have said, I hope we do not skip the date again because it must be done this time. We need to see this start in January.</p>
          <p eId="para_60"> I have a few short questions. My Future Fund is the new name for the project. We just heard about it last week. What is the rationale for rebranding?</p>
          <p eId="para_61"> I would like to know a little bit more about Tata Consultancy Services. Could Mr. Duggan let the committee know about any previous projects it engaged on? Some background on the company would be very useful.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_30">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_62">As to My Future Fund, it was never going to be called the auto-enrolment scheme. That is just a horrible phrase. It was always going to have a brand name and it was eventually worked out in the normal way brands are developed with creative agencies and so on.</p>
          <p eId="para_63"> My Future Fund was chosen because, as I said in my opening statement, it reflects what it is, namely about saving for the future. It is about having a fund for your retirement and about it being yours. It is not like the State pension where you are just part of a big State apparatus, it is your fund. The money in it is yours and nobody else's. The brand is designed to reflect those principles.</p>
          <p eId="para_64"> Tata is a monstrous global company with in excess of 600 million employees worldwide. It is involved in all kinds of business lines. One of the companies within Tata is Tata Consultancy Services, which does business processing, IT systems, managed services and all of that kind of stuff. It does not yet have a great deal of significant contracts in the Irish public service, but it does do a similar job in the UK to the auto-enrolment job it is doing for us, where it is the managed service provider to Nest, the largest auto-enrolment provider in the UK that is operated by the British Government. It has huge experience in running systems and administrations of this type. It also has huge resources available to it to implement the system and to operate it. Tata has some 1,400 plus personnel in Letterkenny already, many of them working on the pension administration system for Nest in the UK, and it will be expanding that workforce to cater for the provision of this service.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#CatherineArdagh" eId="spk_31">
          <from>Deputy Catherine Ardagh<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_65">I thank Mr. Duggan. I wish him and the Department well. I know a significant amount of work has gone into this. The Minister, Deputy Calleary, has done a significant amount of work in the run-up to this going ahead. I hope we see it take off in January. I wish Mr. Duggan the best of luck. I thank him for coming in.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_32">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_66">I thank the Deputy.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnneRabbitte" eId="spk_33">
          <from>Senator Anne Rabbitte<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_67">I thank the witnesses for the presentation this morning. I have three short questions and perhaps a little bit of explanation. I have read the statement and I have listened to the contributions. Could Mr. Duggan confirm the fee structure for members of the plan? Will it be based annually on the AMC or is it combined with a fixed fee? If you do not mind, Chair, I will get the responses as I ask the question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_34">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_68">That is no problem.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_35">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_69">Could I just correct one thing first, I said 600 million employees. I got really excited. I am sorry, it is 600,000-plus employees. Six hundred million would be amazing. I am sorry about that.</p>
          <p eId="para_70"> The fee structure will have two components. There will be a flat fee for the administration and an AMC application for the investment piece. When combined, we expect those to be less than 0.5% of assets under management. We are still working on what precisely the flat fee structure will be, but it is likely to be in the region of 50 cent to 60 cent a week per person, which would amount to approximately a cup of coffee every two months.</p>
          <p eId="para_71"> I cannot yet reveal the investment management charges because we have not finalised the contracts with the providers. In the RFT that we specified to the market we said they had to be less than ten basis points, which is 0.1%. All of the bids that we got significantly beat that. I can assure the committee that the AMC charge will be very low single basis points, which, when we compare with other products on the market, is a phenomenal reduction.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnneRabbitte" eId="spk_36">
          <from>Senator Anne Rabbitte<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_72">To build on that point, will the same fee structure be adjusted for members depending on the amount of funds they contribute to it? Is it the same cup of coffee for people regardless of whether they are on €20,000 or €80,000? How is the fee adjusted?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_37">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_73">The administration fee is the same for everybody because administration is the same for everybody, in the same way that a loaf of bread is the same for everybody. As the investment management charges are based on a percentage of the assets under management, they are dependent on how much you save. Somebody with a small pot will pay a small charge while somebody with a large pot will pay a larger charge. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnneRabbitte" eId="spk_38">
          <from>Senator Anne Rabbitte<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_74">It will be adjusted depending on the fund size. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_39">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_75">It is adjusted based on the fund size, yes. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnneRabbitte" eId="spk_40">
          <from>Senator Anne Rabbitte<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_76">In relation to taxation, how will the member's fund be treated upon death? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_41">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_77">It depends on when the person dies. If a person dies in advance of reaching retirement age, it becomes an asset within the person's estate and is handled in that way, through the estate distribution.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnneRabbitte" eId="spk_42">
          <from>Senator Anne Rabbitte<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_78">Is it subject to income tax or not?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_43">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_79">The tax arrangements for My Future Fund will be set out by the Department of Finance in the forthcoming finance Bill. I am told they will mirror what is currently done for PRSAs, including how trivial funds are handled, as I said in the opening statement. For PRSAs a 25% lump sum is tax free and then the rest has to be invested and drawn down over time. In the case of a trivial pension, which is a pot of less than €30,000, it can be drawn down tax free regardless of whether it is in excess of 25% of the fund or not.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnneRabbitte" eId="spk_44">
          <from>Senator Anne Rabbitte<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_80">Further to last night's discussions in the Seanad regarding the bereavement Bill which is passing through the Houses, does the treatment differ depending on whether the beneficiary is a spouse, a child or another relation? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_45">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_81">I am not a tax expert. Whatever the tax treatment is for any kind of pension arrangement, dependent on the relationship with the person who owned that pot, will be exactly the same as if it was a PRSA. If a person with a PRSA dies, that goes to their estate and is distributed within their estate and the tax treatment applied to that is the same tax treatment that will be applied to My Future Fund, depending on whether the beneficiary is a spouse, a child or some other relative, or not a relative at all. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_46">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_82">I welcome the witnesses. It is a very exciting day. I am delighted to be a member of this committee. We will be remembered for all time when it comes to January for having given a helping hand to everybody to be in a pension scheme. I wish the scheme well. It is an onerous task to get something like this up and running. It will benefit everybody in the working community. It is very exciting for people starting off in a career. Many people who are half or three quarters of the way through their working careers would love to have had this at the initial stages. It is being set up now. It is an equal spread across. The Government will make the same contribution to everybody, which is very good. Going forward, it will be an incentive for people to save and to continue their standard of living when they retire. At the moment there are huge anomalies in the system. People had to give up work many years ago because when women married it was not permissible to work in sections of the workforce at that time. Those people are now dependent on their spouses for their old-age pension. It is totally wrong. That has to be fixed. This is a very exciting opportunity. I do not know how anybody could not be in favour of this. I am delighted to be a TD to be present here today. </p>
          <p eId="para_83"> I wish Letterkenny very well. It is getting many jobs out of this. It is a pity it is not coming to Laois. I would be shocking excited altogether if it was coming to Laois. Unfortunately, it is not. When it starts up, a great many people will have questions on it. I hope there will be a special line of communication for all of those people. I thank the officials and the Minister. I look forward to 1 January for the inaugural part of this. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_47">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_84">I thank the Deputy and very much appreciate his remarks. The Minister is disappointed it is not in Ballina. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyGuirke" eId="spk_48">
          <from>Deputy Johnny Guirke<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_85">When money is invested, the return on it is not known. That will depend on how the investment does over time. When signing up for this scheme, people will not know what they will be able to draw down on reaching pension age. Senator Rabbitte touched on the tax implications. That is the aspect people will probably look at when deciding whether to invest in the scheme. For example, if the fund makes 100% over the lifetime of a person investing in it, will he or she be able to draw down that 100% or would it be a percentage of that 100%? Somebody has to pay for the hundred employees in Letterkenny and the communications campaign around this. Depending on the percentage it makes, what percentage of the fund would the person be entitled to, come retirement age? Will it be a tax-free lump sum? What effect that might it have on small businesses where they have to pay €3 per employee? I refer to small businesses such as corner shops and cafés. That is not a negative take on the scheme; it is just to find out for myself and for others what the implications are when it comes to investing and drawing down. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_49">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_86">The treatment at drawdown will depend on a number of factors. The first is how big a fund the person has. The second factor is the various drawdown products that may or may not be available when they do it and the third is how that is dealt with in taxation terms. What is definitive, though, is that once a person's pot is crystallised on retirement there will be no charge on that pot for the national automatic enrolment retirement savings authority, NAERSA, or Tata Consultancy Services, TCS. NAERSA and TCS are paid from the administration charges that are applied every week on every contribution so there will be no charge on the pot when it is drawn down at retirement to pay for administration. </p>
          <p eId="para_87"> As I said to Senator Rabbitte, based on discussions with finance officials my understanding is that drawdown from My Future Fund will be taxed in the same way that PRSAs are taxed. The simple explanation for that is that a person will be able to draw down 25% of their pot as a tax-free lump sum and the rest will go into some kind of pension vehicle. That could be an annuity, an approved retirement fund, ARF, or it could be something new that is developed over the coming years. One of the jobs of NAERSA will be to look at options for drawdown products for participants in this scheme. It is not necessary to have them right now because anyone who is automatically enrolled in My Future Fund from January next year will be in it for at least six years before drawing anything down. There is time to look at options that are available and try to build something that is particularly useful for the participants in My Future Fund. There are no administration charges on the drawdown and the tax treatment is going to be the same as applies to PRSAs. If a person's fund is less than €30,000 when drawn down, the trivial pensions taxation arrangements apply, which means they can draw it all down as a lump sum. NAERSA will be looking at developing products and possibly engaging with the market to develop new products for drawdown that are particularly suited to participants of My Future Fund. An example of that might be a combination whereby it is not necessary to choose between an annuity or an ARF. A person might be able to draw down part as a lump sum, put some of it into an annuity to guarantee a particular level of income every week for the rest of his or her life, and put some of it into an investment vehicle so that it continues to grow over the period of retirement.</p>
          <p eId="para_88">There is no such hybrid product on the market right now, but there is a possibility that could be designed over the coming years and made available through My Future Fund. That will be explored.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnnyGuirke" eId="spk_50">
          <from>Deputy Johnny Guirke<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_89">What is the effect on small businesses? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_51">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_90">Undoubtedly, this is an additional cost for someone who is employing people. However, it has been deliberately designed - some people have criticised this because they say it takes too long to get to the maximum rate and the level of contribution is too low - that instead of introducing the contribution at 6% from the beginning, it is phased in over a decade to allow employers and employees to adjust budget-wise to this new cost on employment. The experience in other countries has shown that when it is introduced on a gradual basis like this, it becomes part of the normal remuneration negotiation that goes on between employers, employees and employee representatives on a continuous basis. Over that ten-year period, even though it starts out as a cost on employment, it should work its way into the normal remuneration packages of employees as part of those negotiations.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatTheCopeGallagher" eId="spk_52">
          <from>Deputy Pat the Cope Gallagher<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_91">I thank Mr. Duggan for his presentation. I welcome the principle of auto-enrolment. When this was being formulated, and it was in gestation for some time, were there communications with IBEC or small businesses? Those of us who come from rural areas will always think of the additional costs on companies. The interesting thing about this scheme is that I have not heard too many complaining. I hope that is a good sign and that they want to be part of it because if their staff are happy, it is a good reflection on the company. </p>
          <p eId="para_92"> I welcome the additional jobs for Letterkenny. It brings me back many years when I turned the first sod on behalf of Dr. Michael Woods, who was Minister for social welfare at the time, when the building that is there now was built. How many jobs will be created in Letterkenny if additional facilities are required? What will be the grades of those jobs? Will it be largely clerical officers or executive officers? Will a new panel be established nationally or is there a significant number on the panel at the moment to be able to draw down from that?</p>
          <p eId="para_93"> Auto-enrolment is important for those who would not have had a pension otherwise. To take a hypothetical case, for someone aged 55 at the moment who is faced with only the non-contributory old age pension, at what stage will that person be in a position to avail of the full pension if he or she buys into this system?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_53">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_94">There has been extensive consultation with both employer and employee representatives of all kinds since we started this project for real back in 2017. When we produced what we call the "strawman proposal", we engaged in a major public consultation exercise at that time. We toured the country and visited many centres. We held open public forum meetings. We did online surveys, focus groups and all that kind of stuff. Emerging from that was this ten-year lead-in time, going from a low contribution level up to the maximum contribution level. That idea emerged from that consultation exercise because both employee representatives and employer representatives felt that going much faster than that would be too penal and result in too great an income shock and cost shock for employers.</p>
          <p eId="para_95"> Extensive consultation has continued with employer and employee representatives through the Labour Employer Economic Forum, the LEEF structure, that the Government operates but also bilaterally. We have had many meetings IBEC. We have had meetings with ISME, small firms and numerous other employer representative bodies. We have run numerous webinars with all of them over the past two years to try to ensure that they are up to speed as possible with their obligations under this scheme.</p>
          <p eId="para_96"> The Deputy is right. Most employers - in fact, practically all of them - are fully supportive of the scheme. Even now, recognising that it is a cost on their business, at least initially, they are still supportive of it because they see the value and benefit of it.</p>
          <p eId="para_97"> In terms of additional employment in Letterkenny, there are two parts to it. There is the additional employment that will be generated in TCS as a result of being the managed service provider of administration services for the scheme. As I noted in my opening statement, TCS estimates that will be in excess of 100 additional posts. When established, NAERSA will begin with in the region of 35 posts. That may increase to north of 40 eventually. There are different grade structures in that. It will be headed up by a chief executive officer at the deputy Secretary General level. He or she will have three senior managers reporting at principal officer and director level. The other 30 staff will be spread over assistant principal, higher executive officer, executive officer and clerical officer levels. The competition for the CEO is concluding this week. For the three senior managers, the competition will be concluding during August. We are running competitions and expressions of interest for all of the other positions over the course of August, September and October.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatTheCopeGallagher" eId="spk_54">
          <from>Deputy Pat the Cope Gallagher<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_98">Will the roles be specifically for Letterkenny when applicants are being invited?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_55">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_99">All posts are in Letterkenny.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PatTheCopeGallagher" eId="spk_56">
          <from>Deputy Pat the Cope Gallagher<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_100">I want Mr. Duggan to be fair about it. As long as 99% of them are from Donegal, we will be happy about it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_57">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_101">I am sure Donegal people will put their best foot forward to try to achieve the Deputy's wish.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NoelODonovan" eId="spk_58">
          <from>Senator Noel O'Donovan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_102">While there was a discussion about jobs coming to Letterkenny and Donegal, I hoped Mr. Duggan would bring some to west Cork as well.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_59">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_103">One would think I would.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NoelODonovan" eId="spk_60">
          <from>Senator Noel O'Donovan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_104">He might consider it. I welcome his presentation. This is a pragmatic and prudent project to deliver for this country, and not before time. Auto-enrolment is a cost on business. Businesses have had additional costs over the past number of years. Broadly, the scheme needs to be welcomed because any employer wants to keep their employee happy and plan into the future. I will make the point to the Government in the Seanad that in the years ahead we have to be mindful that it is small businesses that have additional costs. That message needs to go back through the Government.</p>
          <p eId="para_105"> Where employees have an existing pension scheme with their employer, how can that be transferred into this new pension? On the low, medium and higher risk options that will be afforded employees, I presume that is near so that will be advised in the time ahead. There could be an extra burden for employers in terms of advising employees because there will be employees who do not have pension schemes. There is the lack of information and lack of understanding. That is important information that will have to be explained and communicated to employees. How does the Department envisage that will be communicated to employees?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_61">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_106">The Senator is absolutely right. As I acknowledged, at least at the beginning this will be an additional cost on employment. It is a relatively low level, at 1.5%. All studies show that when it is done on an incremental basis over a decent period of time it becomes part of the normal remuneration negotiations and packaging. Therefore, that cost element should dissipate over time. However, the Government and the Minister are conscious that it is, even though it is relatively small, an additional cost in the beginning. That is why that phasing was done. It was to mitigate the impact of that additional cost as much as possible.</p>
          <p eId="para_107">Somebody with an existing scheme who wishes to transfer it into My Future Fund will not be facilitated at the beginning. The whole focus has been on getting the system up and going for the 750,000 people who have nothing. That will be the concentration at the beginning. However, there is a design principles document behind this scheme that the Government approved in 2022. It is publicly available but I will send it to the clerk to the committee so that members can all have a look at it if they wish. It sets out what future phases of the scheme may facilitate. One of them is that very thing, which is allowing transfers into and out of My Future Fund, if somebody were either to join an occupational scheme or were to move country and needed to move it. The intention is, once we have the system in, bedded down, operating well, and NAERSA has the capacity to start looking at options for expanding and enhancing the scheme, that one of those options would facilitate transfer in and out. That will come in time.</p>
          <p eId="para_108"> On the risk strategies and advising people on it, I said that the scheme facilitates choice but does not require it. We expect that the vast majority of people are unlikely to exercise choice at all. That has been the experience with auto-enrolment systems around the world. We expect that well north of 90% of people will not exercise that choice. That means people will go into the default strategy, which is lifestyled, as I said. If they are under the age of 51, their money will be invested in the higher risk options. In the main, those are equities, usually on a global basis. Once they reach the age of 51, their money will be transferred into medium-risk options. Typically, these are built, either on a 50:50 or 60:40 basis, on equities and bonds. The bonds can be made up of government bonds or corporate bonds, but they are primarily government or sovereign bonds. Once people reach the age of 61, their money will be transferred into low-risk funds, which are primarily government and European government bonds.</p>
          <p eId="para_109"> Employers will not know that and will not need to know it. It is not the job of employers, under My Future Fund, to provide advice to their employees on the structures, formats and options available in My Future Fund. It is NAERSA's job to do that. NAERSA will have comprehensive information on all of these matters on its portal, which people will be able to access. It will also make loads of information available through social media and, if needs be, and people prefer to receive information that way, it can be made available on paper. It is possible that NAERSA may use distribution networks throughout the country to allow leaflets, brochures and things of that nature to be distributed as well. We expect, however, that the majority of people are likely to engage electronically with NAERSA and use its portal systems.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SarahOReilly" eId="spk_62">
          <from>Senator Sarah O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_110">I thank the officials for coming. I agree this has to be broadly welcomed but, like a few people here, I am from a self-employed background. Small- and medium-sized businesses are the backbone of the area I come from. We know that they have struggled with extra costs over the past couple of years. The additional improvements to employees' wages, extra bank holidays, extra sick days and all of that are welcomed by employees but, at the same time, these are an additional burden on SMEs. It was said that this will be at a low level of 1%, but there are all these incrementals or little additionals. Has any impact assessment been done for SMEs regarding the additional payroll burden for auto-enrolment?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_63">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_111">There has not been what you would call a formal assessment with a document that states, "formal assessment of - done", but what has been done are very extensive discussions with business representative groups, from IBEC, down to ISME, the Small Firms Association, SFA, the convenience stores network association, all the hospitality ones and so on. We have had extensive engagement with all of those groupings over the past couple of years explaining this system, outlining its implications for them and hearing those very concerns that this will be an additional cost. I have acknowledged that it will be an additional cost but equally, over time, that cost impact of it will dissipate considerably. I assure the Senator that wage inflation over the next ten years will be massively in excess of 6%. I have never seen a ten-year period where it has not been. This is just an element of that wage inflation that will occur over that long period. In that way, it effectively gets consumed within that remuneration inflation. While there will be a little bit of a hit at the beginning, it will dissipate over time as the scheme is rolled out.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SarahOReilly" eId="spk_64">
          <from>Senator Sarah O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_112">In light of the bogus self-employment scandal in RTÉ, has the Department conducted any research into the potential for employers to reclassify workers? I see that as an issue that is on the increase, particularly in my own area.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_65">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_113">If employers behave badly and try to reclassify people, who are currently classified as employees paying PRSI at class A, as paying class S, then obviously other legal issues are at play there. The scope section in the Department of Social Protection would follow up on that wherever complaints are made or where it came to light that such practices were going on. In the event that somebody were found to have done that and to have engaged in bogus self-employment, they would be liable for the PRSI implications of that and NAERSA would have to use its compliance functions to chase down employee contributions that should rightly have been made to My Future Fund. You are into a whole legal piece there.</p>
          <p eId="para_114"> There are also provisions within the auto-enrolment Act to discourage employers from behaving in a way that would coerce or seek to persuade employees from not engaging in auto-enrolment, either by forcing them to opt out, suspending their participation in the scheme where they have been auto-enrolled, or dissuading them from opting into the scheme, if they wish to do that. If an employer behaves using such practices, sanctions, penalties and prosecutions can be applied under the auto-enrolment Act by NAERSA in such circumstances.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SarahOReilly" eId="spk_66">
          <from>Senator Sarah O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_115">What statutory, if any, safeguards will be in place to protect against funds being raided, as happened during the banking crash?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_67">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_116">It is very important that everyone understands this is not a State fund at all. It has nothing to do with the State, in fact. All of the money in this scheme is private money. It is exactly the same as if somebody had a PRSA. It is that person's money and does not belong to anyone else. Therefore, the only way the State can get at it is if it were to introduce an incredible piece of legislation, I would have thought, and I assume everyone in this room would have a lot to say about such a thing. It is private money and, as such, it is private property and has all of the constitutional protections that are available for private property. It would be incredibly difficult for a future government to do what the Senator might be suggesting.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_68">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_117">I have a few questions. I thank Mr. Duggan for coming in and giving us a detailed presentation. There was also a presentation in the audiovisual room this week for Members of the Oireachtas to consult a little more. It is a game-changer scheme, as all members have said. It provides that bit of security for people who have no pension other than the State pension and to have that quality of life going forward.</p>
          <p eId="para_118">I think this will be reflected upon in many years' time, to say that the decision made was a good one. I want to say thanks in particular to the Minister, Deputy Calleary, who has been here to discuss this with us and the former Minister, Heather Humphreys, as well. I also acknowledge the last Government, which took the big task on and passed the legislation in July 2024. It is good to see that. In his opening remarks, Mr. Duggan made reference to having that communication and context, when it comes. When people look at their payslips in January and see something going out and something coming in, there will obviously be questions for people. He mentioned in his statement that there will be a phone line and an email address available. This is critically important, because on 1 January there will be lots of questions in relation to it. I know the Department has a very good explanatory document but sometimes that might not be readily available and it is important to have those lines of communication - by phone and online - going. </p>
          <p eId="para_119"> I know that the UK has had a similar scheme for some years. What engagement did the Department have in reviewing that operational model, <i>per se,</i> compared with the model that is being defined now in the auto-enrolment scheme? Did the Department learn anything from that? Did the Department take any other jurisdictions into account when setting up the auto-enrolment My Future Fund scheme? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_69">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_120">The Chair is right about communications. We have already ramped up in the past week and we will be ramping up even further in the course of the autumn and going into winter. We will be highlighting to people that they will see a new thing in their payslip, which will be a deduction on their pay. It will be happening at the same time as many other budgetary changes that may or may not emerge over the course of October, so people will be looking at a number of different things, perhaps, in their payslips. We will put a lot of effort into trying to ensure that as many people as possible understand that this new initiative is coming and what it means. The Chair is right when he says that there will be people who will miss all of that and therefore there will be phonelines and other means of getting information for them to use to get the assistance and understanding that they need. </p>
          <p eId="para_121"> We had very extensive engagement with other jurisdictions. We visited the UK a number of times and had engagement with the Department for Work and Pensions there and with Nest Pensions, which is the Government-operated system there. We looked extensively at what Australia and New Zealand have done. We also looked extensively at what some of the Scandinavian countries, particularly Sweden and Denmark, have done. We also looked at other auto-enrolment systems in other parts of the world, such as in Poland and Chile and places like that. We learned a huge amount from looking at those models. Essentially, the design of this system is a distillation of all of the lessons we learned from those models. Examples would include things like the contribution rate. It became very clear that the contribution rate implemented by most auto-enrolment systems in other parts of the world was not sufficient. If one asks any of the designers or operators of any of those systems they will say that the biggest mistake they made was not building in a step increase in the contribution rates, over time. Now they have a big problem in the UK where they are trying to get the contribution rates increased from 3% and 5%. The scheme is 13 years old in the UK, at this stage. In Australia, they took the view at the beginning that they had to invest in low-risk, conservative funds, with the consequence that people did not make any money in their pots. The situation almost became a scandal and it became clear that they needed to do something very different regarding investments. They found that there is just as big a risk going for low-risk investments in that people's money does not grow and therefore does not provide them with adequacy in their retirement. </p>
          <p eId="para_122"> We learned those types of lessons. We also learned if it is all done through the market - and we are doing some of this through the market, using market investment managers and market administrators - without a degree of State management and regulation of the system, it can result in a lack of consistency and quite different offerings being made to people. We also learned that the cost can be significantly greater. The beauty of what we are doing is that bringing it all together through one scheme means that the scale allows us to reduce the cost massively. As I said earlier, the assets under investment management charges is a fraction of what one would normally expect in the market. In addition, it is a consistent scheme for every single employee who participates in it. </p>
          <p eId="para_123"> The last big lesson was to do with incentivisation. I am sure the committee will hear people giving out about the fact that tax relief is not being used in this system and that we are using a State top up instead. Tax relief would not have done a great deal for nearly three quarters of the people who will be in the scheme. This is because they pay tax at 20% or they do not pay tax at all, because they earn so little. Consequently, there would have been little or no incentivisation from the State, if we were to use the tax relief system instead of a State top up. First of all, this approach enhances the pension pot because the money goes directly into it and second, it is consistent, in that regardless of a person's level of income, the State incentivisation is set at the same rate. In this way, it does not favour people who are better off over people who are not as well off. </p>
          <p eId="para_124"> We learned all of those lessons and distilled them as best we could into the design that is reflected in the legislation now. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_70">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_125">Thank you, Mr. Duggan. From your comments and those of your team, I think we can be confident about being online for 1 January and that there will be no further delays, which is important. Senator Rabbitte has indicated that she wants to come in again. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnneRabbitte" eId="spk_71">
          <from>Senator Anne Rabbitte<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_126">I should have said in my initial contribution that I want to thank the witnesses for the work they have done. It is great to have it in the programme for Government. It is wonderful to have the Minister behind this and it is good that the witnesses acknowledged that previous Ministers have been full square behind getting this delivered for people. It is important, so while I might ask thorny questions, it is only because I think people are trying to understand more about it. </p>
          <p eId="para_127"> My next question relates to comments by Deputy Gallagher and Senator O'Donovan which Mr. Duggan answered regarding whether funding can be put into it. What about ill health? Say,God forbid, I was to get sick. Say I am 55 and I still have 11 years to run on it, what are the options to support me if I suffered ill health? If it was an occupational scheme, I would have cover to protect me. I take on board what Mr. Duggan has said about the scheme being private but are there any safety clauses for ill health in the case that a person might not be able to continue to work and to contribute to the scheme? That is one of two questions. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_72">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_128">It depends on what the Senator means by ill health. If the Senator means ill health to such an extent that she has to retire, then yes, there is early access provision to one's My Future Fund in such circumstances. If the Senator means ill health as sort of an insurance piece that some schemes offer, then that is not in it. As I said to the Senator in my reply, one of the things that NAERSA will have to do over the coming years is look at additional design features to enhance the scheme. Secondary benefits from the scheme is one of the things that will be looked at. Up to now, the focus has been on getting the scheme going for three quarters of a million people and then we will look at enhancing it afterwards. To sum up, there is early provision if a person has to retire because of ill health, the same as with an occupational scheme and secondary benefits will be looked at down the line. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnneRabbitte" eId="spk_73">
          <from>Senator Anne Rabbitte<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_129">I thank Mr. Duggan for clarifying that, it is very welcome. My next question relates to what Mr. Duggan said earlier about the Revenue assessments. Will Revenue be working in tandem with the Department to say how many people are contributing to occupational pensions at the moment?</p>
          <p eId="para_130">I know it was said there are approximately 700,000 people who might have no pensions at all and this will be targeted directly at them but have we a line of sight as to how many people - across the different age brackets as well - have occupational pensions?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_74">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_131">That information is already available through the Pensions Authority. I just do not have it to hand right now but we can certainly get that from the Pensions Authority and send it on to the committee. It will be able to see how many people are in defined benefit schemes, defined contribution schemes, PRSAs and in the other types of schemes as well. I will try to get that granular detail for the committee. The system already has it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnneRabbitte" eId="spk_75">
          <from>Senator Anne Rabbitte<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_132">To explain it a bit better, it is meeting the minimum requirements I ask about. You could have an occupational pension and be 55 years old but you might not be meeting your minimum requirements. Can Revenue see whether contributions within the occupational pension will meet the minimum requirements to support the person on retirement?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_76">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_133">One of the things auto-enrolment is designed to do is allow you to be exempt from auto-enrolment if you are in an occupational or private pension scheme, operated through payroll. However, the law also sets out that will be subject to exemption standards but they are not yet defined. At the beginning, if you are a member of such a scheme, you are exempt. The law says that within the first six years of the scheme, standards will be defined. For an occupational scheme or a PRSA operated through payroll to be exempt from auto-enrolment, it will have to comply with whatever standard is developed by NAERSA in conjunction with the Department, the Government and the Parliament over the next six years. That is a piece of work NAERSA needs to do.</p>
          <p eId="para_134"> People automatically jump to that it has to be the same contributions levels, at least. It is not that simple. Contribution levels can be based on different things. In most occupational schemes, they are based on base pay, whereas in auto-enrolment they are based on gross pay. The Senator knows there can be a world of difference between those things when you take into account allowances, overtime and all that kind of stuff. You cannot just do it on a contribution rate on its own, you have to have a more sophisticated manner of developing such a standard. There is a bit of work to be done to come up with such a standard.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnneRabbitte" eId="spk_77">
          <from>Senator Anne Rabbitte<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_135">The Department and elected representatives have worked to ensure we are at this stage. Is Mr. Duggan concerned that over the six years, there will still be a gap for those in occupational schemes if their employer is not gradually partaking in it? I will not use the term "cliff edge", but is he concerned there will still be a sizeable amount employers will have to bridge to bring their employees in-line if they do not get in at the start?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_78">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_136">Does the Senator mean the contribution levels within the occupational scheme will be low and will stay low and, by year six, will not be up at 4.5%?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnneRabbitte" eId="spk_79">
          <from>Senator Anne Rabbitte<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_137">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_80">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_138">There is the possibility of it happening in a few places but I do not think it would be a widespread practice, to be honest. Most occupational schemes are already reading those kind of thresholds, or thereabouts. There are some that are a little low but the standard in the industry seems to be 5% and 5%, which is in excess of what would be the case in six years' time. I have heard it said there is a danger that because auto-enrolment is starting low at 1.5% and building up to that level over the next number of years, some employers may be tempted to drop their contribution level from the current 5% downwards. Looking at what has happened in other countries, there is very little evidence to support that is a feature when you introduce such systems. Does it mean that one employer might do it? Of course, but by and large it is not a trend we have witnessed occurring anywhere else. I think it is unlikely to be a thing.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AnneRabbitte" eId="spk_81">
          <from>Senator Anne Rabbitte<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_139">I thank Mr. Duggan.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_82">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_140">Why is the timeline six years? Is there a possibility of doing it earlier or within the six years?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_83">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_141">Six years is the maximum, Chair. The reason it is six years is that it is 1.5% for the first three years and it is 3% for the next three. At the end of the six years, in year seven, the contribution rate increases to 4.5%, which is very close to what is typically the rate in occupational schemes. At that juncture, it would be important to start having a standard that would be applicable across all schemes as a consequence.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterRoche" eId="spk_84">
          <from>Deputy Peter Roche<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_142">Apologies for my late attendance, which was due to the health committee next door, which was fundamentally important as well. There is more good in this for the employee than there is for the employer is the way I see it. My initial concerns are for small and medium enterprises and those type of employers. Some of them are operating on very thin margins. Any additional financial burden on them will certainly be of concern. My question is about an impact assessment of this and could it lead to job losses, reduced hours or elements like that. That is my concern. As I mentioned, some of them are operating on a very small margin and some might be discouraged from employing more as a consequence of this financial burden.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_85">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_143">There are different ways of looking at this. We have always acknowledged that at the outset - I said the same in response to Senator O'Reilly - there is an additional cost on employment when you introduce something like this. The initial cost is quite low, at 1.5%, and has been deliberately designed that way. The increase up to the actual rate of 6% is being graduated over a ten-year period, very deliberately, to ensure it can be factored in to remuneration discussions in order that it becomes part of normal wage increases and in that way, does not become a significant additional cost on businesses of any size. That came about as a result of the consultation the Department had with employer representatives of all types, from the big groups like IBEC down to the very small representative groups for hospitality, convenience stores and that micro-enterprise level. That consultation has resulted in that ten-year phasing-in period to deal with the very issue the Deputy raises.</p>
          <p eId="para_144"> The ESRI has done an impact assessment of auto-enrolment and has highlighted how it will result in some additional cost but over time, they will dissipate in the way I have said. In addition to that, it will result in people in the future having significantly greater spending capability, which in itself is critically important for small and micro-enterprises so that people in localities actually have money to spend in those localities. Auto-enrolment will be critical to facilitate that in the years to come. Otherwise, as we discussed earlier, lots of people will be critically dependent on the State pension on its own. While that is great at keeping people from poverty and providing them with necessities, it is not great for facilitating the discretionary spend on which a lot of micro-enterprises are critically dependent.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterRoche" eId="spk_86">
          <from>Deputy Peter Roche<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T10:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_145">This minute, I think about Joe Public; the person who is down there in rural Ireland and is beavering away this morning and everything is going grand. Here, we are fully aware of what is coming down the tracks and I am not saying it is bad but in terms of the general employer, how will this information about the scheme filter down to them and how will they be informed about its introduction or the impact it may have on them?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_87">
          <from> Mr. Tim Duggan<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_146">They are two different things. We have been doing extensive work with as many representative organisations as possible to try to get messages and information delivered to all kinds of employers. That has been done through webinars, leaflets, turning up in person at events that they organise and all of that kind of thing, and we will do a lot more over the coming months. If there are any groupings or representative bodies that the Deputy wants us to engage with, or bodies he has some influence with whereby we can get introductions to them, by all means, he should let us know. We will meet anybody to discuss this and explain it to them in as much detail as they need. We are doing that. We have already reached thousands of employers, but we want to do a lot more of that because there are so many employers, particularly of the type mentioned by the Deputy.</p>
          <p eId="para_147"> I do not sit in an ivory tower. I have a brother in west Cork who runs such a microenterprise and, believe me, I get it in the neck any time we mention anything that results in an increase in costs for him. I absolutely appreciate where the Deputy is coming from in highlighting this. It is designed by consultation with employer groups in order to phase it in as best we can and to mitigate that implication.</p>
          <p eId="para_148"> With regard to employees, we are undertaking a massive public relations campaign right now. If the Deputy looks at buses going up and down the road, he will see the ice cream advertisement, and it is also on television, radio and all social media. That is the beginning of our intensive campaign. We will be ramping that up over the coming months and doing much more to engage as many people as possible and help them understand it.</p>
          <p eId="para_149"> We have an auto-enrolment hub that has a lot of information for all kinds of stakeholders, such as employers, employees, agents and so on. Anything they need to know about the system, and how it will work and be implemented, is there. We are more than willing to engage with any party to assist.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterRoche" eId="spk_88">
          <from>Deputy Peter Roche<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_150">One body that I hear a lot from, as I am sure others do, is the Restaurants Association of Ireland. The restaurant sector is one that is really struggling. I can see an issue with regard to this scheme because restaurants are struggling as matters stand, and I feel that any additional burden on them could potentially mean closure and certainly job losses.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_89">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_151">Thank you. We are out of time so we will have to pause the discussion. I thank the officials for attending. It was a very engaging and proactive discussion on auto-enrolment. I wish them well in their preparations over the next couple of months. The committee will be keeping informed with regard to progress. I am sure we will have the officials back in with regard to how the scheme is going in 2026. I again thank them for their attendance and for providing the briefing material, which was very helpful.</p>
          <p eId="para_152"> We will suspend to facilitate a change of witnesses.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_7">
          <i> Sitting suspended at 11.04 a.m. and resumed at 11.08 a.m.</i>
        </summary>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_3">
        <heading>Engagement on Matters Relating to Pre-Budget Submissions: Discussion (Resumed)<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:00:00+01:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_90">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_153">Before we begin, I will read a note on privilege and housekeeping matters. Witnesses and members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice that they should not criticise or make charges against any person or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable or otherwise engage in speech that would be regarded as damaging to the good name of the person or entity. Therefore, if their statements are potentially defamatory in relation to an identifiable person or entity, they will be directed to discontinue their remarks. It is imperative they comply with any such direction I may make.</p>
          <p eId="para_154"> Members attending remotely are reminded of the constitutional requirements that to participate in public meetings, members must be physically present within the confines of the Leinster House complex. This is due to the constitutional requirement that to participate in public meetings, members must be physically present within the confines of the place where Parliament has chosen to sit. In this regard, I ask any members participating on Microsoft Teams to confirm they are on the grounds of the Leinster House complex if they wish to make a contribution. I remind all those in attendance to make sure their mobile phones are switched off or in silent mode.</p>
          <p eId="para_155"> I welcome from the Local Development Companies Network, Mr. Philip O'Donnell, research, policy and rural affairs officer, Mr. Terry Hyland, chief executive officer of Cavan County Local Development, and Mr. Thomas Fitzpatrick, chairperson; from Irish Rural Link, Ms Louise Lennon, policy and communications officer; and from the Public Participation Network, Ms Grainne Fleming, Kildare PPN co-ordinator, and Ms Siobhan Cronogue, Longford PPN co-ordinator.</p>
          <p eId="para_156"> The committee welcomes the opportunity to engage with the witnesses.</p>
          <p eId="para_157">I thank all those who have contributed to the committee's call for pre-budget submissions. Engagement and consultations are very much key to the process and the committee is aware of the importance of citizens' engagement and deliberative democracy. Many of the submissions received are from those actively involved in supporting our communities to grow and develop. We commend them and look forward to reviewing the contents of their submissions as part of the committee's wider examination in advance of budget 2026. I now invite the Local Development Companies Network to make its opening remarks.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_91">
          <from> Mr. Philip O'Donnell<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_158">I thank the committee for the opportunity to be here this morning. The Local Development Companies Network, LDCN, is the national representative body for local development companies, LDCs, in Ireland. LDCs are not for profit and community-based. They deliver a wide range of Government-funded and EU-funded programmes that address poverty and social inclusion through local and community development. LDCs deliver services on an integrated basis, with a suite of individual and household supports in areas like employment, education, disability, health and well-being, and parenting delivered under one roof in tandem with a broad range of community-level supports like social enterprise, climate and environment, and outdoor recreation and tourism.</p>
          <p eId="para_159"> It is clear from the work of LDCs on the ground that while the Irish economy is performing strongly overall, it is not working equally well for everyone. Consistent poverty stands at 5% but this rises to 19% among people unable to work due to a disability, 11% among single-parent households and more than 8% among children. We understand that welfare measures were discussed at last week's sitting of this committee. Important as these measures are, local development companies focus on building people's capabilities to work, engage with society and contribute meaningfully to their communities.</p>
          <p eId="para_160"> The social inclusion and community activation programme, SICAP, is a central to this work. It is the State’s flagship social inclusion programme and a key pillar of its anti-poverty strategy. Funding for SICAP today is only around 60% of what it was in 2007. On the demand side, an analysis of the POBAL deprivation indices that we performed last year showed that between 2016 and 2022, the number of communities classified as “very disadvantaged” or “extremely disadvantaged” rose by 60% and the number of people living in these communities more than doubled. While welfare is essential for containing poverty, it cannot do the kind of community development that trends like this tell us is vital. That requires boots on the ground. One area where we see the impact of those boots on the ground is in the area of migrant integration, which is supported by the new arrivals funding, first introduced in 2022. This €10 million annual fund is essential and should be retained. It also needs to be moved to a multi-annual footing. Currently, staff are hired under this programme on one-year contracts and must be put on protective notice every December while waiting for confirmation of continued funding. Formalising this fund within the five-year SICAP framework would address the issue overnight.</p>
          <p eId="para_161"> We highlight in our pre-budget submission the value of community employment, Tús and the rural social scheme. These schemes benefit not just participants but whole communities. The recent review of the rural social scheme, RSS, warned that declining participation could leave rural areas without vital services. LDCs do all they can to make these schemes appealing but the €27.50 weekly to-up payment is increasingly inadequate. Sometimes it is not even enough to cover the transportation costs involved in participation. We are supporting a phased increase of €7.50 per week per year for the next three years, in addition to any underlying welfare increases.</p>
          <p eId="para_162"> We also encourage greater alignment between our national and European funding efforts. We are especially keen to draw attention to the opportunity presented by INTERREG, which is about addressing regional, economic and infrastructural disparities across Europe. Most community organisations are aware of INTERREG funding but they are unable to tap into it because of matched funding constraints. A €1 million annual national fund to bridge that gap could potentially unlock €3 million annually from Europe. This would not be without precedent. Belgium and the Netherlands do it already and they reap very sizeable rewards. From an Irish point of view, it is a simple, high-return investment that would bolster the social economy and support our regions. In this and in other areas the infrastructure is already in place and it has proven itself to be robust, dynamic and effective whenever supported.</p>
          <p eId="para_163"> Similarly, the LEADER food initiative supported 168 local producers while operational between 2018 and 2021. A recent once-off call in 2023 was heavily oversubscribed. This is a clear sign of capacity and appetite for growth. Supporting small-scale food producers through established and effective structures like LEADER aligns directly with Food Vision 2030. All of this speaks to what resilient communities look like, namely, connected, self-reliant and innovative, provided they are supported. That is the essence of local development. It is the guiding philosophy of programmes like LEADER, which we are working to strengthen post 2027. We recognise the economic challenges ahead but our message is simple - investment in communities and the resilience of communities is needed now more than ever.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_92">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_164">I thank Mr. O'Donnell. We will now go to Ms Louise Lennon from Irish Rural Link.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_93">
          <from> Ms Louise Lennon<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:10:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_165">I thank the committee for inviting us to present our pre-budget submission. Irish Rural Link represents more 600 community groups in disadvantaged and marginalised rural areas. We work to highlight the challenges facing these communities and we advocate for inclusive, sustainable rural development.</p>
          <p eId="para_166"> In the current context, many rural households continue to feel the impact of the cost-of-living crisis, especially with ongoing increases in the costs of food, fuel and essential services. Access to public transport remains extremely limited in many rural areas, leaving households dependent on private cars for work, education, health appointments and daily activities. For working families, this often means needing two cars, which significantly increases their cost of living. Even those households where both adults are working full time on minimum wage often struggle to meet a minimum essential standard of living. The annual minimum essential standard of living, MESL, report continues to highlight the income adequacies rural households face, due in large part to the dependency on a car and the high cost of transport associated with that and the lack of accessible services.</p>
          <p eId="para_167"> This is not just a social welfare issue; it is also a broader income adequacy and public service issue. Without sufficient investment in infrastructure like transport and social supports, rural people continue to be left behind. Long-term targeted investment in public services and infrastructure is vital for balanced regional growth. Without reliable public transport, affordable childcare, healthcare and education, rural communities will continue to be disadvantaged. Irish Rural Link became aware of just one example where the lack of transport is impacting on peoples lives. It involves an accommodation centre in a rural village where the limited transport prevents young children from accessing early years education and leaves the adults unable to reach employment and training or even just to be able to attend appointments or do a weekly shop. Some residents walk long distances along unlit roads to reach services. This is putting their safety at risk also.</p>
          <p eId="para_168"> The majority of Irish Rural Link's membership are working in the community or in community and voluntary organisations. The cost pressures, especially insurance and rising operational expenses, are threatening the viability of these services, such as meals on wheels, rural transport, community childcare, community education and other community, health and social services. Funding for these groups remains limited, short term and insecure. Many organisations receive only annual funding, making it extremely difficult to plan ahead or retain staff. Section 39 organisations in particular are struggling to compete with public sector wages.</p>
          <p eId="para_169"> Irish Rural Link co-ordinates the national meals on wheels network and providers are seeing significant increases in food and fuel costs. Budget 2025 did not go far enough. We are calling for €10 million in ring-fenced funding in budget 2026 and for the introduction of multi-annual core funding to help providers plan sustainably and avoid passing the costs on to vulnerable older people.</p>
          <p eId="para_170"> Some of our key asks for budget 2026 are that the budget be rural-proofed with a strong focus on regional equity. We want an increase in rural welfare rates to reflect the true cost of living for people in rural areas, along with investment in public services and rural infrastructure, including transport, digital inclusion and health and social care.</p>
          <p eId="para_171">We are also looking for expanded and improved rural transport services, with demand-led models and sustainable vehicle options. We are also asking for multi-annual core funding to community and voluntary organisations delivering essential local services. Meals on wheels must be supported with ring-fenced funding and recognition of their role in healthcare and social care. Insurance barriers for voluntary groups should be reviewed to free up more resources for service delivery. We should strengthen and retain employment scheme participants by creating long-term, paid roles in community services.</p>
          <p eId="para_172"> Adequate incomes, investment in services and sustainable supports for the community and voluntary sector in budget 2026 are essential for the sustainability of rural communities. I thank the committee for the opportunity to speak.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_94">
          <from> Ms Grainne Fleming<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_173">I am the co-ordinator for the Kildare Public Participation Network, PPN. I am joined by my colleague, Ms Siobhan Cronogue, from Longford PPN. I thank the committee members for the opportunity to speak to them on behalf of the Kildare PPN. I am grateful for the chance to present our pre-budget submission and to outline both our achievements and the serious challenges we face without sufficient and sustained investment.</p>
          <p eId="para_174"> Kildare PPN now represents 831 member organisations, collectively reaching nearly 83,000 people across the county. Since January alone, we have welcomed 149 new member groups, demonstrating the increasing appetite for civic participation and the rapid pace of population growth in our area. Kildare is now the fifth most populous local authority in Ireland, with over 247,000 residents according to the 2022 census, which is double the number in 1991. The figure is projected to exceed 266,000 by 2031. With this growth comes greater complexity, more diverse needs and higher expectations placed on our network to support and engage. Despite this, core funding for PPNs has remained largely flat since 2016. Inflation, which has risen by 18.5% since 2021, has driven significant cost increases across staffing, programme delivery, technology and venue hire, but the resources available to us have not kept pace.</p>
          <p eId="para_175"> In addition, our small team of only two staff members supports 22 representatives on decision-making committees within Kildare County Council, and more are expected under the new community safety partnerships. These are volunteer roles that require and deserve structured training, monitoring and sustained administrative support. Meeting that demand requires time, systems and personnel, none of which come free.</p>
          <p eId="para_176"> Staff capacity is a critical issue. Our team undertakes tasks in HR, event management, finance, reporting, communications, website management, policy development, social media, graphic design and more. This far exceeds the original scope of the PPN model. In line with recruitment benchmarks such as those recently applied in Fingal, we respectfully propose regrading PPN co-ordinators to grade 6, at a minimum, but preferably grade 7, and support workers to grade 5, at a minimum, and preferably grade 6. This would align us to colleagues in similar roles. Without such recognition, we risk staff burnout, turnover and a decline in network capacity.</p>
          <p eId="para_177"> We are also calling for a shift from the current annual funding cycle to a five-year funding model. The current approach breeds insecurity and hampers long-term planning. It also impacts staff’s ability to secure financial supports such as mortgages. A five-year model, already in place for other public grants, would provide the stability and accountability we need to meet the strategic goals outlined in the Kildare local economic and community plan, the Kildare climate action plan, the Kildare connected digital strategy and the Kildare integration strategy. Increased investment would allow us to deliver more targeted capacity-building supports for smaller and emerging groups, to improve our digital infrastructure to reach more rural and under-represented communities and to expand our support for community-led initiatives on climate action, youth engagement and social inclusion.</p>
          <p eId="para_178"> I want to raise a pressing concern with the Department’s financial controls document. The clause stating that statutory leave payments cannot be funded without offering alternatives creates legal and financial uncertainty for PPNs and host organisations. This is particularly problematic in areas such as maternity and sick leave, which are standard entitlements under Irish law.</p>
          <p eId="para_179"> More broadly, these issues are not unique to Kildare. Since their establishment under the Local Government Act 2014, PPNs across the country have grown substantially in scale, impact and responsibility. Yet, the funding model has remained outdated and insufficient. The role of PPN staff has evolved dramatically and the salary structures and support systems must evolve too. Our request is clear: that the funding and support structures for PPNs reflect the reality of our role in community development, participatory democracy and local governance.</p>
          <p eId="para_180"> We are extremely proud of what we have achieved to date but we are operating at full stretch. If PPNs are to remain the Department’s key vehicle for community engagement and policy input, we must be resourced accordingly. I thank committee members for their time and attention. We look forward to taking additional questions on funding.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_95">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_181">I thank all the witnesses for their introductory remarks. I will invite members to discuss. I remind members participating remotely to use the raised hand feature and to cancel it when they have spoken. I call Senator Sarah O'Reilly.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#SarahOReilly" eId="spk_96">
          <from>Senator Sarah O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_182">The groups are all welcome and I thank them for their presentations. I will ask some questions about their submissions. I thank the witnesses for all the work they are doing in our communities. They are visible on the ground in my community.</p>
          <p eId="para_183"> I want to highlight LDCs and their budget cuts. In 2008, €84 million was available. That was reduced to €49 million for 2025. I know the LCDN is a national organisation, which is not true of some of the groups that come before the committee. It is visible in my county. What has been the impact of the budget cuts? Where do the witnesses see that impact on the ground in respect of the services they provide?</p>
          <p eId="para_184"> We hear that the cost-of-living supports in last year's budget will not be in this year's budget. Have those supports disguised the levels of poverty at the moment? Are cost-of-living supports required? Should more long-term supports be put in place?</p>
          <p eId="para_185"> I will touch on the community engagement schemes, Tús and the rural social scheme. Those are vital to our communities. I heard Mr. O'Donnell say that the LCDN is looking for a top-up or a raise in that regard. To allow people to go to work and put petrol in the car, especially in rural areas, I must support the LCDN fully. That is needed. If those groups of people were not in our rural communities, we would see the impact. When we lost the gateway scheme workers, we very much saw that.</p>
          <p eId="para_186"> Many local communities want to apply for funding through the LEADER programme. These are voluntary groups and the system is very bureaucratic. I have discussed this issue at the committee previously. Is there anything we can do to simplify the application process?</p>
          <p eId="para_187"> Irish Rural Link provides a lifeline for people, especially elderly people, in rural areas. We have a shopper service in two areas of east Cavan. They are excellent, but we need more. During Storm Éowyn, we had no meals on wheels in the east of the country. I had to buy and deliver food. We need more of that. I support the organisation's requests in that respect. I am sorry for going on, Chair.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_97">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_188">I thank the Senator. Perhaps we can go to each organisation to respond. Would Mr. O'Donnell like to go first?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_98">
          <from> Mr. Philip O'Donnell<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:20:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_189">Mr. Hyland might like to talk about SICAP and its impact.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_99">
          <from> Mr. Terry Hyland<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_190">I thank the Senator for the questions. We are delighted to be here today and really appreciate the invitation. The Senator is right to say that SICAP is a very impactful programme. It is a national programme that is delivered in the heart of every disadvantaged community in the country. It has huge reach. Between 2018 and 2023, for example, we engaged with 131,000 individuals, over 6,000 community groups and 209,000 members of family groups. It was hugely impactful across that period but unfortunately, according to the survey on income and living conditions which was published in March of this year, the at risk of poverty rate, which is the percentage of people with less than 60% of the median disposable income level, increased from 10.6% in 2023 to 11.7% in 2024. Numbers-wise, that is 618,000 people. If the cost-of-living supports were pulled away, that figure would actually have been 14.1%. That tells us what the cost-of-living supports have been doing recently. In terms of consistent poverty, which combines low income with enforced deprivation, the figures rose from 3.6% in 2023 to 5% in 2024. Child poverty, which is a huge focus at the moment, was 15.3% in 2024 compared to 14.2% in 2023. Those indicators are important and hopefully they will inform decision-making at budget time.</p>
          <p eId="para_191"> Cost-of-living supports are important because they help to deal with immediate need whereas programmes like SICAP, as Mr. O'Donnell said in his opening statement, are about sustainable approaches to tackling poverty on the ground within communities and about social inclusion. SICAP employs community development workers who work as boots on the ground, hand-holding communities and individuals to come up with bespoke, tailor-made plans to deal with the issues they face within their households, whether that is progression towards the labour market, returning to education, dealing with transport issues or securing childcare. A tailor-made plan is built with our community development workers and we link in with local agencies and actors on the ground. We also provide wraparound supports within our own organisations to deal with those issues.</p>
          <p eId="para_192"> In terms of the LEADER programme and simplifying the application process, the Senator is right that because LEADER is funded by the EU, bureaucratic issues transfer across to the application process. We are advocating as a network and working with the Department of Rural and Community Development and the Gaeltacht at a European level to make the application process more simple for people to access. We want people to access the LEADER programme who may not necessarily have had the opportunity to apply for it previously. That is really important and we are pushing for that. We would love the opportunity to work with the committee on channelling that message to the relevant parties at EU level and within the Department. The Senator is correct that there is a body of work to be done on simplifying the application process.</p>
          <p eId="para_193"> In terms of the rural social scheme and the Tús initiative, the Senator is absolutely correct and in our pre-budget submission we advocate that people who participate in labour activation schemes such as community employment and Tús or social schemes like the RSS should not be at a financial loss. Currently, a lot of people are because in order to get to their scheme placement, they have to put diesel in the car and they have other expenses to get there. The current top-up rate of €27.50 on the payment does not cover it, unfortunately, and that is why we are advocating for that nominal increase of €7.50 per week in each year over the next three years to try to alleviate that. If we lost those schemes tomorrow, I fear what would happen to communities across Ireland.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_100">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_194">I invite Ms Lennon to respond on behalf of Irish Rural Link.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_101">
          <from> Ms Louise Lennon<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_195">On the cost-of-living measures, I agree with Mr. Hyland that they were very useful at the time. They did reduce the rate of poverty a bit but we need to start looking at long-term investment in social welfare payments and start lifting people out of poverty. The committee engaged with some of our colleagues from the community and voluntary pillar last week and they spoke about the minimum essential standard of living basket of goods. We would also recommend that social welfare payments be benchmarked against that basket of goods instead of the consumer price index, CPI, because it is more reflective of people on low income and their living standards. We are looking for an increase in core welfare rates but, as I mentioned in my opening statement, for people in rural areas long-term investment in transport and other services is also hugely important.</p>
          <p eId="para_196"> Meals on wheels was mentioned earlier and there are still lots of gaps in the provision of services. We have 308 providers involved in our network but 33% of them do not get any funding from the HSE. They are wholly voluntary or they try to get funding from elsewhere. Approximately 35% of providers are running a waiting list because they cannot meet the demand. I know that Mr. Hyland's organisation provides a lot of meals in Cavan. It filled the gap that was there, especially during Covid when it was set up. New services are being set up but it is very difficult for them to meet the demand. It is a national problem. It is not just a rural issue but is nationwide.</p>
          <p eId="para_197"> On the RSS and community employment schemes, a lot of the community services like community childcare and community education rely on those schemes to provide services. When someone finishes on a scheme it is very difficult to find a replacement, especially now when we are supposedly at full employment. Mr. O'Donnell mentioned the review of the RSS and the recommendations on extending it to rural dwellers through a pilot scheme. However, there does not seem to be any movement on any of those recommendations, another of which was allowing someone who has been on a community employment scheme for more than six years and who is aged over 50 to move on to the RSS to fill those gaps that are there.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_102">
          <from>Senator Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_198">I welcome all of the speakers and greatly value the work they are doing on the ground. Coming from Longford, which is one of the most socioeconomically challenged communities in the country, I can attest to the work that is being done on the ground which is greatly appreciated. As a member of a Government party, it is disappointing to hear that issues with pay and security of tenure in relation to SICAP and the PPN have not been addressed. It is particularly disappointing as the witnesses are engaged in work that is meant to tackle socioeconomic challenges. It is disappointing and reflects poorly on us but I can assure our guests that we are making every effort to address matters in this budget.</p>
          <p eId="para_199"> Is Mr. O'Donnell concerned about the news from Europe today on funding for the Common Agricultural Policy? There are obvious implications for his organisation in that it is funded by Europe.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_103">
          <from> Mr. Philip O'Donnell<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:30:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_200">Yes, we are deeply concerned and it is something we have been keeping a very close eye on. We have been trying to be as active as we can in that conversation in the last couple of months. We had been advocating for the retention of CAP Pillar 2 and for LEADER to be placed therein. LEADER has a very natural home in CAP Pillar 2 which is focused on rural development. We certainly have a concern that if LEADER was to exist elsewhere, it would be competing for resources and visibility with other types of funds. It also has some very specific protections within CAP Pillar 2. For example, a minimum of 5% of the overall CAP Pillar 2 envelope, which is funded through the European Agricultural Fund for Rural Development, is allocated to LEADER. </p>
          <p eId="para_201">There would be a real concern, given long-term budgetary trends, around LEADER that this may be eroded going forward. Our position on it for the moment is that, in the first instance, we are waiting to see exactly what the proposals will look like, although reports this morning give us a pretty good sense of that. These are proposals at the moment and proposals only. There will be an important role for the Council, the member states, the Ministers and also for the Members of the European Parliament to have their say in these conversations. We are reassured by the perspectives we have heard across both of those European structures during the past couple of months as regards the retention of CAP pillars 1 and 2 and we will support them in their work in advocating for that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_104">
          <from>Senator Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_202">In regard to INTERREG funding, Mr. Hyland made a case for a €1 million amount in matching funding. Will he give an example of where INTERREG funding has been used anywhere in Ireland?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_105">
          <from> Mr. Terry Hyland<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_203">A number of community and voluntary organisations can draw INTERREG funding down. For example, our counterpart in Donegal - the development company in Ballyhoura - has run a successful INTERREG programme. There are probably very few organisations that can-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_106">
          <from>Senator Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_204">What did that programme do?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_107">
          <from> Mr. Terry Hyland<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_205">I do not have the details to hand.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_108">
          <from> Mr. Philip O'Donnell<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_206">Could I come in on that? I have been discussing this quite a lot with one of our member companies in County Kerry, South Kerry Development Partnership, which has been very active in this area. I believe it is currently delivering three INTERREG projects. Two are in the energy space, those being, community energy and the ownership of energy assets, and one is on peatland restoration. These programmes would typically be funded to the tune of €500,000 to €750,000 overall. That is the magnitude. The programmes would involve international partners, so they would not necessarily all be funded through, for example, South Kerry Development Partnership.</p>
          <p eId="para_207"> This is an anomaly and something we are quite keen to stress. For a community and voluntary organisation to tap into INTERREG funding, its funding model effectively needs to be clean of other European funds because European funds are not allowed to be matched with other European funds. It is okay if an organisation has trading income or access to income from the public purse but if an organisation is largely reliant on other European funds, which is the case for many community and voluntary sector organisations now, it is locked out of INTERREG. The figures involved are not very large. The Southern Regional Assembly did research on this, which I have shared with the Senator, and it estimated that the contribution of an Irish organisation to an INTERREG project would typically be in the region of €20,000 to €30,000, or a third of the overall project budget.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_109">
          <from>Senator Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_208">I am conscious of time. Would it be fair to say that the INTERREG fund mainly operates in the community energy sphere?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_110">
          <from> Mr. Philip O'Donnell<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_209">It is broader than that. It would be around addressing-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_111">
          <from>Senator Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_210">In terms of the advantages for Ireland and opportunities for community energy, could we look to the Department of energy to fund that €1 million pot?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_112">
          <from> Mr. Philip O'Donnell<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_211">The Department of rural and community development could potentially have an important role in this, because I would see it as being very targeted and supportive of civil society organisations.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_113">
          <from>Senator Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_212">If I still have time, I will come back to the Local Development Companies Network representatives. Irish Rural Link is doing fantastic work and we can see its growth. I visited Galway a couple of weekends ago and I could not believe it. Even in Longford, I see huge progress. People ring now and say they want more buses, which is great. We are coming to that time of year when people call to say they do not have school bus tickets. Does the Department of education ever meet Irish Rural Link to see if the routes could be co-ordinated to try to resolve any issues there are with school transport?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_114">
          <from> Ms Louise Lennon<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_213">Just to clarify, we are not Local Link. Irish Rural Link advocates for more transport and would be very supportive of Local Link services. I am not sure if the Department of education has gone out directly to the individual Local Link services but I could ask someone to get in touch with the Senator, maybe Damien O'Neill from Longford-Westmeath.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_115">
          <from>Senator Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_214">During the lifetime of the previous Government, we did a piece of work on where we would go with school transport, but I have a sense we did not engage with a sufficient number of stakeholders when that was being done.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_116">
          <from> Ms Louise Lennon<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_215">Yes, and Irish Rural Link would be very-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_117">
          <from>Senator Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_216">For example, if a Local Link route was tweaked by ten minutes, it could resolve an issue and get children to school on time rather than them being ten minutes late. Small tweaks such as that can really make a huge change for us.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_118">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_217">The time is up, so we sadly have to move on. Deputy O'Reilly is next.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LouiseOReilly" eId="spk_119">
          <from>Deputy Louise O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_218">I thank the Cathaoirleach and all of our witnesses for the overview and their pre-budget submissions, which are very interesting and comprehensive. In regard to multi-annual funding and keeping pace with public service wages, will the witnesses speak about the difficulties that presents? It strikes me that the organisations will lose staff to another sector. I do not just mean one that might be able to pay them more money. Even where there is equality of pay, staff in the organisations cannot get maternity or sick leave, their holidays covered or career progression offered to them because the organisations do not have multi-annual funding. Will the witnesses talk about the impact this has on staffing and if there is a value-for-money argument to be made for multi-annual funding? I believe there is one but I would be interested in hearing about it from each of our witnesses in terms of being able to make plans.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_120">
          <from> Mr. Philip O'Donnell<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_219">Fundamentally, the question is how we see the future of the community and voluntary sector in Ireland and its importance. The Deputy is right in all she said. There are tremendous difficulties in attracting and retaining staff when there is such a clear disparity in pay and conditions between similar types of work in the community and voluntary sector and in the public service, for example. That is already becoming very real on the ground. I know representatives from The Wheel were present last week. The Wheel took a very systematic look at this issue and examined the pay disparities. For the community and voluntary sector to continue to deliver, it needs to have that capacity. Having multi-annual funding that is sufficient to pay at a grade commensurate with what is available in the public sector and elsewhere is very important.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_121">
          <from> Mr. Terry Hyland<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_220">May I jump in there as well? As an employer who is multifunded, the terms and conditions are often set by various funders. There are disparities between them as well. We have staff within our own organisation who will have no pension entitlements until auto-enrolment comes in, yet there are people sitting beside them who do have pension entitlements. The problem with annual funding is that, when the Revised Estimates come out around December, we potentially have to put people on protective notice two weeks before Christmas because we cannot guarantee them contracts of employment in January.</p>
          <p eId="para_221"> The community and voluntary sector has become so professionalised in terms of the services delivered that staff are highly sought after by local authorities and the HSE due to their skill sets. Therefore, the community and voluntary sector is competing with the public sector for high-quality employees but cannot offer the same terms and conditions, or even salaries. Our offering is about 10% or 15% behind on salaries with no security of employment. These people have their own homes, lives and mortgages and we cannot be competitive. That puts us on the back foot. We look after the most vulnerable in society, so we need to make sure we have the right quality of people. Ms Lennon mentioned that in her opening statement.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_122">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_222">Does Ms Fleming want to comment?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_123">
          <from> Ms Grainne Fleming<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:40:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_223">I thank the Deputy for asking the question. This is a major problem, not just for the PPN in Kildare, but for PPNs throughout the country. We are hosted in a number of different ways. The way in which we have been set up left the decision in the hands of very capable volunteers at the time. Twenty-one PPNs are hosted by the local authorities and the rest are split between private CLGs and hosting by third parties within the community. As a result of this, their staff are all on different terms and conditions. As can well be imagined, this leads to major difficulties within the organisation as a whole. We have no entitlements to sick leave or maternity leave. We have no entitlement to incremental increases year on year.</p>
          <p eId="para_224">We have no right to permanent contracts in many cases. Our staff were never really in a position to look for mortgages, never mind short-term personal loans. The attrition levels within PPNs are a major concern for us. What we do is quite complex. We are very passionate about what we do, but unfortunately a huge amount of expertise is walking out the door on us every day. That is something we have to address. At least if we look at changing the way in which we are funded to a long-term model, it gives some level of stability to the really good people we have in place who are very experienced in what they do. It would certainly go a long way towards addressing some of the challenges we encounter.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LouiseOReilly" eId="spk_124">
          <from>Deputy Louise O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_225">Let us take meals on wheels as an example and then consider the school meals provision programme for which multi-annual funding is available. The process is constructed in a way that only massive companies can tender. They do not pay their workers well unlike in the community and voluntary sector. A stream of funding and certainty is available to that sector for private businesses. I have previously asked this of the Minister. I believe there is scope for meals on wheels to get involved in that. This would give us real oversight on the quality of the food and the local element, as well as using the considerable resources of the State to drive decent wages. That needs to be considered.</p>
          <p eId="para_226"> The witnesses referred to the SILC data, which contain a variety of one-off cost-of-living measures. Thanks to the media and leaks from the Cabinet, we know that there are people who sit at the Cabinet table who believe the cost-of-living crisis is over. I would be interested to know if that is the witnesses' view or the view of the people they support. Obviously, the one-off measures were important but in terms of the cost-of-living crisis, I do not believe it is over and my constituents say it is not-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_125">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_227">The Deputy should ask a question because we are running out of time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LouiseOReilly" eId="spk_126">
          <from>Deputy Louise O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_228">I will indeed. The Government has signalled that there will not be any one-off measures. What will the impact of that be on the people the witnesses represent?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_127">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_229">We will move on to Deputy McGuinness.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ConorDMcGuinness" eId="spk_128">
          <from>Deputy Conor D. McGuinness<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_230">I am very grateful for the very comprehensive submission that Irish Rural Link provided. I am really interested in the concept of rural proofing, which should be done for all Government policy and funding decisions. Would Irish Rural Link like the Government to start rural proofing, both for the budget we are talking about here and in general?</p>
          <p eId="para_231"> I have major concerns about how housing policy is failing rural communities and how rural communities are being hollowed out. The national planning framework's objective to push people into cities and larger urban areas is adding to demand for housing in those areas while removing people from the areas they grew up in and where they would like to rear their children.</p>
          <p eId="para_232"> I note that Irish Rural Link referenced capital funding for transport. I always tell the story of the senior roads engineer in my county of Waterford when I was a councillor. He was tearing his hair out when we came to the roads programme every January saying that the roads needed to be resurfaced or maintained every 20 years and that, with the budget allocation he was being given by the Department, it would be every 40 years at best.</p>
          <p eId="para_233"> That is the context. I would like to hear from the witnesses how the Government might put rural proofing in place.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_129">
          <from> Ms Louise Lennon<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_234">I thank the Deputy for his questions. I know the Department of rural and community development ran a pilot on this, engaging other Departments. There has been no update from that and it would be good to get an update.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ConorDMcGuinness" eId="spk_130">
          <from>Deputy Conor D. McGuinness<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_235">What methodology would Irish Rural Link recommend to the Government so that might work?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_131">
          <from> Ms Louise Lennon<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_236">Each Department needs to be involved and it needs to be cross-departmental. They need to look at how their policies would impact. In healthcare, for example, the lack of access to GPs is a real problem, given the retirement of GPs in rural areas. Even when GPs reach the age of 66, it has an impact because they may no longer see medical card patients. There is an impact on a rural community with no GP or where a GP can only see private patients. There is the impact of no public transport as I indicated in my opening statement and the accommodation centre not having access to transport. It goes back to Senator Flaherty's comment that extending it by ten minutes could solve that issue. People have been excluded from society and excluded from reaching employment, education and hospital appointments. Each Department should be required to look at what the impacts are.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_132">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_237">We will take the two remaining speakers and then have final comments from our witnesses.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#LouiseOReilly" eId="spk_133">
          <from>Deputy Louise O'Reilly<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_238">I asked a question about cost-of-living measures and I would appreciate an answer to that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_134">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_239">We can get the answer to that as well.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_135">
          <from>Deputy Micheál Carrigy<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_240">I welcome all the representatives today. For a long time, I have been involved in local community work, working with the local LEADER company in Longford, Longford Community Resources Limited. I have been involved in numerous applications and I know the tedious paperwork associated with it. It is that way for a reason - to ensure it is done right and there are no issues when it comes to the project being done and any money being claimed back. It has done a massive amount of work in my community over the last two programmes. We have one of the highest percentages of funding in the county and all that money has been well spent in every community in our county.</p>
          <p eId="para_241"> I do see what the witnesses have said. A number of the staff are now staff members in Longford County Council. They have worked hard in Longford Community Resources, trained up and worked with communities. Needless to say, Longford County Council can see the benefit of having staff members like that. They have moved on to get more benefits for themselves, security of employment and pension rights. I would be fully supportive of that entitlement being there for staff members of Longford Community Resources as well as other bodies across the country.</p>
          <p eId="para_242"> I have a question slightly away from Longford Community Resources but it is an issue where community organisations struggle with funding. The Western Development Commission is able to provide low-cost matching grant funding for projects, including LEADER projects. Should that be established across the country?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_136">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_243">We will go on to the answers now.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_137">
          <from>Deputy Micheál Carrigy<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_244">I have another question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_138">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_245">I ask the Deputy to be brief.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichealCarrigy" eId="spk_139">
          <from>Deputy Micheál Carrigy<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T11:50:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_246">I apologise; I did not think I would be limited on time. I welcome, in particular, Ms Cronogue from Longford. I have worked closely with her for many years. County Longford PPN does fantastic work. We have the highest percentage of organisations in the country registered with the local PPN. We had an event here in September of last year where Ms Cronogue came to Leinster House and explained to members the issues that were there and the need for more funding to be put in place for security of employment for staff. I ask her to outline how the PPN has benefited our community in Longford. What challenges is the PPN facing? What funding is needed to resolve these issues? I believe that any funding provided is money well spent in my community.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterRoche" eId="spk_140">
          <from>Deputy Peter Roche<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_247">I thank the panel for their opening statements. I can only speak for myself, but when it comes to rural development and making a case to this committee, the witnesses are pushing an open door. In my previous role as a councillor, I was chair of Galway Rural Development, and we were all the time preaching and shouting about the lack of funding. I will always reference this, for what it is worth, because the funding model is something I take issue with. I am not suggesting for one second that I should be naming counties, but I will draw a comparison if that is okay. County Roscommon gets €97 LEADER funding per person. It is €76 in County Offaly, €64 in County Mayo and €53 in County Clare. Galway east gets €37 per person. As previous speakers have referenced, I see every day of the week the outstanding work going on in communities from that small investment and the wonderful rewards reaped as a consequence.</p>
          <p eId="para_248"> The witnesses referenced the local development companies. Their submission highlighted the success of the new arrivals fund. Would they anticipate or support its full integration into SICAP?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_141">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_249">I thank the Deputy. Unfortunately for the other Deputies and Senators, we have run out of time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_142">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_250">Are you not going to allow me in at all now-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_143">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_251">Unfortunately, not.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_144">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_252">-----after sitting here the whole length?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_145">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_253">I am sorry, Deputy. I said there was another committee meeting at 12.30 p.m., and we have to vacate and be out.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_146">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_254">I think the Chair should start a rule. I came here to this meeting this morning. I left my house at 7.05 a.m.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_147">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_255">That is fine.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_148">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_256">I think I am entitled to talk at the meeting. I am just saying that the Chair should be able to judge and allocate time, whether it is four minutes each or whatever.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_149">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_257">The witnesses will be around afterwards, Deputy.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_150">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_258">It is not right. In fairness, I was here hours before Deputy Carrigy and they will not allow me to speak.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_151">
          <from>Senator Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_259">Deputy Aird was here.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_152">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_260">I think it is unfair.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_153">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_261">I am chairing. I really apologise.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_154">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_262">There is no point coming to the meetings then.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_155">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_263">We have three witnesses here, and we are doing our best to accommodate them. They will be around after the discussion.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_156">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_264">It is up to the Chair to allow every person in.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_157">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_265">Absolutely, Deputy Aird, and I do so as best I can. I ask the three witnesses now-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_158">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_266">Well, it is not good enough when you do not get in.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_159">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_267">-----to give just a roundup of one minute.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_160">
          <from>Senator Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_268">Sorry, Chair, just before they come in-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_161">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_269">I am sorry, Senator. I am the Chair, so a bit of respect.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeFlaherty" eId="spk_162">
          <from>Senator Joe Flaherty<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_270">Sorry, Chair.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_163">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_271">Will Mr. O'Donnell give a one minute roundup please?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_164">
          <from> Mr. Philip O'Donnell<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_272">I will leave the question of one-off welfare measures to some of my colleagues in the interests of the time we have left. In respect of the possibility of the Western Development Commission as an example of providing match-funding, I say "Yes" in principle. However, we have a concern about catchment and the Western Development Commission's remit is in that part of the country to ensure there is equitability of access.</p>
          <p eId="para_273"> On the broader point about access to things like LEADER funding, we have a concern about the movement towards larger organisations tapping into it and the difficulty smaller organisations have because of the bureaucracy and difficulty of applying for LEADER funding.</p>
          <p eId="para_274"> On the new arrivals fund and the potential roll into SICAP, the answer is "Yes" on the basis that it does not come at the expense of funding that is already there for SICAP or what SICAP as a core programme actually needs.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_165">
          <from> Ms Louise Lennon<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_275">On the impact of the cost-of-living measures, the cost-of-living crisis is not over. We see that especially for essential food items with the people we represent. The meals on wheels services are feeling the impact of that too. As I mentioned, we need to start investing in social welfare and providing adequate income for people on low incomes. The one-off measures did not bring up the consistent poverty rate. There would have been a slight increase had they not been there, but we need to start focusing on lifting people out of poverty.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_166">
          <from> Ms Siobhan Cronogue<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_276">I thank Deputy Carrigy for the question. I will start with the challenges. I am speaking on behalf of the 31 PPNs today. We are looking for an increase of €2.5 million. That is to support the proper regrading of staff. Our support workers are on unstable one-year temporary contracts. The co-ordinators were piloted ten years ago at grade five and although the remit, role and responsibility have grown substantially, the grade has not changed. I will give an example. We started with approximately 300 community groups and the anticipated membership for this year is 24,000 groups. We have more than 1,000 reps on 418 decision-making committees, both within and outside the local authority.</p>
          <p eId="para_277"> On the benefits Longford PPN has given the county, the social value of Longford PPN and the efforts of our community groups is estimated at approximately €62 million, and that is a conservative figure. However, if we multiply it by 31, then PPNs around the country are saving the Government just under €2 billion. It is a small ask to stabilise PPNs and retain staff.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JohnPaulOShea" eId="spk_167">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-07-16T12:00:00+01:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_278">I thank Ms Cronogue and the local development companies network, Irish Rural Link and the Kildare Public Participation Network for their contributions today and providing the various briefing materials in advance of the meeting. Following both sets of hearings I propose the committee send a letter to the Minister enclosing the meetings' transcripts for review as part of the budgetary process. Is that agreed? Agreed.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_8"> The joint committee adjourned at 12.06 p.m. <i>sine die.</i></summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
