<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0/CSD13 ./akomantoso30.xsd">
  <debate name="Official Report">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#debates">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_and_food/2025-11-12/debate/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_and_food/2025-11-12/debate"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-11-12" name="#generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#author" href="/ie/oireachtas/committee/dail/34/joint_committee_on_agriculture_and_food"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="ie"/>
          <FRBRname value="debate"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_and_food/2025-11-12/debate/mul@/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_and_food/2025-11-12/debate/mul@"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-11-12" name="#reported"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_and_food/2025-11-12/debate/mul@/main.xml"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/ie/debateRecord/joint_committee_on_agriculture_and_food/2025-11-12/debate/mul@.akn"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2025-11-18" name="#publication"/>
          <FRBRauthor as="#editor" href="#debates"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#debates">
        <TLCPerson eId="AindriasMoynihan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Aindrias-Moynihan.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Aindrias Moynihan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="JoeCooney" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Joe-Cooney.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Joe Cooney"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MartinKenny" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Martin-Kenny.D.2016-10-03" showAs="Martin Kenny"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="MichaelFitzmaurice" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Michael-Fitzmaurice.D.2014-10-10" showAs="Michael Fitzmaurice"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="NatashaNewsomeDrennan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Natasha-Newsome-Drennan.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Natasha Newsome Drennan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="ParaicBrady" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paraic-Brady.S.2025-01-29" showAs="Paraic Brady"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaulDaly" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paul-Daly.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Paul Daly"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PaulLawless" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Paul-Lawless.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Paul Lawless"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="PeterChapCleere" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Peter-'Chap'-Cleere.D.2024-11-29" showAs="Peter 'Chap' Cleere"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="VictorBoyhan" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/Victor-Boyhan.S.2016-04-25" showAs="Victor Boyhan"/>
        <TLCPerson eId="WilliamAird" href="/ie/oireachtas/member/id/William-Aird.D.2024-11-29" showAs="William Aird"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/chair" showAs="Chair" eId="Chair"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/vice_chairman" showAs="Vice Chairman" eId="Vice_Chairman"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/author" showAs="author" eId="author"/>
        <TLCRole href="role/editor" showAs="editor" eId="editor"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <block name="title_ga">
        <docTitle>DÍOSPÓIREACHTAÍ PARLAIMINTE</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="title_en">
        <docTitle>PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES</docTitle>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_ga">
        <docProponent>TITHE an OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="proponent_en">
        <docProponent>HOUSES OF THE OIREACHTAS</docProponent>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_ga">
        <docCommittee>AN COMHCHOISTE UM THALMHAÍOCHT AGUS BIA</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="committee_en">
        <docCommittee>Joint Committee on Agriculture and Food</docCommittee>
      </block>
      <block name="status_ga">
        <docStatus>TUAIRISC OIFIGIÚIL</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="status_en">
        <docStatus>(OFFICIAL REPORT)</docStatus>
      </block>
      <block name="date_ga">
        <docDate date="2025-11-12">Dé Céadaoin, 12 Samhain 2025</docDate>
      </block>
      <block name="date_en">
        <docDate date="2025-11-12">Wednesday, 12 November 2025</docDate>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_en">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
      <block refersTo="#unrevised" name="version_ga">
        <docStatus/>
      </block>
    </preface>
    <debateBody>
      <debateSection name="prelude" eId="dbsect_1">
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_1">Tháinig an Comhchoiste le chéile ag 03:30 p.m.</summary>
        <summary class="Center" eId="sum_2">The Joint Committee met at 03:30 p.m.</summary>
        <rollCall>
          <summary class="Center" eId="sum_3">Comhaltaí a bhí i láthair / Members present:</summary>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_1">Teachtaí Dála / Deputies</p>
              </th>
              <th>
                <p eId="para_2">Seanadóirí / Senators</p>
              </th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_3">
                  <person refersTo="#WilliamAird">William Aird</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_4">
                  <person refersTo="#VictorBoyhan">Victor Boyhan</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_5">
                  <person refersTo="#PeterChapCleere">Peter 'Chap' Cleere</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_6">
                  <person refersTo="#ParaicBrady">Paraic Brady</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_7">
                  <person refersTo="#JoeCooney">Joe Cooney</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_8">
                  <person refersTo="#JoanneCollins">Joanne Collins</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_9">
                  <person refersTo="#MichaelFitzmaurice">Michael Fitzmaurice</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_10">
                  <person refersTo="#PaulDaly">Paul Daly</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_11">
                  <person refersTo="#DannyHealyRae">Danny Healy-Rae</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_12">
                  <person refersTo="#EileenLynch">Eileen Lynch.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_13">
                  <person refersTo="#MartinKenny">Martin Kenny</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_14">
                  <person refersTo="#PaulLawless">Paul Lawless</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <p eId="para_15">
                  <person refersTo="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan">Natasha Newsome Drennan.</person>
                </p>
              </td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <summary eId="sum_4">
            <person as="#Chair" refersTo="#AindriasMoynihan">Teachta / Deputy Aindrias Moynihan sa Chathaoir / in the Chair.</person>
          </summary>
        </rollCall>
      </debateSection>
      <debateSection name="debate" eId="dbsect_2">
        <heading>Collection of Farm Plastics: Discussion<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:30:00+00:00"/></heading>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_1">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_16">I draw to the attention of the witnesses that when giving evidence from within the parliamentary precincts, they are protected by absolute privilege in respect of the evidence they give to the committee. This means they have a full defence in any defamation action in respect of anything said at a committee meeting. However, witnesses are expected not to abuse this privilege and may be directed at the Chair's discretion to cease giving evidence on any issue. They should follow the direction of the Chair in this regard. I remind witnesses of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that, insofar as is reasonable, no adverse commentary should be made against an identifiable third person or entity. Witnesses who are to give evidence from a location outside the parliamentary precincts are asked to note that they may not benefit from the same level of immunity from legal proceedings as witnesses giving evidence from within the parliamentary precincts. They may consider it appropriate to take legal advice on this matter. Privilege against defamation does not apply to the publication by witnesses outside the proceedings held by the committee of any matters arising from the proceedings.</p>
          <p eId="para_17"> I advise members of the constitutional requirement that they must be physically present within the confines of the Leinster House complex to participate in public meetings. I will not permit members to participate where they are not adhering to the constitutional requirement. Therefore, a member who attempts to participate from outside the precincts will be asked to leave the meeting. In this regard, I ask any members participating via MS Teams, prior to making their contribution to the meeting, to confirm they are on the grounds of the Leinster House campus.</p>
          <p eId="para_18"> Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice that they should not criticise or make charges against any person or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable, or otherwise engage in speech that might be regarded as damaging to the good name of the person or entity. Therefore, if their statements are potentially defamatory in respect of an identifiable person or entity, they will be directed to discontinue their remarks. It is imperative that they comply with any such direction.</p>
          <p eId="para_19"> Today's meeting is to discuss the collection of farm plastics. I welcome the following witnesses from the Department of Climate, Energy and the Environment: Ms Bernie Kiely, principal officer; and Ms Danielle McCormack, assistant principal officer. We will also hear from the following witnesses from the Irish Farm Film Producers Group, IFFPG: Mr. Tom Dunne, chairperson; Mr. Liam Moloney, general manager; and Ms Geraldine O'Sullivan, co-secretary and director. Cuirim fáilte rompu go léir.</p>
          <p eId="para_20"> Copies of the witnesses' opening statements have been circulated to members but we will allow five minutes for opening comments, after which there will be an opportunity for questions and answers.</p>
          <p eId="para_21">Since this is only one session, I propose that we take extra time for each speaker slot of ten minutes -----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_2">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_22">Can the Chair let us back in?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_3">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_23">If we do the ten minutes, then there is an opportunity for a second round of questions. I will not be excluding members. I want to give people the opportunity to ask as many questions as they feel appropriate and we will use the full time on it. Are members okay with that? Okay.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_4">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_24">I thank the committee for giving us the opportunity to be here this afternoon to talk about farm plastics. One of the Department’s functions in relation to waste management is to set the policy and legislative framework for the extended producer responsibility, EPR, model in Ireland across the various waste streams. Ireland uses the EPR model for dealing with a number of waste streams, including farm plastics, tyres, end of life vehicles, packaging, electrical equipment and batteries. These schemes have been developed based on the producer pays principle. This is where producers have responsibility to finance the collection and environmentally sound management of their products at end of life. To date, these schemes have operated successfully and have assisted Ireland in reaching its domestic and EU recycling targets. Producer responsibility schemes operate under ministerial approval. The Department has oversight of the ministerial approval. Day-to-day operational matters are the responsibility of the schemes.</p>
          <p eId="para_25"> Ireland is one of a few countries in Europe to have introduced legislation specifically designed to promote the recycling of farm plastics. This legislation places a legal responsibility on producers of farm film products to specifically support recycling. The options open to producers placing farm film products on the Irish market are to either become directly involved in the recycling of farm plastics waste and operating a deposit and return scheme or to participate in an approved farm plastics recycling scheme. To date, producers have opted to meet their obligations in this respect by becoming members of a compliance scheme.</p>
          <p eId="para_26"> Under the legislation, the Irish Farm Film Producers Group Limited, IFFPG, operates further to an approval granted by the Minister as the national farm plastics recycling scheme. IFFPG has been doing so since 1998. The company is a not-for-profit body, which is owned by its producer members and the Irish Farmers’ Association. IFFPG’s current approval is due to expire at the end of 2025. It is open to producers to establish an alternative scheme at any time and seek ministerial approval under the regulations, should they wish to do so. The Department is not aware of interest by other groups in applying for ministerial approval. </p>
          <p eId="para_27"> Under the approved scheme, producers pay a producer recycling contribution to IFFPG based on the quantity of product they place on the market. The recycling contribution applies to all product based on the Irish market and, along with a collection fee for farmers set by IFFPG, is used to fund the collection, transportation and treatment of farm plastics. The role of the Department is oversight of IFFPG’s adherence to the terms of its approval. A mid-term review of IFFPG’s current approval was concluded in 2024 and the Department requested IFFPG to undertake a series of actions relating to the board, the contingency fund and enforcement matters. The Department is satisfied that IFFPG is engaging positively with the outcomes of the review and we continue to monitor same to ensure that the requirements set by it are fully implemented.</p>
          <p eId="para_28"> IFFPG is performing well in relation to its record of collection and recycling of farm plastic as set out in its annual report published on its website. The Department is supportive of IFFPG’s contribution to the environmental management of farm plastics.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_5">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_29">Thank you.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_6">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_30">There was also a letter - a reply from the Minister - issued earlier today that came to the committee. I am not sure whether the Chair received that. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_7">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_31">It is received. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_8">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_32">Okay. If anybody needs to know what was in the letter, I am happy to -----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_9">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_33">We will be dealing with that under correspondence later. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_10">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_34">Okay. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_11">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_35">We need to know what was in the letter. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_12">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_36">We would typically be getting our correspondence on Friday and we would deal with it the fortnight after. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_13">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_37">That letter could influence proceedings here this evening. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_14">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_38">I have not seen it. We have received it but I have not seen it. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#VictorBoyhan" eId="spk_15">
          <from>Senator Victor Boyhan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_39">Will Ms Kiely read it into the record now?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_16">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_40">I second that. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_17">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_41">One moment.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#VictorBoyhan" eId="spk_18">
          <from>Senator Victor Boyhan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_42">With Ms Kiely's agreement and that of the Chair, she can read it into the record of this meeting, as I think it may be relevant. We do not want to waste anyone's time. It would be Ms Kiely's decision and we would not be forcing anyone to do anything. If Ms Kiely and the Chair are agreeable, I think we should have it read into the record of the meeting now. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulDaly" eId="spk_19">
          <from>Senator Paul Daly<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_43">I support that. Agreed. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_20">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_44">I am happy to read the body of the letter, subject to the official receipt of the letter through the committee. </p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_45">Cathaoirleach,</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_46">Thank you for your correspondence of 16 October 2025 in relation to the performance of Irish Farm Film Producers Group (IFFPG), which operates the waste farm plastics extended producer responsibility scheme under Ministerial Approval. I note that IFFPG and officials from the Department accepted the invitation to appear before your committee on 12 November. My response to your specific queries is set out below.</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_47">Mid-Term Review</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_48">As you are aware from correspondence issued to the Committee on 12 September 2025, IFFPG was provided with a list of recommendations further to the conclusion of the Mid-Term Review. The Department has been monitoring compliance with these recommendations and while it continues to prove challenging to build up the Contingency Fund, IFFPG has been engaging positively and constructively with all recommendations and I have provided an update on some key areas below. </p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_49">- Annual training is being provided to IFFPG board members to support discharge of their functions. A comprehensive presentation to the board from its solicitor was delivered in May 2025. </p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_50">- IFFPG has agreed an enforcement protocol with the Waste Enforcement Regional Lead Authorities (WERLAs), with an initial focus on targeting non-compliant retailers in the border region. </p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_51">- IFFPG is developing an enforcement portal which is expected to be operational by the end of the year. </p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_52">- IFFPG has approved scrutiny of product codes presented by farmers at bring centres. </p>
          <p class="indent_2" eId="para_53">- IFFPG has been successfully addressing the storage of legacy farm plastic waste at its contracted sites, and this is being monitored on a monthly basis by the WERLAs. </p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_54">Contingency fund</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_55">IFFPG commissioned a business review of its operations, which was undertaken by IFAC. This was completed in March 2025 and makes recommendations across IFFPG’s areas of operation in the context of its challenging operational environment. As the report was commissioned by IFFPG, I have requested the group to provide you with the report.</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_56">Contract</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_57">The Waste Management (Farm Plastics) Regulations, 2001, state that a producer of farm plastics may self-comply with the Regulations by operating a deposit and return scheme, or they may join a collective compliance scheme to discharge their responsibilities under the Regulations. Any organisation representing producers may apply for approval to operate a scheme at any time, and once all required information has been provided, the application will be considered by the Department. A key issue for any producer responsibility organisation is support from industry, and therefore, it is a matter for the sector to initiate any such application.</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_58">IFFPG submitted its application for a further Ministerial Approval under the Waste Farm Plastics Regulations in July 2025. </p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_59">I trust the above addresses the concerns of the Committee.</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_60">Yours sincerely,</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_61">Alan Dillon TD, Minister of State with responsibility for Circular Economy at the Department of Climate, Energy and the Environment</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_21">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_62">Just to clarify a point. Correspondence was issued on 12 November, which is today. It was to an email address: "JCAM". That is not the committee. The committee has not had an opportunity to consider it. The information within it is available. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#VictorBoyhan" eId="spk_22">
          <from>Senator Victor Boyhan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_63">It is now on the record.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_23">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_64">Yes, and it will be made available to the committee and discussed in due course. We will move on to the second submission.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_24">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_65">We are very happy to be here today. We have circulated an opening statement and the independent IFAC review of the scheme, which was carried out earlier this year. I am going to give a quick verbal overview of the opening statement to provide an idea of who we are, where we are coming from and what are currently focused on.</p>
          <p eId="para_66"> We were one of the first EPR schemes established in the country. We were established in 1998 by the key stakeholders, namely, the farm plastic producers, the companies that put farm plastic products on the market, and the IFA. As the committee has heard already, we are licensed for five-year periods by the Department of the environment. We are a not-for-profit company and our focus is on providing a comprehensive collection service to farmers and to exceed the national recycling targets as set by the Department of the environment for farm plastic waste. Our board is representative of the key stakeholders, the farm plastic producers and the IFA, as well as some independent directors. We are funded primarily by the recycling levy but also by a weight-based collection charge. That encourages farmers to bring in cleaner plastics to the bring centres.</p>
          <p eId="para_67"> As far as collecting the plastic goes, we collect through a network of approved contractors. They are selected following an open national tendering process that is typically held every five years. The most recent one was concluded at the beginning of this year and we currently have five approved contractors.</p>
          <p eId="para_68"> When it comes to results, what the scheme has achieved is hugely impressive by any standard. We have 100,000 farmer customers, so the vast majority of farmers in Ireland are engaging with the service. They engage with the service because it is convenient, cost effective and, above all, reliable. We are collecting and recycling virtually all plastic that is being put on the market by our members. We have a virtual 100% recycling rate. There is no other waste plastic stream in the country that comes anywhere close to this.</p>
          <p eId="para_69"> Everything has not been easy, however, in recent years. We have had to deal with a very difficult recycling market situation. That has come about because of global events such as war in Ukraine, Covid and, before that, a decision by the Chinese to stop importing plastic waste. That has resulted in a 600% increase in the cost of recycling farm plastics in the last six or seven years. It has been a difficult operating environment, but I am pleased to say that we have worked our way through financial and storage pressures that were there over the last few years and are in a very good space now. If members have not had an opportunity to do so already, I recommend they look at the IFAC independent review, particularly the executive summary, which highlights how difficult the recycling market was. Not only did we navigate our way through that difficult market but we continued to achieve record recycling levels. However, we are aware there are no grounds for complacency. The current geopolitical situation is very uncertain, so we have to stay alert and agile to deal with anything else that comes our way.</p>
          <p eId="para_70"> I thank the committee for the invitation today and we look forward to engaging with members in a constructive discussion.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_25">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_71">The IFAC report has been circulated to members. It will not be included in the minutes of the meeting but it will be published as part of any of the correspondence that would be available to members, along with the opening statement. I have seven speakers offering. Deputy Fitzmaurice has ten minutes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_26">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_72">I will do quick-fire questions, to Ms Kiely first. The Department is reviewing a licence renewal at the moment. I presume she knows off the top of her head the amount of plastic that is lying in yards around the country. What tonnage is it?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_27">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_73">It is a moving target, if you like. It is monitored by the enforcement-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_28">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_74">Most of the plastic is gathered now, so let us be honest. What are the figures around Ireland at the moment, in all the different yards, before the Department gives out a licence?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_29">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_75">I will defer to the scheme on that. We are not operating-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_30">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_76">Sorry, you are the Department, you give out licences. Obviously the Department would have an independent assessor going around checking that up, so what is the tonnage?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_31">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_77">We are not deciding the licence today.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_32">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_78">What?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_33">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_79">We are not deciding the licence today.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_34">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_80">I know that. I asked what is the tonnage today. Obviously the Department has an up-to-date account of it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_35">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_81">I can give the Deputy the last figures I have. At the end of September we were advised that there was approximately 24,440 tonnes of farm plastics stored at contractors' yards.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_36">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_82">Is that advised by somebody else or does the Department have its own independent person who looks?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_37">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_83">In the first instance, the IFFPG gives us information and that is verified with the-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_38">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_84">Yes I understand that but does the Department have its own independent assessor?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_39">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_85">The waste enforcement regional lead authority, WERLA is there, which is the local authority enforcement body. They verify on a monthly basis.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_40">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_86">They have a person who goes out to each yard and they know the accurate tonnage. They have a QS who is able to assess it. Is that right?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_41">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_87">They go out if they need to go out, or-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_42">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_88">Are those figures available to this committee where each person went out to different yards and assessed the tonnage?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_43">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_89">We can get that kind of information for the Deputy if he likes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_44">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_90">Okay. At the moment I am aware there is an investigation from Europe into plastics in Ireland. Is the Department aware of that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_45">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_91">We are aware of that but we are not party to it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_46">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_92">Has the Department to do any correspondence on that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_47">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_93">Not now. I do not think we have either. We have not provided any input into it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_48">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_94">There are 24,000 tonnes around the country, going by what Ms Kiely is saying. My next question is to IFFPG. Where does most of its plastic go at the moment?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_49">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_95">Our plastic is going to a combination of Irish and European facilities.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_50">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_96">What are the European facilities? Is that Cedo?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_51">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_97">Cedo is actually in the process of-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_52">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_98">Is Mr. Moloney aware that Cedo is now closed or closing?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_53">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_99">It is in the process of relocating to another facility elsewhere, that is right. It is relocating at the moment.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_54">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_100">Will that cause a problem?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_55">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_101">We would prefer if it were open but we can manage it. We have enough recycling capacity elsewhere.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_56">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_102">What percentage is recycled in Ireland in tonnage?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_57">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_103">It is 50:50, so last year around 50% was-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_58">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_104">What is 50%? Give me tonnage.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_59">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_105">That was 20,000 tonnes. We recycled 40,000 tonnes last year and half was recycled in Ireland.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_60">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_106">Were 40,000 tonnes recycled altogether?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_61">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_107">Correct.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_62">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_108">Of that, 20,000 tonnes was recycled in Ireland. There is one plant in Ireland that had 4,000 tonnes of a licence and looked for 20,000 tonnes last January. I understand Mr. Moloney's operation has sent plastic to it since. It was refused a licence. Does that worry Mr. Moloney?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_63">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_109">I am not aware of any such action. We are supplying plastic just to permitted facilities and the facilities we are supplying to have permits at this time and point.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_64">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_110">For running this business, going by the figures I am looking at, what does Mr. Moloney's business get paid for by the importers every year?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_65">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_111">We charge companies that put plastic on the market in the first instance through the recycling levy.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_66">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_112">How many tonnes come in that you get paid for?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_67">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_113">It varies but it is in the region of 20,000 to 22,000 tonnes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_68">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_114">Then when it is going out, it is obviously twice as heavy.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_69">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_115">Correct.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_70">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_116">So that is 40,000 tonnes. So you would get €286 for the 22,000 tonnes and €120 for the 40,000 tonnes. Is that right?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_71">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_117">That is correct.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_72">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_118">A tonne is costing roughly around €500, would that be right?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_73">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_119">The Deputy can add up the figures and see what it is costing at the moment. It is costing the €286 plus the €120 per tonne to recycle what we are recycling.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_74">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_120">You will have twice as much tonnage then, going out, will you not?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_75">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_121">There is twice as much tonnage, exactly.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_76">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_122">So the €120 is €240 really.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_77">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_123">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_78">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_124">So €240 and €286 would be €526 a tonne, which is what it is costing the farmers. It is the farmers who are paying this.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_79">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_125">Ultimately, yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_80">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_126">It was €5 a roll. That is what we used to put it down as. It is actually costing something like €11 or €12 a roll now when we double it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_81">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_127">Excluding VAT, around €7.40 or €7.50.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_82">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_128">That is when it comes in but when it goes out as well.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_83">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_129">That is the price excluding VAT for the farmer when they buy the product, the hardware.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_84">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_130">I am talking about when they get rid of it as well. It is costing about €12 a roll when you add it up</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_85">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_131">It could well be.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_86">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T15:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_132">Maybe more, maybe €14.</p>
          <p eId="para_133">The IFFPG is forward paid by the different companies. Is it this time of year they are paid?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_87">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_134">Typically, we are paid from May onwards.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_88">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_135">For the amount of tonnage around the country, what financial lump has the group in the kitty? If there is 24,000 tonnes, is the IFFPG paid now for next year's import part?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_89">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_136">No. Next year, when the product goes on the market, we will get the money for next year. We are in a very good financial position at the moment and well capable of covering the recession cost of everything that we have in storage.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_90">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_137">What is that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_91">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_138">Is the Deputy asking how much is in storage at the moment? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_92">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_139">No, I am asking about the group's financial position. What is the financial back-up? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_93">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_140">If the Deputy was to look at our reserve, which is total assets minus liabilities, we would probably----- </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_94">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_141">I am talking about cash and cash is needed to get rid of plastic.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_95">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_142">Yes. We would have at the moment not far off €3 million. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_96">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_143">Going by what I am looking at, if there is 24,000 tonnes around the country and the charge is €125 a tonne, will that get rid of plastic at the moment? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_97">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_144">It would.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_98">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_145">Will it? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_99">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_146">We are going to get more money coming through in the new year as well.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_100">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_147">If €125 a tonne gets rid of plastic, which means €3 million will get rid of 24,000 tonnes. So why are farmers paying €540 a tonne?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_101">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_148">Maybe the Deputy did not get a chance to look at our audited accounts, which are published on our website. The accounts show the amount of money that we need, that we bring in and what we spend. At the moment we are generating a surplus and we feel very comfortable that we have enough money.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_102">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_149">Can you square that circle for me? Mr. Moloney has said that the IFFPG can get rid of the plastic at the moment at a cost of €125 a tonne. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_103">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_150">This is what the Deputy is saying, yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_104">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_151">No, Mr. Moloney is saying that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_105">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_152">No.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_106">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_153">Mr. Moloney has said that his group has €3 million in its account. At the moment it has been stated that there are 24,440 tonnes of plastic around Ireland. If every bit of that plastic is got rid of, Mr. Moloney has said that his group is financially solvent, and if I calculate the figure rough in my head then it costs €125 a tonne to get rid of every bit of the plastic if the group has €3 million in its account. That is what Mr. Moloney is saying his group can rid of the plastic for but I am saying that farmers, between what they are paying coming in and going out, is paying €540. Where is the discrepancy? Either the group has not a heap of money in the bank or there is a link missing.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_107">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_154">There is no discrepancy and there is no link missing. If the Deputy looks at our accounts for last year he will see that we-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_108">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_155">I am not questioning the accounts but the figures in terms of what Mr. Moloney has said.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_109">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_156">I can only speak in aggregate terms. At the end of this year, we will have collected and recycled in the region of 40,000 tonnes and we will expect to still have €2.5 million to €3 million in the bank, and more money will be coming in in the new year. By the end of this year we would expect to have no more than, maybe, 14,000 or 15,000 tonnes in the yards.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_110">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_157">If there is a problem with Cedo in Holland, which is my understanding from everything that I have read, it means 20,000 tonnes is in a bit of jeopardy at the moment., is it?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_111">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_158">We were not quite sending them that much but we are working hard at the moment and putting in place notifications to supply to other recyclers in Europe. We expect some of those notifications to come through quite shortly. Indeed, when Cedo relocates to another location we will also supply to it at that new location.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_112">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_159">Is it fair to say the IFFPG sends plastic to different plants in Ireland?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_113">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_160">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_114">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_161">How many?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_115">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_162">At the moment, three.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_116">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_163">They are recycling plants.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_117">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_164">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_118">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_165">If there was a problem, does the Department watch where the plastic goes? If there was a problem with planning, would the Department be concerned?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_119">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_166">If we are notified by the enforcement authority of the local authority or the EPA, of course that would be a matter of concern.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_120">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_167">If notified. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_121">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_168">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_122">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_169">On contracts, is the Department open to different operators submitting a proposal in smaller scale around the country? What is the story with that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_123">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_170">If the producers of the plastics, who put the products on the market, come forward with their proposal we will look at it of course.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_124">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_171">Hold on now. Ms Kiely said, "the producers of the plastics". With all due respect, they do not produce plastic. They gather it. The producers are the crowds that make it or import it. Is that who Ms Kiely is saying has to make an application?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_125">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_172">The people who place the plastic on the market in Ireland, whether they produce it or retail it here as the first people to place it on the market.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_126">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_173">Is that closed to just them? With due respect, the IFFPG does not place plastic on the market in Ireland. Are there different rules for different folks?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_127">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_174">No. The members of the IFFPG, please correct me if I am wrong, are producers of plastic.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_128">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_175">So what the IFFPG is saying is that the importers are members of IFFPG. That is grand.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_129">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_176">The next speaker listed is Senator Boyhan but Deputy Cleere is here. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterChapCleere" eId="spk_130">
          <from>Deputy Peter 'Chap' Cleere<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_177">The IFFPG has operated as the approved body since 1998 and its approval is reviewed on an ongoing five-yearly basis. I also know that it is open to producers to establish an alternative scheme at any time. Is this advertised for alternative producers?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_131">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_178">It is not advertised at any particular point in time. No more than for any material stream, we do not advertise. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterChapCleere" eId="spk_132">
          <from>Deputy Peter 'Chap' Cleere<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_179">Does that not sound funny? There is a contract awarded for five years. With any local authority contract, where there is a deal with somebody for five years there is a public consultation to see if anybody else wants to come in and bid and, maybe, do a better deal. Ms Kiely has said that the Department does not even advertise this. It is just tick a box every five years and away you go. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_133">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_180">It is not a contract. When the regulations were made, back in the day, the obligation was placed on producers to put a scheme together. It was from that day forward that producers could approach the Department on any day of the week with a proposal. It just so happens that the proposal that came in is on its fifth-year anniversary.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterChapCleere" eId="spk_134">
          <from>Deputy Peter 'Chap' Cleere<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_181">Earlier Ms Kiely said that the Department is not aware of interest by other groups in applying for ministerial approval, but it is not advertised anywhere.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_135">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_182">No, but producers are aware that they have an obligation to do that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterChapCleere" eId="spk_136">
          <from>Deputy Peter 'Chap' Cleere<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_183">To be clinical, it is not advertised.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_137">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_184">No.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterChapCleere" eId="spk_138">
          <from>Deputy Peter 'Chap' Cleere<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_185">That seems strange to me. On the financial elements of the operation, I note that there has been significant increases in both the levy and collection charges in recent years. Please indicate where they have come from and where they are now. So we know now it is €286 per tonne and €120 per tonne at the collection points. What was it five years ago?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_139">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_186">That question is for the group.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_140">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_187">In simple terms, the levy and collection charges have pretty much doubled in the last four or five years. That has been necessary to meet the huge increase in recycling costs associated with all the global events of which we are aware.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterChapCleere" eId="spk_141">
          <from>Deputy Peter 'Chap' Cleere<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_188">Are there financial incentives for farmers?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_142">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_189">On the financial incentive in terms of the collection charge, because we charge by weight the farmer has an incentive to take out any pieces of contamination and we have made a lot of progress in that particular area. There is an incentive on that front.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterChapCleere" eId="spk_143">
          <from>Deputy Peter 'Chap' Cleere<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_190">Is there a cash or financial incentive?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_144">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_191">No. Unfortunately, the plastic has a huge negative value and the scheme is very expensive to run. So we have to charge both the members and farmers at the current rates in order to wash our face.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterChapCleere" eId="spk_145">
          <from>Deputy Peter 'Chap' Cleere<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_192">Can introducing incentives for farmers be considered in the future?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_146">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_193">In the past, when our finances were very flush, which was ten or 12 years ago, we reduced both the recycling levy and collection charges to farmers. If we should get into such a position again we would most certainly consider reducing both the levy and collection charges. We are a not-for-profit body but we must have a certain amount of funding in order to run ourselves.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterChapCleere" eId="spk_147">
          <from>Deputy Peter 'Chap' Cleere<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_194">I want to discuss the lack of infrastructure. I am a rural Deputy from Carlow-Kilkenny and sometimes there is a lack of infrastructure in areas. There are four providers. How many collection points are located around the country?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_148">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_195">Typically, we run about 200 bring-centres so, on average, there are seven or eight bring-centres per county. Farmers can also drop the material into our contractors' yards and there is a farmyard collection service for farmers who prefer that service.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterChapCleere" eId="spk_149">
          <from>Deputy Peter 'Chap' Cleere<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_196">Deputy Fitzmaurice mentioned that there is about 24,000 tonnes in storage at the moment.</p>
          <p eId="para_197">Looking at the existing operators, their maximum capacity is less than 24,000 tonnes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_150">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_198">No, that would not be correct. Our contractors have a storage capacity of 45,000 tonnes. In recent years, a number of them have come through the planning process and the permit review process.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterChapCleere" eId="spk_151">
          <from>Deputy Peter 'Chap' Cleere<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_199">That contradictory to the IFAC report.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_152">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_200">No, it is not. The IFAC report talks about it going up to 45,000 tonnes this year.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterChapCleere" eId="spk_153">
          <from>Deputy Peter 'Chap' Cleere<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_201">Page 36 of the IFAC report gives a breakdown per entity. The figures are 3,500 tonnes, ten tonnes, 2,100 tonnes and 10,000 tonnes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_154">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_202">Yes, but also if you-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterChapCleere" eId="spk_155">
          <from>Deputy Peter 'Chap' Cleere<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_203">Is this out of date?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_156">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_204">If you look at the detail of the IFAC report, you will also see that it expects capacity to go up to 45,000 tonnes by the end of this year. The capacity has actually already gone up to 45,000 tonnes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterChapCleere" eId="spk_157">
          <from>Deputy Peter 'Chap' Cleere<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_205">That is not in this report, just to be very clear. It must be an older report. I just wanted to acknowledge that. Is there much plastic coming in from the North?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_158">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_206">There is a problem with the illegal trade. Plastic is definitely coming down from the North. We have no statutory enforcement powers. We work with the local authorities and the WERLAs and do all we can to assist them but there is an issue with illegal plastic coming from the North.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterChapCleere" eId="spk_159">
          <from>Deputy Peter 'Chap' Cleere<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_207">Roughly how much, in tonnage terms?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_160">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_208">It is impossible to quantify an illegal activity because there are no records. It could be 5% or 10%. It could be higher in the Border counties. There is a problem with illegal plastics. There always has been. All we can do is work to minimise it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterChapCleere" eId="spk_161">
          <from>Deputy Peter 'Chap' Cleere<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_209">Let us say it is roughly 10%. If we bring in about 40 million tonnes, we would be looking at about 4 million tonnes, give or take, based on those mathematics.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_162">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_210">Typically, there is 20,000 to 22,000 tonnes going on the market so 1,500 to 2,000 tonnes might be being lost, but it is impossible to say.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterChapCleere" eId="spk_163">
          <from>Deputy Peter 'Chap' Cleere<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_211">Okay, it is about 2,000 tonnes. On recycling in Ireland, 20,000 tonnes are done in Ireland and 20,000 abroad. What is the breakdown of that international side?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_164">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_212">It typically goes to the UK or Holland. We are working to put notifications in place to supply to other countries such as Poland and Lithuania.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterChapCleere" eId="spk_165">
          <from>Deputy Peter 'Chap' Cleere<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_213">Why are we not doing it in Ireland?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_166">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_214">At the moment, the maximum recycling capacity is 20,000 tonnes and we are meeting that demand from Irish recyclers. We are working with the Irish recyclers and encouraging them to expand. We would love for everything to be recycled in Ireland.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterChapCleere" eId="spk_167">
          <from>Deputy Peter 'Chap' Cleere<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_215">What kind of economic benefits do farm films bring to local rural economies? What kind of employment are we looking at?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_168">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_216">We have five contractors who typically employ between five and ten people. There is some employment there. There are also three recyclers, who employ ten, 15 or 20 people each, so there is employment there as well. Our key role is to provide a service to farmers and to hit recycling targets, and we do that very well.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterChapCleere" eId="spk_169">
          <from>Deputy Peter 'Chap' Cleere<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_217">What kind of turnover was achieved last year in terms of farm payments and the tonnage that came through?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_170">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_218">As a company, our turnover was approximately €10.5 million for the year.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterChapCleere" eId="spk_171">
          <from>Deputy Peter 'Chap' Cleere<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_219">Will Mr. Moloney say a little bit about regulatory challenges?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_172">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_220">As the Deputy mentioned, there is an issue with illegal product coming down from the North. We work very hard with the county councils, which have the remit for enforcing farm plastics regulations, and with the WERLAs. We do all we can to identify potential illegal operators, bring them to the attention of authorities, and help in whatever way we can to close those operators and, ideally, to get a prosecution.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterChapCleere" eId="spk_173">
          <from>Deputy Peter 'Chap' Cleere<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_221">Is there a possibility of a compatible scheme being established in the North? There may be some cross-Border challenges. Has the IFFPG explored that area? Where is it in that regard?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_174">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_222">One of the recommendations of the IFAC review was that we would explore that. We are in the early stages of exploring that with the Department. We are going to see what is possible there. It certainly would be a big help if there were a comparable scheme in Northern Ireland because it would reduce the price difference between the North and the Republic.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterChapCleere" eId="spk_175">
          <from>Deputy Peter 'Chap' Cleere<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_223">Is the Department satisfied that the IFFPG is engaging positively with the regulations?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_176">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_224">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterChapCleere" eId="spk_177">
          <from>Deputy Peter 'Chap' Cleere<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_225">On the public awareness campaigns, I believe Mr. Moloney said there were 100,000 farmers engaged in this scheme. How many are not? Is it 20,000?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_178">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_226">CSO figures suggest there might be 135,000 livestock farmers, but it must be borne in mind that some livestock farmers do not winter cattle and others winter only very small numbers of cattle and might get rid of their plastic in their wheelie bin. The overwhelming majority of farmers who are farming in any sort of serious way are engaging with the scheme.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterChapCleere" eId="spk_179">
          <from>Deputy Peter 'Chap' Cleere<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_227">What percentage of farmers are not engaging in the scheme?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_180">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_228">The IFAC report identified that 77% of farmers are engaging with the scheme.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterChapCleere" eId="spk_181">
          <from>Deputy Peter 'Chap' Cleere<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_229">That means 23% are not. I am worried about this 23%. What are we doing to engage with this 23%? What educational programmes are in place? How are we getting at that 23%?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_182">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_230">We are advertising as hard as we can through various media. We advertise in the <i>Irish Farmers' Journal</i> and on Agriland. We text message farmers and advertise through the IFA and Farm TV. We are interested in getting as many farmers as possible engaging with the scheme. The numbers are currently huge so there is already massive engagement, but we would like to see as many more as possible avail of our services.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PeterChapCleere" eId="spk_183">
          <from>Deputy Peter 'Chap' Cleere<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_231">That is fine. I thank Mr. Moloney very much.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_184">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_232">I will have to tip off in a minute because I am going to speak on farm safety. Regarding the IFFPG, there is a levy on the purchase of farm plastic. Per roll, that is roughly €5 to €7. It is actually more now. With the new contractors and the new balers, there is no netting going on. A double layer of plastic goes on bales, which results in almost a third more plastic coming into the sector. Does Mr. Moloney accept that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_185">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_233">Netting is reducing. As the Senator is probably aware, we do collect netting as well. It is being replaced with net replacement film. There is still quite a volume of netting going on the market. The net replacement film is collected and recycled with the wrap and the sheeting. We collect the net replacement film as well.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_186">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_234">It is collected with the plastic.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_187">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_235">Exactly. It is collected with the wrap and the sheeting.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_188">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_236">The IFFPG will therefore have seen an increase in tonnage in the last 12 months.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_189">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_237">It is not so much determined by that. The increase is largely determined by the weather. If we have a very long winter, we will collect more plastic. If we have a very short winter, we will collect less plastic. The market itself is determined by the weather. If we have really good growth conditions, we see a big increase in plastic because more silage is made. If the weather is difficult, we see less silage made. The weather is the big determining factor. For the most part, the net replacement film is replacing netting, which is reducing.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_190">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_238">Roughly the same amount of silage is made year on year.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_191">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_239">It is approximately the same, yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_192">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_240">What I am saying is that netting will reduce and plastic will increase.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_193">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_241">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_194">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_242">Mr. Moloney is telling me that the IFFPG is doing roughly 40,000 tonnes of recycling a year.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_195">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_243">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_196">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_244">That is going to increase in the next year or two by whatever percentage because there will be less netting and more plastic.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_197">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_245">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_198">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_246">That will come at a higher cost.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_199">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_247">Yes, but it must be remembered that we will be collecting less netting. That will be compensated by the increase in net replacement film. One will largely cancel out the other.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_200">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_248">The fee for the netting at the beginning is, let us say, €7 a roll. When the farmer brings it in for recycling, it is roughly €14 per tonne when it is weighed in. Does Mr. Moloney accept that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_201">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_249">The cost per tonne is €120. The minimum charge is €60 for a half tonne at the moment. They are the costs.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_202">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_250">It is twice the weight.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_203">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_251">It is twice the weight, yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_204">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_252">What I am saying is that figure of 40,000 tonnes will be greater going forward.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_205">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_253">It might be slightly more. For example-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_206">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_254">So-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_207">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_255">If I may make this point, we had a short winter, so collections are down 15% this year.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_208">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_256">The plastic is still there.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_209">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_257">It is and it is not.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_210">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_258">It might not have been collected but it is still there on the farms.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_211">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_259">Most farmers bring it out on a one-year cycle. Some do so on a two- or three-year cycle. On the Senator's point on net replacement film, all things being equal, it will slightly increase the amount we collect. The net replacement plastic is heavier than the netting but, as we collect more net replacement plastic, we collect less netting.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_212">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_260">The cost is going to go up, therefore.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_213">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_261">I do not see that as necessarily being the case.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_214">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_262">The figures say that the IFFPG had roughly €3 million of a surplus.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_215">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_263">We expect something like that at the year's end, yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_216">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_264">That is 40,000 tonnes recycled.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_217">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_265">It is 40,000 tonnes this year, yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_218">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_266">If we break that down, it will be less than €125 a tonne.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_219">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_267">It would make more sense to look at our accounts for last year. That would give the Senator the big picture and let him know how much we get in from the levy and from collection income and how much recycling we are collecting.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_220">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_268">How much does the IFFPG get from the levy?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_221">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_269">It is typically around €6 million a year.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_222">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_270">How much does the IFA get from the levy?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_223">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_271">The IFA does not get any money from the levy. Separately, the farmers pay a weight-based collection charge, which might make up another €4 million or €4.5 million. That is overall funding for the scheme.</p>
          <p eId="para_272">If you want to look at a breakdown of our costs, between €9 million and €9.5 million is spent on collecting and recycling it, and a bit on administration.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_224">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_273">There are five approved contractors at the moment.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_225">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_274">That is right.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_226">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_275">Is that adequate for the whole country?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_227">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_276">I think it is adequate. To be honest, we would like to have more collectors, but it is hard to get people to engage with our tendering process because the business is niche and seasonal. We advertised our most recent national tendering process extensively but not a huge number of tenders were submitted. However, we can provide a good service, as we are currently doing with five collectors.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_228">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_277">I am sure the five approved contractors would need to have EPA licences.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_229">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_278">They would either have to have an EPA licence or a county council permit, and they are all properly permitted.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_230">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_279">I return to the 24,000 tonnes that are already here. That is in yards.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_231">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_280">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_232">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_281">What will the cost be to recycle that at the moment?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_233">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_282">The best way I can answer that without running figures in my head is to say that to recycle 40,000 tonnes this year, which is what we expect to recycle, will cost approximately €4.5 million. That is the easiest way I can answer that. To collect between 38,000 tonnes and 40,000 tonnes or whatever we intend to collect will probably cost another €4.5 million.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_234">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_283">To collect 40,000 tonnes will cost how much?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_235">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_284">It will probably cost another €4.5 million. Our operating costs will probably be between €9 million and €10 million depending on where the figures fall by the end of the year.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_236">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_285">Some 24,000 tonnes at €125 per tonne comes in at €3 million.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_237">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_286">I have not run the figure, but if that is what it comes to, yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_238">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_287">If 24,000 tonnes at €125 per tonne costs €3 million, how is Mr. Moloney going to do 40,000 tonnes for €4 million?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_239">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_288">Overall, all I can tell the Senator is that we will spend approximately €4 million this year.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_240">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_289">It is not adding up.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_241">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_290">It is adding up. The €125 per tonne was the Senator's figure, not our figure.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_242">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_291">What is their figure?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_243">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_292">Our figure would divide 40,000-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_244">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_293">No, what is their figure? Have they a price on it?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_245">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_294">The only way I could give that figure is to divide €4.5 million by 40,000 and you will see the cost of recycling.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_246">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_295">That is the net.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_247">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_296">If the Senator is trying to find out if the scheme is financially stable, which is what I think he is coming at, this scheme is financially stable at the moment. We have enough money to do what we need to do and to put enough aside to satisfy the requirements of our approver. The Senator can rest assured that the scheme is financially stable. I cannot be running figures here in my head, but I can point him to our audited accounts from last year, which will give him all the detail with regard to what the company takes in from certain areas and spends in certain areas.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_248">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_297">It is hard to accept that. Coming into a committee we should have figures in our heads. I go back to collaboration and the illegal tonnage coming across. Mr. Moloney stated approximately one third of it, is that correct?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_249">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_298">No, we estimate between 5% and 10%, but we do not know for sure it is illegal activity. Between 5% and 10% of the market is perhaps lost to this illegal activity, but we do not know for sure.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_250">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_299">How is that funded?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_251">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_300">It is lost, it is illegally put on the market, and we have to fund our scheme with what is legally put on the market.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_252">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_301">Is that in the 40,000 tonnes?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_253">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_302">We do all we can when the material comes in at bring centres to check to see if the levy has been paid so we are working hard there and with the local authorities and the-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_254">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_303">Is it in the 40,000 tonnes they have estimated?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_255">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_304">There may be some illegal product in there. I could not say for sure, but we are doing all we can to make sure there are checks in place at the bring centre when the farmer comes in to make sure he has paid the levy.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_256">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_305">IFAC estimates up to 25%.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_257">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_306">That was a possible figure, but we would say between 5% and 10%. They quoted various people they interviewed. Some said 25% and some said different figures. Our feeling is that it is between 5% and 10% of the market.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_258">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_307">Is the 5% or 10% included in the 40,000 tonnes in this year's estimate?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_259">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_308">Some illegal product and plastic might make its way into our bring centres despite our best efforts. I cannot say for sure.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_260">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_309">Mr. Moloney gave me a figure there.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_261">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_310">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_262">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_311">It is either in the figure or it is not. Is it in it?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_263">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_312">If a farmer buys illegal product and is in some way able to trick us into thinking that he paid the levy, that plastic may end up at our bring centre.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_264">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_313">The figure Mr. Moloney is giving the committee today is that they are going to recycle 40,000 tonnes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_265">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_314">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_266">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_315">Is that 40,000 tonnes in the Republic of Ireland or is that including the 5% Mr. Moloney is saying is already recyclable? That is all I am asking.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_267">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_316">The only way I can answer that question is by saying we are doing all we can to check to ensure that everything that comes into our bring centres has the levy paid on it. If it does not, we have a traceability system whereby a farmer has to present a code. He gets the code when he buys the plastic. The code is validated, and he has produced proof of purchase. If the farmer is able to trick us - if he has bought illegal plastic - into thinking he has paid the levy when he has not, then we will take the plastic.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_268">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_317">Surely Mr. Moloney and his company knows all the plastic that is imported per tonne. Double that up in the Republic of Ireland and it gives you a figure.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_269">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_318">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_270">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_319">Are those figures adding up with what they have?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_271">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_320">They are adding up.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_272">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_321">Then they are not losing anything from illegal activity.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_273">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_322">Okay.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#ParaicBrady" eId="spk_274">
          <from>Senator Paraic Brady<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_323">If the figures add up, they are not losing anything.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_275">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_324">There is collecting the plastic and what goes on the market. Of what goes on the market we reckon between 5% and 10% is being lost to the illegal trade. We are doing all we can through our traceability system at bring centres to ensure farmers who might have bought illegal plastic cannot get the plastic weighed at our bring centres at the lower price. That is what we are doing there.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_276">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_325">I thank the witnesses for their opening statements. I suppose a lot of this has been teased through. There are basically five contractors doing the work. If you have a situation where those contractors are not able to get rid of the product they have and it builds up, what happens then? Where do they reach capacity and what mechanism can kick in?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_277">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_326">Although we have five collectors collecting the plastic, we retain ownership of the plastic. It is our responsibility in its entirety. We must ensure that those yards are kept under their limit. We work hard with the contractors and our recyclers to make that happen. Once a contractor collects plastic on our behalf, we have a responsibility to make sure that plastic goes for recycling, and that is what we do.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_278">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_327">Have they had instances where that has not happened?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_279">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_328">We have had situations over the past few years. I alluded to this in my opening statement, where yards were under storage pressure because we were collecting so much plastic and at the time there was not enough storage capacity. That issue has been addressed now by getting more recycling capacity and by a number of contractors expanding their yards. They have gone through the planning and permit review processes. We have almost doubled our storage capacity in the past year or year and a half.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_280">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_329">Those permits are generally issued by local authorities in most cases.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_281">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_330">Exactly.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_282">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_331">Is it a slow process to get additional contractors and yards if needed?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_283">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_332">The process involves having a national contractor tendering process every five years. We advertise it heavily and we look for as many applicants as possible to get tenders in. We assess those tenders, and we go with the best tenders on offer. That is the process.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_284">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_333">In respect of exports, it has been alluded to that there is a difficulty in one of the main facilities in Europe at the moment and where the additional level of plastic will go. The amount of plastic that has to be exported is substantial because we do not have the capacity here to deal with it. Are we in a situation where Mr. Moloney could foresee a difficulty in the future if that facility in the Netherlands were not to reopen or come back on stream?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_285">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_334">We hope not because we are working hard with the authorities in various countries in Europe to get permission to supply facilities located elsewhere. We are also hopeful that Cedo will relocate its plant to another country, and we would be looking to supply there. We feel quite comfortable that we have enough recycling capacity.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_286">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_335">A lot of this comes down to the money collected from the farmer, because the farmer ultimately pays for all of this. There is the money collected from the farmer and the money in this system. I respect Mr. Moloney's attempt to be clear about this but there are lots of hazy areas. Certainly, many farmers feel that they are not sure what is happening, where it is all going and how it is all working out. The maximum amount of clarity and transparency around that needs to be brought to the table. It is something that has raised a lot of questions in the past. There is maybe an opportunity to relieve that and put additional and better processes in place.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_287">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_336">I take the Deputy's point. Perhaps we have a job of work to communicate more effectively with farmers exactly how we are funded and how we spend our money.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_288">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_337">On the amount of illegal plastic, I live in the Border county of Leitrim and I am aware it is something that happens. There may be many farmers who may not purchase all their film north of the Border, but would get a proportion of it there. How hard is it to trace that? The farmer might have a receipt and a code for plastic. Sometimes there is a guy who arrives in a truck to pick it or sometimes there is a collection area in the yard at a mart and the plastic is just thrown. They are not going to be weighing it or checking it in very much detail.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_289">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_338">We have a traceability system. I am not saying it is watertight but we have made big efforts just this year to tighten it up. We have had a very heavy advertising campaign aimed at farmers. We have said to them they will be charged double if they cannot confirm when they come into a bring centre that they have brought levied plastic. They have to bring in a valid label code and proof of purchase. It is checked on an app. We feel we are doing all we can. That is not to say there is not some leakage. I am not going to say the system is watertight but we are making it as uncomfortable and difficult as possible for farmers to buy unlevied plastic, bring it into the bring centre and avail of the lower charges.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_290">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_339">Obviously the Department has a role here in the oversight. I am sure the officials are aware that a lot of people in the farming community have a lot of questions and have raised eyebrows about the finances of this operation. What level of oversight do the officials have at present? At what level do they feel they need to have an additional role in respect of that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_291">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_340">We meet the group regularly. We have an approval document as well as the regulation, so there is a template for us to ensure there is compliance with all the terms of the approval and the regulations. The scheme is obliged to publish an annual report in the first half of the year and that is available on its website every year. That gives very comprehensive detail on the tonnages that have been collected and recycled and the money that has gone through the scheme. There is a wealth of information there on the scheme, so it is very transparent. We are conscious that as conditions in the market vary, different challenges arise for the group over time. By keeping good communication between the Department and the group we are satisfied we get good notice of any issues that arise and what the scheme is doing to meet those challenges.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_292">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_341">Is there an issue that it is basically a closed shop?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_293">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_342">No. Our objectives are that the plastic is taken out of the environment and safely recycled and that farmers have a cost-effective and efficient system to that end. The obligation is on the producers. If you want to sell plastic into the Irish market, you have to participate in this scheme or set up a deposit and return scheme under the regulations. All producers have come in behind this scheme and they are complying with their obligations under the regulations by doing so.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_294">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_343">Going back to the bigger picture, we expect additional levels of recyclables being required to be taken care of. Are there plans to expand the capacity in the country to do that so we have less of a dependence on export?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_295">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_344">Yes. Mr. Moloney has outlined his efforts to maximise the material that is recycled within the country and if there were more operators available to do that he would send material to them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_296">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_345">Absolutely. We would like to recycle everything in Ireland if we could but there is just insufficient capacity at the moment. We are working with the recyclers to encourage them to expand so we can get more of it recycled in Ireland. The end goal would be to recycle everything here, if at all possible.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MartinKenny" eId="spk_297">
          <from>Deputy Martin Kenny<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_346">Are there technological advances that are improving the prospect of that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_298">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_347">It is a difficult business. It is very capital-intensive. It is difficult to recycle the plastic and the markets are not brilliant at the moment for the finished product. Nonetheless, we have three Irish recyclers operating and they are taking 50% of what we recycle, which is a big improvement on three or four years ago. We will keep working with them and encouraging them and I hope we will see that capacity increase in Ireland.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_299">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_348">My first question is for the producers group. In my area outside Portlaoise we had a collection yard licensed by the local authority in Clonkeen. You bought your permit or you brought your licence, you weighed in, you paid your money and you went off, and that plastic is still out there now. What has the group planned to remove that plastic? I am a public representative who represents that area as well. That is the first question.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_300">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_349">Any plastic we have responsibility for in that yard has been removed. The plastic that is in that yard now is not the IFFPG's responsibility. It has come from other sources. That is not our responsibility. We have taken everything we owned out of that yard, so I am afraid we can give no further assistance with regard to that yard.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_301">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_350">Mr. Moloney is telling me the plastic I brought into that yard is gone.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_302">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_351">I am telling the Deputy that the plastic we supplied into the facility-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_303">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_352">I am sorry, but how does Mr. Moloney know that? There was a big pile of plastic. Did the group go through it or what?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_304">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_353">Because we-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_305">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_354">I am asking you straight up.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_306">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_355">Indeed. We did an audit. We did an audit of that particular contractor's yard and we did a match between what went in and what was recycled in that particular contractor's recycling facility because that contractor also had a recycling facility. We were able to see that we had recycling certificates received from the recycler for everything we put into the yard, so we have taken full responsibility for everything we have-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_307">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_356">You are saying that you got no levy on the plastic that is left in the yard.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_308">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_357">I am not saying that. I am saying it is not our plastic.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_309">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_358">If you are not saying that, you will have to come out and prove that you did not take the levy. If you claimed the levy off the plastic that went in there and is in there, in my opinion you have a responsibility to move that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_310">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_359">No. That plastic has come from other sources. We have-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_311">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_360">What do you mean by other sources? Where can it come from?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_312">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_361">Other collectors that were operating outside the IFFPG scheme. The IFFPG has carried out a detailed audit of that yard. We are 100% certain that we have recycling certificates back from the recycler for everything we put into the yard. The plastic that is in that yard has come from non-IFFPG sources. We sympathise with the position the yard finds itself in but we have no responsibility there.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_313">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_362">What will happen then eventually? I think you have an awful lot more. I cannot understand what you are telling me, because no matter where the plastic came out of - and 5% comes from outside the country or from the North of Ireland and you say you cannot account for that, which is fair enough - the group got money out of the other amount of plastic that is there. That is Irish plastic.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_314">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_363">There may or may not have been a levy-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_315">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_364">Mine is in there.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_316">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_365">-----paid on it, but it was other collectors who collected it and it was a recycler who took it in but it has not been recycled. It is not our responsibility. We are 100% sure that everything we put into that yard-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_317">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_366">But you got the money for the plastic. I am not happy because you get money for every piece of plastic that is wrapped around a bale or put on a silage pit, like I do. You got the levy. I brought it out there and I handed in my notes saying where I got it, 100% above board. The people in the area are asking me. That plastic is there. You got money out of that and now you are walking away from your responsibility, in my opinion.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_318">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_367">The money we get from our members is there to run our scheme. We collect plastic through our approved collectors.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_319">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_368">Yes, and I am one of them.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_320">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_369">Yes. Therefore, if the Deputy dropped plastic into that yard with our approved collector at the time, his plastic was recycled because we are certain that everything we dropped into that yard was recycled by the recycler. We have paperwork and an audit to confirm that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_321">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_370">So is the question about who brought it in, not where it came from?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_322">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_371">We will take responsibility for what we have responsibility for. That yard was also-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_323">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_372">But you have the money.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_324">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_373">You have the money.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_325">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_374">-----being supplied by plastic from non-IFFPG sources. We are not taking responsibility for the plastic that came from non-IFFPG sources.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_326">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_375">Would you accept that your group drew the money from the people who imported it-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_327">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_376">Deputy.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_328">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_377">-----into this country? You drew the money and the Department should wake up to the fact that money is drawn from-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_329">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_378">Deputy.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_330">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_379">-----all importers into this country and then if someone else has it, tough luck, leave it there. That is some set-up. The Department should wake up to what is going on.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_331">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_380">Deputy Aird, it is your time.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_332">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_381">The bottom line is that the plastic is there. I am asking the Department as well. I want this plastic moved. It is in an area and the people are entitled to have it removed because there was a subsidy paid on that. Someone somewhere has the money for it. In fairness, this non-profit organisation still has €3 million in the bank. All I am saying is that this has to be moved. I do not know how anybody would be able to say exactly that my plastic is gone.</p>
          <p eId="para_382">Do you understand? I am just saying that. I do not know how that is done. We will be in again and we will come back to that. I just think it is wrong, if you understand what I mean.</p>
          <p eId="para_383"> I have a couple of questions I would like to ask. As we all know, with levy and collection charges rising sharply, what steps are being taken to stabilise or reduce the costs to farmers while maintaining high recycling rates? It is a quickfire question because I have only four and a half minutes left.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_333">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_384">The money we are charging in the levy and collection charges is the money that we have to charge at the moment to fund the scheme. That is the cost of collecting and recycling 40,000 tonnes of plastic every year. It is regrettable but that is where it is. If we do not charge at that level, we will erode our financial resources.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_334">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_385">There are only five approved collectors now for the whole country. As Mr. Moloney said, this is seasonal work. How will this scheme ensure that farmers in the most remote areas will get a fair collection with only five people?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_335">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_386">Those five people are able to provide that comprehensive collection. We ran 200 bring centres this year with our five collectors. We do it every year. We provide a farmyard collection service for farmers who cannot make the bring centre. We are able to provide a comprehensive and timely collection service for farmers with five collectors.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_336">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_387">How does the Department ensure that the producer pays model works fairly without shifting the excess cost to farmers? I feel that the farmer is paying an excessive amount at the moment for this scheme. That is my personal opinion as a farmer.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_337">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_388">The obligation is on the scheme to balance the books. As Mr. Moloney outlined, the cost of recycling is such that the fees required are the fees required to make sure that the collection and recycling costs could be met. There was a time when you could be paid for your plastic. Obviously, those times have passed and now it is a cost. There is a widespread difficulty in the recycling industry across Europe, as the market for recycled plastics has suffered a number of shocks from pressures elsewhere in the world. It is a difficult business to be in and unfortunately that translates into high costs for the people who use the plastic. We acknowledge that the consumers and customers of those producers are ultimately the ones who-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_338">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_389">What actions did the Department require of the IFFPG after the mid-2024 review, monitoring compliance and so on? What did the Department ask of it?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_339">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_390">It was set out in a letter to the committee too. It touched on things like training of the board to ensure the highest standards of governance at board level, working with enforcement authorities to ensure that non-compliant retailers were targeted, developing an enforcement portal, and working on the product codes so that farmers who have paid for the levy at the time of purchase have proof when they are they are bringing it to the collection and to ensure that non-levied plastic does not get into the collection system. It also addressed the storage of legacy farm plastic which had built up in the yards over the years but has now been tackled successfully. They were the main issues.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_340">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_391">The IFFPG is the only approved scheme as we speak here today. What is being done to encourage alternative or competing recycling schemes? If we do not do that, we are going nowhere.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_341">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_392">There is an annual promotion by the scheme of what the scheme does. That creates an awareness of the obligation to have a scheme, that there is activity and that a service is being provided. There is a high level of awareness of the requirement for a scheme. All that awareness has not generated an application from anybody else to run an alternative scheme.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_342">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_393">We have been told that 50% of what IFFPG collects is being recycled in three different centres. Is that correct?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_343">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_394">Some 50% in Ireland and the other 50% abroad.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_344">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_395">That is 50% in Ireland. Has IFFPG to pay those recycling centres?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_345">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_396">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_346">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_397">How much is IFFPG paying them?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_347">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_398">The best way to answer that is that last year, we spent €4.5 million supplying plastic to centres.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_348">
          <from>Deputy William Aird<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_399">It is very difficult. When Mr. Moloney says IFFPG spent €4.5 million paying these people, I am trying to see how much less money it should be taking out of farmers' pockets in the levy for plastics because, as far as I can see, the only person who is paying money is the farmer. He is carrying the whole book. Farm incomes are reducing at the moment. Milk is going down and cereals have nearly gone out of business. From a recycling point of view, IFFPG takes plastic drums in. I am asking the Department to look into recycling them. Look at what happened with the plastic bottles. You could not get a plastic bottle anywhere in this country if you were searching. I know that because we used to be collecting because our farm was near the town. There is not a plastic bottle to be seen since there have been refunds for them. Can the Department not think outside the box on something like that? Wash out the 5 gallon drums that are coming in with all the different stuff, then they can be recycled and stuff can be put back into them. It is nonsensical and the Department should be doing something like that. If the Department continues the way it is going, there is no incentive for any recycling. Some 50% is being recycled and the Department is going to store the other 50% if it can and send it out of the country. Be honest about it.</p>
          <p eId="para_400"> We should be able to do our own recycling of plastic in the country. I am fearful that there is no push to increase that 50%. The Department should learn from the plastic bottles. Everyone would agree that it was the best scheme that ever came out, which everybody in every town and village in the country is using. The Department should be thinking outside the box. The witnesses' organisations should be happy enough, since they have €3 million already, and I am giving them part of that €3 million as a farmer, as is every other farmer. They have all the money. That could go up to €4 million or €5 million. It is time that we gave a reduction back to the farmer.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_349">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_401">I welcome the witnesses. The economics of this just do not make sense. I have listened for the past hour. In the levy, €6 million paid by the farmer is taken in. The collection fee is over €4 million, also paid by the farmer. That is a total revenue turnover of €10 million. The cost per tonne of removing recycling is €112, by the witnesses' figures, as they said to Deputy 'Chap' Cleere. There are 40,000 tonnes per year and it costs about €4.5 million to dispose of it at €112 per tonne. There should be a yearly surplus, on those figures, of about €5.5 million. Where is the money going?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_350">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_402">It would be, except we also collect the plastic and bale it before we send it to the recycler. Another €4.5 million is spent on collecting, baling and preparing the plastic for recycling, then €4.5 million is spent on sending it to the recyclers. I assure the Deputy that we are not awash with money. If anything, financially, it has been quite challenging for the last few years but our finances are stable and good now. We are generating a modest surplus and building up our contingency. We have pretty much just enough money to provide the service we are currently providing.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_351">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_403">How many people work in the organisation?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_352">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_404">There are only five people in the office. Our administrative costs are around €600,000 a year.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_353">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_405">What are the top three salaries of individuals in the organisation?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_354">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_406">I am not revealing that but I can tell the Deputy that €600,000 per year is spent on administration. That includes salaries, rent of the office, advertising and consultancy. I assure the Deputy that there is no waste when it comes to the administration of the scheme.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_355">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_407">Mr. Moloney mentioned a recycling cost of €112 per tonne but exporters are saying it is €150 per tonne. Who is wrong and who is right?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_356">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_408">We can talk about that until the cows come home. I can tell the Deputy what we are spending overall on recycling 40,000 tonnes. It will come in at around €4.5 million. We will spend another €4.5 million on collecting that 40,000 tonnes and baling it. We have administration costs of around €600,000 and we will take in maybe €10 million to €10.5 million depending on how the year pans out. This scheme just about washes its face. It generates a little surplus, which we need, because we need to build up our contingency fund, so there is no surplus of money but we are financially stable.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_357">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_409">Where is the company Cedo going?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_358">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_410">I do not know and I do not know if it knows at this point but it has closed its plant in the Netherlands and is seeking to relocate the various recycling lines it had in that plant to other countries. I do not know at this time where it will relocate the farm plastic recycling to.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_359">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_411">If it goes outside Europe, will we be able to continue to use it?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_360">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_412">It does not intend to go outside Europe but we do not supply to any recyclers outside Europe. We will just supply to recyclers within Europe.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_361">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_413">Four or five years ago, IFFPG was before the committee and said the recycling cost per tonne was €150 to €180. Since that time, the levy has doubled and the collection fee has doubled.</p>
          <p eId="para_414">It does not really add up. What is happening? Where is the money going? How can we have a situation where the cost of recycling per tonne has fallen, yet the cost to the farmer with the levy and collection has doubled? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_362">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_415">If the Deputy went back to our accounts of four or five years ago, he would see that we probably turning over €4 million or €5 million per year. The turnover cost of the company has doubled. Hence, unfortunately, we have had to pretty much double what we charge in the recycling levy and collection charges. We have no other form of income. We cannot get income from anywhere else. These were hard decisions. We did not like doing it. If we did not increase the levy and collection charges by the amount we increased them, the scheme would have folded. We would not have had enough money. We take in enough money to run the scheme, generate a surplus and that surplus goes into a contingency fund. The scheme is financially stable but there is no excess. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_363">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_416">What is in the contingency fund?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_364">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_417">That fund is building up at the moment. By the end of the year, we would expect to have around €700,000 in it. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_365">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_418">What is the current situation in Littleton in Tipperary? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_366">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_419">We supply plastic there on an on-off basis. We pay a gate fee, and it looks after it from there. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_367">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_420">Is it operational as normal?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_368">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_421">I believe so. We have nothing to do with the company apart from supplying it with plastic. It is a separate company. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_369">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_422">I have questions for the Department. Is the Department satisfied with the economics of the scheme at the moment? Will it consider opening this up to have a greater level of competition in the market? Competition is a good thing. It appears that there is no willingness to open this up to other operators. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_370">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_423">We have performed a lot of scrutiny of the scheme over the past number of years. There has been the independent report as well. We have done our own analysis. We have worked closely with the scheme in pointing out where we saw there was room for improvement. We have been satisfied that they have responded adequately to all of our requests. They have been quite open and transparent in that regard. We are open to an approach for any other competing body that might represent producers to set up an alternative scheme. That is absolutely the case. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_371">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_424">It is one thing being open to it and another thing creating a process to facilitate it. There needs to be work there in relation that. There is a contract but there is no public consultation, advertising and tendering process. It seems that there is not really engagement or willingness there. Does Ms Kiely agree?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_372">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_425">In other schemes, for example, in textiles, it is a new requirement from the EU to require the setting up of a new extended producer responsibility for textiles. We have had a number of bodies approaching us saying that would be willing to run a scheme. There is appetite out there where there is a prospect of being able to do business successfully. I would not think it was so much that it is not known to producers because all of the producers are members of the IFFPG. There are no other producers operating. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_373">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_426">Why is it the case that the Department has precluded that outside agencies or companies, in that they must be producers?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_374">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_427">It is a producer responsibility scheme. If you want to place material on the market, you have to take responsibility for its end-of-life destination and how it is handled. It is an obligation on the producer. If someone wants to do business here, they have to facilitate the scheme which collects and recycles the material.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_375">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_428">That creates a closed loop. It leaves itself open to a level of or potential for corruption in relation to it if the Department is excluding any outside agency. It is a closed loop and therefore it is not open to the full competition of the market.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_376">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_429">I do not see how it is closed. The producers can break away or new producers can come in and set up their own scheme subject to them meeting the requirements of the regulations. There is nothing to stop them doing that. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_377">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_430">In relation to the non-levy plastic that is coming in from the North, what level of tonnage was that last year? What is the charge for that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_378">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_431">As I was saying earlier, we do not know for sure the illegal activity but we estimate that 5% or 10% of the market might be illegal. We do all we can at the bring centres to try to identify that plastic through our traceability system. If a farmer brings that in and he does not have a valid label code or proof of purchase, he is going to be double charged. We had a big push on that this year. We found it effective. We estimate it is maybe 5% or 10% of the market.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_379">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_432">What tonnage of plastic was double charged last year?</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_5">
          <b>
					</b>
          <i> Deputy William Aird took the Chair.</i>
        </summary>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_380">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_433">This year is the first year we went hard at that. I can talk more on farmer numbers. Two hundred to 300 farmers were perhaps double charged this year. This was a difficult thing to do because, as the Deputy, can imagine nobody wants to be double charged but we take our responsibility seriously when comes to assisting the enforcement authorities. We tightened up on the traceability this year. Some farmers ended up paying double charges.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_381">
          <from> Ms Geraldine O'Sullivan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_434">If they had proof it was bought through the scheme that was refunded. It was just to try to address the illegal volumes of plastic coming in. If there was an issue with not having the right documentation and it was provided, that was immediately refunded. That was part of it. It was just to try to address the volumes of illegal plastic going through the scheme.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_382">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_435">I thank the witnesses very much for coming in. Unfortunately, I had to step out to another meeting. We believe there is over 24,000 tonnes of plastic still to be collected throughout the country. Is that what we said at the outset? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_383">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_436">To clarify that, we probably have a little less than 24,000 tonnes in yards. That is plastic has been collected. It is in our contractors' yards. We are recycling it as we go. Our bring centres are over now. By the time the bring centres start next April or May again, that should be down to no more than 7,000 or 8,000 tonnes. We want to keep a certain amount in the yards to honour our recycling agreements. That plastic is not a problem; we know it is there. We are prepared and have made arrangements for it to be recycled over the coming months.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_384">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_437">Is that not an issue?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_385">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_438">It is not an issue. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_386">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_439">Is it in contractors' yards, with contractors who collected that plastic?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_387">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_440">Yes, for us.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_388">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_441">Was it on the organisation's behalf?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_389">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_442">Correct.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_390">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_443">That is fine.</p>
          <p eId="para_444"> Farmers have been charged twice. They are being charged the levy and then for the collection. Will Mr. Moloney explain that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_391">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_445">We have gone with a hybrid funding system whereby most of the funding comes through the recycling levy that is paid when the product is purchased but we also get funding through a weight base collection charge at the bring centre. We have gone with that funding model because it encourages the farmer to take contamination out of the plastic. It leads to better quality plastic being delivered and makes it easier for us to then find a recycling outset for that plastic.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_392">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_446">The charges for collection are increasing. Are they going to continue to increase? It is putting another burden on top of the farmers.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_393">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_447">No. For next year, we are comfortable and confident at this stage that the prices will stay the same. We expect no increases for next year.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_394">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_448">Could we be looking at a decrease in the cost of it at the moment? Is the levy still going to be in place?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_395">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_449">We are just not ready for a decrease yet but if our finances get into a position where we feel comfortable to give a decrease, we will do so. We have done this in the past. We have quite significantly decreased the recycling levy and collection charges going back ten or 12 years ago. Our finances will have to get into a good position before we would take that decision but we are not a for profit body. We do not hoard money. If we get to that position, we are happy to make reductions.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_396">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_450">Is the levy going to stay as it is? The<i> status quo</i> will remain going forward.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_397">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_451">Yes. For next year, we expect no changes. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_398">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_452">Where does the recycling take place? Is a lot of it exported out of the country? Is there a good share recycled here in our own country? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_399">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_453">Around 50% is in Ireland and 50% in facilities elsewhere in Europe. That is currently where we are at. We are meeting the recycling intake requirements of Irish recyclers in full. As they increase capacity, we will give them more.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_400">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_454">How many recycle centres do we have in Ireland?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_401">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T16:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_455">Three.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_402">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_456">There are three in the country and as for the depots where the plastic is collected from farmers around the country, I must compliment the IFFPG on that. While it tries to get local as much as possible, I presume it has a good share of those depots throughout the country.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_403">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_457">We have five contractors collecting on our behalf and 200 bring centres.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_404">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_458">Sorry, will Mr. Moloney repeat that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_405">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_459">There are 200 bring centres scattered throughout the country, so there should be one within a reasonable distance of every farmer. We also provide a farmyard collection service for farmers who cannot make it to the bring centre.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#JoeCooney" eId="spk_406">
          <from>Deputy Joe Cooney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_460">That is good. They are my questions. I thank the witnesses.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_407">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_461">Does any of the IFFPG plastic going for recycling go to Monaghan?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_408">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_462">Yes, it does. There is a recycler there we supply.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_409">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_463">Mr. Moloney will be aware, as it was in the newspapers, that the licence is to store 4,000 tonnes. I will not mention names, but it was in the newspapers and is public knowledge so I am not saying anything untold. Planning was refused for it to be able to go up to 20,000 tonnes. Did IFFPG send plastic there since that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_410">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_464">We supply it all the time. As I understand it, its permit is compliant.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_411">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_465">Does Mr. Moloney know what tonnage is there? Is it inside the boundaries of 4,000 tonnes?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_412">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_466">I have no idea. That is a matter for the recycler but none of the authorities have brought to our attention any problem with the plant.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_413">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_467">My next question is for Ms Kiely and the Department. We try to encourage recycling everywhere. I ask Ms Kiely to look at it from this side for a moment. If I am an entrepreneur who decides to put in a system - someone in Clare is doing that at the moment and has put in a huge effort - the Department tries to encourage people to do these things. If I head off and put down my tanks, get my shredding machine and try to get it to green waste - amber is a problem - washed, cleaned and baled, I can get it to some facilities for little money. The Department is preventing people from being entrepreneurs because €286 per tonne is paid for that, but if I set up in my plant to do this and collect plastic, I am prevented from that. Should the Department not be looking outside the box to encourage more around the country - IFFPG provides a service - rather than stuff having to leave the country as amber waste with big problems. Loads that went out of the country through Antwerp had to come back. They are the facts. There is a lot of hassle in that. Instead of just doddling along, why do we not have a system or opportunity, for people who decide to set up a plant? Everything is about the importer. The Department said today that the person who sends it in is responsible for that plastic, end of story. These plants are tricky - let no one say they are not - and the volumes that can be got through are small. I have been to plants around the country that had great aspirations, but it is tricky stuff and the machinery is pretty complicated. The Department is now preventing people, like the outfit in Clare from getting the €286 per tonne that might make it viable. I have looked at what the outfit in Clare is doing. It is able to wash the plastic, get it baled and so on. It is well known that there are many more openings for it if it is that way. Why is the Department not prepared to think outside the box?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#WilliamAird" eId="spk_414">
          <from> An Leas-Chathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_468">Can we let Ms Kiely answer that?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_415">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_469">I am not familiar with the precise case the-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_416">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_470">I am talking about if I decided to do it in the morning.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_417">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_471">I do not see how the scheme is preventing any of that happening.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_418">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_472">How would I get the €286 per tonne?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_419">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_473">The scheme is there-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_420">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_474">If I set up a plant recycling plastic, I will not be the importer. I will have nothing to do with it. If farmers bring the plastic to me, they will pay the €120 or whatever they get to me, but the €286 per tonne for when it comes into the country will not be paid to me. Is that not preventing me being an entrepreneur in that industry?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_421">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_475">The scheme is open to any proposal from a domestic recycler. I do not see how that is a difficulty. If the Deputy is talking about the levy on the plastic at the point of purchase, that is how the producers meet their obligations-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_422">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_476">Yes, that is what I am talking about.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_423">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_477">-----and they place it on the market. The producers have chosen under the regulations, as is their right, to set up a scheme, to organise for the payment of that levy into the scheme and organise the recycling in that way. It means all that plastic is collected and recycled successfully. The scheme would like to see more of it recycled in Ireland.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_424">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_478">Would it not be a better system to encourage different things such as if on every bit of plastic that came in, the levy was paid like it is on other things? We pay carbon tax to the Government. The levy could be paid and whatever IFFPG does, it is paid; whatever Johnny down the road does with his recycling, as long as he has the numbers on every roll, he is paid. Why is there no thinking outside the box? This shop is closed to anyone who wants to set up a recycling business in Ireland because they will get €120 as against €286. The maths do not stack up. A place in the Netherlands is gone. If that goes outside the EU, under the green deal we cannot go there, so we need to look outside the box to try to encourage more people to find more ways to recycle. I cannot understand the Department's closed door on all this.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_425">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_479">Is there a question?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_426">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_480">Yes. Is the Department open to looking at something like I described?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_427">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_481">As far as we are concerned, the scheme is meeting the objectives.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_428">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_482">Yes, Ms Kiely should keep repeating herself. There is no point. We know that under the scheme that is there, whoever brings it in pays this levy. However, if I set up an industry that will provide employment, recycle plastic and do good for both farmers and our country, I will be left out of the €286 no matter what I do. Is that the way the Department wants to go on?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_429">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_483">I think the Deputy is putting the €286 together with setting up-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_430">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_484">No, it is €286 per tonne for plastic coming into the country. That is it. It is €120 after that. That is what it is and the €120 is doubled because every tonne that comes in clean, goes out as two tonnes, so that is €240.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_6">
          <i> Deputy Aindrias Moynihan resumed the Chair.</i>
        </summary>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_431">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_485">The commercial undertaking is a matter for the IFFPG and if someone has a proposal to put together-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_432">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:00:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_486">No, hold on. IFFPG runs its own business. The officials are the Department of climate action and all that, so it is their Department. In fairness, the bottle scheme, as Deputy Aird said earlier, has been a good success. These are new ideas. However, if I decide I will be Mr. Recycler of Ireland, that I will set up a plant and do everything, all I get for every tonne I put in is to lose €286. That is some system if a country it talking about recycling. I advise the Department to think about what it is doing and think outside the box for entrepreneurs. What is going in Clare is small scale, but what the person has done to recycle is phenomenal.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_433">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_487">I apologise for being in and out of the meeting. Going back to some of the figures mentioned, the cost of recycling 40,000 tonnes is €4.5 million, the cost per tonne to remove the recycling is €112.50, there are 24,000 tonnes in storage at the moment, and there will be roughly €3 million left at the end of the year. At the same rate as for the 40,000 tonnes, the 24,000 tonnes would cost €2.7 million. Mr. Moloney said we could use the money coming in next year but that will be for the product sold next year and it should not be used for this year's figures. Obviously it does not need to be, if the figures are correct.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_434">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_488">It is better just to speak in aggregate terms. We will collect and recycle approximately 40,000 tonnes of waste this year. It will cost around €4.5 million to collect it and bale it and around €4.5 million to recycle it. At the end of the year we expect to have no more than 14,000 tonnes or 15,000 tonnes in our yards. In the early part of next year we will comfortably recycle it before we go out collecting again in April or May. Then the money will start flowing again. We are in a financially sound situation and it is important to state this, although we have no great excess of funding. We have enough funding to do what we are doing but we are not yet in a position where we could look at, for example, giving reductions to farmers and members. Maybe a few years down the line we will be able to do this.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_435">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_489">The collection charges are used to recycle.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_436">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_490">We have two sources of funding. There is the recycling levy and the collection charge. It goes into a kitty and we draw from that kitty to pay all of our costs. This is how we operate.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_437">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_491">It seems to me that at the end of this year there will only be €300,000 left in the bank if the 24,000 tonnes in storage are recycled. This is what will be left over, using the figures based on 40,000 tonnes costing €4.5 million.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_438">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_492">I would expect that at the end of the year, when we have recycled 40,000 tonnes and paid for collecting it, we will have somewhere between €2.5 million and €3 million in the bank. There will still be 14,000 tonnes or 15,000 tonnes to be recycled early in 2026. There is more than enough funding to do this and there will be money flowing through again from around May and June. If there is a concern about our finances, I want to make it clear that we are financially stable and sound.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_439">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_493">I ask Mr. Moloney to speak to me little about the regulations on plastics coming down from the Six Counties. What are people required to do at the bring centres? Are they required to hand in receipts? Are receipts being forged? How is it that some might be sneaking in?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_440">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_494">We have made a very big strong push to tighten it up this year. People are required to provide a valid label code, which they get when they purchase the plastic. They are also required to provide proof of purchase, such as an invoice or a receipt. When they come to the bring centre the contractor will check on the app whether the label code is valid, invalid or overused. The paperwork will also be checked. If the requirements are not met, the person risks being double charged. As my colleague, Ms O'Sullivan, said, if they can subsequently show us they did in fact buy levied product they get a refund. I am not saying the system is watertight. It is not watertight-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_441">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_495">But it will get better though.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_442">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_496">It is getting tighter and it is getting better. It is making it more uncomfortable for farmers to buy unlevied plastic. This is what we are trying to do. We are trying to help the authorities to curb the illegal trade.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_443">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_497">Of all of the tonnes of plastic that are sold, a certain amount is not brought back by farmers.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_444">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_498">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_445">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_499">Does Mr. Moloney think it is a case they hang on to it for two or three years? Perhaps a smaller farmer can store it at home. Will more regulations be coming into place? We all know most farmers will have this, unless they have pit silage or whatever. Will the Department come and investigate this?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_446">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_500">We have to make it very clear that farmers are doing a magnificent job, with 100,000 of them engaging with the scheme. Over a three-year period, virtually everything put on the market for one year is collected and recycled. We have nearly a 100% recycling rate for the plastic our members put on the market. There is not an awful lot more we can expect of farmers. We would like to get those who are not recycling involved in recycling but the overwhelming majority of farmers are using the service. Most of them will use it each year and some of them on a two- or three-year cycle.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_447">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_501">Mr. Moloney is saying 50% of the waste was recycled in Ireland.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_448">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_502">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_449">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_503">What is the difference between the cost of the recycling in Ireland compared to the cost of recycling at a European facility?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_450">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_504">It is approximately the same. It can vary a little bit up and down. We require the Irish recyclers to operate in the same ballpark as the European recyclers. It is approximately the same.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_451">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_505">That goes on a ship and is exported.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_452">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_506">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_453">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_507">And they can recycle it cheaper than us.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_454">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_508">Not necessarily.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_455">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_509">But there is an-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_456">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_510">The cost per tonne for us when we supply to recyclers is made up of transport and gate fees. The transport cost to Irish recyclers can be low but the gate fee can be high, whereas with European recyclers the transport costs tend to be high, for obvious reasons, and the gate fee is lower. They are approximately the same.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_457">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_511">This is a big issue I have with the bottle and can return scheme. The whole idea of doing it is to do better for the environment but then we are shipping them out of the country. This is a contradiction in itself when it comes to the environment. Are we going to get to a stage where we can recycle all of it in Ireland? How far away does Mr. Moloney think this is?</p>
          <p eId="para_512"> Did I hear Mr. Moloney say earlier there is not a massive uptake on the recycled products? What is being made from it? I know there are stable doors and plastic fencing. Will there be a little bit of an incentive to get more people to use these products? I would suggest there should be an incentive for farmers who buy it back in as fence posts, stable doors or shed doors, so it is more economical to do it here and to have a centre in Ireland. We could do this and keep the products in Ireland.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_458">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_513">At present, 50% is recycled in Ireland and we are meeting the intake requirements of these recyclers in full. We would love to see a situation where everything was recycled in Ireland, for obvious reasons. We are working with the recyclers, encouraging them to expand their plants, and go through planning and review processes, so they can take more in. The operating environment is quite difficult at present. This is because of world commodity prices and so the recyclate they produce, the finished product, is not commanding a high price at present. I hope that in time this will change. I also hope that some of the recyclers will produce a higher value pellet that can go into higher value products, which would be good for everybody. We would love to see some of the plastic we collect turned into a high value pellet by an Irish recycler, which would go back into Irish wrap, which would go back on the market. This would be a true circular economy. We are working with recyclers and our producers to try to bring this about. Most definitely we would love to see everything recycled in Ireland but the capacity just is not there at present.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_459">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_514">Can Mr. Moloney see this changing? Is there a part the Government can play to incentivise people to try to get all of the recycling done in Ireland-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_460">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_515">I cannot speak for the Government-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_461">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_516">-----or maybe in Europe?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_462">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_517">I know one of the recyclers in particular has ambitious plans to take in more material from us next year. This is the sort of thing that we welcome. We will give them as much as they can take, provided they can recycle it and they are some way commercially in the same ballpark as other recyclers. This is something we encourage and cajole inasmuch as we can but we have no direct control over it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_463">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:10:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_518">I have seen some of the recycled plastic products and they are extremely good. When they get a kick they can take a bit of shock, unlike timber which will snap. They are quite good and it would be nice to see it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_464">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_519">We have a recycler in west Clare who is doing something really nice. She is taking in plastic sheeting, sheeting from pit covers and fertiliser bags and turning it all into fence posts that are being sold back to farmers. That is the sort of thing we are trying to support and encourage. We want to see more of that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_465">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_520">Can I come in for a second round?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_466">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_521">Yes. Before that, however, I have one more person who wants ask a few questions in the first round.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_467">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_522">Work away.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_468">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_523">There will be plenty of opportunities to speak.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#NatashaNewsomeDrennan" eId="spk_469">
          <from>Deputy Natasha Newsome Drennan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_524">I would like to go again.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_470">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_525">I have a few questions myself. The IFFPG is required to carry a contingency of €3 million. Earlier, in response to Deputy Lawless, Mr. Moloney referred to a figure of €700,000. The accounts from last year suggest that there is €1.7 million in reserve.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_471">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_526">Yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_472">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_527">Where is the gap and what is the reserve?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_473">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_528">It can be a bit confusing. If you look at our accounts, the reserve is total assets minus total liability, which is the truest reflection of the financial health of a company. We had €1.7 million in the reserve at the end of last year. We would expect that to maybe go back to €2.5 million or €3 million by the end of this year. Within that, we are setting up a contingency fund, which is money that is locked away and can only be accessed in exceptional circumstances with the co-operation of the Department. We expect that contingency fund to be at €700,000 at the end of the year. It can be a bit confusing but I hope that has explains it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_474">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_529">Would that €700,000 would be for the likes of clean-ups or whatever?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_475">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_530">That would be for dealing with exceptional circumstances if they should come our way, as happened over the past number of years, for example, with the recycling market being extremely difficult or some other major global event that impacts how the company operates. It is there for the rainy day, shall we say.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_476">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_531">There was a rainy day when it came to the situation in Leinster, as described by Deputy Aird earlier. There was a clean-up needed. Mr. Moloney is telling us that the plastics that are there did not come through his operation. What is the likelihood of a similar situation occurring elsewhere?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_477">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_532">I can only speak for our yards. We take 100% responsibility for whatever-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_478">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_533">This would have been one of the IFFPG's yards.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_479">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_534">That is true, but, as I said earlier, we would have taken responsibility for whatever we supplied into that yard. Of whatever we supplied into that yard, we got recycling certificates back from the contractor confirming it was recycled. However, there was material coming in from non-IFFPG sources too. What is left in the yard is not our responsibility.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_480">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_535">Yes, but what I want to know what is the likelihood of that situation or something similar emerging in other places?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_481">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_536">I was just going to say that with regard to our contractors, that situation will not happen because we have 100% responsibility for the plastic they collect. We own it at all points until it goes to the recycler. It will not happen with any yards that we have responsibility for.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_482">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_537">With regard to the levy on the bale of wrap, the farmer pays up front. What is that levy based on?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_483">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_538">It is based on giving us the majority of our funding through the recycling levy. Approximately 70% of our funding comes in from the recycling levy. The rest comes in from a weight-based collection charge from farmers.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_484">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_539">How was the figure originally arrived at? As I understood, it was supposed to cover the cost of the operation.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_485">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_540">If you go back a long time ago, it did. Maybe 25 years ago, the recycling levy covered the full cost of the operation. We have gone with a hybrid funding model, however, because we feel it leads to better quality plastic being delivered at the bring centres. We charge the farmer by weight and it gets the farmer thinking about the quality of the plastic he or she is delivering. That is why we have gone with that funding model. If we did not have a collection charge, we would have to substantially increase the recycling levy to make up for the loss of the collection charge. We feel that would have an impact on the quality of the plastic we collect.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_486">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_541">I will return to the reserve. The IFFPG would have to go to the Department to get approval to eat into that reserve and that approval was forthcoming on one or two occasions. Would it have set out a plan on how quickly they were going to recover?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_487">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_542">Yes, that is part of an ongoing conversation with the group. It has been such a dynamic situation in the past number of years. This year and last year have probably been a bit better, but when there were a lot of crosswinds, if you like, it was difficult for the scheme, and then it responded with proposals to put up the fees.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_488">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_543">When is the reserve expected to be back at 100%?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_489">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_544">It will probably take a couple of years yet, given the-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_490">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_545">Even though it is at €1.7 million now and it is expected that €700,000 to €800,000 will be put into a contingency.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_491">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_546">The contingency fund is a ring-fenced account, so it can only be accessed in certain circumstances, as opposed to the surplus available to the scheme on an ongoing basis.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_492">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_547">It is going to take a number of years.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_493">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_548">It will, yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_494">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_549">In the meantime, IFFPG is treading water. It has absorbed a number of shocks, and Mr. Moloney is telling us it is financially sound provided it is not going to be subjected to another shock in the next seven or eight years. It will be then before it will be back up again at €3 million.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_495">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_550">No. We would expect, as was just mentioned, that maybe in a couple of years we would have €3 million ring-fenced.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_496">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_551">A couple, as in two.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_497">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_552">Yes, hopefully, and then we would have a surplus on top of that, which is an operating surplus over and above that.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_498">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_553">Other than hope, has Mr. Moloney set a target?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_499">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_554">It is very difficult. I would say within two years or so we would be hopeful. I have to say hopeful because things have been so chaotic over the past number of years. It is very hard to predict things with certainty.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_500">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_555">I need to move to one other aspect of it. Where does the plastic go? Farmers load it in at the mart and they expect, having paid for it, that it is being recycled. Where is it going at present? Is it stockpiled in the different yards or where does it go?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_501">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_556">There are what I would describe as comfortable amounts of material in our contractors' yards, but it is going to recyclers all the time. Some 50% goes to Irish recyclers and the other 50% goes to recyclers located elsewhere in Europe. At the moment, we are recycling around 40,000 tonnes per annum.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_502">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_557">IFFPG has capacity for about 40,000 tonnes in the different yards.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_503">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_558">Around 45,000, yes.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_504">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_559">That means there is about a year's space.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_505">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_560">Exactly. One of the recommendations of the IFAC review was that we should have something approximate to the equivalent of one year's storage in spare capacity. When we start our bring centres next-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_506">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_561">Mr. Moloney wants to be able to stockpile more.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_507">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_562">No, ideally we do not want to be able to stockpile more but, if there is another big global event that really impacts the recycling market and we are left with no choice but to stockpile for a number of months, we want to have spare capacity.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_508">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_563">There have been quite a number of references to the very successful plastic bottle levy. This thing is very much in contrast to it because if you are using the plastic bottle levy, you pay once. When you go back in with your bottle, you get money back. If you go in with your plastic for farming, you are being charged again in respect of it. It does not make sense that you would be paying again and again. Farmers feel very much aggrieved about this. It is very much like there is a system set up and the opportunity for an alternative system to compete with it is not there. You would have to have the plastics guys involved, and they are already involved in one particular organisation. The opportunity does not seem to be there for another company to come in, compete and provide better value for the farmer. It is almost like the farmer is very much a price taker in the whole thing. You can run a highly efficient organisation or an inefficient organisation, and the farmer will end up having to pick up the tab for it. It is really difficult for farmers to take that. They are very keen to have a highly efficient organisation on their own farms, and they expect it from their suppliers and customers as well.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_509">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:20:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_564">I will respond to the references to the deposit and return scheme. The Department welcomes the positive reaction to that scheme. They are two entirely different markets. The plastic the Chair is talking about, from the plastic bottles, is polyethylene terephthalate, PET, and it has a positive market value.</p>
          <p eId="para_565">When someone collects and recycles it, it has a value. It has a very high market value. Used silage wrap that is in a wet and mucky condition has a negative value because somebody else will have to be paid to deal with it. They are two entirely different types of material and two entirely different markets.</p>
          <p eId="para_566"> It is very difficult. That is one of the reasons a scheme like this has its challenges. At the same time, however, it provides security. Regardless of where the market goes in terms of it being attractive or unattractive to get involved in plastic recycling, there is a scheme that bears the responsibility and is answerable for how it collects, handles and manages the plastic throughout its life cycle. However, it is not out there in the market and necessarily available to all those who may be caught holding the plastic when the price drops dramatically and it is suddenly undesirable. The scheme offers security for the environmental and economic risk that kind of material carries. I know the group would like to come in on another point.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_510">
          <from> Ms Geraldine O'Sullivan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_567">From my perspective, with farmers, the basic thing is that there is a service and there are local bring centres. One of the key asks is that there is a reliable service they know they can bring their plastic to and that here is full transparency on the cost and price, and when they are on. That is the biggest thing. We have spoken to our members on this. The biggest thing is that there is a local centre. There are 200 of these per year. The farmers know exactly where they are taking place and there is a weights system, so they know exactly what is going on.</p>
          <p eId="para_568"> When looking at this, it is very important to recognise that what we have in this country is very unusual. It is a massive success for the farmers who are participating in this scheme, and that should be recognised. Obviously, everyone would love to go back to the day when there was a value. With regard to the plastic, as Ms Kiely said, it is not a massive cost. There is a concern. We need to be looking at value markets or else the cost could potentially increase. It is a big issue. We need to be looking at markets to try to optimise so that-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_511">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_569">Costs could increase further than they have already increased.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_512">
          <from> Ms Geraldine O'Sullivan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_570">Yes, we need to be looking at whether there are opportunities to do it domestically or at what innovations in technology are available to allow us to reduce the cost.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_513">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_571">I have a question for Ms Kiely. It concerns the situation for those who are outside the IFFPG for one reason or another. On the previous occasion the group was in, a contractor gave evidence that their contract would cease that day. On average, if we tally it around the country, there are probably at least 10,000 tonnes of plastic that the levy is being paid on, but that is outside the IFFPG. The IFFPG has been paid €2.8 million. Would it not worry the Department if €2.8 million was paid in for stuff that the IFFPG had not handled, when it still had only €3 million in its account and there were 24,000 tonnes around the country? Would that not worry the Department?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_514">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_572">Obviously, if the plastic is outside the system and is not treated-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_515">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_573">Hold on. It is paid for. Let us be clear about that. It is paid on the imports. Would that not worry the Department?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_516">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_574">If the chain of responsibility has been broken-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_517">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_575">I am not talking about the chains. I am talking about the figures. If there are 10,000 tonnes that a levy has been paid on outside of it, and someone else picked up the money and there is still only €3 million in its account, along with 24,000 tonnes hanging around the country. Would that not worry the Department?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_518">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_576">I do not know. Is the Deputy talking about a true situation or a hypothetical situation?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_519">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_577">It is very simple what I am talking about. I am talking about a factual situation, not a hypothetical one. Would that not worry the Department?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_520">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_578">If there is no safe way of dealing with the plastic, I would be worried, absolutely.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#MichaelFitzmaurice" eId="spk_521">
          <from>Deputy Michael Fitzmaurice<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_579">I propose that we write to the Minister to see if the statutory instrument can changed. I talked about entrepreneurs and different people. I ask the Chair to consider that we would write to the Minister to change the statutory instrument to try to facilitate options in this country whereby an entrepreneur who sets up a recycling plant would not be left out of getting this €280.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_522">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_580">I second that proposal. The Department has created a closed loop that is preventing entrepreneurship and innovation in this space. Ms Kiely talked about a company that was producing chips to put back into the market and the circular economy, but the Department is preventing entrepreneurship in this space. That is what it is doing. In fairness, the Department has sort of shrugged its shoulders and said this is how it is. It is important that we open up this space to allow entrepreneurship to come in. The Department is preventing that. The levy is €286 a tonne, and no independent recycler could afford to lose that per tonne. I would like us to write to the Minister to change the statutory instrument in order to allow this to be opened up.</p>
          <p eId="para_581"> When is the contract up?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_523">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_582">It is not a contract; it is an approval. The approval for the group expires at the end of this year.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_524">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_583">At the end of 2025.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_525">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_584">That is correct.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#PaulLawless" eId="spk_526">
          <from>Deputy Paul Lawless<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_585">It is only right and proper that the Department would engage in a public advertising campaign, in the same way as for every other tendering process, to outline that this is open for applications.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#VictorBoyhan" eId="spk_527">
          <from>Senator Victor Boyhan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:30:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_586">I welcome the witnesses. I want to break this down into two segments. I want to talk to the IFFPG, but I will go first to the Department. At the outset, I apologise because I had to chair a meeting for the past hour that I could not get out of. I have just left there to be here. I hope I am not going to repeat what others have said because I was not tuned into this meeting.</p>
          <p eId="para_587"> I am a man who likes detail. I want to raise with the Department the fact that there was an opening statement by Ossian Smyth, the then Minister of State at the Department of the Environment, Climate and Communications with responsibility for communications and the circular economy, on 15 May 2024. I ask the witnesses to hold the date of that statement in their minds. The Department is back before us for this meeting today, Wednesday, 12 November 2025. We have had the two statements, and we might as well have had the same thing. There are sentences and sentences in today’s statement that are an exact copy of what was said a year ago. That is an important exercise that I would like the Department to look at tomorrow. As a matter of fact, I will give the witnesses the statements on their way out of today's meeting. It does not instil confidence in me that somebody could cut and paste the essence of a statement to the Houses of the Oireachtas. This is the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Agriculture and Food. I am disappointed about that, and I want that message to go back loud and clear to the Department and the Minister. The Department should not be represented in this way.</p>
          <p eId="para_588"> I thank Ms Kiely for agreeing to read the letter into the record. That allows us to make some reference to it because it is now on the public record of the Houses. Ms Kiely raised a number of issues that I thought were of concern. One of them was in relation to the concerns about the Border area. Ms Kiely and I are aware of the fluidity, the flexibility or - call it what you like - the porous nature of the Border between North and South. We would also be aware of anecdotal suggestions of inappropriate behaviour in relation to the movement of recyclable goods across the Border and how that is being policed. I want to flag that as a concern. It is an important point that I want Ms Kiely to confirm to me. I do my research before I come into these meetings. I want Ms Kiely to confirm to me what she knows of the concerns around that. It is an important point to make.</p>
          <p eId="para_589"> The devil is in the detail. It all hinges on the final paragraph of the statement that Ms Kiely read to the committee, which states:</p>
          <p class="indent_1" eId="para_590">The role of the Department is oversight of IFFPG’s adherence to the terms of its approval. A mid-term review of IFFPG’s current approval was concluded in 2024 and the Department requested IFFPG to undertake a series of actions relating to the board …</p>
          <p eId="para_591"> I can only presume these relate to the contingency fund, the importance of corporate governance and the suggestion or possible hint that there were irregularities or concerns in relation to those matters. Again, I want Ms Kiely to share with this committee on the record of this House what those concerns were.</p>
          <p eId="para_592">We need to get to the bottom of this and drill down into the coded language used. It goes on to say that, "The Department is satisfied that [the] IFFPG is engaging positively". It gives the impression that the group was not engaging positively until now. Someone chose those words. Please remember I have had sight of last year's statement that was read into the record of the House by the Department. We are now being told that, "The Department is satisfied that [the] IFFPG is engaging positively with the outcomes of the review and continues to monitor same ... ". The Department clearly had concerns here and it is monitoring them. I want to know fairly quickly what those concerns were and how the monitoring is going. If it is not possible to do it now, the Department can write to the committee with additional information. I ask this question because I think it is an important point.</p>
          <p eId="para_593"> In relation to the licensing or tendering, call it what you will, I was struck when I read these papers the other day that there should be a public campaign around this matter. The public needs to know about it. We live in an open economy where competitiveness is important but transparency is also important. This is especially true for areas under the corporate governance codes for the private, semi-State and State sectors. I do not know how many people are geared up with the capacity to take on this project. This is another matter Ms Kiely will be privy to and she might share something with us on this point.</p>
          <p eId="para_594"> I am very pleased to see some of the major stakeholders who have a huge interest in and experience of this area. I engage with stakeholders all the time. I thank them for their engagement on this and other matters. It is great to see them here. I acknowledge their presence. Ms Kiely will be aware that the Irish Rural Association raised a number of serious issues, including legacy issues and the amount of leftover waste stockpiled, etc. What is Ms Kiely's view? Have things changed in a year? Is she aware of the stockpiling of waste anywhere in Ireland that has not gone through the processes? What has the Department done about it?</p>
          <p eId="para_595"> It must be remembered that the key message in the statement concerned the regulatory aspect. The Department was mandated with responsibility for regulation over this area. Ms Kiely might share with us what she knows and I will share with her what I sort of think I know. This is important. People are looking in. Farmers and the media are looking in. People look at "Oireachtas Report" and take great interest in the work of this committee. I am only a conduit to ask some of the hard questions. Hopefully, Ms Kiely will be able to give us some of the answers. I am also conscious of my time. The Irish Rural Association and other organisations have raised very serious concerns. Ms Kiely will be aware of them. They were discussed at previous meetings. She might just give this area some attention.</p>
          <p eId="para_596"> In terms of the opening statement of the IFFPG, I am encouraged when I read words like, "The IFFPG scheme clearly demonstrates that farmers are willing and able to effectively engage with ... environmental protection [incentives]". That is encouraging and really important. We need to get the message across that the people involved are not wasters and are not dumping stuff. They want to play a meaningful role. It is the case that it must be cost-competitive and there must be incentives and the farmers want the capacity to have the waste taken from farms. There are different methods and cost and time constraints in all of this. We must, though, play our role.</p>
          <p eId="para_597"> I think most of what I want to hear about is from the perspective of the Department and from Ms Kiely and Ms McCormack. They are charged with the policing of this area. I would like them to quickly touch on these issues. What are their concerns about the Border? What is their knowledge? I want them to tell me their knowledge of the stockpile of waste that has not been processed. I would like to know about the cost factor and the implications of that. Are there scams? Is the Department suspicious there may be scams in this sector? I am. I want to hear from Ms Kiely about the knowledge the Department has of these matters. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_528">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_598">I thank Senator Boyhan. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_529">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_599">There were a lot of questions to be addressed in a short time. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_530">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_600">It is okay. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#VictorBoyhan" eId="spk_531">
          <from>Senator Victor Boyhan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_601">I am the last contributor and we have plenty of time. We are here until 6 p.m. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_532">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_602">Yes. If Ms Kiely feels we are running out of time, there will be an opportunity for the Department to write back to the committee.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#VictorBoyhan" eId="spk_533">
          <from>Senator Victor Boyhan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_603">I did say that. I thank the Cathaoirleach. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_534">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_604">A number of letters have been exchanged over the past while between the Department and the committee. A lot of detail has been provided, as requested. The opening statement is designed to be helpful but not to swamp the committee with a lot of original material. Hence it might have looked very similar to the previous one. The Senator is absolutely right in that the Department's role is in governance and oversight. Some of the recommendations we made as a result of the mid-term review did relate to governance. We were concerned that there were vacancies on the board. One of the matters addressed to the group was to ensure board members were recruited from the appropriate sectors and all vacancies were addressed and that any upcoming renewals and vacancies would be addressed. It was all addressed in the annual report for 2024 published this year. It has a wealth of information on corporate governance. Training was also provided for board members. Like any board, it is an ongoing situation and a developing context around governance. There are a lot of updated regulations and responsibilities and it is important boards are aware of them. That was all done and we were satisfied that it was addressed.</p>
          <p eId="para_605"> The contingency fund has been treated. Measures have been taken to ring-fence the funds available to the scheme separately. These are the funds to be put into the contingency fund. We are working with the scheme to ensure the fund is built up steadily over the coming years to an adequate level. </p>
          <p eId="para_606"> In terms of enforcement, there was a legacy of plastic in yards. We and waste enforcement authorities at the local authority level were concerned by it. Working with the scheme, they have addressed that issue to remove the excess plastic to be recycled. As we requested, they have organised a campaign to get that plastic out of yards and recycled in a timely manner. We are satisfied it has been completed to our satisfaction.</p>
          <p eId="para_607"> I think the Border was another concern of the Senator's. My understanding is that there is quite a differential between the price of plastic here and in the North. A large part of this difference relates to VAT. There is more than just the levy in the difference. People have quite an incentive to avoid paying that VAT. The enforcement authorities, the local authorities, the Revenue and the Garda are all available to the waste enforcement system and they have all been co-operating with the IFFPG to tackle that illegal activity. The group has taken steps to ensure farmers who have paid the levy are also in a position to produce a code at the time of collection to ensure no illegal material is coming into the system. That costs everybody more money and drives up expenses. Were they all the concerns the Senator had? Was there anything else? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#VictorBoyhan" eId="spk_535">
          <from>Senator Victor Boyhan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_608">Can I have a minute to come back in? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_536">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_609">Go ahead. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#VictorBoyhan" eId="spk_537">
          <from>Senator Victor Boyhan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_610">I thank Ms Kiely. She has dealt with the points I made but she has not really got into the specifics. I am going to be very quick. It has not been confirmed that all the waste in yards has been cleared. Ms Kiely is saying she is satisfied it is happening.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_538">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_611">They are not all cleared, no. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#VictorBoyhan" eId="spk_539">
          <from>Senator Victor Boyhan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_612">Right, but I wanted to hear that. I expected Ms Kiely to come in and tell me today the level of the problem that exists today. I do not want to hear about a plan, trajectory, a road or how many yards are involved. I am just going to flag this. Turning to the VAT issue, the Revenue is involved. Is Ms Kiely aware if Revenue is actively involved currently in relation to matters around this issue? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_540">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_613">My understanding is that it has been in recent months. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#VictorBoyhan" eId="spk_541">
          <from>Senator Victor Boyhan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_614">It has been in recent months. That is grand. An Garda Síochána is involved. Can Ms Kiely tell me she has been engaging in the past few months with An Garda Síochána in relation to these matters? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_542">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_615">That would be for the enforcement authorities to do and the Garda Síochána is available.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#VictorBoyhan" eId="spk_543">
          <from>Senator Victor Boyhan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_616">Is Ms Kiely aware of it? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_544">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_617">I do know that the Garda has been directly involved in this instance.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#VictorBoyhan" eId="spk_545">
          <from>Senator Victor Boyhan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_618">Whether it is directly or indirectly, would Ms Kiely be aware of it? She should be aware of it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_546">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_619">I am not necessarily-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#VictorBoyhan" eId="spk_547">
          <from>Senator Victor Boyhan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_620">Her Department should be aware of it.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_548">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_621">It is not a regulatory matter for the Department. It is a matter for the local authorities.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#VictorBoyhan" eId="spk_549">
          <from>Senator Victor Boyhan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:40:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_622">Surely, down the corridor or up the back stairs, someone would tell Ms Kiely they know the Garda or the Revenue, the big boys, are on the case here, there are problems, they have not been sorted out and they are coming at the Department. People do not mess with the Revenue or An Garda Síochána. These are the enforcement agencies if there are issues around illegality, as Ms Kiely suggested.</p>
          <p eId="para_623"> I will finish by saying that I will be making a further call in this regard. Indeed, I have a number of questions in my head. I will go up to my office and type them out now, so they will come Ms Kiely's way in a few days. The issue of the involvement of An Garda Síochána will be among them, and rightly so, if there is illegality.</p>
          <p eId="para_624">If there are issues about avoidance of tax, or the VAT rates, North and South, Revenue should be on that case too. We have got to clean up our act, literally, excuse the pun. I was not aware of what I have been told today that there are yards full of stuff that has not been processed.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_550">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_625">No, they are not full of stuff, it is-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#VictorBoyhan" eId="spk_551">
          <from>Senator Victor Boyhan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_626">Plastics. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_552">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_627">Yes. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_553">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_628">It is about farm management-----</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#VictorBoyhan" eId="spk_554">
          <from>Senator Victor Boyhan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_629">Can I just finish with Ms Kiely? What are the yards full of?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_555">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_630">I said at the beginning that at the end of September there was about 24,000 tonnes, so it is a cycle of filling yards and emptying yards. I am sure there is hardly a time of the year when yards do not have some material in them. At any point in time, there will be plastic. It is within the permitted provisions of the contractors' environmental licensing that they may hold material in the yards, so there is nothing wrong with material being in the yards.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#VictorBoyhan" eId="spk_556">
          <from>Senator Victor Boyhan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_631">Is Ms Kiely satisfied that everything is in full compliance and there is nothing irregular or illegal in any part of the sector?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_557">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_632">I have no reports of any illegal activity.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#VictorBoyhan" eId="spk_558">
          <from>Senator Victor Boyhan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_633">Can Ms Kiely say that on behalf of the Department?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_559">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_634">Yes, I would be confident.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#VictorBoyhan" eId="spk_560">
          <from>Senator Victor Boyhan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_635">Would Ms Kiely be reasonably confident or confident?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_561">
          <from> Ms Bernie Kiely<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_636">I would be very confident.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#VictorBoyhan" eId="spk_562">
          <from>Senator Victor Boyhan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_637">Okay, well say that so. I need reassurances, as does the public.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_563">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_638">I just want to reiterate what Ms Kiely was saying. We collect the material typically between April and around October, so the yards are quite full then. Then onwards until April of the next year we collect very little, so we empty them out. We are very comfortable with the volume of material that is currently in our contractors' yards. We expect to have no more than 7,000 tonnes or 8,000 tonnes in our contractors' yards when they head out next April and May with the spring centre programme. The capacity for our contractors is 45,000 tonnes, so there is a lot of spare capacity. We do not want to fill up the yards but it is good to have so much extra capacity. As I said, we are comfortable with where things are at in the yards at the moment.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#VictorBoyhan" eId="spk_564">
          <from>Senator Victor Boyhan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_639">Is Mr. Moloney happy with how this new service agreement contract is going? Is he keen to keep going and be involved or does he know of other stakeholders that may wish to express an interest? </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_565">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_640">I have no idea about other stakeholders. They have the opportunity at any time to get an application in to the Department if they want to become a competing scheme but we are happy with the process that is under way with the Department in terms of the current approval renewal process.</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#VictorBoyhan" eId="spk_566">
          <from>Senator Victor Boyhan<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_641">Is Mr. Moloney is happy with the progress being made to date?</p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#" eId="spk_567">
          <from> Mr. Liam Moloney<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_642">Yes, we are. </p>
        </speech>
        <speech by="#AindriasMoynihan" eId="spk_568">
          <from> An Cathaoirleach<recordedTime time="2025-11-12T17:50:00+00:00"/></from>
          <p eId="para_643">Sin deireadh na gceisteanna, tar éis plé suimiúil. Mo buíochas leis na bhfinnéithe. On behalf of the committee, I thank the witnesses for their presentation and their answers. That concludes the business of the committee and, as there is no further matter for discussion, the committee stands adjourned.</p>
        </speech>
        <summary eId="sum_7"> The joint committee adjourned at 5.53 p.m. until 3.30 p.m. on Wednesday, 19 November 2025.</summary>
      </debateSection>
    </debateBody>
  </debate>
</akomaNtoso>
